<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 10:29:06 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 09:29:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Women Have Swung Toward Democrats Since The Dobbs Decision</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/women-have-swung-toward-democrats-since-the-dobbs-decision/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Meredith Conroy</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Gender</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Women Have Swung Toward Democrats Since The Dobbs Decision</h1>
																			<h2>Men have too.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Meredith Conroy</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/meredith-conroy/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Meredith Conroy</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 28, 2022, at 1:06 PM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Lieutenant Governor John Fetterman Abortion Rights Rally In Montgomery County" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1243153651-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1243153651-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1243153651-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1243153651-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>MICHELLE GUSTAFSON / BLOOMBERG / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">With about a month before the midterm election, some Republican candidates across the country are <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/republicans-tried-sidestep-issue-abortion-now-seeking-reset-rcna47415" target="_blank" rel="noopener">scrambling to moderate</a> their position on abortion. Supporting the recent Supreme Court decision in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization — which overturned Roe v. Wade and ended the constitutional right to abortion — might be a winner in a Republican primary, but <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/2022-live-primary-election-race-results/2022/08/02/1115317596/kansas-voters-abortion-legal-reject-constitutional-amendment" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early signs</a> are that it <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">makes it harder</a> to win a general election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The conventional wisdom is that that’s in part because women <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/08/25/upshot/female-voters-dobbs.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are more motivated</a> to vote this election season thanks to the Supreme Court’s ruling. Conventional wisdom isn’t necessarily based on evidence, though. And while abortion is an increasingly important issue for women, there are signs it is galvanizing some men too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If the Dobbs decision were motivating more women than men, then there’s a metric where that change would probably show up: <a href="https://cawp.rutgers.edu/facts/voters/gender-gap" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the gender gap</a>. The gender gap is calculated by looking at the difference between the share of men and women who voted for a particular candidate or party. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/women-won-the-right-to-vote-100-years-ago-they-didnt-start-voting-differently-from-men-until-1980/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A higher share of women than men</a> have voted for Democrats in every midterm election since 1980, and in the past two midterm cycles the gap has been even bigger. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The 2018 midterm elections are a good example. That year, according to the exit polls, 59 percent of women — and only 47 percent of men — voted Democratic, which means the gender gap was historically wide, at nearly 12 percentage points.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>The 2018 gender gap was historically wide</h2>
 <p>Share of women and men who supported the winning party* in each midterm election since 1982, according to exit polls</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="atd-conroy.gender-gap.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Year</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Winning Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Women</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Men</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Gender gap</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1982</td>
 <td><span>Democrat</span></td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">59%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">54%</td>
 <td>+5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1986</td>
 <td><span>Democrat</span></td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>53</td>
 <td>+5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1990</td>
 <td><span>Democrat</span></td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>51</td>
 <td>+3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1994</td>
 <td><span>Republican</span></td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>-10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1998</td>
 <td><span>Republican</span></td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>-6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2006</td>
 <td><span>Democrat</span></td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>+5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2010</td>
 <td><span>Republican</span></td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>-6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2014</td>
 <td><span>Republican</span></td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>-7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2018</td>
 <td><span>Democrat</span></td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>+12</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Data for the 2002 election is not available.</p>
 <p>* “Winning party” refers to the party that won the popular vote in the House of Representatives.</p>
 <p>Source: Exit polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">It will be hard to exceed that gap, even with abortion at the forefront of many voters’ minds. Our analysis of polls conducted between June and September suggests that, yes, women are leaning heavily toward Democrats, while men are more likely to support Republicans. But in our polling average,<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Sept. 24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> the gender gap isn’t quite as big as it was at this point in 2018. </p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>The generic ballot’s gender gap was wider at this point in 2018</h2>
 <p>Average share of female and male voters who said they would support the Democratic or Republican candidate in an election, in polls from June through September of their respective years</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="atd-conroy.gender-gap.3"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="3" scope="colgroup">Polling from June-September 2018</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Gender</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Democrat</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Republican</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Women</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">49.7%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">34.2%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Men</td>
 <td>42.4</td>
 <td>43.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Gap</td>
 <td><span>+7.3</span></td>
 <td><span>-9.6</span></td>
 </tr></tbody><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="3" scope="colgroup">Polling from June-September 2022</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Gender</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Democrat</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Republican</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Women</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">47.6%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">39.4%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Men</td>
 <td>42.1</td>
 <td>46.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Gap</td>
 <td><span>+5.6</span></td>
 <td><span>-7.3</span></td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Includes polls of likely and registered voters. September 2022 polls as of Sept. 24, 2022.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the size of the gender gap will vary depending on the poll. We looked at two Pew Research Center polls — one conducted in August 2018 and one in <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/08/23/midterm-election-preferences-voter-engagement-views-of-campaign-issues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">August 2022</a> — and found that, in contrast with our average, the gender gap for Democrats among registered voters was a little wider in 2022 (6 points) than it was at the same point in 2018 (5 points), although it’s in the same ballpark. And it is noteworthy that Pew’s data says the 2022 gender gap is looking similar to the gap at the same point in 2018, given that Democrats have more electoral headwinds this year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“I expect that the [Supreme Court] ruling will lead women — especially Gen-Z women — to be far more engaged with the midterms than they would have been otherwise,” said <a href="https://www.melissadeckman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Melissa Deckman</a>, the CEO of the Public Religion Research Institute, a nonprofit polling organization. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the gender gap is a measure of one fairly specific thing: how women vote <em>relative</em> to men. And that can be complicated when it comes to abortion, because men and women overall have very similar views on the issue. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-real-dividing-line-on-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">As we’ve written before</a>, whether someone supports or opposes abortion rights has much more to do with their view of gender roles than their own gender. It’s possible, for example, that if left-leaning men are also unusually motivated to turn out, the gender gap could be smaller. A similar dynamic happened in 2020, when <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-gender-gap-may-have-shrunk-in-the-2020-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">men moved toward President Joe Biden</a>, resulting in a smaller gender gap compared with 2016. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, the evidence about how men are responding to the Dobbs ruling is mixed. Over the past few months, polls have found <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/poll-finding/kff-health-tracking-poll-july-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over</a> and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/support-for-legalized-abortion-grows-since-dobbs-ruling-wsj-poll-shows-11662210020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over</a> again that rising concern over abortion is most dramatic among women, and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/09/07/1121427463/more-women-are-registering-to-vote-how-could-that-affect-midterms" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reports</a> of surging voter registration have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/09/20/roe-abortion-dems-voter-registration-00057618" target="_blank" rel="noopener">focused on women</a>. <a href="https://cawp.rutgers.edu/node/408" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kelly Dittmar</a>, a political science professor at Rutgers University-Camden, said this makes sense because women — in particular, reproductive-aged women who support legal abortion — are more likely than men to feel personally threatened by the sudden loss of abortion rights.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But there have also been reports of higher-than-usual voter registration among young men. An analysis of a series of polls by the nonpartisan firm PerryUndem,<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conducted using YouGov’s online panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> shared with FiveThirtyEight, before and after the Dobbs ruling found that men of reproductive age were more likely to prioritize “safe and legal abortion” as a voting issue. In our polling average,<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Sept. 24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> we found that the gender gap for both Democrats and Republicans grew from June through September, but the gap grew more for Republicans than for Democrats. The two gaps are lopsided because men’s share of support for Democrats has grown as well as women’s, which means that the full magnitude of the shift doesn’t show up in that party’s side. Meanwhile, the shift in the Republicans’ gender gap shows something different: While the share of men supporting Republicans hasn’t changed meaningfully since June, the share of women supporting Republicans has declined, causing the gap to increase.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>The generic ballot’s gender gap has widened since June</h2>
 <p>Difference in share of female voters and share of male voters who say they would support the Republican or Democratic congressional candidate in an election</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="atd-conroy.gender-gap.2"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Gender Gap in voters who would vote for …</th>
 </tr><tr><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Democratic candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Republican candidate</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>June</td>
 <td><span>+5.3</span></td>
 <td><span>-6.5</span></td>
 </tr><tr><td>July</td>
 <td><span>+5.5</span></td>
 <td><span>-7.3</span></td>
 </tr><tr><td>August</td>
 <td><span>+4.8</span></td>
 <td><span>-6.3</span></td>
 </tr><tr><td>September</td>
 <td><span>+6.7</span></td>
 <td><span>-9.1</span></td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Includes polls of likely and registered voters. September polls as of Sept. 24, 2022.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.fdu.edu/profiles/daniel_cassino/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Daniel Cassino</a>, a professor of government and politics at Fairleigh Dickinson University, said that abortion-rights opponents might also be fired up by the Dobbs decision — but that’s less likely to show up as a change in the polls because those people are a solid part of the Republican base and more likely to vote in midterm elections to begin with. “This year, motivating those [anti-abortion voters] doesn’t really help Republicans, because they’re already motivated,” he said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">He explained that reports of higher-than-usual voter registration among women and young voters are another complicating factor because it’s hard for pollsters to account for unexpected surges in turnout. Young voters tend to have <a href="https://www.npr.org/2018/09/10/645223716/on-the-sidelines-of-democracy-exploring-why-so-many-americans-dont-vote" target="_blank" rel="noopener">particularly low turnout</a>, and pollsters sometimes rely on how demographic groups have behaved in the past <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/methods/2016/01/07/measuring-the-likelihood-to-vote/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when they create models</a> to determine who’s likely to vote and who isn’t. If young women are unusually motivated to vote this year, that could throw off pollsters’ estimates.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And then there are all the other factors that influence how people vote. Inflation and the economy <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/395408/abortion-moves-important-problem-list.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are other issues</a> that still consistently show up at the top of voters’ priority lists, and that’s not good for Democrats. Even though the economic outlook has <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/09/13/business/economy/us-economy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">improved in some respects</a> over the past few months, <a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NPR_PBS-NewsHour_Marist-Poll_Politics_USA-NOS-and-Tables_202209021321.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent NPR/PBS NewsHour/Marist College poll</a> found that only 26 percent of Americans said that Democrats would do a better job handling the economy, while 39 percent said Republicans would do a better job. (An additional 20 percent said that neither party would do a better job, and 12 percent said they’d do an equally good job.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So the question isn’t just whether abortion is motivating women more than men — it’s whether concern about abortion will lead voters who might be skeptical about the Democratic Party to vote for its candidates anyway. That group includes men as well as women, and their decisions will do a lot to shape how wide or narrow the gender gap turns out to be.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Mary Radcliffe and Cooper Burton contributed research.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 18:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1664388001865618</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Progressives Took A Step Back In The 2022 Primaries — But They’re Playing The Long Game</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/progressives-democrats-2022/</link>
						<dc:creator>Meredith Conroy</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Meredith Conroy and Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 House Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</category>
			<category>Bernie Sanders</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Progressives</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Progressives Took A Step Back In The 2022 Primaries — But They’re Playing The Long Game</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/meredith-conroy/" title="" rel="author">Meredith Conroy and Nathaniel Rakich</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Meredith Conroy and Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 27, 2022, at 1:30 PM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Jessica Cisneros, Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez, Greg Casar" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22043745475370-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22043745475370-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22043745475370-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22043745475370-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (center) endorsed four House and Senate primary candidates without an incumbent on the ballot. Greg Casar (right) won his primary for Texas’s 35th District, but Jessica Cisneros (left) wasn’t so lucky in the race for the state’s 28th District.													<p>Eric Gay / AP Photo</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">When Rep. Kurt Schrader, a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/2022-midterm-elections-oregon-portland-congress-kurt-schrader-0bce17b40f80f96950358b5c4ee1862e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seven-term incumbent</a> endorsed by President Biden, lost his primary in May, he joined a small but slowly growing list of congressional veterans defeated by progressive candidates with the backing of an increasingly influential campaign apparatus on the left. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This renewed progressive movement emerged following Sen. Bernie Sanders’s 2016 presidential primary run, yet despite some <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/historic-upset-28-year-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-unseats/story?id=56188380" target="_blank" rel="noopener">high-profile wins</a> in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-ayanna-pressleys-upset-win-in-massachusetts-isnt-really-like-alexandria-ocasio-cortezs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2018</a>, its candidates <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-establishment-is-beating-the-progressive-wing-in-democratic-primaries-so-far/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lost more often than they won</a> due to a scattershot strategy. Then, in 2020, when progressives <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/progressive-groups-are-getting-more-selective-in-targeting-incumbents-is-it-working/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">got more targeted with their electoral strategy</a>, their win rate increased. But in 2022, the progressive movement appears to have taken a small step back.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight tracked every endorsement made by a major progressive group for Senate, House and governor this primary season. We consider a candidate “progressive-backed” if they were endorsed by Sanders, Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez or any of the following groups: <a href="https://indivisible.org/candidates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Indivisible</a>, <a href="https://justicedemocrats.com/candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Justice Democrats</a>, <a href="https://www.ourrevolution.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our Revolution</a>, the <a href="https://www.sunrisemovement.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sunrise Movement</a> or the <a href="https://www.boldprogressives.org/candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Progressive Change Campaign Committee</a>.<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though some of these groups have local chapters, we counted only the candidates endorsed by national organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> We also looked at candidates backed by various groups and leaders representing the more moderate or establishment wing of the Democratic Party and found that, overall, the Democratic establishment has an edge in the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/04/26/ohio-11thdistrict-primary-turner-brown/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">battle for the party’s soul</a>. </p>



<h4><strong>Incumbents largely staved off progressive challengers</strong></h4>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Eleven candidates endorsed by at least one of those progressive organizations or people went into the 2022 election cycle hoping to topple an incumbent.<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That includes two who were incumbents themselves, Reps. Marie Newman and Andy Levin. New congressional maps threw them into the same district as their fellow Reps. Sean Casten and Haley Stevens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> Only one of them won: Schrader’s opponent, attorney Jamie McLeod-Skinner. By contrast, in 2020, progressives won three out of 17 such battles.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>Most progressive challengers lost to incumbents</h2>
 <p>How candidates endorsed by Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez, Sen. Bernie Sanders, Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, the Progressive Change Campaign Committee or the Sunrise Movement fared against incumbents in the 2022 Democratic primaries for Senate, House and governor</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich-conroy.democratic-primaries.8"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Result</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Endorsements</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Mike Ortega</td>
 <td>CA-46</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Marie Newman*</td>
 <td>IL-06</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Justice Democrats, PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kina Collins</td>
 <td>IL-07</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Junaid Ahmed</td>
 <td>IL-08</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Andy Levin*</td>
 <td>MI-11</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sanders, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Amy Vilela</td>
 <td>NV-01</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Alessandra Biaggi</td>
 <td>NY-17</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jumaane Williams</td>
 <td>NY Gov.</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nina Turner</td>
 <td>OH-11</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jamie McLeod-Skinner</td>
 <td>OR-05</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution, PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jessica Cisneros</td>
 <td>TX-28</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sanders, Sunrise</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>*Incumbent running against another incumbent.</p>
 <p>Sources: Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sunrise Movement, Twitter, news reports, ABC News</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Of these races, one of the most closely watched was in Texas’s 28th Congressional District, where progressive attorney Jessica Cisneros took on Rep. Henry Cuellar for the <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/08/05/jessica-cisneros-henry-cuellar-democratic-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">second time</a>. <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/24/jessica-cisneros-henry-cuellar-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cuellar is a long-time moderate in the party</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/28/us/politics/texas-primary-candidates-midterms.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an opponent of abortion rights</a>. In 2020 Cisneros came within 4 percentage points of unseating him. Cisneros and her supporters were looking to replicate the success of Rep. Marie Newman, who defeated eight-term Democratic Rep. Dan Lipinski in 2020 after she lost to him by 2 points in 2018. (Lipinski also opposed abortion rights.) But despite all seven progressive entities we tracked being in her corner, Cisneros came up short: After forcing a runoff, she lost to Cuellar by <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/06/21/henry-cuellar-jessica-cisneros-south-texas-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only 289 votes</a>. (Newman is out this cycle too. She lost to fellow incumbent Rep. Sean Casten.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Incumbents’ myriad advantages help them <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ed-markey-won-but-its-still-been-a-rough-year-for-incumbents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">win primaries most of the time</a>. For one, they (usually) have the support of party leadership. For instance, in the race between Cisneros and Cuellar, Cuellar was endorsed by House Speaker Nancy Pelosi, House Majority Whip Jim Clyburn and House Democratic Caucus Chair Hakeem Jeffries. And while Biden does not typically issue primary endorsements as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-endorsees-have-started-losing-more-but-dont-read-into-that-for-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his predecessor did</a>, the president made <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/Endorsements_by_Joe_Biden" target="_blank" rel="noopener">three exceptions for House candidates this cycle</a>, all for incumbents facing progressive primary challengers: Schrader and Reps. Shontel Brown and Danny Davis. Schrader lost, but both Brown and Davis prevailed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Races like these that pit a progressive against an establishment Democrat are watched closely as <a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2022-05-16/oregon-congress-primary-democrats-schrader-mcleod-skinner-left-vs-center" target="_blank" rel="noopener">referenda on the future direction of the party</a>. And among more moderate Democrats, progressive losses are seized upon to suggest that the party’s base is still pro-establishment — or at least satisfied with the status quo. For instance, Jeffries, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/democrats-house-incumbents-challengers/2021/07/13/5dad62a4-e327-11eb-8aa5-5662858b696e_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a known critic of the progressives in his party</a>, was asked in August if he thought the progressive movement had stopped gaining ground. <a href="https://www.cityandstateny.com/politics/2022/08/hakeem-jeffries-again-challenges-left-eve-primary/376162/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">He responded</a>, “Politically, the left did have some success in primarying Democratic incumbents in 2018, and 2020 … But a lot of their electoral momentum began to dissipate shortly after Biden was elected … Perhaps the voters are sending us a message.”</p>



<h4><strong>Progressives had more luck in open-seat races</strong></h4>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Jeffries’s analysis ignores that progressive-backed candidates do much better in primaries without an incumbent on the ballot. For example, in 2022, the progressive-backed candidate won 14 out of the 25 open-seat primaries in which they ran — good for a 56 percent win rate. </p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>Progressives won more than half of open-seat primaries</h2>
 <p>How candidates endorsed by Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez, Sen. Bernie Sanders, Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, the Progressive Change Campaign Committee or the Sunrise Movement fared in the 2022 Democratic primaries for Senate, House and governor without an incumbent on the ballot</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="conroy-rakich.progressives.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Result</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Endorsements</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Maxwell Alejandro Frost</td>
 <td>FL-10</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>PCCC, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jonathan Jackson</td>
 <td>IL-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Delia Ramirez</td>
 <td>IL-03</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Litesa Wallace</td>
 <td>IL-17</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Charles Booker</td>
 <td>KY Sen.</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, PCCC, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Attica Scott</td>
 <td>KY-03</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution, PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Trish Gunby</td>
 <td>MO-02</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Randi McCallian</td>
 <td>MO-08</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Lucas Kunce</td>
 <td>MO Sen.</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, PCCC, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Tom Winter</td>
 <td>MT-01</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Erica D. Smith</td>
 <td>NC-01</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>PCCC, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nida Allam</td>
 <td>NC-04</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Sanders, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Melanie D’Arrigo</td>
 <td>NY-03</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Brittany Ramos DeBarros</td>
 <td>NY-11</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Our Revolution, PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Josh Riley</td>
 <td>NY-19</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Morgan Harper</td>
 <td>OH Sen.</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Doyle E. Canning</td>
 <td>OR-04</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>PCCC</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Summer Lee</td>
 <td>PA-12</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sanders, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>David A. Segal</td>
 <td>RI-02</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Odessa Kelly</td>
 <td>TN-07</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Indivisible, Justice Democrats</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jasmine Crockett</td>
 <td>TX-30</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Greg Casar</td>
 <td>TX-35</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, Sanders, Sunrise</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Peter Welch</td>
 <td>VT Sen.</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Becca Balint</td>
 <td>VT-AL</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Our Revolution, Sanders</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Mandela Barnes</td>
 <td>WI Sen.</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>Ocasio-Cortez, Indivisible, PCCC, Sanders</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Sources: Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sunrise Movement, Twitter, news reports, ABC News</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">And some of these were pretty big wins. For instance, after Rep. Mike Doyle announced his intention not to run for reelection in Pennsylvania’s safely Democratic 12th Congressional District, most progressive groups lined up behind state Rep. Summer Lee. As a result, Lee edged out Doyle’s chosen successor by less than 1 point. Likewise, in Wisconsin’s U.S. Senate race, progressive-backed Lt. Gov. Mandela Barnes was such a formidable candidate that his closest rivals could not gain traction and <a href="https://www.wpr.org/once-competitive-race-wisconsins-democratic-u-s-senate-primary-all-decided" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropped out one by one</a>. That eventually led to his primary coronation (though it remains to be seen whether he will win the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">general election in November</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, progressives also won fewer of these primaries than they did in 2020. That year, their win rate in incumbent-less primaries was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/progressive-groups-are-getting-more-selective-in-targeting-incumbents-is-it-working/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a robust 69 percent</a> (22 wins in 32 tries). Part of the decline could be because of the emergence of a well-funded opposition mobilizing against them. For example, progressives endorsed two congressional candidates in North Carolina, former state Sen. Erica Smith and Durham County Commissioner Nida Allam, who failed to win their primaries. In both those elections, the same foe stepped up to block them: the <a href="https://businessnc.com/new-aipac-money-boosting-don-davis-valerie-foushee-campaigns/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">United Democracy Project</a>, a pro-Israel super PAC funded by the American Israel Public Affairs Committee. The United Democracy Project spent <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00799031/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly $24.3 million</a> this election cycle helping to elect moderate Democrats over progressives, with their biggest outlay coming on behalf of former Prince George’s County State’s Attorney Glenn Ivey over former Rep. Donna Edwards in Maryland’s 4th Congressional District.<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Edwards is ideologically progressive, interestingly, none of the seven progressive entities we tracked endorsed her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a> The super PAC’s efforts were not always successful — it also spent heavily against Lee, for example — but it did win more races it got involved in than progressives did: seven out of nine, or 78 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Similarly, progressives’ win rate was far lower than the win rate of candidates supported by the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, the official House campaign arm of the Democratic Party. All 18 candidates who were put on the DCCC’s “<a href="https://redtoblue.dccc.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Red to Blue</a>” list before their primaries advanced to the general election.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Governors Association does not endorse in open-seat primaries, and in a departure from past practice, nor did the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee this cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a></p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>The establishment wing of the party decides</h2>
 <p>How candidates supported by the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee or United Democracy Project fared in the 2022 Democratic House primaries without an incumbent on the ballot</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="conroy-rakich.progressives.3"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="3"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Supported by…</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Result</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">DCCC</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">UDP</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Jevin D. Hodge</td>
 <td>AZ-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Rudy Salas</td>
 <td>CA-22</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jay F. Chen</td>
 <td>CA-45</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Brittany Pettersen</td>
 <td>CO-07</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Yadira Caraveo</td>
 <td>CO-08</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Annette Taddeo</td>
 <td>FL-27</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Christina Bohannan</td>
 <td>IA-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Liz Mathis</td>
 <td>IA-02</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nikki Budzinski</td>
 <td>IL-13</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Glenn Ivey</td>
 <td>MD-04</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hillary Scholten</td>
 <td>MI-03</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Adam Hollier</td>
 <td>MI-13</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Don Davis</td>
 <td>NC-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Valerie Foushee</td>
 <td>NC-04</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Gabriel Vasquez</td>
 <td>NM-02</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Bridget Fleming</td>
 <td>NY-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jackie Gordon</td>
 <td>NY-02</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Max N. Rose</td>
 <td>NY-11</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pat Ryan</td>
 <td>NY-18</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Francis Conole</td>
 <td>NY-22</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Greg Landsman</td>
 <td>OH-01</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Emilia Sykes</td>
 <td>OH-13</td>
 <td><span>✓ Won</span></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr><tr><td>Steve Irwin</td>
 <td>PA-12</td>
 <td><span>✗ Lost</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>The United Democracy Project also opposed CA-42 candidate Cristina Garcia (who lost) but did not explicitly support any of her opponents.</p>
 <p>Sources: DCCC, OpenSecrets, ABC News</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, the party went head-to-head against progressives only once: in New York’s 11th Congressional District, where former Rep. Max Rose defeated Army veteran Brittany Ramos DeBarros. Ramos DeBarros was endorsed by Indivisible, Our Revolution and the PCCC. In fact, 13 of the DCCC’s Red to Blue candidates faced no Democratic opposition in their primaries. This is a good reminder that progressive and establishment candidates aren’t necessarily in opposition. </p>



<h4><strong>Different progressive groups have different strategies</strong></h4>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also important to remember that not all progressive groups are the same. Some groups and leaders still see the value in endorsing a longer-shot candidate with little chance of winning to influence agenda-setting or remind more establishment candidates that their party’s tent is big. Others, by contrast, are more strategic, hoping to funnel their resources into the races they feel they have the best chance of winning. As a result, certain progressive endorsers have better records than others. </p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>Which progressive group or leader has the best endorsement record?</h2>
 <p>Number of candidates endorsed by progressive groups and figures in the 2022 Democratic primaries for Senate, House and governor without an incumbent on the ballot, and how often the candidates won</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="conroy-rakich.progressives.4"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Endorser</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Endorsements</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Wins</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Win Rate</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Justice Democrats</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">100%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Sen. Bernie Sanders</td>
 <td>10</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>80</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>75</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Indivisible</td>
 <td>12</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>67</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Sunrise Movement</td>
 <td>5</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>60</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Our Revolution</td>
 <td>12</td>
 <td>7</td>
 <td>58</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Progressive Change Campaign Committee</td>
 <td>11</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>36</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Sources: Indivisible, Justice Democrats, Our Revolution, PCCC, Sunrise Movement, Twitter, news reports, ABC News</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, Justice Democrats have a 100 percent win rate in incumbent-less primaries (three for three), up from 67 percent in 2020 (two for three) and a marked improvement from 2018 (32 percent), when they endorsed more broadly (50 candidates). As <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/progressive-groups-are-getting-more-selective-in-targeting-incumbents-is-it-working/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we wrote in 2020</a>, of all the progressive groups emerging since 2016, Justice Democrats, in particular, seem most targeted in their recruitment efforts and deliberate about their endorsements, which helps explain their success. Ocasio-Cortez (three for four) and the Sunrise Movement (three for five) also succeeded with limited endorsement strategies.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of the progressives who were a bit freer with their endorsements, Sanders did the best with an 80 percent win rate in incumbent-less primaries (eight for 10), up from 75 percent in 2020 (six for eight) and 56 percent in 2018 (five for nine). This could reflect Sanders’s status as the godfather of the party’s progressive wing, but given the growth in his <em>own</em> win rate, it could be the product of a shrewder endorsement strategy. Finally, the PCCC was the only progressive endorser we looked at with a losing record (36 percent, or four for 11).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The 2022 primaries continued to display all the factors working against progressives — factors that have kept the soul of the Democratic Party fairly establishment-friendly. But it’s also important to remember that progressives are playing the long game. They may not have won as often as their opponents. Still, many <em>did</em> win their primaries and will join a growing number <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/greg-casar-summer-lee-delia-ramirez-house-progressives-1389261/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">already on the inside</a>. It may not be a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/congressional-republicans-left-office-in-droves-under-trump-just-how-conservative-are-their-replacements/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sudden transformation</a>, but progressives are slowly gaining strength within the Democratic Party with every passing election cycle.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 18:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1664302501259655</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Come To Our Politics Podcast Live Show!</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/come-to-our-politics-podcast-live-show/</link>
						<dc:creator>Chadwick Matlin</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Chadwick Matlin</dc:creator>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Housekeeping</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" name="">FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</a></p>
						
													<h1>Come To Our Politics Podcast Live Show!</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/chadwick-matlin/" title="" rel="author">Chadwick Matlin</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 27, 2022, at 11:55 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="538-Live-Pod-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/538-Live-Pod-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/538-Live-Pod-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/538-Live-Pod-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/538-Live-Pod-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
						
		</figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">After a couple of years stuck inside our makeshift home studios, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a> is finally going back on the road. We’ll be in Washington, D.C., for a live show on Tuesday, Oct. 25. Nate Silver will be there! Galen Druke will be there! Nathaniel Rakich will be there! Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux will be there! Will <em>you</em> be there?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Topics will include the latest odds for Democrats and Republicans headed into the midterms, how the current political environment has upended expectations, why this year’s election could be historic and much more. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The live podcast show will take place at Sixth &amp; I at 7 p.m. Eastern. In-person and virtual tickets are available. For <a href="https://www.sixthandi.org/event/fivethirtyeight-elections-podcast-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tickets and more information</a>, check out Sixth &amp; I’s events page. Hope to see you there!</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 16:55:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1664298001244343</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Why Biden’s Unpopularity Doesn’t Seem To Be Tanking Democrats</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-bidens-unpopularity-doesnt-seem-to-be-tanking-democrats/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Latino Voters</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<category>Senate</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-bidens-unpopularity-doesnt-seem-to-be-tanking-democrats/">
	<div data-podcast-id="344896" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Why Biden's Unpopularity Doesn't Seem To Be Tanking Democrats">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP2153798394.mp3?updated=1664229846">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">A president’s approval rating is traditionally tied to how his party performs in a midterm election, but Democrats have been outpacing President Biden in the polls for months. In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses how Biden’s approval rating may impact the midterm election and how the Democrats’ performance in November could influence the president’s 2024 reelection plans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The team also debates whether <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.axios.com/2022/09/22/midterm-elections-immigration-abortion" target="_blank">tracking Google search terms over time</a> is a better barometer than traditional polling when it comes to understanding the issues shaping American voting patterns. Lastly, politics reporter Alex Samuels and visual journalist Elena Mejía break down <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-black-americans-reshaped-politics-in-georgia/" target="_blank">their reporting</a> on how Black voters are changing the political landscape of Georgia.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 23:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1664230501972270</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Black Americans Reshaped Politics In Georgia</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-black-americans-reshaped-politics-in-georgia/</link>
						<dc:creator>Elena Mejía</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Elena Mejía and Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Atlanta</category>
			<category>Black Voters</category>
			<category>Georgia Politics</category>
			<category>Jon Ossoff</category>
			<category>Raphael Warnock</category>
			<category>Stacey Abrams</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Black Americans Reshaped Politics In Georgia</h1>
																	</div>

					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="GA-BLACK-VOTERS-topper" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GA-BLACK-VOTERS-topper.png?w=1024" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GA-BLACK-VOTERS-topper.png?w=1024" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GA-BLACK-VOTERS-topper.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GA-BLACK-VOTERS-topper.png?w=2048 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

							<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
									</figcaption></figure></div>

						<div>
				<div>
											<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/elena-mejia-lutz/" title="" rel="author">Elena Mejía and Alex Samuels</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Elena Mejía and Alex Samuels</a></p>
															<p>
						<time>
							Sep. 26, 2022, at 6:00 AM						</time></p>

				</div>
				<div>
									</div> 
			</div>
			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">In the 2020 election cycle, Democrats’ decades-long dream of winning Georgia finally became a reality. The state voted for a Democrat, Joe Biden, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/joe-biden-wins-georgia-flipping-state-democrats-74308658" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the presidential race</a> for the <a href="https://www.270towin.com/states/Georgia" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first time since 1992</a>, and it elected <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/odds-georgia-democrats-make-history-senate-runoffs/story?id=75095109" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two Democrats to the U.S. Senate</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Looking back, it’s hard to pinpoint what turned Georgia blue. Was it antipathy toward then-President Donald Trump? After all, anti-Trump sentiment among Democrats was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2018/09/17/democrats-are-twice-likely-republicans-name-trump-reason-their-pick-congressional-elections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">particularly high</a> in 2018 and 2020. Then again, the wheels for a Democratic takeover were already set in motion when the party’s gubernatorial nominee, Stacey Abrams, pioneered a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/georgia-democrats-may-have-found-their-own-southern-strategy-a-black-centric-campaign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new playbook focused on Black voters</a> in 2018, something that nearly won her the governorship that year and motivated more Georgians to vote blue in 2020 and 2021.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, a lot of what happened in 2020 can be <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/research/a-new-great-migration-is-bringing-black-americans-back-to-the-south/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">credited to Black voters</a>. In the prior two decades, Georgia slowly tilted toward Democrats, in large part because of an influx of Black Americans moving back to the South since the 1970s, a <a href="https://www.history.com/topics/black-history/great-migration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reversal of the Great Migration</a> that started in the 1910s. This trend has been particularly pronounced in Georgia. More than any other state, it has seen the biggest increase in its share of Black<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defined throughout this article as single-race and not Hispanic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> Americans 18 years or older.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1360" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-desktop.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-desktop.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-desktop.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-desktop.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1808" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-mobile.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_1-mobile.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In other words, new Black voters in the state — and their participation in recent elections — have helped the Peach State make history, and a continuation of that trend could significantly shift the balance of power toward Democrats in competitive statewide races there this year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Not only do you have a higher percentage of Black people coming in, but they are geographically dispersed. And they’re largely voting for Democrats. So, from a political perspective, the map is changing every day. I wouldn’t necessarily call Georgia a blue state, but it certainly is purple, and it can go blue during any given election,” said Andre Perry, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s 2022 election forecast,<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Senate race is a toss-up</a>, while the governor’s race is <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more squarely in Republican Gov. Brian Kemp’s column</a>. Still, though, in a state that has changed so much in the past 20-odd years, a lot may come down to how many — and if — Black voting-age Georgians cast their ballots.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, both parties have made an intentional effort to reach Black voters this year. Abrams’s campaign, for instance, has hosted conversations called “Stacey and the Fellas” to <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/richardfowler/2022/09/12/stacy-abrams-talks-georgia--gubernatorial-race-and-expanding-the-electorate-days-before-the-midterms/?sh=52bd6f964076" target="_blank" rel="noopener">engage Black men</a> in the state. And in an August campaign event, <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/politics-blog/the-jolt-stacey-abrams-if-black-men-vote-for-me-ill-win-georgia/RSMN2D6JNNG2VBENLYE6H7COAM/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">she bluntly explained why</a>: “If Black men vote for me, I’ll win Georgia.” But Spencer Crew, a professor of history at George Mason University, told us it’s clear that Republicans are also trying to appeal to Black voters. For example, prominent Republicans’ decision to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/24/us/politics/hershel-walker-georgia-senate.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">back former NFL star Herschel Walker</a>, a Black man, to challenge Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock, also a Black man, is “a recognition from the party that Black voters are important and that they’re trying to figure out ways to tap into that electorate.” It’s possible there will be an opening for Republicans, too, as Black voters have <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/biden-falling-poll-numbers-georgia/2021/10/10/3606c99e-2002-11ec-8200-5e3fd4c49f5e_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">soured on Biden</a> and a renowned celebrity like Walker could be serious competition.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But either party’s success will likely hinge on how they perform in Georgia’s capital city, Atlanta. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Case in point: In 2020, the counties in Atlanta’s metro areas<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defined as U.S. Census core-based statistical areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a> that saw the biggest increases in the number of Black Americans casting their ballots also saw some of the strongest shifts toward Biden and were key to helping him win. About 32 percent — or over 136,000 — more Black voters showed up in 2020 than in 2016, when Democratic presidential nominee Hillary Clinton was on the ballot.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1066" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-desktop.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-desktop.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-desktop.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-desktop.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1558" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-mobile.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_2-mobile.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">These shifts have been a long time coming. Since 2000, the growth in Atlanta’s Black voting-age population has been close to four times as fast as the growth of its white<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defined throughout this article as single-race and not Hispanic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> voting-age population. Moreover, the city’s surrounding metro area has been a center of Black voting-age population growth in the U.S., with close to 700,000 more Black Americans 18 years old or over calling the Atlanta area home since 2000. Put another way, this 6-percentage-point increase in the area’s Black voting-age population has been a pivotal factor in its politics.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“For the Black community, Atlanta is clearly an attractive place in the South to go live. And clearly that’s impacting the political environment in and around the city as well and the surrounding suburbs,” Crew said. The election of two Democratic senators following a very close race for governor “shows that the state’s demographics are changing and the organizing of Black voters is shifting the balance of power.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Cobb and Gwinnett counties, the Atlanta area’s most-populated urban counties<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on FiveThirtyEight’s urbanization index, calculated as the natural logarithm of the average number of people living within a 5-mile radius of a given resident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> after Fulton, have grown by over 200,000 Black Americans of voting age in 20 years. In 2000, the two counties were heavily Republican and had an average vote-share margin of R+27 in that presidential election. But by 2020, the average vote share had swung 16 points toward Democrats. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1126" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-desktop.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-desktop.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-desktop.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-desktop.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="2408" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-mobile.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_3-mobile.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, it wasn’t until Trump ran for president in 2016 that Cobb, Gwinnett and Henry, one of Atlanta’s largest suburbs, flipped blue, even though the Black electorate had already been changing. And some counties, like Fulton, haven’t seen sharp increases in Black voters but have still moved to the left. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s true that racial demographics alone cannot tell us everything about Georgia’s political landscape. Educational attainment has also been <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-suburbs-have-shifted-blue/?ex_cid=story-twitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a driving factor</a>. It all comes down to whether these factors are reflected in who turns out. We can see this in the suburbs, which were simply vital for Biden in 2020, when he won Georgia by close to 12,000 votes. As the chart below shows, Democrats’ biggest suburban gains in vote margin from 2016 happened in counties where Black voters turned out in high numbers, underscoring the importance of Black suburban voters.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="852" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-desktop.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-desktop.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-desktop.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-desktop.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1058" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-mobile.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_4-mobile.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The reversal of the Great Migration in recent decades has been <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/research/a-new-great-migration-is-bringing-black-americans-back-to-the-south" target="_blank" rel="noopener">propelled largely by young, college-educated Black Americans</a>, whose votes were key to Biden’s winning Atlanta, which was in turn important to his success in the state overall: 60 percent of Georgia’s electorate came from the capital city’s metro area.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Those middle-income Black people who truly fit the profile of the ‘suburban mom or dad’ like to see leaders who look like them,” said Perry, of Brookings. “So they’re electing Black people in the counties and municipalities they’re moving into. So there is also a power shift that’s going on at the local level that can bubble up to affect statewide races.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s no question, then, that Black voters have transformed Georgia’s electorate and put it at the forefront of southern Black political might. This is especially true in the state’s suburbs, which have gotten <em>really</em> competitive. Most suburbs in Atlanta have shifted toward Democrats by 31 points or so in 20 years and have gained, on average, more than 315,000 voting-age Black Americans, far outpacing the growth of the white voting-age population by 200,000. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“White voters are leaving the suburbs, and Black Americans are moving into the state’s cities and suburbs,” said William Frey, a demographer and senior fellow at the Brookings Institution. “And you’re seeing that big time in Atlanta, which is essentially a prototype of what the Black population can do in terms of changing not only the demography but also the <em>political </em>demography of different parts of the state.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Frey told FiveThirtyEight that the white population has declined since 2016, especially in the Atlanta metropolitan area. Henry County, for example, lost nearly 13,500 white people while gaining more than 30,000 Black people between 2016 and 2021. “There are several counties that have had absolute declines of their white population and gains of [their] Black one, like Gwinnett and Cobb counties,” he said. This, according to Frey, suggests a significant share of the state’s white voters are moving out of the suburbs and urban areas and into more rural parts of the state.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Keneshia Grant, a professor of political science at Howard University, went one step further describing what may happen if the rate of Black people moving into Atlanta remains high, saying there could be “a tipping point at which the number of people living in these metropolitan areas or metropolitan-adjacent areas will be high enough to overcome the rural areas.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Consider what happened in Georgia in the last presidential and Senate elections, particularly Warnock’s defeat of Republican Kelly Loeffler in the Senate runoffs. His win was due, in part, to almost every single suburb in the state <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-democrats-won-the-georgia-runoffs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shifting further to the left</a> from the November 2020 presidential election, with nearly 92 percent of November’s Black voters turning out again in January 2021 for the runoffs, but Warnock also benefited from more Republican-heavy parts of the state <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-2021s-biggest-upset-elections-tell-us-about-the-losing-parties/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not turning out to vote</a>. Both he and Jon Ossoff, the other Democrat who won in the Senate runoffs, improved on Biden’s margins, especially in counties with the largest share of Black voters.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1316" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-desktop-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-desktop-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-desktop-1.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-desktop-1.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1772" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-mobile-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-mobile-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-mobile-1.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mejia.samuels.BLACK-VOTERS-GA.0926_5-mobile-1.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Per the FiveThirtyEight forecast, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most U.S. House races</a> in the Peach State aren’t that competitive this year. But, once again, the suburbs are likely to be important for both parties as they fight for control of the U.S. Senate. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to Perry, there’s a good chance that having multiple Black candidates on the ticket will energize voters in ways they weren’t previously. Abrams’s close election in 2018, he added, also might encourage Black Democrats to go out and vote, even in a midterm year. Nationally, turnout among Black voters is <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1096123/voter-turnout-midterms-by-ethnicity-historical/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">typically lower</a> than that of voters overall in both midterm and general elections. But it’s possible Georgia may see higher turnout this year, as the state saw an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-high-turnout-in-georgia-doesnt-mean-voting-restrictions-havent-had-an-effect/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">uptick in early voting</a> in the May primaries. That said, it’s still <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-high-turnout-in-georgia-doesnt-mean-voting-restrictions-havent-had-an-effect/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">too early to know</a> how the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-georgias-new-voting-law-is-such-a-big-deal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">restrictive voting law</a> Georgia recently passed will affect turnout in November.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But don’t miss the forest for the trees. That higher early-voting turnout in the Georgia primaries was among <a href="https://sos.ga.gov/news/georgia-election-law-results-record-early-voting-turnout" target="_blank" rel="noopener">both Democrats <em>and </em>Republicans</a>. At this point, it doesn’t seem as if Republicans have made inroads with Black voters in the state, as a Sept. 8-12 poll from <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3855" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac University</a> found that Black likely voters overwhelmingly support Abrams (91 percent) and Warnock (92 percent) over their GOP opponents. But the overall toplines show just how competitive these statewide races are: The gubernatorial race showed Abrams behind Kemp by just 2 points, while the Senate matchup had Warnock leading Walker 52 percent to 46 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, greater turnout among Black voters won’t guarantee Democratic victories up and down the ballot, as a lot of other factors are at play in Georgia. But as Perry told FiveThirtyEight, recent Democratic victories in the state have also energized Black voters. “Once you start getting a few people elected and get some statewide wins under your belt, then you start believing that you belong and that those seats are yours,” Perry said. “There is a palpable empowerment that Black people are feeling in Georgia like they’ve never felt before.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/politics-podcast-time-start-worrying-polls-fivethirtyeight-89978501</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1664190001591244</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We Fixed An Error In Our Deluxe Midterm Forecast </title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-fixed-an-error-in-our-deluxe-midterms-forecast/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Election Forecast</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>We Fixed An Error In Our Deluxe Midterm Forecast</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 23, 2022, at 8:30 PM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
				
			</span>

			
			
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The Deluxe version of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight midterm forecast</a> just shifted slightly, but it’s not because of anything that happened in politics. Rather, it’s because we identified — and fixed — an error related to missing data that was leading to incorrect odds for several Senate, House and gubernatorial races. We wanted to take some time to explain what happened, how we identified it and the effect the correction had.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Thursday, <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sabato’s Crystal Ball</a> — one of three election forecasters whose race ratings factor into the Deluxe version of the FiveThirtyEight midterm forecast — <a href="https://twitter.com/kkondik/status/1573028316981886977?s=20&amp;t=pYC6OhjJG8aZYBRDwMps1g" target="_blank" rel="noopener">moved the Ohio 9th Congressional District</a> from “toss-up” to “leans Democratic.” When we went to input this change into our forecast, though, we found that our spreadsheet of race ratings was missing any Crystal Ball rating for the Ohio 9th whatsoever. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Upon closer inspection, we discovered we were actually missing Crystal Ball ratings for dozens of races. We used to have this data, but a look back at old files shows it was accidentally deleted on June 30.<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can see a sudden change in our forecast odds on that date for &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/arizona/2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;certain races&lt;/a&gt;, but it went unnoticed because June 30 was the day we launched the forecast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>13</sup></a> (Ratings from the other expert race raters, <a href="http://www.insideelections.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Inside Elections</a> and the <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cook Political Report</a>, were unaffected.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Friday, we re-collected the Crystal Ball ratings data and added it back into the model — and the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Deluxe version of the forecast</a> has changed slightly as a result. (The Lite and Classic versions of the forecast, which don’t incorporate expert race ratings, remain unchanged.) Democrats’ overall odds of winning the House increased by 0.7 percentage points to 32-in-100, but their odds of winning the Senate decreased by 0.5 points to 70-in-100. More importantly, though, some individual races did shift significantly. Here’s every race whose odds changed by at least 1 percentage point.</p>


<div>

<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Several races shifted after we fixed a bug in our forecast</h2>
 <p>Every race where the odds of winning shifted by 1 percentage point or more after we added missing Sabato’s Crystal Ball ratings to the FiveThirtyEight Deluxe forecast</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.model-bug.1" data-expandable-rows="20">
 <thead>
 <tr aria-hidden="true">
 <td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Dem. Chance of Winning</th>
 <td colspan="1"></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Before</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">After</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Change</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>TX-15</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">41.3%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">55.9%</td>
 <td>+14.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NC-13</td>
 <td>45.6</td>
 <td>32.4</td>
 <td>-13.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>MI-03</td>
 <td>81.7</td>
 <td>68.9</td>
 <td>-12.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IA-03</td>
 <td>34.2</td>
 <td>46.1</td>
 <td>+11.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CO-08</td>
 <td>44.7</td>
 <td>33.0</td>
 <td>-11.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>WA-08</td>
 <td>75.8</td>
 <td>85.9</td>
 <td>+10.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NV-03</td>
 <td>64.9</td>
 <td>74.6</td>
 <td>+9.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>OR-05</td>
 <td>38.7</td>
 <td>46.6</td>
 <td>+7.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-13</td>
 <td>69.5</td>
 <td>77.3</td>
 <td>+7.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-19</td>
 <td>43.3</td>
 <td>50.9</td>
 <td>+7.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NH-01</td>
 <td>77.2</td>
 <td>84.8</td>
 <td>+7.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-45</td>
 <td>38.0</td>
 <td>30.4</td>
 <td>-7.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IN-01</td>
 <td>79.3</td>
 <td>86.3</td>
 <td>+7.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>TX-28</td>
 <td>76.8</td>
 <td>83.0</td>
 <td>+6.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>AK-AL</td>
 <td>35.2</td>
 <td>41.2</td>
 <td>+6.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-18</td>
 <td>62.5</td>
 <td>68.5</td>
 <td>+6.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>RI-02</td>
 <td>76.8</td>
 <td>82.3</td>
 <td>+5.5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NJ-07</td>
 <td>43.0</td>
 <td>37.7</td>
 <td>-5.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IL-13</td>
 <td>86.2</td>
 <td>90.6</td>
 <td>+4.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>MD-06</td>
 <td>66.8</td>
 <td>62.5</td>
 <td>-4.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-09</td>
 <td>77.8</td>
 <td>82.0</td>
 <td>+4.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-03</td>
 <td>77.2</td>
 <td>73.3</td>
 <td>-3.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CT-05</td>
 <td>77.6</td>
 <td>81.5</td>
 <td>+3.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-22</td>
 <td>54.2</td>
 <td>50.5</td>
 <td>-3.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CT-02</td>
 <td>87.6</td>
 <td>84.3</td>
 <td>-3.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NE-02</td>
 <td>17.1</td>
 <td>14.0</td>
 <td>-3.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>TX-34</td>
 <td>81.1</td>
 <td>78.1</td>
 <td>-3.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CO-07</td>
 <td>88.1</td>
 <td>91.0</td>
 <td>+2.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NJ-03</td>
 <td>92.3</td>
 <td>89.5</td>
 <td>-2.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>MI-07</td>
 <td>78.8</td>
 <td>76.1</td>
 <td>-2.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>OH-09</td>
 <td>72.4</td>
 <td>74.8</td>
 <td>+2.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-41</td>
 <td>11.4</td>
 <td>13.7</td>
 <td>+2.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>OR-06</td>
 <td>72.7</td>
 <td>74.9</td>
 <td>+2.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>MI-08</td>
 <td>83.1</td>
 <td>81.0</td>
 <td>-2.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>WI Gov.</td>
 <td>67.8</td>
 <td>65.8</td>
 <td>-2.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>WI Sen.</td>
 <td>42.0</td>
 <td>39.9</td>
 <td>-2.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-01</td>
 <td>33.2</td>
 <td>31.2</td>
 <td>-2.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>AZ-04</td>
 <td>91.9</td>
 <td>93.8</td>
 <td>+2.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IA-02</td>
 <td>13.0</td>
 <td>11.1</td>
 <td>-1.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NY-17</td>
 <td>89.1</td>
 <td>87.2</td>
 <td>-1.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IL-14</td>
 <td>91.0</td>
 <td>89.2</td>
 <td>-1.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IA-01</td>
 <td>11.4</td>
 <td>9.9</td>
 <td>-1.5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>IL-11</td>
 <td>96.3</td>
 <td>94.9</td>
 <td>-1.5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>GA-02</td>
 <td>93.8</td>
 <td>95.2</td>
 <td>+1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NC-14</td>
 <td>97.4</td>
 <td>96.0</td>
 <td>-1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-25</td>
 <td>96.6</td>
 <td>95.3</td>
 <td>-1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>VA-02</td>
 <td>50.6</td>
 <td>49.3</td>
 <td>-1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NJ-05</td>
 <td>96.5</td>
 <td>95.2</td>
 <td>-1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>WA-03</td>
 <td>2.9</td>
 <td>4.2</td>
 <td>+1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>WI-03</td>
 <td>26.8</td>
 <td>25.6</td>
 <td>-1.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>AZ-02</td>
 <td>50.8</td>
 <td>49.6</td>
 <td>-1.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>TN-05</td>
 <td>3.8</td>
 <td>2.7</td>
 <td>-1.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>CA-49</td>
 <td>93.7</td>
 <td>92.6</td>
 <td>-1.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NH-02</td>
 <td>95.1</td>
 <td>94.0</td>
 <td>-1.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>NM-03</td>
 <td>97.2</td>
 <td>96.2</td>
 <td>-1.0</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <div><a>Show more rows</a></div>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">We know how much readers rely on our forecast to be as accurate as possible, and we’re aware that, for some people — politicians, campaign staffers and voters alike — the forecast represents something more than just a number on a page. So we’re taking steps to ensure this error doesn’t recur. We usually use an automated process to collect and update race ratings, but we’ve turned that off so that we can manually check all future ratings changes from all three election forecasters. And while we’re still unsure how the data got deleted, we are actively investigating to ensure we patch up any systematic problems in our workflow. We hope you’ll continue to use and trust our forecast.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (Sept. 23, 2022, 8:36 p.m.): </strong>An earlier version of this article transposed Democrats’ chances of winning the House and Senate. Democrats have a 32-in-100 chance of winning the House and a 70-in-100 chance of winning the Senate, not the other way around. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 01:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663983001358153</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Polls Still Do Not Show A GOP Bounceback</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-polls-still-do-not-show-a-gop-bounce-back/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Polls Still Do Not Show A GOP Bounceback</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 23, 2022, at 1:49 PM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0923-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0923-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0923-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0923-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0923-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-are-favored-to-win-the-house-but-not-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ever since we launched our election model in late June</a>, it has moved entirely in one direction: toward Democrats. Pretty much every week, they’ve either gained ground in our forecast or held steady. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This week has been more in the “held steady” category. In the Deluxe version of our model, Democrats’ chances of keeping the Senate are <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">71 percent</a>, while their chances of holding the House are <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">31 percent</a>. Neither number has meaningfully changed from a week ago.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As Democrats’ position has continually improved, I’ve tended to focus on <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-this-be-an-asterisk-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">optimistic scenarios for Democrats</a>. Frankly, I’ve been looking for an opportunity to reiterate why Republicans could still have a pretty good midterm. They are, after all, reasonably clear favorites to flip the House, and a 30 percent chance to flip the Senate is nothing to sneeze at, either. That 30 percent chance is <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2016-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pretty much the same one</a> our model gave to Donald Trump against Hillary Clinton on Election Day in 2016.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that Republicans <em>could win</em> doesn’t mean that their situation is <em>improving</em>. I’ve seen <a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/09/18/democrats-midterm-reality-check" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several</a> <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/senate-polls-tighten-border-crime-grow-issues-note/story?id=90201864" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent</a> <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/bcf24508-37b5-40e7-b976-2b9bb79c3720" target="_blank" rel="noopener">claims</a> about Republican momentum in the polls that I don’t think are yet justified in the evidence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s leave our probabilistic forecast aside for now and just look at the polls themselves. Specifically, we’ll look at what our polling averages say as I write this on Sept. 22 and how that compares to one month ago, on Aug. 22. A fair amount has happened since then: The White House <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2022/08/24/fact-sheet-president-biden-announces-student-loan-relief-for-borrowers-who-need-it-most/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced</a> its student loan forgiveness program on Aug. 24; there’s been some <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/13/business/markets-inflation-stocks.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fairly negative inflation news and other economic data</a>; Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis sent <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/14/politics/marthas-vineyard-massachusetts-migrants-planes/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">around 50 migrants to Martha’s Vineyard</a>; Russia is facing significant <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/14/world/europe/russia-retreat-northeast.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">setbacks in its war with Ukraine</a>; and campaigns are <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-spend-millions-tv-ads-midterms-why-doesnt-trump-2022-09-21/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">kicking into higher gear in many states</a> after Labor Day.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First up, the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic Congressional ballot</a>. Democrats currently lead by 1.9 percentage points in our average. That reflects continued improvement from Aug. 22, when they led by 0.4 percentage points.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Our generic ballot average, however, is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/heres-a-new-less-volatile-version-of-our-generic-ballot-tracker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">designed to be somewhat slow-moving</a> — so if there’s been a recent reversal in the improving electoral environment for Democrats, it may be slow to detect it. Our <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval average</a> is more aggressive, by contrast. As of Sept. 22 at 5 p.m. Eastern, Biden has a 42.5 percent approval rating and a 53.0 percent disapproval rating. That’s mediocre, although similar to where several other presidents have been in advance of their first midterm. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Nonetheless, those numbers are improved from Aug. 22, when Biden had a 40.9 approval rating against 54.3 percent disapproval.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What about individual Senate and gubernatorial races? FiveThirtyEight publishes <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/ohio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling averages in these races</a> once there are a sufficient number of polls. Technically speaking, these polling averages are calculated separately from the version used by our forecast model, which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">performs various fancy adjustments to the polls</a> (for instance, our model adjusts outdated polls based on changes in the generic ballot). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For the purposes of this article’s exercise, though, the comparative simplicity of our standalone polling averages should work well. So let’s look at all races where there have been a) at least two polls between the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Roe v. Wade on June 24<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;clearly seems to have been an inflection point in the race for Congress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>14</sup></a> and Aug. 22, and b) at least two polls between Aug. 22 and now. In these states, we have enough data to establish a post-Dobbs baseline and to see whether there’s been a meaningful shift. Eleven Senate races meet this criteria;<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I excluded Utah, where the race is between an independent and a Republican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> here is how the polling average has changed in each one:</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>How the polling in key Senate races has changed</h2>
 <p>Democratic margin in FiveThirtyEight polling average for key Senate races on Aug. 22 and Sept. 22</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.eu0922.1"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">FiveThirtyEight polling average as of …</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">8/22/22</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">9/22/22</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td>+8.3</td>
 <td>+7.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td>+10.0</td>
 <td>+9.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td>-2.7</td>
 <td>-3.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>+1.8</td>
 <td>+2.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>+3.7</td>
 <td>+0.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>+3.7</td>
 <td>+7.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td>+0.1</td>
 <td>-0.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td>+1.0</td>
 <td>-0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>+10.4</td>
 <td>+8.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Washington</td>
 <td>+12.9</td>
 <td>+10.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>+2.6</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Average</td>
 <td>+4.7</td>
 <td>+3.8</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Includes Senate races in which there were at least two polls conducted between June 24 and Aug. 22, and at least two polls conducted from Aug. 22 to Sept. 22. Utah, where the race is between an independent and a Republican, is not included.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">If you squint, you can see some movement toward Republicans. On Aug. 22, Democrats led by 4.7 percentage points in these races on average, and now they lead by 3.8 percentage points.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But few individual races have moved all that much. Republicans have gained at least a full percentage point in Florida, Nevada, Pennsylvania, Washington and Wisconsin, while Democrats have done so in New Hampshire.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Interestingly enough, this movement has often been in line with what the “fundamentals” in each race might have predicted. Most <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/senate-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expert groups</a> had rated races such as Wisconsin and Nevada as tossups, even though polls had shown Democrats ahead there. So this may just be reversion to the mean, given that neither race had been polled terribly often, rather than any actual shift in voter sentiment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, a look at gubernatorial races, using the same parameters as we did for the Senate races:</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>How the polling in key gubernatorial races has changed</h2>
 <p>Democratic margin in FiveThirtyEight polling average for key governor’s races on Aug. 22 and Sept. 22

 </p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.eu0922.2"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">FiveThirtyEight polling average as of …</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">8/22/22</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">9/22/22</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td>+3.3</td>
 <td>+2.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td>-6.6</td>
 <td>-5.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>-5.7</td>
 <td>-5.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Massachusetts</td>
 <td>+29.5</td>
 <td>+25.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Michigan</td>
 <td>+13.2</td>
 <td>+12.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Minnesota</td>
 <td>+4.8</td>
 <td>+9.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>+2.1</td>
 <td>+1.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>-26.2</td>
 <td>-19.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New York</td>
 <td>+18.4</td>
 <td>+13.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td>-14.5</td>
 <td>-15.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>+8.6</td>
 <td>+10.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Texas</td>
 <td>-8.9</td>
 <td>-7.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>-0.4</td>
 <td>+2.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Average</td>
 <td>+1.4</td>
 <td>+1.9</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Includes gubernatorial races in which there were at least two polls conducted between June 24 and Aug. 22, and at least two polls conducted from Aug. 22 to Sept. 22.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">These don’t show any shift toward Republicans. On average, Democrats led by 1.4 percentage points on Aug. 22, and they lead by 1.9 percentage points now. Some individual races have changed, of course, but these moves have been in either direction. Democrats have gained at least a percentage point in Florida, Minnesota, New Hampshire, Pennsylvania, Texas and Wisconsin, while Republicans have done so in Arizona, Michigan, Massachusetts and New York.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We could go race by race and debate which of these shifts are “real” and which reflect noisy or low-quality polling. But that’s beside the point, which is that there hasn’t been any <em>systematic </em>rebound by Republicans. In the 24 gubernatorial and Senate races listed here, Democrats led by an average of 2.9 percentage points on Aug. 22, and they lead by 2.8 percentage points now. There’s been essentially no change, in other words.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, that may not be true in the future. It may be too soon to see the impact of recent news stories in the polls. I tend to think DeSantis’s stunt in sending migrants to Massachusetts will engender more of a reaction on cable news and on Twitter than it will necessarily matter to normal swing voters. But a sustained focus on immigration could <a href="https://twitter.com/richardmskinner/status/1572597839275991042?s=20&amp;t=igJI5MbN_n9Ka7AIwGNYpw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">be worse for Democrats</a> than one on other issues such as abortion. And as I <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-the-polls-overestimate-democrats-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wrote last week</a>, our model does expect the political environment to get slightly better for Republicans between now and November.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Mostly, though, we’ve reached that part of the election cycle where you ought to be wary of media narratives about which party has “momentum.” There are a lot of competitive elections this cycle, and since Labor Day, we’ve started to see a lot more polling. It’s very, very easy to cherry-pick your way into a story that fits your preconceived notions about the race. But when there’s a major, nationwide shift in the race — as there was toward Democrats after the Dobbs decision — you usually don’t have to squint to see it.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 18:49:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663956001211293</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Is Social Media Turning Us Into Political Extremists?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-is-social-media-turning-us-into-political-extremists/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Extremism</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Misinformation</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Social Media</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-is-social-media-turning-us-into-political-extremists/">
	<div data-podcast-id="344708" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Is Social Media Turning Us Into Political Extremists?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP1592241193.mp3?updated=1663886248">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">What effect is social media having on our politics and society more broadly? According to critics, we’re living through an unregulated era of social media that will one day look as outdated as tobacco did in its pre-regulation era.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In his new book, “<a href="https://www.littlebrown.com/titles/max-fisher/the-chaos-machine/9780316703314/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Chaos Machine: The Inside Story of How Social Media Rewired Our Minds and Our World</a>” New York Times reporter Max Fisher explores how social media impacts the psychology of its users and changes how people think, behave and communicate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Galen Druke talks to Fisher about his book and why he believes this is leading to social and political crises in the U.S. and around the world.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 15:18:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663947001160956</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Americans Feel About Republican Governors Sending Migrants To Blue Cities</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-americans-feel-about-republican-governors-sending-migrants-to-blue-cities/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>American Issues</category>
			<category>Immigration</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Americans Feel About Republican Governors Sending Migrants To Blue Cities</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 23, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0923_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0923_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0923_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0923_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0923_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/?s=pollapalooza" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">When nearly 50 migrants arrived unexpectedly in Martha’s Vineyard, Massachusetts, last week, it rekindled the ever-smoldering debate around immigration in America. This was exactly what Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis said he <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2022/09/15/marthas-vineyard-desantis-migrants-venezuela/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">intended</a> when his administration chartered the two flights to relocate the migrants, at least <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/09/17/1123629690/migrants-sent-to-marthas-vineyard-are-being-rehoused-in-cape-cod" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some of whom were asylum seekers</a>. This move followed in the footsteps of Texas Gov. Greg Abbott, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/08/19/us/texas-migrants-bus-washington-dc-new-york/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whose administration has been relocating migrants</a> to liberal places like New York City and Washington, D.C., for months. And just as Americans were divided over these specific actions, they continue to be split on the issue of immigration more broadly — and often hold surprising and contradictory views. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/xeu4apb94g/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll from The Economist/YouGov</a> fielded in the days after the Martha’s Vineyard flights found that Americans were evenly split over whether or not they approved of Texas and Florida sending undocumented immigrants to northern cities without giving those cities notice: Forty-four percent “somewhat” or “strongly” approved, while 44 percent “somewhat” or “strongly” disapproved (12 percent were not sure). Democrats were more likely to disapprove of the relocation efforts, with 71 percent disapproving, while three-quarters of Republicans approved. A <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/09/21/gop-governors-interstate-migrant-maneuvers-divide-voters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll from Politico/Morning Consult</a> found that 42 percent of registered voters said it was appropriate that “some Republican governors from states along the U.S.-Mexico border have been sending thousands of migrants to liberal states and cities in the U.S.,” with another 41 percent saying it was inappropriate. There wasn’t a strong consensus on either side of the political aisle, however. Fifty-nine percent of Democrats said it was inappropriate, and 66 percent of Republicans said it was appropriate, but a quarter of Democrats and 1 in 5 Republicans took the alternate view. And <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/09/19/dcebc/2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in a separate poll from YouGov</a>, Americans were likewise divided when asked whether they approved or disapproved of Southern Republican governors sending undocumented migrants to Democratic-controlled cities without giving those cities notice. This division held even in different regions of the country. About 41 percent of Americans in each listed region (Northeast, Midwest, South and West) approved of these moves from GOP governors, and roughly 44 percent in each region disapproved.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Americans’ views on this specific news story reflect broader divides around immigration. When asked <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/08/18/most-americans-see-border-situation-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in an August Economist/YouGov poll</a> whether immigrants who are in the U.S. illegally should be allowed to stay and apply for citizenship, or whether they should be required to leave the country, Americans were split 44 percent to 41 percent. They were similarly divided in other <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/09/19/dcebc/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov data</a> from this week: Thirty-seven percent of Americans said undocumented immigrants were treated “fairly,” and 38 percent said “unfairly.” And in <a href="https://echeloninsights.com/in-the-news/april-22-omnibus-immigration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an April survey from Republican pollster Echelon Insights</a>, likely voters were evenly split on a number of immigration-related questions. Thirty percent said immigration should stay at its current level, while 45 percent said it should be decreased and 15 percent said it should be increased. Meanwhile, 39 percent strongly supported building a wall along the U.S.-Mexico border, while 32 percent strongly opposed it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Where Americans find consensus on immigration is in the belief that illegal immigration is a problem in the first place. In <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/08/18/most-americans-see-border-situation-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that August Economist/YouGov poll</a>, 59 percent of Americans said the current situation at the U.S.-Mexico border is a crisis. While Republicans were very likely to say so (81 percent did), a plurality of Democrats (45 percent) agreed the situation is a crisis. A majority of Americans also said it was “completely” or “somewhat” true that the U.S. is experiencing an “invasion” at its southern border, according to <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/npr-immigration-perceptions-august-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an NPR/Ipsos poll conducted in July</a>. At the same time, in <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/09/19/most-americans-express-support-for-taking-in-refugees-but-opinions-vary-by-party-and-other-factors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an August Pew Research Center survey</a>, a sizable majority of Americans (72 percent) said taking in refugees should be a “very” or “somewhat” important goal for U.S. immigration policy, and this is true for both Democrats (85 percent) and Republicans (58 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Concerns about immigration are clearly shared among Americans of all political persuasions, and the recent relocation of migrants to Martha’s Vineyard has helped bring it back into focus. While the percentage has gone down over time, a majority of Americans “mostly” or “completely” agreed with the statement that “the current increase of migrants attempting to enter the United States on the southern border due to the fact that Joe Biden was elected president,” according to <a href="https://static.foxnews.com/foxnews.com/content/uploads/2022/06/Fox_June-10-13-2022_Complete_National_Topline_June-30-Release.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a June Fox News/Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Company Research poll</a>. And in <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/first-read/poll-gop-winning-economy-immigration-democrats-are-ahead-abortion-heal-rcna48297" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an NBC News/Hart Research Associates/Public Opinion Strategies survey conducted earlier this month</a>, a majority of registered voters (56 percent) said the Republican Party better handles border security, and a plurality (46 percent) preferred the GOP on immigration. It’s possible Republicans like DeSantis are doing everything they can to put the issue front and center just weeks away from the midterm elections in an attempt to change the channel from issues less favorable to Republicans, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-keep-failing-to-pass-abortion-bans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">like abortion</a>.</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites </strong></h2>



<ul><li>A recent <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/congress-biden-age-poll-term-limits-medical-checks-poll-2022-9">Insider/Morning Consult poll</a> found that almost half of Americans (41 percent) thought the age of our political leaders, such as the president and those in Congress and on the Supreme Court, is a major problem, and another 37 percent considered it a minor one — a breakdown that remained fairly consistent across political leanings. Seventy-five percent of Americans were in favor of introducing age maximums for members of Congress, too. Additionally, a majority agreed that a president should “definitely” undergo a physical and mental assessment to take office, with Americans ages 55 to 64 (71 percent) most likely to say so. </li><li>Older Americans were more likely than younger Americans to say that formerly incarcerated people who have served their prison sentence deserve to be considered for jobs, according to a Sept. 16 <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/legal/survey-results/daily/2022/09/16/0d1e1/1">YouGov survey</a>. Eighty-two percent of adults ages 65 and older agreed, compared with 67 percent of those ages 18 to 29. <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/legal/survey-results/daily/2022/09/16/0d1e1/2">Additional data from YouGov</a> also found that nearly all Americans over 65 (93 percent) said that it’s at least somewhat harder for formerly incarcerated individuals to find employment, while about three-quarters of adults ages 18 to 29. </li><li>Americans were down on both capitalism and socialism, <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/09/19/modest-declines-in-positive-views-of-socialism-and-capitalism-in-u-s/">per a survey conducted by Pew Research Center</a> in August. Slightly more than half (57 percent) of Americans have a “very” or “somewhat” positive stance toward capitalism, which is down from 65 percent in May 2019. On the flip side, 36 percent of Americans today held a positive view of socialism, which is lower than the 42 percent who approved three years ago. Still, a higher share of adults (65 percent) agreed socialism at least somewhat helps people meet basic housing, health and food needs, compared with those who said the same about capitalism (47 percent). Meanwhile, 64 percent also said that capitalism could provide people with equal opportunities to be successful, while only 52 percent said the same about socialism. </li><li>A <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/entertainment/articles-reports/2022/09/14/half-of-americans-enjoy-true-crime-yougov-poll">YouGov poll</a> conducted Aug. 29-Sept. 5 found that half of Americans enjoy true crime content, a breakdown that constitutes a notably higher share of women (58 percent) than men (42 percent). The study also showed a gender breakdown in the who is engaging with more violent topics within the genre: Sixty percent of women reported ever consuming murder-related true crime, while only 43 percent of men said the same. One set of responses, in particular, to another question in the survey might help elucidate that breakdown: Seventy percent of women agreed that the genre helps listeners become “more vigilant and safety-conscious” in their own lives. </li></ul><h2><strong>Biden Approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> 42.5 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 53.0 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.5 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/strongtrust-in-institutions-is-eroding-on-both-sides-of-the-pond-and-the-queen-was-not-exempt-strong/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.3 percent approved and 53.1 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -10.8 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 40.9 percent and a disapproval rating of 54.3 percent, for a net approval rating of -13.4 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a> Democrats currently lead Republicans by 1.9 points (45.2 percent to 43.3 percent). A week ago, Democrats led by 1.4 points (44.8 percent to 43.4 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Democrats by 0.4 points (43.9 percent to 43.5 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663929001072666</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>More Democrats Than Ever Support The Palestinian Cause, And That’s Dividing The Party</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-israeli-palestinian-conflict-divide/</link>
						<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>Israel</category>
			<category>Palestine</category>
			<category>Palestinians</category>
			<category>Progressives</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>More Democrats Than Ever Support The Palestinian Cause, And That’s Dividing The Party</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Zoha Qamar</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 22, 2022, at 12:33 PM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Free Palestine rally in New York City" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1240695769-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1240695769-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1240695769-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1240695769-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>TAYFUN COSKUN / ANADOLU AGENCY / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Twenty years ago, Tallie Ben Daniel was a college student wandering the campus of the University of California, Santa Cruz, when she came across a bumper sticker that read “Free Palestine.” Born to an Israeli family in Los Angeles, Ben Daniel had never heard the phrase before. “I had zero context for what that meant. And I didn’t understand,” she recalled. “Free Palestine from what?” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Today, Ben Daniel is an advocate for Palestinian human rights. She’s currently the managing director of Jewish Voice for Peace, an organization that challenges the way the Israeli government treats Palestinians. But her past confusion makes sense against the backdrop of the early 2000s. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In general, U.S. support for Israel was a common, unquestioned stance on both sides of the aisle, while the aftermath of 9/11 only <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/09/09/1035418760/how-the-events-of-9-11-still-affect-the-israeli-palestinian-conflict" target="_blank" rel="noopener">deepened Americans’ rapport with Israel</a> from the lens of solidarity against terrorism claimed by Islamic extremists. Even among those concerned for the Palestinians, many <a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/oslo/etc/cron.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">clung to the fleeting optimism</a> that the Oslo Accords of the 1990s could yield a peaceful two-state solution for Israelis and Palestinians. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In 2001, when <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/350393/key-trends-views-israel-palestinians.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup polled</a> Americans on the Palestinian-Israeli conflict, views were clear and consistent: Only 16 percent of Americans sympathized more with the Palestinians, while 51 percent sympathized more with the Israelis. Back then, this wasn’t even a particularly partisan issue — only 18 percent of Democrats sympathized more with Palestinians. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Two decades later, though, the landscape has changed. The share of Americans with more sympathy toward the Palestinians has ticked up to 26 percent. And that support has more than doubled among Democrats: Today, 38 percent report feeling more sympathy for the Palestinians. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A confluence of factors over the past decade seems to be driving this shift. Social media has changed how war is witnessed across the globe — especially among young people — and a growing awareness of social inequities in the U.S. may be reshaping how some Americans perceive conflict internationally, too. But most of all, the Palestinian-Israeli question has become a topic that embodies an intra-party identity issue for Democrats, one that has increasingly pushed liberals to reconsider what constitutes progressive politics.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://abcnews.go.com/International/israel-gaza-conflict/story?id=24552237" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Summer 2014</a> marked one of the <a href="https://www.ochaopt.org/data/casualties" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most deadly episodes of violence in Gaza</a>. In May that year, Israel Defense Forces soldiers <a href="https://www.btselem.org/press_releases/20140612_autopsy_finds_nadim_nawarah_killed_by_live_ammunition" target="_blank" rel="noopener">killed two Palestinian teenagers</a>. In June, <a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v36/n15/mouin-rabbani/israel-mows-the-lawn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">three Israeli teenagers were kidnapped</a> while hitchhiking in the West Bank and ultimately killed, and the IDF launched a full-force defense operation in response. According to the <a href="https://www.ochaopt.org/content/key-figures-2014-hostilities" target="_blank" rel="noopener">United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs</a>, 73 Israelis were killed — 67 soldiers and six civilians. Meanwhile, 2,251 Palestinians were killed, 551 of them children. Those casualty numbers affected the way the world saw the conflict, and the narrative of justified self-defense that the IDF presented wasn’t universally accepted outside Israel, said Dov Waxman, director of the Y&amp;S Nazarian Center for Israel Studies at UCLA.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It’s really the last decade, during which so many events and shifts and factors have changed thoughts in the public domain,” Waxman said.” Indeed, myriad dynamics — for example, how U.S. social-justice movements drew parallels to the escalating violence of the 2010s and how Donald Trump’s allied stance toward Israel raised eyebrows during his presidency — have gradually moved the needle on how the American public views the Palestinians. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, what happened in 2014 was the first large-scale escalation in the age of widespread social media. In the years since, researchers have pointed to the ways in which social media has reframed how the international community observes war in real time, whether over the past decade with the <a href="https://cepr.org/multimedia/twitter-changes-how-media-reports-conflict" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Palestinians</a> or this year with the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/25/world/europe/ukraine-war-social-media.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ukrainians</a>. Whereas bumper stickers once spread messages locally, hashtags were now sending information buzzing around the globe. Until then, most wide-scale information, particularly about life in Gaza, came through mainstream media outlets. Now, for the first time, people around the world were exposed and had access to <a href="https://www.voanews.com/a/gaza-social-media-amplifies-new-voice-in-mideast-conflict/1968253.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">firsthand accounts from Palestinians</a>, many of which challenged (or at least contextualized) the details reported by large outlets. Some posts also singled out headlines and language used by such publications, <a href="https://theintercept.com/2019/01/12/israel-palestine-conflict-news-headlines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accusing their framing</a> of the violence as unfairly neglecting the Palestinian struggle. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“That summer, it was just so clear, how disproportionate the violence was,” said Ben Daniel. “The Israeli government will often talk about their assaults as ‘it’s a war,’ but it became clear that there was only one side with a military.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Her change in perspective is indicative of how Americans’ opinions on the Palestinian-Israeli conflict have shifted, too — with change especially pronounced among younger Americans. According to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2022/05/26/modest-warming-in-u-s-views-on-israel-and-palestinians/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center data from March</a>, 61 percent of American adults under 30 have a favorable view of the Palestinian people, compared with 56 percent who have a favorable view of the Israeli people. Ben Daniel thinks it’s important that these young Americans have also been witnessing growing civil rights movements at home.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Younger Americans express warmest views of Palestinians" aria-label="Grouped Column Chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/RwdWD/6/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="474" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Around the same time, Black Lives Matter was having a resurgence. And alliances between folks at, say, Ferguson [Missouri] and Palestine shifted consciousness in general,” said Ben Daniel. She believes that the violence in Gaza in 2014 and the support of Black Lives Matter happening in tandem and underpinned by social media helped circulate comparisons to the conflict by paralleling police brutality in the U.S. with IDF tactics in Gaza.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, the Black Lives Matter movement, which formed following the <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/ABC_Univision/trayvon-martin-trials-stirred-racial-tensions/story?id=19671013" target="_blank" rel="noopener">July 2013 acquittal</a> of the neighborhood-watch volunteer who <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/george-zimmerman-return-jail-bail-revoked-trayvon-martin/story?id=16484963" target="_blank" rel="noopener">killed Trayvon Martin</a>, has aligned itself with the Palestinian cause. <a href="https://www.timesofisrael.com/palestinians-tweet-support-for-ferguson-protesters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In 2014</a> and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/jun/16/black-lives-matter-palestinian-struggle-us-left" target="_blank" rel="noopener">again in 2021</a>, pro-Palestinian activists and Black Lives Matter activists have demonstrated their support for each other on social media.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a growing share of Americans began confronting uncomfortable and embedded injustices in their own country, the parallel details in Palestinian accounts of systematic oppression contextualized a conflict halfway across the world in a new light. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This comparison has been moving. But it has also been controversial. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It can be a starting point for people new to the conflict, but I caution against taking the comparison too far. That’s ignoring a lot of more complicated dynamics and history,” said Laura Birnbaum, the national political director of J Street, a prominent pro-Israel advocacy group that supports a two-state solution. Comparing the BLM and pro-Palestine movements isn’t something everyone will see as fair, Birnbaum said. She and other supporters of Israel don’t think it’s reasonable to analogize Jews in Israel as white, slave-owning colonizers when the Jewish state exists because of the historical oppression of its people. And some still see Israel in a precarious position as the only non-Muslim-majority country in the Middle East, Waxman said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is another place where age may come into play. Whereas some older generations of Americans lived through the latter half of the 20th century, when Israel’s existence was not necessarily considered a guarantee, millennials and Gen Zers are more likely to view Israel as a strong nation with ample financial and military power, Waxman said. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the very least, the use of the BLM comparison shows how the framing of this conversation has changed. What was once a debate over the logistics of land division has now, for liberal Democrats, turned to a discussion about Palestinians’ human rights. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Liberal Democrats sympathize most with Palestinians" aria-label="Range Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Vl69Y/10/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="283" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">And that, Waxman said, helps explain why the pro-Palestine position has become a facet of progressive and Democratic identity. “In the past, supporting Israel was seen as aligned with or consistent with liberal values. And, increasingly, it’s seen as contradicting liberal beliefs and values,” he said. This shift has happened primarily among the most liberal Democrats. <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/390737/americans-pro-israel-though-palestinians-gain-support.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup</a> polling from February indicates that liberal Democrats sympathize more with Palestinians compared with Democrats as a whole, by 52 percent to 38 percent. Moderate and conservative members of the party still tend to sympathize more with Israelis. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And that is exactly what we’ve seen with a small but growing set of politicians. A <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/05/17/clinton-sanders-supporters-differ-sharply-on-u-s-global-role/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research survey from April 2016</a> showed a widening gap on this issue between supporters of Hillary Clinton and supporters of Sen. Bernie Sanders. Meanwhile, the most publicly pro-Palestinian members of Congress — Rep. Rashida Tlaib, who herself is Palestinian American, and Rep. Ilhan Omar, whose hijab renders her visibly Muslim — have also aligned themselves with the party’s progressive left arm. This divide between moderate and liberal Democrats on the Palestinian-Israeli conflict is evocative of recurring debates in the direction of the party <a href="https://apnews.com/article/democrats-divided-progressives-centrists-say-trust-gone-a3d66f83ddac9b18e607f46429dbc408" target="_blank" rel="noopener">across a host of issues</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And the schism occurring within the Democratic Party over Israel is only further facilitated by how staunchly Republicans have doubled down on their support. Conservatives are more sympathetic toward Israel than ever, and interestingly, evangelical Christians, who skew overwhelmingly Republican, report <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2013/10/03/more-white-evangelicals-than-american-jews-say-god-gave-israel-to-the-jewish-people/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even stronger pro-Israeli beliefs</a> than Jewish Americans according to Pew. Meanwhile, Waxman and Ben Daniel also suggested that Trump’s close allyship with Israel’s then-prime minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, and controversial decision to recognize Jerusalem — a city claimed by both Israel and Palestine — as Israel’s capital only drove the notion of unconditional support for Israel further to the right.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Palestine-Israel question has become an increasing variable in politics, determining campaign funding for certain candidates. Earlier this year, in the Democratic primary for North Carolina’s 4th Congressional District, the American Israel Public Affairs Committee, or AIPAC, helped <a href="https://www.salon.com/2022/05/17/aipac-super-pac-funnels-millions-in-dark-money-to-progressive-candidates-in-democratic-races_partner/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raise about $2 million for state Sen. Valerie Foushee</a>, who ran against and ultimately defeated pro-Palestinian and hijabi candidate Nida Allam, a Durham County commissioner. As is usually the case, however, the money in Foushee’s campaign didn’t go toward pro-Israel campaign messaging but instead to closer-to-home everyday issues that resonated with constituents on the ground, like Foushee’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hd07H0trD4A" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pro-choice abortion stance</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That is indicative of the fact that, while the pendulum is shifting for Democrats, it hasn’t really affected policy yet, Waxman said. That’s because no matter their political identity or age, Americans don’t rate Israel as a high priority issue in their daily lives. “Americans aren’t voting on this, really,” Waxman said. “It’s too far removed compared to other, more everyday issues.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, opinions on the Palestinian cause show that issues don’t have to dictate votes to be relevant within a party. This topic will likely continue to matter for Democrats, even if it doesn’t help get them elected. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>UPDATE (Sept. 22, 2022, 7:05 p.m.):</strong> This article and the second chart have been updated with Gallup polling data from Feb. 1-17. They previously cited Gallup polling data from 2021. The second chart has also been updated to clarify that the share of Americans who sympathize more with Palestinians is being subtracted from the share of Americans who sympathize more with Israelis, not Israel itself.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 17:33:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663866001644996</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Latino Voters Shifted Right in 2020. What Does That Mean for Arizona and Nevada This Year?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/latino-voters-shifted-right-in-2020-what-does-that-mean-for-arizona-and-nevada-this-year/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Arizona</category>
			<category>Catherine Cortez Masto</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Latino Voters</category>
			<category>Mark Kelly</category>
			<category>Nevada</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Latino Voters Shifted Right in 2020. What Does That Mean for Arizona and Nevada This Year?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 21, 2022, at 10:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Voters Cast Ballots In Arizona Primary" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1242269726-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1242269726-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1242269726-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1242269726-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>CAITLIN O'HARA / BLOOMBERG / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">One <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-know-about-how-white-and-latino-americans-voted-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">major storyline</a> coming out of the 2020 election was the rightward shift of Latino voters, who supported former President Donald Trump at a higher rate than they had four years earlier. Although about 3 in 5 Latinos <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voted for President Joe Biden</a>, this still represented a decline in Democratic support from 2016, when around 2 in 3 backed Hillary Clinton. With November fast approaching, the outcomes in a number of races in the 2022 midterms could hinge on whether Democrats continue to lose ground among Latino voters. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Nowhere is this more true than in Arizona and Nevada, two states with large Latino populations and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">highly competitive races</a> for U.S. Senate and governor. <a href="https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/exit-polls/president/national-results" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Exit polls</a> from 2020 and other <a href="https://naleo.org/COMMS/PRA/2022/2022-Arizona-Voter-Profile.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey data</a> suggest <a href="https://naleo.org/COMMS/PRA/2022/Nevada-2022-Profile.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Latinos will make up</a> about 20 percent of the 2022 electorate in both states. It’s important to remember that Latino voters aren’t a single voting bloc, as they have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/theres-no-such-thing-as-the-latino-vote/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">diverse views and backgrounds</a>. Still, they will <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-flip-senate-house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">help decide control of the Senate</a> and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/election-deniers-office-2024-fivethirtyeight-89613076" target="_blank" rel="noopener">key swing-state governorships</a>, and recent polls provide mixed signals about how blue or red these voters might broadly go.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In early September, Emerson College looked at the Senate and governor races in both states, finding extremely tight races across the board among likely voters. In Arizona, <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/arizona-2022-mark-kelly-faces-tight-race-with-blake-masters-katie-hobbs-and-kari-lake-in-dead-heat-for-governorship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emerson found</a> Democratic Sen. Mark Kelly ahead of Republican Blake Masters by only 2 percentage points, 47 percent to 45 percent, while Democratic Secretary of State Katie Hobbs and Republican Kari Lake were tied at 46 percent in the governor’s contest. In Nevada, <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/nevada-2022-us-senate--gubernatorial-elections-in-statistical-dead-heat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the pollster’s survey</a>, sponsored by KLAS-TV and The Hill, found Democratic Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto trailing former Republican Attorney General Adam Laxalt by 1 point, 42 percent to 41 percent, while Democratic Gov. Steve Sisolak and Republican Clark County Sheriff Joe Lombardo were knotted up at 40 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In all races, however, the Democratic nominee led among Latino voters: Kelly held an 11-point edge and Hobbs a 12-point advantage, while Cortez Masto led by 19 points and Sisolak by 16 points. Now, like most surveys, the sample sizes for Latinos in Emerson’s polls weren’t very big, meaning those data points have a <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/09/08/understanding-the-margin-of-error-in-election-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">larger margin of error</a>. Nevertheless, they do provide some much-needed information about what’s going on among Latino voters in these two key states. And considering the tight overall margins, the data also shows how reduced Democratic support among Latinos could make or break their chances.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Emerson’s findings suggest Democrats are in a worse position among Latinos now than in 2020. Back then, Biden carried 61 percent of Latino voters in both <a href="https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/exit-polls/president/arizona" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arizona</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/exit-polls/president/nevada" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada</a>, according to the 2020 exit polls. <a href="https://www.aapor.org/Education-Resources/Election-Polling-Resources/Explaining-Exit-Polls.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Exit polls are</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/10/upshot/there-are-more-white-voters-than-people-think-thats-good-news-for-trump.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">imperfect measures</a>, but they also found that Kelly won among Latinos 65 percent to 35 percent in his narrow 2020 special election victory. By comparison, Emerson’s poll gave Kelly an advantage among Latinos of 53 percent to 41 percent — a far smaller advantage than he enjoyed in 2020. The Nevada poll gave Democrats a larger lead in terms of margin but also put Cortez Masto and Sisolak’s overall support among Latinos in the mid-40s, with a large share of undecideds. If those undecideds mostly split evenly, the Democrats would perform at a similar level to what the 2020 exit polls found, but <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2020/11/16/polling-isnt-broken-we-too-often-miss-its-hidden-signals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that’s impossible to say at this point</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">You should never take one poll as gospel, and other recent surveys have found Democrats performing somewhat better among Latinos. A <a href="https://static.foxnews.com/foxnews.com/content/uploads/2022/08/AZ-crosstabs_Sen-Gov-General_conducted-August-12-16_released-Aug-18-2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mid-August survey</a> of Arizona by Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Company Research for Fox News found Kelly with an overall lead of 8 points among registered voters, and Hobbs a 3-point lead. Among Latinos, Hobbs led by 9 points — similar to Emerson’s finding — but Kelly held a 20-point advantage, 53 percent to 33 percent. Although the Fox News poll had a higher share of undecided Latino voters than the Emerson survey, Kelly’s lead was not far from the sort of margin Biden enjoyed in 2020 (though still an underperformance relative to Kelly’s own 2020 margin). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Nevada, a mid-August poll from <a href="https://www.suffolk.edu/-/media/suffolk/documents/academics/research-at-suffolk/suprc/polls/other-states/2022/8_22_2022_tables.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Suffolk University/Reno Gazette-Journal</a> gave Cortez Masto a 7-point lead overall among likely voters, 45 percent to 38 percent, and Sisolak a 3-point advantage, 43 percent to 40 percent. They each led among Latinos, with Cortez Masto leading 48 percent to 30 percent and Sisolak 47 percent to 31 percent. That lead, with a smaller share of undecideds, was comparatively stronger than the Democrats’ leads in Emerson’s survey.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Although we don’t have data for Latino voters from every poll of these races, these Democratic candidates’ overall electoral situations are currently at least a little favorable — if far from certain. Kelly holds an 8-point lead in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s polling average</a>,<a data-footnote-id="18" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-18" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday at 5 p.m. Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>18</sup></a> and the FiveThirtyEight 2022 midterm election forecast <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">views Kelly as a favorite</a>, while Hobbs <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/2022/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">holds a slimmer 3-point advantage</a> in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arizona’s toss-up governor’s race</a>. In Nevada, Cortez Masto has a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3-point edge</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/2022/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sisolak a 2-point lead</a>, and our forecast <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">makes each</a> of them <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a slight favorite</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the economy remains an opportunity for Republicans to make inroads with Latino voters. In Emerson’s polls of Arizona and Nevada, a sizable plurality of likely voters named the economy as the most important issue for their vote (36 percent in Arizona, 42 percent in Nevada), including a plurality of Latino voters. Among all voters who cited the economy (so not just Latinos), the Republican candidates garnered 62 to 67 percent of the vote. And while it’s a national poll, the survey released <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/18/us/politics/latino-vote-polling.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a> by <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/09/16/upshot/september-2022-times-siena-poll-crosstabs.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Siena College/New York Times</a> also found that registered Latino voters were split about which party they agreed with more on economic issues.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the second-most-cited issue in Emerson’s Arizona and Nevada polls was abortion access (16 percent in Arizona, 18 percent in Nevada), and voters who identified it as the key issue in determining their vote almost uniformly backed the Democratic candidates. Abortion is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/16/abortion-latino-issues-voters-midterms-00052119" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an important issue</a> for Latinos, too, and a <a href="https://www.unidosus.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/unidosus_mifamiliavota_nationalsurveyoflatinovoters_81022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent national poll</a> from BSP Research/UnidosUS/Mi Familia Vota found 59 percent of Latino voters thought Democrats would do a better job addressing abortion, compared with only 11 percent who thought Republicans would.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That tension between economic concerns and abortion rights may be especially pivotal for Latino voters because a large number of them are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/have-latinos-really-moved-toward-the-republican-party/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">persuadable voters</a>. That’s because many <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/1065912919888577" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lack strong ties to the two major political parties</a>, often because they are first-generation Americans or had first-generation parents who weren’t as politically engaged and <a href="https://www.robertofcarlos.com/uploads/6/9/4/3/69439129/late_to_the_party_on_the_prolonged_partisan_socialization_process_of_secondgeneration_americans.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t pass along their partisan views</a>. In a 2020 postmortem, Latino-focused Equis Research found that approval for Trump’s economic policies <a href="https://equisresearch.medium.com/2020-post-mortem-part-one-16221adbd2f3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was a pivotal reason</a> for Republican gains among Latino voters. But it’s possible that the headwinds of abortion politics could hinder Republicans from building on that improvement, as 61 percent of Latino respondents told Siena College/New York Times that abortion should be legal in all or most cases.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So while the polling in Arizona and Nevada suggests Democrats could be in a weaker position in 2022 among Latinos than they were in 2020, abortion <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-political-environment-might-be-improving-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">does seem to have fired up</a> the Democratic base and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-abortion-is-becoming-a-winning-issue-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">potentially turned off</a> some persuadable voters — many of whom are Latinos — from the GOP. We anxiously await more polling to get a better idea of just how Latino voters are trending in Arizona, Nevada and elsewhere.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663771501370583</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>People Of Color Make Up 41 Percent Of The U.S. But Only 28 Percent Of General-Election Candidates</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2022-candidates-race-data/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Race</category>
			<category>Race and Ethnicity</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>People Of Color Make Up 41 Percent Of The U.S. But Only 28 Percent Of General-Election Candidates</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 21, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Democratic Senate candidate Rep. Val Demings (D-FL) and a supporter" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241598117-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241598117-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241598117-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241598117-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Democratic Senate candidate Rep. Val Demings is one of more than 800 candidates of color who ran for Senate, House or governor in 2022.													<p>Octavio Jones / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">When people of color see politicians who look like them, it can have profound effects. <a href="https://wappp.hks.harvard.edu/files/wappp/files/should_blacks_represent_blacks_and_women_represent_women_a_contingent_yes1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Political science research</a> suggests that this so-called “descriptive representation” increases Americans’ <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/3088429" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trust in politicians</a> and <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/25749258" target="_blank" rel="noopener">engagement with politics</a>. But in the U.S., the percentage of people of color running for office lags far behind their share of the population (<a href="https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045221" target="_blank" rel="noopener">41 percent</a>). And it’s not enough for nonwhite candidates to simply run; to achieve any sort of proportional representation, obviously, they also have to win.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In 2022, 30 percent of the candidates who ran in Democratic or Republican primaries for Senate, House or governor were people of color, according to new data collected throughout the primary season by political scientists <a href="http://polisci.emory.edu/home/people/biography/fraga-bernard.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bernard Fraga</a> and <a href="https://hunterrendleman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hunter Rendleman</a>.<a data-footnote-id="19" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-19" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using statements made by candidates, membership in racial and ethnic caucuses or organizations, racial and ethnic advocacy organizations, news articles and candidate websites. This research is, by nature, not comprehensive — for example, Fraga and Rendleman were unable to confirm some candidates’ racial identities — but the data is close enough to identify important trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>19</sup></a> And the data shows that only 28 percent of the candidates appearing on the November ballot will be people of color. In other words, in all likelihood, 2023 will not be the year that people of color are proportionally represented in the halls of government.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Unsurprisingly, as has been the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/08/18/democratic-party-was-more-racially-diverse-1996-than-republican-party-is-today/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">case for decades</a>, Democrats had a more diverse candidate pool. At least 46 percent of their candidates this cycle were people of color, as opposed to only 19 percent of Republican candidates. But, in 2022 — possibly because white candidates were more likely to have advantages like incumbency and fundraising, possibly because of racism on the part of voters, possibly for other reasons — candidates of color from both parties had a harder time winning their primaries. As a result, when we mapped Fraga and Rendleman’s data onto the primary results, we found that people of color will constitute just 39 percent of Democratic general-election candidates and 16 percent of Republican general-election candidates.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, several distinct racial groups are included in those numbers, and some are better represented than others. Here is the full breakdown by race for all candidates who ran in this year’s primaries:</p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>Democratic candidates were more diverse than Republicans …</h2>
 <p>How candidates who ran in Democratic and Republican primaries for Senate, House or governor in 2022 racially and ethnically identify</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.primary-candidates-race.1"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Democrats</th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Republicans</th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Total</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Race/Ethnicity</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>White</td>
 <td>586</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">54%</td>
 <td>1,271</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">79%</td>
 <td>1,857</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">69%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Black</td>
 <td>300</td>
 <td>28</td>
 <td>123</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>423</td>
 <td>16</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hispanic/Latino</td>
 <td>121</td>
 <td>11</td>
 <td>104</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>225</td>
 <td>8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Asian American</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>116</td>
 <td>4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Middle Eastern</td>
 <td>12</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>15</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>27</td>
 <td>1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Native American</td>
 <td>10</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>18</td>
 <td>1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Native Hawaiian</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Unknown</td>
 <td>18</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>67</td>
 <td>2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>All candidates</td>
 <td>1,079</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>1,601</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>2,680</td>
 <td>—</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Candidate identity was determined from their own statements, membership in racial and ethnic caucuses or organizations, racial and ethnic advocacy organizations, news articles and candidate websites. Percentages sum to more than 100 percent because some candidates belong to multiple races or ethnicities.</p>
 <p>Source: Bernard Fraga and Hunter Rendleman</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">And here is the breakdown for candidates who won their party’s nomination or otherwise advanced to the general election:<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alaska, California and Washington hold all-party primaries, meaning multiple candidates from the same party can make the November ballot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>20</sup></a></p>


<div>
<section><header><h2>… but both parties’ nominees are whiter than their candidates</h2>
 <p>How Democratic and Republican nominees for Senate, House or governor in the 2022 general election racially and ethnically identify</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.primary-candidates-race.2"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><td colspan="1"></td>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Democrats</th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Republicans</th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Total</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Race/Ethnicity</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">#</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">%</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>White</td>
 <td>300</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">62%</td>
 <td>415</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">84%</td>
 <td>715</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">73%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Black</td>
 <td>111</td>
 <td>23</td>
 <td>31</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>142</td>
 <td>15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hispanic/Latino</td>
 <td>53</td>
 <td>11</td>
 <td>31</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>84</td>
 <td>9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Asian American</td>
 <td>18</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>13</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>31</td>
 <td>3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Middle Eastern</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Native American</td>
 <td>5</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Native Hawaiian</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Unknown</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>All Candidates</td>
 <td>482</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>492</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>974</td>
 <td>—</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Candidate identity was determined from their own statements, membership in racial and ethnic caucuses or organizations, racial and ethnic advocacy organizations, news articles and candidate websites. Percentages sum to more than 100 percent because some candidates belong to multiple races or ethnicities.</p>
 <p>Source: Bernard Fraga and Hunter Rendleman</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Black candidates make up a majority of candidates of color in both charts. According to Fraga and Rendleman, 16 percent of all Democratic and Republican candidates for Senate, House and governor this cycle were Black. In comparison, 15 percent of the final nominees for those offices identified as Black. That’s slightly higher than their share of the U.S. population, which is 14 percent. But of course, one party had a lot more Black candidates than the other: 28 percent of Democratic candidates running in primaries identified as Black, but only 8 percent of Republican candidates did. And while at least 111 Black Democrats are on the November ballot, there are only 31 self-identified Black Republicans. Still, Black Republican members of Congress have been so rare in the past 150 years that there’s a good chance that the 118th Congress will have a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-black-republicans-make-a-comeback-in-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">record number</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The researchers found that Hispanic and Latino Americans are the second-most-common minority group in 2022’s candidate pool, making up 8 percent of all candidates and 9 percent of the final nominees. But both numbers are much smaller than their share of the population (19 percent, though they constitute a smaller share of the <a href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/decennial-census/about/voting-rights/cvap.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">citizen voting-age population</a>). Hispanics and Latinos are also more evenly split between the parties: 53 Democrats and 31 Republicans are running in the general election. That mirrors the fact that, while Latinos still <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/22436307/catalist-equis-2020-latino-vote-trump-biden-florida-texas" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lean Democratic overall</a>, they are much more of a swing demographic than Black voters. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are also interesting patterns among 2022’s Latino candidates. At least 26 Latino Democrats on the November ballot identified as being of Mexican descent, and at least five as Puerto Rican. But Fraga and Rendleman could identify only two who are Cuban American. By contrast, they found Republicans have nominated at least seven Cuban Americans. Fraga and Rendleman could find only 10 Mexican American Republican nominees and no Puerto Rican ones. This jibes with data that shows <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/theres-no-such-thing-as-the-latino-vote/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cuban Americans are a Republican-leaning group</a>, but Puerto Ricans and especially Mexican Americans are generally Democratic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Asian Americans are also underrepresented, constituting 6 percent of the U.S. population but only 4 percent of total candidates and 3 percent of nominees. Once again, the researchers found that Democratic nominees who are Asian American outnumber Republican nominees who are Asian American, 18 to 13. There is evidence that some Asian American voters <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/12/20/us/politics/election-hispanics-asians-voting.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shifted toward Republicans in 2020</a>, but they remain Democratic-leaning overall. There are also significant differences in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-asian-americans-are-thinking-about-the-2020-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how various Asian American groups vote</a>. For example, Indian Americans are predominantly Democratic, while Vietnamese Americans lean Republican. Perhaps it’s no surprise, then, that a plurality of Democrats’ Asian American nominees were found to be of Indian descent (at least seven), while a plurality of Republicans’ were of Vietnamese descent (at least three).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Members of other racial and ethnic groups could also make history this November. At least eight nominees are Native American: five Democrats and three Republicans. Rep. Mary Peltola, a Democrat, became Congress’s first-ever Alaska Native when she was <a href="https://alaskapublic.org/2022/09/13/mary-peltola-makes-history-as-first-alaska-native-person-sworn-into-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sworn in last week</a>. And if Republican Rep. Markwayne Mullin wins his Senate race in Oklahoma, he would be the Senate’s only Native American member. Each party also nominated at least three candidates of Middle Eastern descent, including Republican Mehmet Oz, who would be the <a href="https://www.wesa.fm/politics-government/2022-08-27/mehmet-oz-senate-first-muslim" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first Muslim in the U.S. Senate</a>. Finally, Fraga and Rendleman found that Republicans nominated two Native Hawaiians (both in Hawaii itself). Democrats, meanwhile, nominated none. And given Hawaii’s blue hue, it is quite likely that Native Hawaiians will again go unrepresented in Congress following the retirement of Rep. Kai Kahele.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, these candidates still have to overcome one final hurdle before they really live up to the hopes of <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/ps-political-science-and-politics/article/abs/what-is-a-descriptive-representative/93AF3B26486FFE76B201FBA07E35D1C9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">descriptive representation</a>: They need to win in November. For many of them, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that will be a challenge</a>, as they are running as Republicans in deeply Democratic districts or vice versa. Ultimately, that means that the final number of people of color sitting in Congress or governor’s offices at this time next year will be even smaller than the numbers here. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663758001064541</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Wisconsin Polls Look Good For Democrats, But We Need More Of Them</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/wisconsin-senate-polls/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Election Forecast</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Wisconsin Politics</category>
			<category>Wisconsin Senate</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Wisconsin Polls Look Good For Democrats, But We Need More Of Them</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 20, 2022, at 11:13 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0920_4x3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0920_4x3.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0920_4x3.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0920_4x3.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0920_4x3.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Are pollsters afraid to survey Wisconsin?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It sure looks like it. Wisconsin’s U.S. Senate race has the second-fewest polls of any competitive<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those not rated “Solid Republican” or “Solid Democratic” by &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;our forecast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>21</sup></a> Senate race nationwide. </p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Where are all the Wisconsin polls?</h5>
 <p>Number of polls conducted in each competitive 2022 Senate race, as of Sept. 20, 2022, at 9 a.m. Eastern</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.wi-sen.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">No. of Polls</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td>32</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>31</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>22</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>18</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td>18</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td>18</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td>17</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Utah</td>
 <td>13</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td>9</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Excluding Senate races rated “Solid Republican” or “Solid Democratic” by the FiveThirtyEight midterm forecast.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, until last week, we didn’t even have enough Wisconsin polls to generate a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling average for that race</a>.<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We don’t generate a polling average for a race until there are at least five different polls conducted since Jan. 1 by at least three different pollsters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> But now that we do, it looks like Democratic Lt. Gov. Mandela Barnes holds a slight lead over incumbent Republican Sen. Ron Johnson, 48.7 percent to 47.5 percent.<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All numbers in this article are as of 9 a.m. Eastern on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-711-wisconsin-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-711-wisconsin-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-711-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-711-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-polling-average-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight midterm model</a>, these polls are a bullish sign for Barnes. In fact, based only on polling (as represented by the “Lite” version of our forecast), Barnes has a 60-in-100 chance of winning the election. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Many pollsters may be steering clear of Wisconsin this year because the Badger State has given them plenty of heartburn in recent elections. For example, in the 2020 presidential election, the average poll gave Joe Biden an <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">8.4-percentage-point lead</a> in Wisconsin; he won by only 0.6 points. But the thing is, just because polls missed in a particular direction in one election <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-the-polls-overestimate-democrats-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doesn’t necessarily mean they will miss in the same direction in the next</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, the “Deluxe” version of the forecast — which in addition to polls factors in non-polling “fundamentals” and expert ratings — gives <em>Johnson</em> a 56-in-100 chance of winning. That’s because those other factors simply aren’t as good for Democrats as the polling. While about half of the Deluxe forecast is based on polls, about a third is based on race ratings from experts like those at the <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/senate-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cook Political Report</a> and <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/2022-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sabato’s Crystal Ball</a>, and one-ninth is based on fundamental factors like partisanship, candidate quality and fundraising. Those expert ratings say (on average) that the race <a href="http://www.insideelections.com/ratings/senate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tilts Republican</a>, and those fundamentals suggest Johnson has about a 1-point lead.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="848" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Over the past month, the polls have slowly moved Wisconsin’s Senate race into the toss-up column in our model. According to the Deluxe version of the forecast, on Aug. 16, Johnson had a 67-in-100 chance of prevailing. But then <a href="https://law.marquette.edu/poll/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/MLSP71Toplines.html#Registered_voters" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marquette University Law School</a> dropped a poll giving Barnes a 7-point lead, and <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/official-polls/fox-news-poll-barnes-edges-johnson-wisconsin-senate-race" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fox News</a> released a poll showing Barnes 4 points ahead of Johnson (though still within the margin of error). After that, the race tightened to the point where Johnson had just a 60-in-100 chance of winning. Then, in late August, the <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/WI-Gen-Poll-Report-0827.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trafalgar Group</a> — a Republican pollster — showed Barnes 2 points ahead of Johnson. Finally, as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national polls</a> continued to improve for Democrats, Johnson eventually fell to a 51-in-100 chance of winning on Sept. 13.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="808" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-wisconsin-S3-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-wisconsin-S3-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-wisconsin-S3-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-wisconsin-S3-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="936" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-335-wisconsin-S3-2.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Since then, though, we have gotten four new polls that have averaged out to a 1-point Johnson lead. That suggests the race could be shifting in Johnson’s favor, especially since one of the more recent polls came from a pollster — Marquette — that had previously given Barnes a healthy lead. In this case, Marquette found that Johnson had gained 4 points — and Barnes had dropped 4 points — in the span of a month.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That shift could be because Republicans have blanketed television airwaves with attack ads since Barnes won the Democratic primary on Aug. 9. The ads have <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/15/politics/wisconsin-senate-election-crime-barnes-johnson/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">focused primarily on crime</a>, which according to Marquette is the second-most concerning issue to Wisconsin voters. The ads, which highlight Barnes’s support for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zpo6j1ufjF4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ending cash bail</a> and tie him to the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IW850wtmFvg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“defund the police” movement</a>, have also been criticized for being <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/mandela-barnes-ad-willie-horton-wisconsin-crime_n_63226fcce4b000d98857c4de" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racist dog whistles</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, the shift could be for other reasons, like voters starting to tune into the campaign. It could even be a mirage caused by sampling or another polling error. We’ll need to see more polls to say for sure. Hopefully, pollsters can muster up some courage and give us the Wisconsin polls we’re so thirsty for.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/mandela-barnes-democrats-best-hope-flipping-senate-seat-88399333</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 16:13:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663690501767538</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>When Abortion Isn’t A Partisan Issue</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/when-abortion-isnt-a-partisan-issue/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>Voices Of Color</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>When Abortion Isn’t A Partisan Issue</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Alex Samuels</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 20, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="VOICES-OF-COLOR-0920-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VOICES-OF-COLOR-0920-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VOICES-OF-COLOR-0920-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VOICES-OF-COLOR-0920-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VOICES-OF-COLOR-0920-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Welcome to </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/voices-of-color/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>Voices Of Color</em></strong></a><em>, a column that explores what’s on the minds of voters of color in this year’s midterm elections. Too often, media coverage focuses on the political preferences of white people with euphemisms like “</em><a href="https://www.npr.org/2018/04/07/599573817/what-we-mean-when-we-talk-about-suburban-women-voters" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>suburban women</em></a><em>” or “</em><a href="https://www.vox.com/2016/2/1/10889138/coded-language-thug-bossy" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>middle class</em></a><em>.” But in this column, we want to know what makes voters of color tick. </em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>We want to explore their views on politics, policy, the future of our democracy, our two-party system and everything in between. We hope that this column offers fresh perspectives from the minds of those whose political opinions are often overlooked or </em><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2016/09/13/2-party-affiliation-among-voters-1992-2016/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>assumed</em></a><em>. If you think you might be a good fit for this column, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/are-you-a-voter-of-color-we-want-to-hear-from-you/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>fill out this form</em></a><em> — we might get in touch.</em></p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">When the Supreme Court announced in June that it was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-argument-for-overturning-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overturning Roe v. Wade</a>, the 1973 decision establishing a constitutional right to abortion, Nancy Evans (not her real name),<a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evans asked that we change her name became she fears reprisal at work for her views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>24</sup></a> 51, started to worry about the unintended consequences for low-income women and women of color. Peter Wong, 54, wondered what <em>other </em>enshrined rights might be on the chopping block.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans is an independent, and Wong is a Republican. But both are voters of color, and like many other nonwhite Americans, the decision in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization led them to question how they can put their anger and sadness over the ruling and its aftermath to good use. “I’ve been actively looking at ways that I can engage a bit more with political communities,” said Gregory Dukes, 34, of South Carolina. “Stacey Abrams is right next door, so I’m wondering whether I need to go knock on doors for her, for instance.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But even if they’re not actively campaigning for pro-abortion-rights candidates this fall, one thing is becoming clear: Abortion — or expanding abortion access — is going to be top of mind when they cast their ballots in November. A PerryUndem poll conducted a few weeks after the Supreme Court’s decision found that voters of color, especially Black voters, were substantially more likely than white voters to say that safe and legal abortion was important to their vote.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Voters of color are more likely to prioritize abortion</h5>
 <p>Share of registered voters who say safe and legal abortion is extremely or very important to them personally in getting out to vote in the November election, by race or ethnicity</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="samuels.samuels-voices-abortion.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Race/ethnicity</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Share</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Black</td>
 <td>78%</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr><tr><td>Latina/o/x</td>
 <td>64%</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr><tr><td>Asian American/ Pacific Islander</td>
 <td>63%</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr><tr><td>White</td>
 <td>49%</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Based on a survey conducted July 12-21, 2022, among 1,999 U.S. adults.</p>
 <p>Source: PerryUndem</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">To understand why, I talked to five voters of color about why abortion is now such a high priority for them. In my interviews, I found that concern about abortion access is widespread despite party affiliation and the obvious <a href="https://www.pewforum.org/fact-sheet/public-opinion-on-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">partisan divides</a> in the abortion debate. Several people, like Gianna Gonzalez, 23, questioned the impact the Dobbs ruling would have on women regardless of whether they’d be personally affected. And others told me they viewed axing Roe as more than just a loss of access to reproductive care. (This lines up with my previous reporting on Black voters, who may be more likely to view abortion access as a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-abortion-is-a-civil-rights-issue-for-black-voters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">civil rights issue</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Disagreeing with the court’s decision on Roe, however, doesn’t mean all voters of color are looking for the same thing in terms of abortion’s legality. And that’s what makes it so difficult to evaluate polling on this topic. As I discovered in my conversations, there’s hardly any uniformity when it comes to what restrictions people want lawmakers to put in place. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">I wanted to better understand these fissures and gauge the complex and oftentimes contradicting views of people of color who listed abortion as a top voting concern for them headed into the fall. While everyone had different fears about what a post-Roe world might look like, each person was disappointed or angered by the court’s decision and said that abortion would continue to be a top issue for them until the protections of Roe were codified into federal law or the court’s decision was overturned. </p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong><em>The interviews below have been edited and condensed for clarity. </em></strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Alex Samuels: How do you feel about Roe being overturned?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Nancy Evans (Black and white, 51, North Carolina, independent): It was a horrible decision. It really was shameful. There are going to be unintended, bad consequences to this that people didn’t think through. As a result, I do everything in my power to support abortion rights as much as I can. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Paolo Aquino (Filipino, 47, California, Democrat): I firmly believe in a woman’s right to choose and feel like the current court didn’t appreciate the precedent that Roe set. I also feel that the court isn’t reflective of the majority of the country, since a majority of Americans wanted to keep the law as is.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Peter Wong (Chinese, 54, Oregon, Republican): I’m not happy with it because I don’t think an established right should be withdrawn. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gregory Dukes (Black, 34, South Carolina, Democrat): I’m religious, so my personal and religious beliefs are that I don’t believe in abortion. That said, the overturning of Roe should be viewed as a concern for every person of color and minority group because the underpinning of most of these decisions has to do with privacy. The fact that a settled piece of law could be overturned — in part due to shifts in justices — is a slap in the face considering what the court is supposed to be and who they’re supposed to represent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Also, there was a middle road we could’ve taken here. I think most people will say that they support abortions up to 15 weeks or so, which I think is enough time to make a decision on whether you want a child. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: Are you worried about abortion access in your state? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gianna Gonzalez (Mexican and Filipina, 23, California, Democrat): I’m not because our governor [Gavin Newsom] said he’s going to attempt to enshrine the right to a legal abortion in our state’s constitution. Plus, California is obviously very Democratic-leaning, so I’m not too worried about abortion access here. That said, it still troubles me to hear cases like the one about the 10-year-old rape victim in Ohio who had to travel to Indiana to get a legal abortion. These issues don’t have to affect me personally in order for me to care about them. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: I am, especially because we’re so close to states that have cut off access to the right to get an abortion. Some of them, like South Carolina, tried to do so, and I know Tennessee and Georgia have passed some version of a restrictive abortion ban too, which makes [North Carolina] a potential travel state. And although we have a Democratic governor currently, there’s enough Republicans in the state legislature and enough momentum to where I think they will try to eventually pass a more restrictive law here as well. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: Would you support a ban, or partial ban, on abortion? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: I think there should be common-sense limitations on when you can get an abortion. It doesn’t have to be unrestricted, but I think we can impose restrictions after, say, five months or so.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: I don’t support any bans on abortion because reproductive health is deeply personal and reproductive care looks different for every pregnancy. If there were any bans, I fear that people who may medically need a later-term abortion will fall through the cracks. We’ve already seen doctors hesitant to treat patients because the legalese is so vague in states where bans have been passed, even with exceptions. No one wants to be prosecuted just for doing their job. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Aquino: No. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: I would support a 20-week abortion ban with exceptions for rape, incest, severe fatal anomalies or the life of the mother.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: How do you think of Democrats versus Republicans on this issue (i.e., what do you think Democrats and Republicans each want to do on abortion)?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: There are different extremes of the parties. There are probably some Democrats who want open access to abortions no matter how far along the pregnancy is versus some extreme Republicans who want to ban <em>all </em>abortions without any exceptions for rape, incest or the mother’s health. I don’t think you can paint either party’s views with a broad brush, but the two extremes are, to me, not where the majority of America is. I think the majority is somewhere in between. And if enough common-sense moderate Republicans and Democrats put their heads together, they could come up with a national law that would codify Roe and allow for abortions up to a certain point — with exclusions accounting for a mother’s health and the health of the fetus.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Wong: I think, currently, that Democrats want to protect abortion rights while Republicans are very much against it. I am a longtime Republican, but the party I grew up with is quite different from the Republican Party as it is now. My ideal Republican Party would be more focused on small government and try not to get into other people’s private affairs, but the current Republican Party is very, very aggressive on abortion rights, in part due to religious reasons — which I’m very against. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: </strong><strong>Does the decision affect you directly? If so, how? If not, why is abortion an issue you care about? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: Yes and no. My husband is a physician who delivers babies, so it affects his work — which affects me. Personally, I think I’m pretty close to being beyond my birthing years, but I have two step-grandchildren, and this decision makes me wonder what type of rights and choices they are going to have for their own personal fertility going forward.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: After the Dobbs decision was announced, my best friend revealed to me that she had gotten an abortion. She was in a terrible relationship with an abusive partner and didn’t want to bring a child into that chaotic environment. To me, that’s completely understandable. Of course, I can’t say whether I would do the same thing because I’ve never been in that position, but there are so many different reasons why someone might need to get an abortion, and it’s not up to me to judge them. Like I said earlier, these issues don’t have to affect me personally in order for me to care.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Aquino: I’m married with two kids, and we’re done having kids, so abortion access or lack thereof doesn’t necessarily impact me directly. But I do consider getting an abortion a woman’s right, and I feel like women’s autonomy is important despite the fact that I’m a man.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: I have friends and family who are women, and watching their reactions after Roe was overturned affected me the most. As I said earlier, this decision for me goes back to privacy, and it scares me that we can just go back and revisit or change established law. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: </strong><strong>What kinds of action would you like the federal government to take on abortion?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: I’m under the impression that some lawmakers want to try and make it illegal to go to another state and have an abortion. But I think the federal government should strengthen HIPAA [privacy] laws in order to further protect the privacy of a woman to go wherever the hell she wants to go and get whatever treatment she wants — whether it’s Botox, a tummy tuck or an abortion. That’s her business. The federal government should take preemptive action to restrict states from trying to make outlaws out of women who try to seek care in other places. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: I would like to see them codify Roe into law. It would be nice to see them finally get it on the books. Should they codify it into law, it won’t have the chance to get overturned by a politicized or lopsided court. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: Let Kansas be an example of what should happen here. The federal government should encourage as many states as possible to put abortion rights on the ballot for their citizens to decide because I think that if you let people just voice their opinion on this issue alone, it’s a winner. I would love for the federal government to codify Roe, but I think that’s a fool’s errand without getting rid of the filibuster at least. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: </strong><strong>Has the Dobbs decision encouraged you to engage in politics in a way that you hadn’t? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: It’s not that I wasn’t doing some of the things that I am now, but I’m definitely more engaged. So, for example, I would from time to time give money to Planned Parenthood; now I have a recurring monthly payment, and I doubled what I was originally giving. And as I seek out candidates to vote for, I’m only considering those who are interested in common-sense limitations on abortion or are open to laws being codified to allow for safe access to abortions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: I started donating to campaigns that have pro-abortion candidates, and I’ve never really donated to politicians before. And this isn’t necessarily <em>new</em> since I protested during the Black Lives Matter marches in 2020, but after Roe was overturned, I broke out my cardboard and my markers and participated in a rally for the first time in almost two years. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Wong: The decision doesn’t make me want to vote more or less because I always do. I have had conversations with my friends who think the issue doesn’t concern them and, as a result, don’t think the Supreme Court’s decision is a big deal. But I’ve tried to express my opinion that rights should be established, not taken away; and if we view this as wrong, even if it doesn’t concern us, we should voice our opposition instead of being silent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: It really has. Particularly here in the South in a conservative state like South Carolina, it can be scary to be a Democrat or a liberal. But this decision has led me to contact and reach out to my state representative and senator to let them know that the country is moving in a direction that I personally don’t agree with. In the past I don’t think I would’ve done that. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: What are you most worried about in a post-Roe world? Do you think voting will help address your concerns?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: I’m concerned about the poor, women of color that won’t have access to safe abortions now. If you have money, you can always go to another state — or even another country — and get whatever access you want. But it’s the people who are continually left behind that will continue to hold the burden of this decision. I think voting will help, yes, because it matters who’s elected as governor and senator in some of these redder states. It matters to the people who live there. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: All of the things I was worried about are already coming true. Like I mentioned earlier, the story of the 10-year-old girl in Ohio was an atrocity, and there are other well-known cases now of people who have ectopic pregnancies and are unable to get proper care too. Obviously, these incidents are some of the more extreme cases, but the fact that this is happening at all is unacceptable — especially in a country as developed as America. I absolutely think voting can change the landscape, though. I think a lot of people forget that democracies require voter participation to work. I know a lot of people probably feel powerless right now, but voting is one way to put some power back in your hands.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Aquino: I’m worried for the women who live in states now where abortion is now illegal. If they want to get an abortion, they may be forced to make difficult decisions, such as going to a state where abortion is legal if they can afford it. And if they can’t afford it, I’m worried that they might have to undertake some medically dangerous procedure or go to an unlicensed professional. Limiting a woman’s right to choose can result in poor health outcomes.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: I’m most concerned about the independence of our judiciary. This decision has shown the importance of showing up, particularly for Democrats, because I feel that we have a tendency not to vote on the issue of the Supreme Court, and we need to stop that. Republicans have voted on this issue, and continue to vote on the issue of the Supreme Court. We all should be scared of that. I think voting would solve some of my concerns here, yes, but we also need national Democrats to stop the infighting and put the independence of the judiciary at the top of their list of concerns. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: Under what conditions would abortion no longer be a top issue for you? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Aquino: Once a woman’s right to choose becomes legal across the country or once the Dobbs decision is overturned.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dukes: Right now, it will always be because I don’t think we’ll get a codification of Roe. As such, this has to remain my No. 1 voting issue because there are other civil rights that are on the line. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>AS: </strong><strong>Was abortion a top issue for you in previous elections? Why or why not?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Evans: It was, especially in the elections for the U.S. Senate, because I kind of saw this coming. I was very disappointed when [former Supreme Court Justice] Ruth Bader Ginsburg did not retire while [Barack] Obama was president. As much as I loved her — and still love her — I really feel like if she had made different decisions, we might not be in this situation today. In previous election cycles, I knew that if the Senate went to Republicans, then we would have consequences. Elections matter. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gonzalez: It wasn’t even on my radar, perhaps selfishly, because I never thought it was going to affect me. In hindsight, I guess that was a bit ignorant because even before the Roe decision, certain states already had abortion bans or trigger laws in place. But, honestly, before Roe was overturned, I took abortion access for granted. I think a lot of other people did too. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Aquino: It was not, because Roe was the legal standard in previous elections and I felt like the precedent set by Roe was in line with what I supported. As a result, I focused more on other issues.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Wong: No, because it was a constitutional right. But in this election, it is affecting my vote. In the last two election cycles, I’ve been voting for Democratic congressional candidates but for Republican statewide candidates. This year, I’m going to vote at the state level for Democrats as well because I don’t like that the states don’t have the freedom to take abortion away, and I want Democrats to be in charge. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663672501408125</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Which Party Are Latino Voters Choosing In 2022?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-which-party-are-latino-voters-choosing-in-2022/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Latino Voters</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<category>Senate</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-which-party-are-latino-voters-choosing-in-2022/">
	<div data-podcast-id="344447" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Which Party Are Latino Voters Choosing In 2022?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP8356084547.mp3?updated=1663624765">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Last week, South Carolina Sen. Lindsey Graham introduced a national 15-week abortion ban, and Senate Majority Leader Chuck Schumer postponed a vote on the Respect for Marriage Act. In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses the strategies behind this proposal — and postponement — before the midterm elections. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The team also covers some original reporting on Colorado Republican congressional candidate Erik Aadland, who told voters in private that how he talks about the legitimacy of the 2020 election depends on whom he’s talking to.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, Galen Druke speaks with Carlos Odio of Equis Research about the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/18/us/politics/latino-vote-polling.html" target="_blank">recent polling</a> from The New York Times and Siena College on which party Latino voters are choosing in the upcoming midterm elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 22:56:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663627501364868</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Lindsey Graham’s Abortion Ban Is Dividing GOP Senate Candidates In Swing States</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/lindsey-grahams-abortion-ban-is-dividing-gop-senate-candidates-in-swing-states/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Lindsey Graham’s Abortion Ban Is Dividing GOP Senate Candidates In Swing States</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 19, 2022, at 2:00 PM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-abortion-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-abortion-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-abortion-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-abortion-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-abortion-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Last week, Republican Sen. Lindsey Graham <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/13/us/politics/lindsey-graham-abortion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">introduced a 15-week federal abortion ban</a>, to the consternation of <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/senate/3649653-these-15-gop-senators-have-signaled-opposition-to-grahams-abortion-ban/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many of his Senate colleagues</a>. Republicans at every level of government are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-keep-failing-to-pass-abortion-bans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">splintering over how far their abortion bans should go</a>, and judging by the campaign trail, Graham’s proposal is yet another wedge. We took a look at how Republican candidates are responding in the 10 closest Senate races, according <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to our midterm forecast</a>.<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 12:30 p.m. Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> They fell into three major categories:</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Supportive:</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Herschel Walker</strong>, the Republican candidate in Georgia, <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/herschel-walker-supports-15-week-proposed-national-abortion-ban/IKTH4YNFMZCDZO47XZGXX5Q7CI/">said he would support</a> a national 15-week abortion ban, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/09/14/republican-abortion-midterms-graham/">as did <strong>Blake Masters</strong></a>, who is running for Senate in Arizona. </li><li>Current Sen. <strong>Marco Rubio</strong> (Florida) and Rep. <strong>Ted Budd</strong> (North Carolina) <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/senate-bill/4840/cosponsors?r=2&amp;s=1">co-sponsored the legislation</a>, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-bill/8814/cosponsors">signaling that they’re</a> on board with its content. </li></ul><p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Cagey:</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Adam Laxalt</strong>, who’s running in Nevada, <a href="https://www.governing.com/now/nevada-candidates-have-mixed-response-to-potential-abortion-ban">hasn’t commented</a>, although he did <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/opinion/voices/2022/08/02/setting-record-straight-adam-laxalt/10187587002/">write an op-ed in August</a> saying that states should decide the issue. Ohio’s <strong>J.D. Vance</strong> has <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/17/politics/abortion-republicans-midterms-graham-bill/index.html">also refused to weigh in</a>. </li><li>Pennsylvania candidate <strong>Mehmet Oz</strong> issued a <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/09/16/lindsey-graham-abortion-ban-bill-splits-gop-on-midterm-message.html">somewhat opaque statement</a> where he implied that he wouldn’t support the legislation, but didn’t say that outright. His spokesperson said that he’s “pro-life with three exceptions: life of the mother, rape and incest,” but added that “as a senator, he’d want to make sure that the federal government is not involved in interfering with the state’s decisions on the topic.”<br></li></ul><p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Against:</strong></p>



<ul><li><a href="https://madison.com/news/local/govt-and-politics/ron-johnson-says-states-should-decide-abortion-laws-wont-commit-to-15-week-federal-ban/article_bf1ae066-03d3-5edf-87d6-a5d70142d9d8.html">Current Wisconsin Sen. <strong>Ron Johnson</strong></a> and <a href="https://www.seacoastonline.com/story/news/politics/2022/09/14/nh-don-bolduc-pivots-15-week-abortion-ban-lindsey-graham-legislation-sen-hassan-speaks-out/10382632002/">New Hampshire candidate <strong>Donald Bolduc</strong></a> both said the issue was for the states to decide.</li><li>Colorado candidate <strong>Joe O’Dea</strong> <a href="https://www.denverpost.com/2022/09/13/joe-odea-lindsey-graham-abortion-bennet-senate/">said he does not support the bill</a> and stands by his view that abortion should be legal in the first five months of pregnancy.</li></ul><p data-paragraph="main">The candidates who came out in favor of Graham’s proposal tend to be in a stronger electoral position — but that’s not uniformly true. Right now, Rubio is in the best position according to FiveThirtyEight’s Senate forecast, where he’s favored to win against Democrat Val Demings. The other Republican who co-sponsored the bill, Budd, is slightly favored, with a 62-in-100 chance of winning his race against Democrat Cheri Beasley. But Walker’s race against Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock in Georgia is a toss-up in our forecast. And in Arizona, Masters is facing steeper odds — our forecast indicates that he has about a 1-in-5 chance of beating Democrat Sen. Mark Kelly. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The candidates who opposed Graham’s bill — or didn’t say anything about it — are in a weaker position in our forecast, generally speaking. The exception is Vance, who is favored to win the Ohio Senate race right now. Johnson’s race is a toss-up, Laxalt has a 39-in-100 chance, and things look worse for Oz and Bolduc, both of whom have slightly less than a 1-in-5 chance of winning. O’Dea — who came out most strongly against the bill — has the most distant odds, with only a 9-in-100 chance of winning.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The candidates’ responses make more sense when you look at public opinion on abortion in each of their states. Drawing on <a href="https://civiqs.com/results/abortion_legal?annotations=true&amp;uncertainty=true&amp;zoomIn=true&amp;home_state=New%20Hampshire" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state-level data from Civiqs</a>, we took a look at the share of registered voters who think abortion should be legal in some or all cases. Majorities of registered voters in every state think abortion should be legal in at least some cases, but support in some states is much higher than others. The four candidates in our subset who are publicly supporting a national 15-week ban — Walker, Masters, Rubio and Budd — are from states where relatively low shares of residents support legal abortion in some or all cases. Support for legal abortion is higher in the remaining states — particularly in New Hampshire, where Bolduc has been trying hard to distance himself from the ban. The only major exception is Vance, who has refused to take a stand on the 15-week ban despite the fact that Ohio residents are the least supportive of legal abortion of the group. Johnson’s opposition to the bill is noteworthy, too, given that support for legal abortion in Wisconsin is not especially high.</p>


<div>

<section><header><h5>Support for legal abortion varies by state</h5>
 <p>Share of registered voters in each state who said they believe abortion should be legal or illegal in all or most cases</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="atd.graham-senate.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="0" aria-sort="descending" data-sort-default="true"><span>State<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="1" data-sort-method="number">Legal in all/most <span>cases<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="2" data-sort-method="number">Illegal in all/most <span>cases<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">53%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">43%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>42</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>40</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>39</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>40</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>38</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>36</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td>62</td>
 <td>35</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>65</td>
 <td>32</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>69</td>
 <td>28</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Does not include respondents who said “not sure.” Based on the Sept. 17, 2022, results of an online daily-tracking survey, which has received 245,506 responses from registered voters since Nov. 6, 2016.</p>
 <p>Source: Civiqs</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">It’s strange in some ways that a 15-week abortion ban is sparking so much controversy since it’s much closer to a consensus bill than anything that’s being implemented by Republicans at the state level. In Republican-controlled states, recent fights have hinged on whether to add limited exceptions to bills that ban abortion completely. And although it’s hard to pin down exactly when Americans want abortion to be legal, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-americans-really-think-about-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a 15-week ban is much closer to the mainstream of public opinion</a> than a full ban.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the mixed reaction to Graham’s proposal is a telling sign of the political status that any abortion ban occupies in the current electoral landscape. There’s mounting evidence that the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn the constitutional right to abortion has galvanized Americans who might otherwise have been ambivalent about voting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to a Kaiser Family Foundation poll <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/poll-finding/kff-health-tracking-poll-july-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conducted from July 7-17</a>, 60 percent of women voters between the ages of 18 and 49 said they are now “more motivated” to vote in the upcoming elections because of the Supreme Court’s ruling, up 19 percentage points from May, when registered voters were presented with a scenario based on the leaked draft of the opinion. (Many men <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-real-dividing-line-on-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also support abortion rights</a>, and there’s evidence that the ruling <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2022/9/4/23333329/roe-voter-registration-dobbs-midterms-democrats" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may have galvanized some of them too</a>.) Support for legal abortion grew by 5 percentage points between March and August, according to <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/support-for-legalized-abortion-grows-since-dobbs-ruling-wsj-poll-shows-11662210020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling by The Wall Street Journal</a>, which is a remarkable shift for an issue where public opinion is typically static. And even though <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/235469/trimesters-key-abortion-views.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some polls have suggested</a> that Americans might support a ban on abortions after the first trimester of pregnancy, which is essentially what a 15-week ban would do, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/support-for-15-week-abortion-ban-outweighs-opposition-wsj-poll-finds-11648821601" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls specifically</a> <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/political-and-religious-activation-and-polarization-in-the-wake-of-the-roe-overturn/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">asking about bans</a> on <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/13/state-abortion-restrictions-opposition-survey/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abortion after 15 weeks</a> show that <a href="https://apnews.com/article/abortion-health-congress-government-and-politics-fc8c68d1c4dd29ef0a364050013b8cf4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">respondents are divided</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And perhaps most worryingly for the Republicans who did throw their weight behind the proposed 15-week abortion ban, their own efforts to restrict or ban abortion don’t seem to be motivating the GOP base. That Kaiser Family Foundation poll from July found that 62 percent of Republicans say the decision to overturn abortion rights hasn’t made a difference for their vote in November. In fact, the share of Republican women who said that abortion is a “very important” issue for their vote dropped from 60 percent in February to 44 percent in July.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These political currents are reshaping many races, including in the Senate. Masters, the Arizona Republican, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/arizona-blake-masters-backtracks-abortion-scrubs-campaign-website-rcna44808" target="_blank" rel="noopener">scrubbed a policy statement</a> advocating for a federal “personhood” law from his website in August. In Georgia, Walker’s opponent <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/meetthepressblog/warnock-becomes-latest-launch-tv-ad-abortion-rights-rcna46858" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is running ads</a> highlighting his support for abortion bans with no exceptions. And in North Carolina, our model shows that the race has narrowed considerably over the past few months, with <a href="https://surveyresearch-ecu.reportablenews.com/pr/ecu-poll-shows-budd-with-narrow-lead-over-beasley" target="_blank" rel="noopener">support growing</a> for Budd’s opponent, Cheri Beasley, in recent polls.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So even if a 15-week abortion ban seems a lot more restrained than some of the bans that are currently in effect around the country, supporting one still might not be good politics for Republican Senate candidates right now. There’s not a lot of evidence that Republican voters will be galvanized by the proposal — and it could end up rallying Democratic voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CLARIFICATION (Sept. 19, 2022, 3:36 p.m.):</strong> This article, including the table, has been updated to clarify that respondents in the Civiqs and Kaiser Family Foundation polls are registered voters.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 19:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663614001251747</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Could A Republican Win Colorado’s Senate Seat?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/could-a-republican-win-colorados-senate-seat/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Colorado Politics</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Could A Republican Win Colorado’s Senate Seat?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Alex Samuels</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 19, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0919-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The conventional political narrative around Colorado is that this <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2016/09/the-state-that-fell-off-the-map/499529/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">onetime purple state now leans blue</a>. And there’s plenty of evidence for that: Democratic presidential candidates have won the state in every election <a href="https://www.270towin.com/states/Colorado" target="_blank" rel="noopener">since 2008</a>, Democrats have occupied the governor’s mansion <a href="https://www.nga.org/former-governors/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">since the 2006 election</a> and the state is currently represented by two Democratic senators.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This year’s midterm elections were supposed to be favorable for Republicans, as they usually are for the party <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not in the White House</a>, but the GOP has seen once reachable Senate races in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arizona</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pennsylvania</a> become <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-is-republicans-path-to-winning-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more challenging</a> — all while races in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia</a>, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wisconsin</a> remain close. In the midst of this, some GOP strategists and national leaders are hoping the Centennial State can become a battleground once again.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s 2022 midterm election forecast</a> gives incumbent Democratic Sen. Michael Bennet about a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">9-in-10 chance</a> of beating his Republican opponent, Joe O’Dea.<a data-footnote-id="19" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-19" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern this past Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>19</sup></a> And Colorado also hasn’t elected a Republican senator <a href="https://www.senate.gov/states/CO/senators.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">since 2014</a>. (The time before that was <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/06/us/the-2002-elections-the-senate-colorado-saving-a-seat-for-the-republicans.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in 2002</a>.) But both parties are taking this year’s race seriously: In an interview with Politico, Bennet warned that “<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/24/michael-bennet-colorado-senate-00034518" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colorado remains a swing state</a>,” while Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell reportedly assured Republicans recently that he’s “all in” on the race and lavished praise on O’Dea, whom he called “<a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/07/20/mcconnell-colorado-senate-race" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the perfect candidate</a>” for the state.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are many reasons why <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/analysis/senate/colorado-senate/colorado-senate-shifts-solid-likely-democrat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some prognosticators think</a> Bennet might be in trouble. But arguably the biggest reason why — despite <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s polling average</a> giving Bennet a nearly 9-percentage-point advantage — is that O’Dea has largely avoided the not-so-great headlines that have plagued other Republicans in races that were initially viewed as easy grabs for the GOP. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Take someone like Herschel Walker, the Republican challenging Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock in Georgia. Walker is under scrutiny for allegedly <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/herschel-walker-lied-about-his-secret-kids-to-his-own-campaign" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not disclosing</a> all of his children, despite repeatedly <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/14/us/politics/herschel-walker-son.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">criticizing absent Black fathers</a>. He’s also under fire for <a href="https://www.ajc.com/news/investigations/herschel-walkers-business-record-reveals-creditor-lawsuits-exaggerated-claims/D3FRT4RA7NFKTN23423ENPUP7A/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exaggerating his business</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/05/25/politics/fact-check-walker-university-of-georgia-graduated/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">academic records</a>. Meanwhile, in Arizona, Republican Senate candidate Blake Masters carries his own problematic baggage: He once blamed <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/trump-backed-senate-candidate-blake-masters-blames-gun-violence-black-rcna32290" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Black people</a> for gun violence in the U.S., and has promoted <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/republican-senate-candidates-promote-replacement-theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the “great replacement” conspiracy theory</a>, the debunked belief <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2022/05/29/republicans-great-replacement-theory/9798199002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">advanced by Republicans</a> who claim that Democrats support more immigration to <a href="https://immigrationforum.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Replacement-Theory-Explainer-1122.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“replace” white American voters</a>. And in Pennsylvania, Republican candidate Mehmet Oz has <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struggled to gain traction</a> after <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/made-by-history/2022/09/08/pa-senate-race-will-it-matter-that-dr-oz-is-carpetbagger/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accusations of carpetbagging</a> and <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/questions-dr-oz-crudites-video.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">being out of touch</a> with voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, a spate of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/aug/16/mehmet-oz-herschel-walker-jd-vance-republican-senate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">controversial or disliked candidates</a> might cost Republicans the Senate — a reality that even <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/mcconnell-says-republicans-may-not-win-senate-control-citing-candidate-rcna43777" target="_blank" rel="noopener">McConnell has acknowledged</a>. There are signs, too, that the party is starting to slowly pull its support for some scandal-ridden Republicans. In late August, there were reports that the Senate Leadership Fund, a Republican super PAC aligned with McConnell, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/26/shifting-strategy-senate-gop-super-pac-cancels-ad-buys-in-arizona-alaska-00053965" target="_blank" rel="noopener">planned to scrap</a> about $8 million worth of ads in Arizona <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/meetthepressblog/gop-super-pac-cuts-senate-ad-spending-arizona-alaska-rcna45033" target="_blank" rel="noopener">throughout September</a>, delaying its entry into the race until early October. This might be one of the clearest signals that the party is pivoting its resources to states where candidate quality is less of an issue. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s why states like Colorado might appeal to the GOP, even if the odds are currently stacked against them. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One reason why Bennet might be a weak candidate is that he didn’t clear the majority-vote threshold in either <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/state.php?fips=8&amp;year=2010&amp;f=0&amp;off=3&amp;elect=0&amp;class=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2010</a> or <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/state.php?fips=8&amp;year=2016&amp;f=0&amp;off=3&amp;elect=0&amp;class=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2016</a>. That’s not necessarily surprising in the 2010 election, given the two-term senator <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2009/01/bennet-to-replace-salazar-in-senate-017001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was originally appointed</a> to the Senate by then-Gov. Bill Ritter in 2009 and senators who are first appointed to office often <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-hard-to-win-a-senate-race-when-youve-never-won-an-election-before/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have weaker electoral track records</a>. But what’s worse for Bennet is that he also had a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/24/michael-bennet-colorado-senate-00034518" target="_blank" rel="noopener">closer-than-expected race</a> against Republican Darryl Glenn in 2016 — despite outspending his opponent <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/races/summary?cycle=2016&amp;id=COS1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than 4-to-1</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Bennet hasn't won a majority of the vote in his Senate elections" aria-label="Stacked Bars" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/fTCrO/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="273" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Candidates who don’t get people excited and don’t make voters passionate don’t get a lot of support. And I just don’t think Sen. Bennet gets people excited,” said <a href="https://polisci.uccs.edu/sara-hagedorn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sara Hagedorn</a>, a professor of political science at the University of Colorado Colorado Springs.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Bennet’s favorability numbers in the state also leave much to be desired. A <a href="https://live-gsg-new.pantheonsite.io/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Q2-Mountaineer-Political-Report-F06.16.22-1-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Global Strategy Group/ProgressNow Colorado</a> survey fielded in June, for instance, showed that he held a 10-percentage-point net-positive favorability with Colorado’s registered voters — but a surprising share, 28 percent, didn’t know or had no opinion of him. Compare that with Gov. Jared Polis, whose net favorability was 5 points better than Bennet’s and only 9 percent of voters didn’t know or had no opinion of him. That being said, the poll had Bennet significantly outperforming President Biden among Colorado voters: Biden’s net favorability was 14 points underwater. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And there are other reasons why national outlets have pounced on Colorado as a pickup opportunity for Republicans. O’Dea, a first-time candidate, has mostly avoided running as far to the right as many of his GOP counterparts. While <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/08/20/colorado-senate-race-sundaytake/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he voted</a> for former President Donald Trump in 2016 and 2020, he has said openly that he hopes Trump <a href="https://www.cpr.org/2022/08/05/gop-senate-candidate-joe-odea-says-he-hopes-trump-doesnt-run-for-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doesn’t run for president</a> in 2024 and that he doesn’t question the legitimacy of Biden’s 2020 win.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that social issues, such as the Supreme Court’s overturning of Roe v. Wade, that have <a href="https://www.vox.com/2022/7/10/23200973/abortion-house-senate-midterms-roe-dobbs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">animated other Senate races</a> won’t be <a href="https://www.rmpbs.org/blogs/news/aclu-of-colorado-2022-poll-of-voters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as much of an issue</a> in Colorado, where the right to abortion <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/04/05/1091041608/colorado-abortion-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is codified</a> in state law. In addition, O’Dea is <a href="https://www.coloradopolitics.com/elections/2022/bennet-attacks-republican-challenger-over-abortion-stance-in-new-tv-ad-odea-fires-back/article_7b34f8ca-1ea2-11ed-b704-0b15517f6ac9.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not as conservative</a> as many Republican politicians on abortion. While he did <a href="https://www.axios.com/local/denver/2022/08/23/joe-odea-abortion-20-weeks-michael-bennet-ad" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vote in favor of a failed ballot measure</a> in 2020 that would have outlawed abortions after 22 weeks of gestation, and has said he’s personally “pro-life,” <a href="https://coloradosun.com/2022/08/19/joe-odea-abortion-ban-22-weeks-vote/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he opposed</a> the Supreme Court decision to overturn Roe. In fact, he’s said he would support abortions for up to about 20 weeks of pregnancy, with exceptions in later months for rape, incest and the life of the mother. And just last week,<strong> </strong>O’Dea <a href="https://www.fortmorgantimes.com/2022/09/13/joe-odea-lindsey-graham-abortion-bennet-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">publicly stated</a> he would not support a proposed bill by South Carolina Sen. Lindsey Graham that would ban most abortions <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/09/16/lindsey-graham-abortion-ban-bill-splits-gop-on-midterm-message.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after 15 weeks of pregnancy</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, Bennet has tried to make abortion <a href="https://www.cpr.org/2022/08/19/colorado-2022-senate-race-abortion-michael-bennet-joe-odea/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a defining line</a> in his race. In August, his campaign <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uLaLze6xBq8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">launched a new commercial</a> where five women are heard criticizing O’Dea for allegedly opposing “the law protecting abortion access in Colorado” and for supporting Trump’s three Supreme Court nominees, all of whom voted to overturn Roe.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also been hard to grasp the state’s political winds since a plurality of its voters <a href="https://coloradosun.com/2022/07/05/unaffiliated-voters-colorado-2022-primaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are unaffiliated with either party</a> and polling on its Senate race <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been sparse</a> so far. Most Democratic-funded polls give Bennet a double-digit lead over O’Dea (which isn’t surprising as partisan polls are often <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-you-shouldnt-always-trust-the-inside-scoop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unreliable and biased</a>), and at least one Republican-funded poll has the two neck-and-neck (also not surprising). Meanwhile, an independent poll by Public Policy Polling showed less support for Bennet than in the Democratic polls but still gave him a fairly large edge.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Colorado's Senate race lacks nonpartisan polling" aria-label="Range Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/4JHA4/7/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="499" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The high number of unaffiliated voters here means that there’s a lot of people who are tired of both Republican and Democratic politics,” Hagedorn said. And a Republican like O’Dea who is willing to buck his party’s line on issues like abortion might speak to those voters, she added. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So do Republicans really stand a chance here? At the very least, the lead-up to November should be competitive since that’s how both parties are treating it. But, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to our midterms forecast</a>, O’Dea is very much the underdog here. Not only does Bennet have a <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/races/summary?cycle=2022&amp;id=COS1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lofty fundraising edge</a>, but a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-this-be-an-asterisk-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democratic upswing</a> might also help him coast through reelection this fall.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This race merits watching, though, as it could become a harbinger for Democrats in what would normally be a difficult election year for the party. And while Colorado hasn’t recently been a bastion of competitive statewide races, O’Dea isn’t a bad candidate for Republicans, and if the political climate worsens for Democrats, the tide could turn for the GOP in Colorado.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663582501024893</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trust In Institutions Is Eroding On Both Sides Of The Pond, And The Queen Was Not Exempt</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/strongtrust-in-institutions-is-eroding-on-both-sides-of-the-pond-and-the-queen-was-not-exempt-strong/</link>
						<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>British Royal Family</category>
			<category>Democracy</category>
			<category>Monarchy</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Queen Elizabeth II</category>
			<category>Societal Distrust</category>
			<category>United Kingdom</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/monarchy/" name="">Monarchy</a></p>
						
													<h1>Trust In Institutions Is Eroding On Both Sides Of The Pond, And The Queen Was Not Exempt</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Zoha Qamar</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 16, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0916_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Last Thursday, word of Queen Elizabeth II’s ailing health captured an international audience. In the United States, media outlets breathlessly covered the story for hours until the announcement of her death unleashed an even larger outpouring from leaders and citizens across the globe. Condolences eulogizing the life of the queen, however, <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2022/09/twitters-messy-mourning-of-queen-elizabeth-ii.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">buzzed alongside commentary</a> criticizing the institution of the monarchy itself. And stateside, some wondered why <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/14/us/america-queen-death-royal-family.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a sizable share of Americans</a> seemed so invested in the life of the leader of a country from which early Americans sought independence. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That tendency is particularly confusing when we don’t have nearly as much positive emotional investment in our own government institutions. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-americans-dont-trust-institutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trust in American political structures</a> is plummeting, and there is a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/national-media-coverage-of-black-lives-matter-had-fallen-during-the-trump-era-until-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">growing awareness of societal inequities</a>. But some dynamics at play in the United Kingdom may not be so removed from the existential crossroads Americans are facing in the States culturally and politically. An increasing disapproval of the monarchy among younger Britons suggests a common plot of crumbling institutional faith is unfolding in parallel on both sides of the pond. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the whole, the crown isn’t necessarily in immediate crisis. According to a mid-May <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/society/articles-reports/2022/06/01/platinum-jubilee-where-does-public-opinion-stand-m" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> that surveyed Britons on whether they thought the monarchy should continue or be replaced with an elected head of state, 62 percent favored the crown, while a mere 22 percent preferred an elected leader. In the modern era, the monarch is by and large a ceremonial figurehead who symbolically oversees the army, heads the Church of England and sits as an aspirational, dignified role model meant to inspire the best of the British. Many Britons saw the queen in this light, and while her son Charles has historically not been the most popular royal — in May, <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/05/31/platinum-jubilee-how-popular-are-royals" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov</a> reported that 54 percent of Britons held positive views of Charles and 47 percent held positive views of his wife, Camilla — Elizabeth II (81 percent), Prince William (75 percent) and Kate (70 percent) all clocked in much higher. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Following Elizabeth’s death, much of the news coverage has labeled the queen as a “stabilizing” or “steadfast” figure who represented continuity for Britain. After all, the vast majority of Britons (and the global population) living today were born after she inherited the crown. But some have pointed out that the gravitas of her reign <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/09/12/1122238140/queen-elizabeth-ii-death-commonwealth-countries-colonial-history" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whitewashed a lot of its colonial empire</a> aftermath, which <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2022/sep/13/queen-reign-death-elizabeth-ii-uk-minorities-british-empire" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wasn’t really so stable</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And the queen’s youngest subjects viewed her reign and her family in the least favorable light. While the overall popularity of the British monarchs has remained relatively stagnant in <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/gv41ilgxav/YouGov%20-%20Jubilee%20Tracker.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prior YouGov polling</a> over the past decade, a breakdown by age group reveals a dramatic, consistent shift among younger Britons in the years since. Whereas 64 percent of 18- to 24-year-olds favored the monarchy in a May-June 2012 survey, just 33 percent agreed in 2022. And while only 23 percent preferred an elected head of state in May-June 2012, that number rose to 31 percent this May. In other words, the gleaming facade of royalty appears to be tarnishing among Britain’s next generation, which various commentators attribute to a host of dynamics and events: calls to recognize <a href="https://time.com/6212824/queen-elizabeth-iis-reign-violence-british-empire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">colonialism’s damage</a>, Prince Andrew’s Jeffrey Epstein-affiliated <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/09/04/jeffrey-epstein-prince-andrew-royal-family-abuse-britain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sexual-assault case</a> and a general distaste for vastly unequal hereditary hierarchy facilitated by <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/king-charles-backlash-tax-exemption-queen-million-fortune-1742402" target="_blank" rel="noopener">taxpayer dollars</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, if you ask most Americans, the shiny promise of a governmental system anchored by an elected leader isn’t all it’s cracked up to be either. As in Britain, the dissatisfaction is especially strong among the young. According to <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071422/f034d2429900e8eb/full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a New York Times/Siena College poll</a> from July, about 67 percent of American voters under 30 said that this country’s governmental structure needs to be completely replaced or majorly reformed, and even 43 percent of U.S. voters 65 and over — by far the least likely to say such change was needed — agreed. Still, other responses from the survey broken down by age reveal just how cynical younger Americans are toward both the current state of the country and the possibility of remedying it. Just 28 percent of 18- to 29-year-olds thought that the nation’s political system could address its problems, versus 47 percent of those 65 and over who agreed. Meanwhile, only 49 percent under 30 have faith that voting in elections lets everyday people make a difference in their government, compared with a solid 81 percent of the oldest age group. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That open attitude toward change is something young Britons and young Americans have in common. Both groups voice a straightforward desire to see refreshed approaches in tackling key issues at the bedrock of national identity. Britons, echoing their American counterparts, display less loyalty toward institutions beyond Buckingham Palace. In 2021, the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/global/2021/05/05/6-tradition-vs-change/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a> found that, across the board, a similar percentage of 18- to 29-year-olds said their country would ultimately benefit from a willingness to change its traditions: 78 percent in the U.S. and 76 percent in the U.K. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the exact political priorities and opinions each cohort has varies based on different national issues and pasts, but both demonstrate a stronger willingness to look their respective histories in the eye, at least relative to their older counterparts. For example, according to a <a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/sites/default/files/RaceBLM100Crosstabs.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Massachusetts Amherst poll in April 2021</a>, 18- to 29-year-old Americans were almost twice as likely (57 percent) as those 55 and over (30 percent) to say that the United States should pay reparations to descendants of enslaved people. Meanwhile, a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/z7uxxko71z/YouGov%20-%20British%20empire%20attitudes.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov survey from 2019</a> reported that 18 percent of Britons age 18 to 24 consider the British empire a proud part of the country’s history; that number more than doubled among those over 65 (43 percent). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The late queen was lauded during her life for her strong ability to stay “apolitical” and “neutral.” Looking ahead, however, younger Britons expressed in a <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/09/13/britons-first-impressions-king-charles-iii" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> that they don’t see an issue with King Charles III taking a fresh approach: 70 percent of 18- to 24-year-olds said it would be appropriate for him to stay vocal on issues he’s cared about and spoken of before, while 51 of those over 65 said such conduct would be inappropriate, suggesting an approach in line with his mother’s. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At 73, Charles hardly counts as a “young person,” but if he chooses to maintain a personal norm on politics different from the queen’s, that could make him a monarch at least somewhat more in line with the younger generation’s views. Still, whether older political figures can bring the changes young people in the U.K. and U.S. clearly want remains to be seen. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>An Aug. 1-14 <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/09/08/republicans-and-democrats-have-different-top-priorities-for-u-s-immigration-policy/?utm_content=buffer13b2f&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer">study from Pew</a> highlights how partisan divides stack up on policy ideas surrounding immigration. A sweeping majority (79 percent) of Republicans said increasing deportations for undocumented immigrants was at least a somewhat important policy goal, while about half as many (39 percent) Democrats agreed. Additionally, a majority of Americans on both sides of the aisle support greater security at the Southern border, although that jumps to almost all (91 percent) Republicans versus about 3 in 5 (59 percent) Democrats. </li></ul><ul><li>As we mark two and a half years since many office workers first adjusted to new in-person, hybrid and remote protocols, American employees’ worries about COVID-19 have tapered overall, according to a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/400904/risk-covid-exposure-concern-employees.aspx">Gallup poll</a> conducted July 26-Aug. 2. The share of the American workforce very or moderately concerned about coronavirus exposure on the job has reached a low of 33 percent, down considerably from its peak of 51 percent in July 2020, although that number continues to look different across gender, party ID and job type. Working women (41 percent) are considerably more concerned than working men (26 percent) about exposure, and employed Democrats (51 percent) are more than three times as likely as their Republican counterparts (14 percent) to say they’re worried. Meanwhile, concern among blue-collar (24 percent) and white-collar (33 percent) employees has dwindled, although the survey did break out two specific fields where worries remain higher than that of the overall share of workers (33 percent): Americans working in health care (42 percent) and education (53 percent). </li></ul><ul><li>When it comes to healthy eating, most Americans would prefer to eat produce and fresh foods over going on diets. Per an Aug. 29-30 <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/09/12/the-paradox-of-healthy-eating/">Morning Consult poll</a>, 91 percent of adults agree that eating fruits and vegetables is at least somewhat necessary for a healthy lifestyle, whereas far fewer said the same about dieting (28 percent) or intermittent fasting (37 percent). Overall, 80 percent reported that major reasons to eat healthy included feeling good long-term, while 70 percent of baby boomers also said not getting sick was a huge motivation. Meanwhile, Gen Z and millennials were the most likely to note that eating healthy helped them feel their best mentally (73 percent), look their best (60 percent) and fuel fitness performance (46 percent). </li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> 42.3 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 53.1 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.8 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-is-more-unpopular-than-ever-that-could-help-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.4 percent approved and 53.2 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -10.8 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 40.2 percent and a disapproval rating of 55.2 percent, for a net approval rating of -15.0 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a> Democrats currently lead by 1.4 points (44.8 percent to 43.4 percent). <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-is-more-unpopular-than-ever-that-could-help-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A week ago</a>, Democrats led Republicans by 1.2 points (44.9 percent to 43.7 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Democrats by 0.5 points (43.9 percent to 43.4 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663326001606776</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Will The Polls Overestimate Democrats Again?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-the-polls-overestimate-democrats-again/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Will The Polls Overestimate Democrats Again?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 16, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">As Democrats’ prospects for the midterms have improved — they’re now up to a 71 percent chance of keeping the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Senate</a> and a 29 percent chance of retaining the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House</a>, according to the 2022 FiveThirtyEight midterm election forecast<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forecast odds throughout are as of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>20</sup></a> — I’ve observed a corresponding increase in concern among liberals that the polls might overestimate Democrats’ position again, as they did in 2016 and 2020. Even among commenters who are analyzing the race from an arm’s-length distance, there sometimes seems to be a <em>presumption</em> that the polls will be biased toward Democrats.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The best version of this argument comes from Other Nate (Nate Cohn, of The New York Times). He <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/12/upshot/polling-midterms-warning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pointed out</a> in a piece on Monday that states such as Wisconsin and Ohio where Democratic Senate candidates are outperforming <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s fundamentals index</a> — like how the state has voted in other recent elections — were also prone to significant polling errors in 2020. Cohn’s analysis is worth reading in full.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here, I’m going to present something of a rebuttal. Not necessarily to Cohn’s specific claims, but rather to the <em>presumption </em>I often see in discussion about polling that polling bias is predictable and necessarily favors Democrats. My contention is that while the polls could have another bad year, it’s hard to know right now whether that bias will benefit Democrats or Republicans. People’s guesses about this are often wrong. In 2014, for example, there was a lot of discussion about whether the polls <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/are-the-state-polls-skewed/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would have a pro-Republican bias</a>, as they did in 2012. But they turned out to have a pro-Democratic bias instead.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s one important complication to this, however.<em> </em>Our model actually assumes that current polling probably <em>does</em> overstate the case for Democrats. It’s just not necessarily for the reasons people assume.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As I mentioned, the Deluxe version of our forecast gives Democrats a 71 percent and 29 percent chance of keeping the Senate and House, respectively. But the Deluxe forecast isn’t just based on polls: It incorporates the fundamentals I mentioned earlier, along with <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/house-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expert ratings</a> about these races. Furthermore, it accounts for the historical tendency of the president’s party to perform poorly at the midterms, President Biden’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mediocre</a> (although improving) approval rating and the fact that Democrats may not perform as well in polls of likely voters as among registered voters. As the election approaches, it tends to put more weight on the polls and less on these other factors, but it never zeros them out completely. (In this respect, it <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-2020-presidential-forecast-works-and-whats-different-because-of-covid-19/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">differs from our presidential forecast</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By contrast, the Lite version of our forecast, which is more or less a “polls-only” view of the race, gives Democrats an 81 percent chance of keeping the Senate and a 41 percent chance of keeping the House. It also suggests that they’ll win somewhat more seats: There are 52.4 Democratic Senate seats in an average Lite simulation as compared with 50.8 in a Deluxe simulation, or 212 Democratic House seats in an average Lite simulation versus 209 in a Deluxe simulation. Notably, this corresponds to current polls overstating Democrats’ position by the equivalent of 1.5 or 2 percentage points. Put another way, we should think of a race in which the polling average shows Democrats 2 points ahead as being tied.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s not quite the same thing as saying that the polls are systematically biased, though. Polls reflect a snapshot of what is happening today, and Democrats might indeed do very well if the election were held now instead of in November. In states like Ohio, for instance, they’ve <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/can-tim-ryan-really-win-ohios-senate-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">enjoyed a significant advertising advantage</a> thanks to superior fundraising, but that will probably even out to some extent by Election Day. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, Biden and Democrats have also been on something of a winning streak lately, between a series of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/16/business/biden-climate-tax-inflation-reduction.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">policy accomplishments</a>, inflation trending downward and the political backlash to the Supreme Court’s <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/07/06/majority-of-public-disapproves-of-supreme-courts-decision-to-overturn-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpopular</a> decision to overturn Roe v. Wade. But a <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-a-single-u-s-inflation-report-roiled-global-financial-markets-11663185895" target="_blank" rel="noopener">worse-than-expected inflation report</a> this week and a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/15/business/rail-strike.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narrowly averted rail workers’ strike</a>, which could have caused substantial supply chain disruptions, are reminders that uncertain real-world events won’t necessarily continue to play out in Democrats’ favor.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also the case that in individual races, information besides the polls can help make a more accurate prediction, even when you have a lot of polls. For example, the <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/tree/master/partisan-lean" target="_blank" rel="noopener">partisan lean</a> of a state still tells you something. Let’s say the polling average has the Democrat ahead by 10 points in a state where the fundamentals put the Republican up by 2. Empirically, the best forecast in a race like this uses a blend of <em>mostly</em> polls and <em>some</em> fundamentals (exactly how much weight is given to the polls depends on how many polls there are and how close it is to the election). And you might end up with a forecast that has the Democrat winning by 7 or 8 points rather than 10 points, for instance. In that sense, in races such as Wisconsin and Ohio where there is a significant divergence between polls and fundamentals, Democrats probably should have concerns.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What I resist, though, is the implication that it can be presumed that the polls have a predictable, persistent, systematic bias toward Democrats. Is Rep. Tim Ryan going to underperform his current polls in Ohio’s Senate race? We’ll see, but more likely than not, the answer is yes. But is it just a thing now<em> </em>that polls <em>always</em> overrate Democrats?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">I’m skeptical. Here are seven reasons why:</p>



<h2>1. Polling bias hasn’t been predictable historically</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Our historical database of polls shows that there’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-death-of-polling-is-greatly-exaggerated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not much in the way of consistent polling bias</a>. Two cycles of a pro-Republican bias in 1998 and 2000 were followed by a Democratic bias in 2002. A fairly sharp Republican bias in 2012 reversed itself, and the polls were biased toward Democrats in both 2014 and 2016.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Polling bias isn’t consistent</h5>
 <p>Weighted-average statistical bias in polls in final 21 days of the campaign</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.pollsterratings2018.13"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Pres.</th>
 <th colspan="3" scope="colgroup">State Level</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Cycle</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">General</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Governor</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">U.S. Senate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">U.S. House</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Combined</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1998</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+5.8</td>
 <td>R+4.5</td>
 <td>R+0.9</td>
 <td>R+3.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1999-2000</td>
 <td>R+2.4</td>
 <td>R+0.2</td>
 <td>R+2.8</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>R+1.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2001-02</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+3.5</td>
 <td>D+2.0</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 <td>D+2.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2003-04</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 <td>D+1.9</td>
 <td>D+0.8</td>
 <td>D+2.1</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2005-06</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+0.4</td>
 <td>R+2.1</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 <td>D+0.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2007-08</td>
 <td>D+1.0</td>
 <td>R+0.1</td>
 <td>D+0.1</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 <td>D+0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2009-10</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+0.2</td>
 <td>R+0.8</td>
 <td>D+1.3</td>
 <td>D+0.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2011-12</td>
 <td>R+2.5</td>
 <td>R+1.6</td>
 <td>R+3.1</td>
 <td>R+3.2</td>
 <td>R+2.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2013-14</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+2.3</td>
 <td>D+2.7</td>
 <td>D+3.9</td>
 <td>D+2.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2015-16</td>
 <td>D+3.3</td>
 <td>D+3.1</td>
 <td>D+2.8</td>
 <td>D+3.4</td>
 <td>D+3.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2017-18</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+0.9</td>
 <td>EVEN</td>
 <td>R+0.8</td>
 <td>R+0.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2019-20</td>
 <td>D+4.2</td>
 <td>D+5.6</td>
 <td>D+5.0</td>
 <td>D+6.1</td>
 <td>D+4.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>All years</td>
 <td>D+1.3</td>
 <td>D+0.9</td>
 <td>D+0.7</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Bias is calculated only for races in which the top two finishers are a Democrat and a Republican. Therefore, it is not calculated for presidential primaries. Pollsters that are banned by FiveThirtyEight are not included in the averages. So as not to give a more prolific pollster too much influence over the average, polls are weighted by one over the square root of the number of polls each pollster conducted in a specific category.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Historically, the correlation between the polling bias in a given cycle and the bias in the previous cycle is either essentially zero or slightly negative, depending on whether you define “previous cycle” as “two years ago” or “four years ago.”<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meaning, the bias is, if anything, more likely to reverse itself than sustain itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>21</sup></a></p>



<h2>2. Pollsters have a strong incentive to be unbiased</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Pollsters get a lot of crap from people, but one nice thing about their job is that they regularly get to compare their results against reality. Sure, it’s possible for a pollster to get unlucky because of <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/PollingUnit/sampling-error-means/story?id=5984818" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sampling error</a> — if you survey 500 people, sometimes you’ll draw a sample showing the Republican winning even if the Democrat is really up by 5 points. For the most part, though, pollsters can and do consider changes to their methodology based on errors in past elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And precisely because pollsters are subject to public scrutiny and there are relatively objective ways to measure their performance, they have strong financial and professional incentives to scrutinize their methods for potential sources of error and fix them if they can. It’s the same incentive that a professional golfer has to fix his swing: If he’s consistently hitting every shot to the left side of the fairway, for instance, at some point he’ll make adjustments. Maybe he’ll even overcompensate and start hitting everything to the right side instead.</p>



<h2>3. The way polling averages weight pollsters changes</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even if pollsters don’t change their methods, the market will change the polling landscape on its own, at least to some degree. Pollsters who performed well in previous elections will get more business, and those who performed poorly will lose it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, we’ve seen relatively few traditional “<a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/04/19/politics/democrats-falling-lead-generic-ballot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gold standard</a>” polls sponsored by major media organizations this cycle, perhaps because those polls tended to have a Democratic bias in 2020. That’s a shame, because most of these polling organizations have <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/pollster-ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">good long-term track records</a> despite some recent problems. But it does mean that polling averages are more weighted toward Republican-leaning firms that have done comparatively well in recent election cycles, such as Rasmussen Reports and Trafalgar Group. This is especially true for FiveThirtyEight’s polling averages, which weight polls in part based on their historical accuracy. Groups like Rasmussen, for instance, get more say in the polling average than they did in 2020 because their rating is now higher.</p>



<h2>4. Polls haven’t had a Democratic bias in elections without Trump on the ballot</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">As you can see in the table in the first point, polls did <em>not</em> have a systematic Democratic bias in 2018. That seems relevant, considering that was the most recent midterm.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polls have also generally not had a Democratic bias in other elections in the Trump era when Trump himself was not on the ballot. They didn’t have one in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_United_States_Senate_special_election_in_Alabama" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alabama Senate special election in 2017</a>, for instance, or the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/georgia-senate-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia Senate runoffs in January 2021</a>, or in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last year’s Virginia gubernatorial race</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There have also been some races where Democrats have overperformed their polls, such as in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/california-recall-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last year’s California gubernatorial recall election</a> and in the <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/2017/governor/va/virginia_governor_gillespie_vs_northam-6197.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2017 governor’s race in Virginia</a>. But these errors don’t tend to get as much attention from the media as those that underestimated Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It may be that Republicans benefit from higher turnout only when Trump himself is on the ballot. A certain number of voters were willing to walk over glass to vote for Trump: Would they do the same for J.D. Vance, Mehmet Oz, Ron Johnson or Blake Masters? Evidence from non-Trump elections in the Trump era suggests maybe not. I tend not to buy the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-11-19/-shy-trump-voters-re-emerge-as-explanation-for-pollsters-miss" target="_blank" rel="noopener">so-called “shy Trump” theory</a>, or that voters are reluctant to state their preference for Trump. But it may <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-supporters-arent-shy-but-polls-could-still-be-missing-some-of-them/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nonetheless be hard to reach Trump voters</a>, who may be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/could-social-alienation-among-some-trump-supporters-help-explain-why-polls-underestimated-trump-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more socially isolated</a>, or who may be irregular voters who are screened out by likely voter models. </p>



<h2>5. Polls have been unbiased or underestimated Democrats in recent elections in 2022</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had a lot of success in elections since the Supreme Court’s Dobbs decision</a> — and importantly for our purposes, they’ve done as well or better than polls predicted in these races:</p>



<ul><li>In the Kansas abortion referendum, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-abortion-vote-in-kansas-looks-like-its-going-to-be-close/">only poll</a> showed the “yes” side — which would have enabled the Kansas Legislature to implement additional abortion restrictions — winning by 4 percentage points, but it lost by 18 points (!) instead.</li><li>Meanwhile, the only <a href="https://www.surveyusa.com/client/PollReport.aspx?g=6a557ea4-bde8-49df-a0f0-9d077812693f">nonpartisan poll</a> of the special election in Minnesota’s 1st Congressional District showed Republican Brad Finstad winning by 8 points, but he actually won by 4, although an internal poll released by his opponent <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/579258412/MN-01-Poll-Results-Memo-Ettinger-Campaign">did underestimate Finstad’s margin</a>.</li><li>That said, polls of the special election in Alaska’s at-large House seat were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2022_Alaska%27s_at-large_congressional_district_special_election">quite accurate</a> in predicting both the first-round vote and that Democrat Mary Peltola would narrowly defeat former Alaska Gov. Sarah Palin if they were the final two candidates using Alaska’s ranked-choice system.</li><li>Finally, of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2022_New_York%27s_19th_congressional_district_special_election">five polls</a> of the special election in New York’s 19th Congressional District, which were from a mix of Democratic and Republican firms, all showed Republican Marc Molinaro winning by margins ranging from 3 points to 14 points. But Democrat Pat Ryan <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/">won by 2 points instead</a>.</li></ul><p data-paragraph="main">I couldn’t find any polls for the special elections in New York’s 23rd Congressional District or Nebraka’s 1st Congressional District, also held since the Dobbs decision.</p>



<h2>6. Pollsters have a semi-decent excuse for 2020: COVID-19</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ironically, polls conducted before large parts of the country were shut down in March 2020 in response to the COVID-19 pandemic were more accurate than those conducted immediately before Election Day in 2020. Take the FiveThirtyEight polling average on March 1, 2020. It showed <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden up by 4.1 percentage points nationally</a>, very close to his eventual 4.5-point popular vote margin. Our polling averages also correctly showed a very close race in states such as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pennsylvania</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wisconsin</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This may be because the pandemic <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2020/11/10/21551766/election-polls-results-wrong-david-shor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">profoundly affected who answered the polls</a>. Specifically, Democrats were more likely to be in jurisdictions that implemented stay-at-home orders, and liberals were otherwise more likely to voluntarily limit their social interactions. Having more time at home on their hands, they may have been more likely to respond to polls. That’s less of a concern this year, with <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1675/most-important-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">few voters treating COVID-19 as a high priority</a> and few government restrictions in place.</p>



<h2>7. People are too hung up on polls from 2016 and 2020</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/Politics-Voices/2014/1121/Elections-have-consequences-Does-Obama-regret-saying-that-now" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Elections have consequences</a>, and they’re relatively infrequent events. So the second-guessing and recriminations tend to linger for a while.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that doesn’t change the fact that people’s concerns about the polls stem mostly from a sample of exactly two elections, 2020 and 2016. You can point out that polls also had a Democratic bias in 2014. But, of course, they had a Republican bias in 2012, were largely unbiased in 2018, and have either tended to be unbiased or had a Republican bias in recent special elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">True, in 2020 and 2016, polls were off the mark in a large number of races and states. But the whole notion of a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-need-a-systematic-polling-error-to-win-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">systematic polling error</a> is that it’s, well, systematic: It affects nearly all races, or at least the large majority of them. There just isn’t a meaningful sample size to work with here, or anything close to it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Again, that doesn’t mean you should expect the polls to be spot-on. It may be that we’re living in a universe with larger polling errors than before in response to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/02/27/response-rates-in-telephone-surveys-have-resumed-their-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">declining response rates</a>. And there are some decent reasons to suspect that Democrats won’t perform as well in November as they would in an election right now. Still, I’ll stick to my usual advice: Prepare for the polls to be wrong — in either direction.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663326001606775</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: It’s Not Yet Time To Start Worrying About The Polls</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-its-not-yet-time-to-start-worrying-about-the-polls/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Model Talk</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-its-not-yet-time-to-start-worrying-about-the-polls/">
	<div data-podcast-id="344296" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: It's Not Yet Time To Start Worrying About The Polls">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9025875590.mp3?updated=1663270621">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Why have Democrats’ odds of winning the House and Senate improved so consistently in recent months? Can the polls be trusted? In this installment of “Model Talk” on the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Nate Silver and Galen Druke discuss what’s behind the recent movement in the forecast and answer questions from listeners.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 20:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663272001329716</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
