<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 19:29:06 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 18:29:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>No President Is Safe From His Own COVID-19 Policy</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/no-president-is-safe-from-his-own-covid-19-policy/</link>
						<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/covid-19/" name="">COVID-19</a></p>
						
													<h1>No President Is Safe From His Own COVID-19 Policy</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/maggie-koerth/" title="" rel="author">Maggie Koerth</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 22, 2022, at 12:56 PM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="JAPAN-US-DIPLOMACY" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240850141-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240850141-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240850141-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240850141-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>SAUL LOEB /AFP / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The French philosopher Joseph de Maistre once said that every country gets the government it deserves. Likewise, perhaps every American president gets the COVID-19 infection <em>he</em> deserves. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">OK, “deserves” might be a strong word. While de Maistre, a counter-Enlightenment intellectual who believed in the divine right of kings as the most stable form of government, probably would endorse the concept of pathogen as karmic comeuppance, we here at FiveThirtyEight believe a case of COVID isn’t anyone’s punishment for anything. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, <em>mayyyybe</em> that’s a little less true if you’re the guy deciding what choices are available to everyone else. The news this week that <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/wireStory/explainer-biden-catching-covid-19-87198494" target="_blank" rel="noopener">President Biden had been diagnosed with COVID</a> started me thinking about the ways an American president can set the stage for his own infection through his decisions about pandemic policy. If anyone in this country ever got a case of COVID because of their own mistakes, it’s Biden and Donald Trump. It’s almost as if each man’s illness was a microcosm of the larger way he chose to approach the virus — and of how those choices affected everyone else in the country he led. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump likely got his infection via a famously cavalier approach to party planning — throwing a largely unmasked gathering at a point in the pandemic when vaccines weren’t yet available. On Sept. 26, 2020, the then-president held a Rose Garden event to celebrate the nomination of Amy Coney Barrett to the Supreme Court. Case numbers in Washington, D.C., were low at the time, but this was a party full of hugging and handshakes — and it launched a <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/white-house/fauci-calls-amy-coney-barrett-ceremony-rose-garden-superspreader-event-n1242781" target="_blank" rel="noopener">superspreader event</a> that likely <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/10/19/seeing-rose-garden-superspreader-convocation-as-a-never-event/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">infected not just the president</a> and first lady but also multiple members of Congress, White House staffers, members of the media and a whole litany of government and campaign workers. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2021/02/trumps-covid-case-was-reportedly-more-severe-than-he-led-on.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ended up in the hospital</a> with a case so severe, he came close to being put on a ventilator and was given basically every drug doctors could think of to treat COVID — a mixture of dexamethasone, remdesivir and monoclonal antibodies. Throughout the ordeal, Trump’s large-scale <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/latest-updates-trump-covid-19-results/2020/10/02/919432383/how-trump-has-downplayed-the-coronavirus-pandemic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public policy choices</a> — mocking and dismissing masks and other ways of preventing transmission, downplaying the severity of COVID risks, promising a miracle would come along and make the virus disappear, etc. — were reflected in his own experience.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But while President Biden has approached the pandemic in a very different way than President Trump, he, too, has made a series of choices that set the stage for his own infection. If the overarching theme of Trump’s approach to COVID was to shut his eyes and hope the pandemic couldn’t see him if he couldn’t see it, the overarching theme of Biden’s approach has been to frame a collective disaster as just another matter of personal responsibility. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The administration thought it had a silver bullet, going so far as to declare that July 4, 2021, would be a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/15/white-house-to-host-july-4-independence-from-virus-bash-494638" target="_blank" rel="noopener">celebration of freedom from COVID</a>. They were so certain that individual vaccinations would be enough that they rolled back federal <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/14/us/no-masks-cdc.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mask mandates in May 2021</a> under the assumption that if you did the right thing and got vaccinated, then you’d be fine. Even as delta, omicron, and multiple omicronlets proved this theory wrong, Biden’s policy has continued to focus mainly on getting more Americans vaccinated and boosted. Other policy options that could prevent spread — ventilation requirements, reliable data collection on case numbers, masking during periods of high transmission, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/26/health/the-biden-administration-is-being-criticized-for-falling-short-on-its-pledge-to-provide-vaccines-to-the-world.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">getting vaccines to other countries</a> where the virus still spreads unchecked — <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2022/01/18/1073292913/a-year-in-experts-assess-bidens-hits-and-misses-on-handling-the-pandemic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have largely been left to wither</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The result is an America where COVID keeps mutating, waves of disease keep coming and the populations of the most vulnerable remain isolated, trapped and dying. We have an America where we take COVID seriously but not literally. We have an America where even the most responsible and well-protected of Americans is almost guaranteed to get COVID eventually. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even a president who trusts the science. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 17:56:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658511001523952</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New Hampshire Is Tiny And Pretty Weird. That Could Help Maggie Hassan.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-hampshire-is-tiny-and-pretty-weird-that-could-help-maggie-hassan/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Elastic States</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>New Hampshire Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>New Hampshire Is Tiny And Pretty Weird. That Could Help Maggie Hassan.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 22, 2022, at 8:45 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0722-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0722-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0722-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0722-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0722-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">We remain in something of a summer doldrums for polling, and the overall outlook for November remains about the same as in recent weeks. But polls on the race for Congress <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have continued to inch slightly toward Democrats</a> in what may reflect the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maybe-dobbs-did-change-the-race-well-need-more-time-to-know-for-sure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">impact of the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Roe v. Wade</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the Deluxe version of our <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">midterm election forecast</a>, Republicans have a 85 percent chance to win the House and a 51 percent chance to win the Senate, both largely unchanged from when <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-are-favored-to-win-the-house-but-not-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we launched the model three weeks ago</a>. Meanwhile, in the Classic version of the model, which sticks to purely quantitative factors and leaves out the expert race ratings published by <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/house-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Cook Political Report</a> and other such groups, Republicans are actually underdogs to win control of the Senate, with a 39 percent chance.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Part of the reason Republicans are not better positioned in the Senate is they don’t have a lot of easy pick-up opportunities, but one race where Republicans could gain traction is <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the New Hampshire Senate race</a>. Democratic incumbent Sen. Maggie Hassan has led in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all but one poll this year against a series of potential Republican opponents</a>, but the GOP shouldn’t write the race off. Hassan’s lead is small in most of these polls, and it’s still early, with the primary not scheduled until Sept. 13.<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What the hell, New Hampshire?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">New Hampshire is also an unusual state in that it has some factors that should make it relatively fertile ground to defeat an incumbent, and others that should make it a challenging one. So let’s take a look under the hood.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-pessimistic-changing-politics-87044495</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">The factor that could help Republicans most is that New Hampshire — famous for polling leads that seem to evaporate overnight, like <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna22551718" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Barack Obama’s against Hillary Clinton’s in the Democratic primary there in 2008</a> — is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/swing-voters-and-elastic-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">notoriously swingy</a>. I don’t just mean that it’s a <em>swing state</em>, although it frequently is in general elections. I also mean that it has a lot of swing <em>voters</em>: moderate, independent voters who split their tickets. Consider that, in 2020, Democratic Sen. Jeanne Shaheen won reelection there by 16 percentage points, while Republican Gov. Chris Sununu was reelected by 32 points on the same ballot.<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contrast to a state like New Hampshire is a state like Georgia, which is also a swing state, but not because it has a lot of swing voters. Instead, it’s mostly a swing state because it has some very Republican-leaning groups like evangelical white voters and some very Democratic-leaning groups like Black voters and young, college-educated professionals, who roughly cancel one another out. Races in Georgia, then, tend to be more about who can turn out their base. New Hampshire is more about persuasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight measures this with our elasticity index, which is derived from voter-level survey data<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we use the &lt;a href="https://cces.gov.harvard.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Cooperative Election Study&lt;/a&gt; from 2014 through 2020, which contains demographic information and presidential voting preferences for tens of thousands of voters. From this data, we can then determine how many voters in each state are likely to vote for each party and how many are plausibly up for grabs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>3</sup></a> to reflect how sensitive a state is to national trends. New Hampshire has an elasticity index of 1.21 — the fourth-highest in the country — which means that for every 1-point shift in the national environment, we’d expect New Hampshire to shift by about 1.2 points instead. So, for instance, a 5-point swing toward Republicans nationally would produce a 6-point swing there. That makes Hassan a bit more vulnerable.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What makes a state swingy? Generally speaking, the most reliable group of Democratic voters are Black voters, and the most reliable group of Republican voters are evangelical white Christians. New Hampshire is <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/02/29/how-religious-is-your-state/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quite secular and quite white</a>, so neither party’s base is very large there.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Likewise, most other high-elasticity states are relatively nonreligious and have relatively few Black voters, although states with large numbers of Latino voters <em>can</em> be pretty swingy, as <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/07/11/latino-voters-are-shifting-right-heres-where-democrats-will-be-hit-hardest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats are discovering to their dismay</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><section><header><h5>New Hampshire is a swingy state</h5>
 <p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight’s 2022 state elasticity scores</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.eu07222022.3"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Elasticity Score</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Rhode Island</td>
 <td>1.29</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hawaii</td>
 <td>1.23</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Alaska</td>
 <td>1.22</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>1.21</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Vermont</td>
 <td>1.15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Massachusetts</td>
 <td>1.14</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maine</td>
 <td>1.14</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Utah</td>
 <td>1.11</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Connecticut</td>
 <td>1.10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Dakota</td>
 <td>1.09</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td>1.09</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wyoming</td>
 <td>1.08</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Mexico</td>
 <td>1.08</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Iowa</td>
 <td>1.07</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td>1.07</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Washington</td>
 <td>1.06</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>1.06</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>1.05</td>
 </tr><tr><td>West Virginia</td>
 <td>1.04</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Indiana</td>
 <td>1.04</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Michigan</td>
 <td>1.03</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nebraska</td>
 <td>1.03</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kansas</td>
 <td>1.03</td>
 </tr><tr><td>South Dakota</td>
 <td>1.03</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td>1.02</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td>1.02</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Idaho</td>
 <td>1.02</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arkansas</td>
 <td>1.02</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Texas</td>
 <td>1.01</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Jersey</td>
 <td>1.01</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Minnesota</td>
 <td>1.00</td>
 </tr><tr><td>California</td>
 <td>1.00</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>0.99</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oregon</td>
 <td>0.98</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New York</td>
 <td>0.97</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Illinois</td>
 <td>0.96</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Montana</td>
 <td>0.96</td>
 </tr><tr><td>South Carolina</td>
 <td>0.96</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oklahoma</td>
 <td>0.96</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kentucky</td>
 <td>0.95</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Missouri</td>
 <td>0.94</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Tennessee</td>
 <td>0.94</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Virginia</td>
 <td>0.94</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td>0.93</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Louisiana</td>
 <td>0.92</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>0.90</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maryland</td>
 <td>0.87</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Delaware</td>
 <td>0.86</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Mississippi</td>
 <td>0.85</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Alabama</td>
 <td>0.83</td>
 </tr></tbody></table></section></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Elasticity isn’t the only factor the model considers, however. Another is a state’s population. And in smaller states, the incumbency advantage is larger.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If you’re a Senate history buff, think about states that have a handful of electoral votes, like Vermont, West Virginia, Hawaii or North Dakota. They tend to have fairly long-tenured senators. Only four senators (Bernie Sanders, Patrick Leahy, Jim Jeffords and Robert Stafford) have represented Vermont since 1975, for example. (Although Leahy is retiring and not seeking reelection this year.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why might the incumbency advantage be larger in small states? I can think of a few theories. One is that, in a smaller state, it’s easier for a senator to maintain a strong, personal relationship with influential constituents and to be visible in her community. A second theory is about competition: In a smaller state, there are fewer highly talented politicians with national aspirations, so an incumbent will be up against weaker opponents, on average.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A third hypothesis: It’s all about the pork. Since each state has the same number of senators, a senator from a small state is more likely to extract concessions in exchange for pork-barrel spending,<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, any senator can ask for concessions. But a pork-barrel project that makes a big dent in California or Texas’s finances is going to be pretty expensive. A small state is much cheaper to buy off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> and this can make them more popular across party lines with voters at home (think Sens. Lisa Murkowski of Alaska or Joe Manchin of West Virginia). Whatever the reason, the statistical tendency of small-state Senate incumbents to overperform is fairly robust, and this is accounted for by our model.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What else helps an incumbent? The weirder a state, the bigger the incumbency advantage. OK, I should probably clarify what I mean by “weird.” A more precise term would be “dissimilar” or “distinctive.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As part of our forecast, we <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">apply a process called CANTOR</a><a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the tradition of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PECOTA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;PECOTA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/carmelo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;CARMELO&lt;/a&gt;, we created a stupid backronym for it: Congressional Algorithm using Neighboring Typologies to Optimize Regression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>5</sup></a> that determines which states and congressional districts are most similar to one another according to a variety of demographic, geographic and political variables — such as race, religion, income and education, population density, latitude and longitude, and voting behavior in recent presidential elections. A state like Hawaii qualifies as distinctive by this process, for instance. It has a far bigger Asian American and Native Hawaiian population than other states, it’s very Democratic, it’s very expensive and it’s <a href="https://www.nps.gov/havo/learn/nature/index.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">truly out there in the middle of nowhere in the Pacific Ocean</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">New Hampshire counts as <em>somewhat</em> distinctive, by contrast. As I mentioned, it’s quite white and quite nonreligious relative to the rest of the country. It also has above-average incomes and education levels but below-average population density (in <a href="https://twitter.com/NateSilver538/status/1527753858621050886?s=20&amp;t=MLisH9eBBztsGjaGpI675w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the way that FiveThirtyEight measures it</a>). On the other hand, it is toward the middle of the road politically. Overall, it ranks as the 25th-most distinctive state. Michigan is the state which most closely resembles the rest of the country, by contrast.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><section><header><h5>New England is distinctive</h5>
 <p data-paragraph="main">States that are least similar to other states, according to FiveThirtyEight’s CANTOR</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.eu07222022.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Rank</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td>
 <td>Hawaii</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2</td>
 <td>California</td>
 </tr><tr><td>3</td>
 <td>Utah</td>
 </tr><tr><td>4</td>
 <td>Alaska</td>
 </tr><tr><td>5</td>
 <td>Vermont</td>
 </tr><tr><td>6</td>
 <td>Massachusetts</td>
 </tr><tr><td>7</td>
 <td>Wyoming</td>
 </tr><tr><td>8</td>
 <td>New York</td>
 </tr><tr><td>9</td>
 <td>Maryland</td>
 </tr><tr><td>10</td>
 <td>West Virginia</td>
 </tr><tr><td>11</td>
 <td>New Jersey</td>
 </tr><tr><td>12</td>
 <td>Mississippi</td>
 </tr><tr><td>13</td>
 <td>North Dakota</td>
 </tr><tr><td>14</td>
 <td>Rhode Island</td>
 </tr><tr><td>15</td>
 <td>South Dakota</td>
 </tr><tr><td>16</td>
 <td>Idaho</td>
 </tr><tr><td>17</td>
 <td>Maine</td>
 </tr><tr><td>18</td>
 <td>Arkansas</td>
 </tr><tr><td>19</td>
 <td>New Mexico</td>
 </tr><tr><td>20</td>
 <td>Connecticut</td>
 </tr><tr><td>21</td>
 <td>Washington</td>
 </tr><tr><td>22</td>
 <td>Texas</td>
 </tr><tr><td>23</td>
 <td>Alabama</td>
 </tr><tr><td>24</td>
 <td>Oklahoma</td>
 </tr><tr><td>25</td>
 <td>New Hampshire</td>
 </tr><tr><td>26</td>
 <td>Nevada</td>
 </tr><tr><td>27</td>
 <td>Montana</td>
 </tr><tr><td>28</td>
 <td>Louisiana</td>
 </tr><tr><td>29</td>
 <td>Florida</td>
 </tr><tr><td>30</td>
 <td>Delaware</td>
 </tr><tr><td>31</td>
 <td>Oregon</td>
 </tr><tr><td>32</td>
 <td>Tennessee</td>
 </tr><tr><td>33</td>
 <td>Kentucky</td>
 </tr><tr><td>34</td>
 <td>Illinois</td>
 </tr><tr><td>35</td>
 <td>South Carolina</td>
 </tr><tr><td>36</td>
 <td>Colorado</td>
 </tr><tr><td>37</td>
 <td>Georgia</td>
 </tr><tr><td>38</td>
 <td>Arizona</td>
 </tr><tr><td>39</td>
 <td>Nebraska</td>
 </tr><tr><td>40</td>
 <td>Virginia</td>
 </tr><tr><td>41</td>
 <td>Iowa</td>
 </tr><tr><td>42</td>
 <td>Minnesota</td>
 </tr><tr><td>43</td>
 <td>North Carolina</td>
 </tr><tr><td>44</td>
 <td>Kansas</td>
 </tr><tr><td>45</td>
 <td>Missouri</td>
 </tr><tr><td>46</td>
 <td>Pennsylvania</td>
 </tr><tr><td>47</td>
 <td>Indiana</td>
 </tr><tr><td>48</td>
 <td>Wisconsin</td>
 </tr><tr><td>49</td>
 <td>Ohio</td>
 </tr><tr><td>50</td>
 <td>Michigan</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p data-paragraph="main">Factors that CANTOR considers include race, religion, age, gender, household income, educational status, voting behavior in recent presidential and state legislative elections, percentage of residents born abroad, population density, geographic region, latitude and longitude. </p>
 </footer></section></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How could distinctiveness provide an advantage to an incumbent? In some ways, the answers are similar to why small states have a leg up. If a state has a population with unique concerns — say, religious minorities like Mormon or Jewish voters, or a racial minority like Native Hawaiians — incumbents can exhibit competence by serving those populations in ways that somewhat cross party lines and are less subject to the whims of the national political environment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Another related theory is that there could be a stronger bond between voters and politicians in distinctive states. The politician may be a member of the minority group, or they may have ties to an industry that is uniquely important in the state. In the same sense that you probably know a married couple who are “perfect for one another,”<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Often, of course, a backhanded compliment which means they’d annoy the living hell out of anyone &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a> there may be <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/27/upshot/marriages-of-power-couples-reinforce-income-inequality.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stronger matching</a> in these cases.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But a statistical measure of distinctiveness is only as good as its inputs, and there are some things CANTOR leaves out. Being home to an industry like gambling in Nevada or coal production in West Virginia is potentially politically important, for instance, but CANTOR doesn’t take this into consideration.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Overall, New England is a culturally distinctive region that is hard to pin down statistically, but is visible in everything from its cuisine to its <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/04/23/upshot/24-upshot-baseball.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">intense loyalty to the Boston Red Sox</a>. My subjective experience is that New England is considerably weirder — excuse me, “more distinctive” — than our metric describes it, and that means New England tends to be quite loyal to its incumbents. Hassan will hope that pattern holds.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although New Hampshire itself has had reasonably high turnover in the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 13:45:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658497502243535</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Jan. 6 Committee’s Closing Argument Was About Trump’s Morality</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-jan-6th-committees-closing-argument-was-about-trumps-morality/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Jan. 6 Investigation</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/january-6th/" name="">January 6th</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Jan. 6 Committee's Closing Argument Was About Trump's Morality</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 22, 2022, at 7:56 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="House Select January 6 Committee Holds Its Eighth Hearing" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1410179291-e1658489993282.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1410179291-e1658489993282.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1410179291-e1658489993282.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1410179291-e1658489993282.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Tasos Katopodis / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">As a violent mob of his supporters smashed through windows to enter the U.S. Capitol building on Jan. 6, 2021, then-President Donald Trump did nothing. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As members of Congress and his vice president, Mike Pence, were forced to flee for their safety, Trump did nothing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As members of Pence’s security detail were telling colleagues over the radio to tell their families they loved them, Trump did nothing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the final summertime hearing from the House Select Committee investigating the Jan. 6 attack, the focus was on <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/live-updates/jan6-hearing-live-updates/?id=87139053" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s inaction for more than three hours</a> during the violence at the Capitol. After eight hearings detailing everything Trump had done that led to the attack, and framing it as potentially criminal, the committee spent this last hearing focused on what the former president didn’t do — and framed it as a moral failing. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s no secret that the Jan. 6 committee has been using the hearings, in part, to lay out an argument that Trump may be liable for criminal charges. In <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/02/jan6-trump-obstruction-justice-00013440" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a court filing in March</a>, the committee suggested it had sufficient evidence to conclude that “the President and members of his Campaign engaged in a criminal conspiracy to defraud the United States.” Committee members, including <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/prosecuting-trump-jan-fuel-graver-threat-liz-cheney/story?id=86132933" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the vice chair, Rep. Liz Cheney</a>, have said the Department of Justice should not shy away from prosecuting Trump if prosecution is warranted. And the hearings have prompted endless speculation over what crimes, if any, the <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/jan-6-panel-trump-broke-laws-riot-2020-election-lost-2022-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">former president could</a> be charged with. Though it’s ultimately up to the Department of Justice (which is conducting its own investigation into Jan. 6) to decide whether charges are warranted, the committee has made its case over the past few months. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it’s hard to prove that inaction constitutes a crime. And so on Thursday the committee tried to make a different case. The committee focused on evidence showing that everyone around Trump that day — his staffers, his attorneys and even his children — had urged him to speak out, to condemn the violence and to tell the rioters to go home. The committee shared an assortment of text messages sent to Trump’s chief of staff, Mark Meadows, from Republican members of Congress, Fox News hosts and Trump’s son Don Jr., all urging him to persuade the president to condemn the violence. Trump eventually did, <a href="https://www.c-span.org/video/?507774-1/president-trump-claims-election-stolen-tells-protesters-leave-capitol" target="_blank" rel="noopener">putting out a public statement</a> asking the rioters to go home peacefully, though he also added: “We love you. You’re very special.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/latest-jan-hearing-testimony-affect-midterm-elections-86274149</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">There were repeated references to oaths throughout the hearing — Trump’s oath of office, the oath his Cabinet members take, the oaths members of law enforcement and Congress take — and the dereliction of duty that comes from not honoring those oaths. The committee juxtaposed Trump’s inaction with other leaders who, as Rep. Elaine Luria phrased it, “honored their oath” that day. Pence worked to try to get military and law enforcement mobilized to the Capitol. Senate leaders Chuck Schumer and Mitch McConnell, as revealed in a never-before-seen video, worked together on a call with acting Secretary of Defense Chris Miller to determine how quickly they could resume the joint session and complete the vote count. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But in case the target of the committee’s criticism wasn’t obvious, committee members minced no words as the hearing drew to a close. Rep. Adam Kinzinger called Trump’s inaction on Jan. 6 “a dereliction of duty,” emphasizing why they were closing the summer hearings with a focus on this small chapter of the Jan. 6 saga. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Oaths matter,” he said. “Character matters. Truth matters.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (July 22, 2022, 11:40 a.m.):</strong> This article has been updated to correct Rep. Liz Cheney’s role in the House select committee. She is the vice chair, not the co-chair, of the committee.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 12:56:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658493002178990</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Democrats Are Disillusioned Over Climate Change</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democrats-are-disillusioned-over-climate-change/</link>
						<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>Climate Change</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/climate-change/" name="">Climate Change</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Democrats Are Disillusioned Over Climate Change</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Zoha Qamar</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 22, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0721_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0721_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0721_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0721_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0721_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Senate Democrats’ monthslong effort to negotiate a budget reconciliation bill with ambitious climate change provisions <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/manchin-appears-sink-biden-agenda-climate-tax-reform/story?id=86882215" target="_blank" rel="noopener">crumbled last week</a> when Sen. Joe Manchin announced he wouldn’t back the proposed legislation. It now appears unlikely that Congress will pass any substantive environmental legislation ahead of this year’s midterm elections. And although President Biden did issue <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-executive-actions-climate-change-fall-short-activists/story?id=87105954" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some executive orders on Wednesday to address climate change</a> — and is expected to announce more in the coming days — activists have criticized those measures as not going far enough.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This lack of action on climate change is becoming a real problem for Democrats, as it’s something their voters really want. In mid-January, the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/02/16/publics-top-priority-for-2022-strengthening-the-nations-economy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a> asked Americans which among 18 issues should be a top priority for Congress and the president to address, and 65 percent of Democrats selected climate change, ranking it as their fourth-most-important issue. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For the most part, Democrats overwhelmingly support the Biden administration’s policies combating climate change: 79 percent, <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2022/07/14/americans-divided-over-direction-of-bidens-climate-change-policies/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">per a survey conducted by Pew in early May</a>, said Biden’s environmental policies were moving the country in the right direction. The problem is that, even among Democrats who approve of the Biden administration’s approach, three in five (61 percent) still think the administration could be doing more — and this was even before Manchin torpedoed Democrats’ latest environmental policy efforts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This has created a situation where Democrats, <em>especially</em> younger ones, are dissatisfied with how climate change is being addressed. Younger Americans of both parties are more likely than older Americans to rate climate change as a top priority, and in the Pew poll from May, younger Democrats were also more likely to say that the Biden administration should be doing more. Nearly three-quarters (73 percent) of U.S. adults under 30 said the administration should be doing more, compared with 54 percent of those over 65 who said the same.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why haven’t Democratic politicians done more to prioritize this issue, given its importance to Democratic voters? Climate change just isn’t an issue other Americans prioritize.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, even though climate change was a top priority for Democrats in the January Pew poll, it was only the 14th-most-important issue for voters overall. That’s in part because Republicans do not prioritize climate change: Just 11 percent said it should be a top priority for Congress and the president, compared with 65 percent of Democrats. In fact, climate change was the <em>most</em> polarizing issue Pew asked about — even more so than views on dealing with the COVID-19 outbreak.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/supreme-court-undermined-bidens-climate-change-agenda-fivethirtyeight-87151207</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">In Pew’s more recent polling, Republicans were also overwhelmingly likely to disapprove of how the Biden administration was handling climate change. Eighty-two percent said the Biden administration’s climate policies were moving the country in the wrong direction. Notably, however, this was less true among younger Republicans, who <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-some-socially-liberal-gen-z-voters-arent-leaving-the-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are more likely</a> than their older counterparts to prioritize climate change. In fact, 47 percent of Republicans under 30 said that the federal government wasn’t doing enough for the environment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This means that, practically, there is a very limited set of climate change policies where we see any bipartisan agreement. Of five specific climate change policy issues Pew asked about in May, only two garnered support from a majority of both Democrats and Republicans: a proposal to plant trees to absorb carbon emissions and a proposal to provide tax credits to businesses that are developing methods to store or capture carbon emissions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, this makes passing substantial climate change policy, such as what Democrats were hoping to get through Congress this summer, a nearly insurmountable challenge — especially when a party-line vote is contingent on the support of someone like Manchin, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Business/wireStory/manchin-wavers-bidens-plan-rebuffs-progressives-80910895" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a longtime challenger</a> to sweeping climate change reform. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So where does that leave the many Democrats who think climate change is a key priority? Largely disillusioned and cynical, according to a late-January poll by Pew: <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2022/03/01/americans-largely-favor-u-s-taking-steps-to-become-carbon-neutral-by-2050/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">51 percent of Democrats</a> said they didn’t believe the U.S. and other countries would make enough of an effort to combat climate change, and among liberal Democrats alone, that share ticked up to 60 percent. Climate change is a really important issue for Democrats, but it’s not one that resonates as deeply for others.</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Vanilla reigns supreme as the nation’s top ice cream flavor, <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/lifestyle/articles-reports/2022/07/19/favorite-ice-cream-flavors-yougov-poll-july-13-18-">per YouGov polling</a> conducted<a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/lifestyle/articles-reports/2022/07/19/favorite-ice-cream-flavors-yougov-poll-july-13-18-"></a> July 13-18. In a multiple-choice question, 59 percent of American adults reported liking vanilla, with chocolate (51 percent), strawberry (43 percent) and cookies and cream (43 percent) rounding out the top four. In terms of toppings, hot fudge was the most popular, at 40 percent, while 41 percent said they preferred their ice cream in a cup or bowl instead of in a waffle (33 percent) or sugar (12 percent) cone. </li><li>Thirty-eight percent of Americans think a lack of child care options very often stops mothers who’d like to work beyond the home from doing so, according to a July 15 <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/07/15/9609d/1">poll from YouGov</a>. Meanwhile, a second <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/07/15/9609d/2">question from YouGov</a> reveals that only 13 percent of Americans say the same barrier exists for fathers very often. </li><li>Most Americans (58 percent) are “just a little confident” or “not at all confident” that the country’s elections reflect the will of its citizens, per a <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/22090467-rel9d-elections46">CNN/SSRS poll</a> conducted June 13-July 13. That share has steadily been increasing since January 2021, when only 40 percent said the same. Overall, almost half of U.S. adults think it’s somewhat (33 percent) or very likely (14 percent) that their elected politicians will “successfully overturn” election results in response to their party’s loss. </li><li>More bad news for the news: <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/a-gas-holiday-might-be-popular-but-its-unlikely-to-do-much-to-lower-inflation/">Confidence in the media</a> continues to sink to an all-time low, according to <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/394817/media-confidence-ratings-record-lows.aspx">Gallup</a> polling from June 1-20. Only 16 percent of Americans said they have “a great deal” or “quite a lot” of faith in newspapers, while just 11 percent said the same about television news. Newspapers were at their most trusted in 1979 (51 percent), six years after Gallup first asked the question about that platform, while confidence in broadcast journalism peaked in 1993, the first year Gallup began surveys for television news, too. Now, close to half of Americans report very little or no confidence in either print (46 percent) or broadcast (53 percent) news. </li></ul><h2>Biden approval</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> 37.5 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 57.2 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -19.7 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/one-of-the-few-things-americans-agree-on-space-is-cool/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 38.7 percent approved and 56.0 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -17.3 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 39.6 percent and a disapproval rating of 54.8 percent, for a net approval rating of -15.2 points.</p>



<h2>Generic ballot</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main"><br>In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 1.1 points (44.3 percent to 43.2 percent). A week ago, Republicans led Democrats by 1.8 points (44.8 percent to 43.1 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 2.2 points (44.7 percent to 42.5 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658488502162529</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Want To Know Where The Supreme Court Goes Next? Look At Alito’s And Thomas’s Dissents.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/want-to-know-where-the-supreme-court-goes-next-look-at-alitos-and-thomass-dissents/</link>
						<dc:creator>Laura Bronner</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Laura Bronner and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Affirmative Action</category>
			<category>Civil Rights</category>
			<category>Clarence Thomas</category>
			<category>Criminal Justice</category>
			<category>Samuel Alito</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/supreme-court/" name="">Supreme Court</a></p>
						
													<h1>Want To Know Where The Supreme Court Goes Next? Look At Alito's And Thomas's Dissents.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/laura-bronner/" title="" rel="author">Laura Bronner and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Laura Bronner and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							<p>Graphics by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/paroma-soni/" rel="author">Paroma Soni</a></p>
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 20, 2022, at 10:23 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT-4x3-1.png?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT-4x3-1.png?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Supreme Court Justices Clarence Thomas and Samuel Alito have been angry for years. Over and over, they watched as conservative justices joined the liberal justices in high-profile decisions. First, a coalition of Republican-appointed justices <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/505/833" target="_blank" rel="noopener">upheld the right to abortion</a>. Then there was the ruling that <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/2011/11-393" target="_blank" rel="noopener">preserved the Affordable Care Act</a>. A few years later, the court established <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/14-556" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a constitutional right to same-sex marriage</a>. Then — when the court’s conservative majority was even stronger — the justices ruled that <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/19pdf/17-1618_hfci.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sexual orientation is covered</a> under employment discrimination law. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In those kinds of cases, all Thomas and Alito could do was write furious dissents that accused their fellow justices of misunderstanding the Constitution and abusing their role as judges. Now, they’re in a very different position. With a conservative supermajority in place on the court, there are three other justices — Neil Gorsuch, Amy Coney Barrett and Brett Kavanaugh — who are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-partisan-divide-hasnt-been-this-sharp-in-generations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">much more likely to agree with Thomas and Alito</a> than previous Republican-appointed justices were.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a result, the court’s two most conservative justices are writing majority opinions on issues that they repeatedly used to write dissents for. This term, <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alito wrote an opinion</a> declaring that there was no constitutional right to abortion. Thomas went a step further, writing a concurring opinion that said that the court should use the logic of the abortion-rights case to dismantle the right to contraception, consensual same-sex intercourse, and same-sex marriage.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Thomas and Alito would like to revisit more than just that, and their past dissents give us hints at how they might change the country next. Writing a dissenting opinion is a sign of when a justice was particularly unhappy with a given case’s outcome, since each justice <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/glossary-of-legal-terms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t required to write their own dissent</a> — they can (and often do) sign onto another colleague’s dissenting opinion. A FiveThirtyEight analysis of every case Thomas or Alito considered since they joined the court<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We looked at dissents that were specifically authored or co-authored by Thomas or Alito, rather than dissents they joined that were authored by other justices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a> found that Alito and Thomas have both dissented a lot, on some issues more than others. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="842" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-use.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-use.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-use.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-use.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1226" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-mob-use.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-mob-use.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-mob-use.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-1-mob-use.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">These findings underscore just how far-reaching the conservative bloc’s priorities might be. Both justices, for example, seem eager to cut back significantly on criminal defendants’ rights established by earlier precedents. But that’s not all. Legal experts told us that if Alito and Thomas are helping to set the agenda, an even wider range of rights and precedents could be threatened — including on issues like civil rights, due process and privacy.</p>



<h2><strong>Criminal defendants’ rights are already being cut back</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Over their years on the court, Thomas and Alito have collectively written more dissents on criminal procedure — cases that involve the rights of people accused of crimes — than any other topic. Using data from the Supreme Court Database, we found that since Alito’s first full term in 2006, Alito wrote 19 percent of the dissents in criminal procedure cases and Thomas wrote 17 percent, together writing 86 dissents out of the 239 dissents written on this issue in total.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1098" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1456" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/atd.bronner.SCOTUS-GOES-NEXT.0720-2-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And with the court’s conservative supermajority in place, the pair are already helping to reshape the law on this issue. Last term, both Alito and Thomas wrote majority opinions with sweeping consequences for people accused of crimes, making it harder for suspects and criminal defendants to seek recourse if their rights are violated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/21-499_gfbh.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In the opinion written by Alito</a>, the court’s conservative majority ruled that if a <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/1965/759" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Miranda warning against self-incrimination</a> isn’t read, suspects don’t have the ability to sue the federal government for violating their constitutional rights. “A violation of Miranda does not necessarily constitute a violation of the Constitution,” Alito wrote. Which means that if someone doesn’t get a Miranda warning, they can’t sue the person who failed to give it to them — substantially undercutting the right against self-incrimination.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This hostility toward criminal defendants’ rights is typical of Alito, according to <a href="https://law.duke.edu/fac/siegel/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Neil Siegel</a>, a professor of law and political science at Duke University, <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2854909" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who has written</a> about Alito’s record on the Supreme Court. Alito, a former prosecutor himself, tends to see those rights narrowly. “In his worldview, the government always wins and the prisoner always loses,” Siegel said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/20-1009_19m2.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thomas’s opinion</a>, meanwhile, made it more difficult for criminal defendants to challenge their convictions by saying that they had bad legal help. In that case, two Arizona death row inmates argued that they ended up with a death sentence because their defense lawyers had failed to investigate or present evidence that could have exonerated them or resulted in a less severe sentence. Their lawyers had missed deadlines that would allow them to bring up the cases in state court, but hoped that a federal judge could intervene. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Thomas’s ruling was relatively technical, but in practical terms, it makes it much, much harder for other defendants to get convictions overturned on the basis of bad legal assistance, which is connected to the broader right to legal counsel. In her own dissent, Justice Sonia Sotomayor wrote that the decision “will leave many people who were convicted in violation of the Sixth Amendment to face incarceration or even execution without any meaningful chance to vindicate their right to counsel.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-supreme-court-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86637136</p>


<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://michigan.law.umich.edu/faculty-and-scholarship/our-faculty/leah-litman" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Leah Litman</a>, a law professor at the University of Michigan, predicted that there will be more cases where the court upholds a right in name, but makes it functionally impossible for suspects or criminal defendants to actually get a remedy when their rights are infringed. That doesn’t mean that longstanding protections for people accused of crimes are safe — Miranda, in particular, has <a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/2777198/mirandas_waning_protections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long been a target</a> of the conservative legal movement — but the justices might hollow them out before declaring them dead. “I think the court will make [these rights] impossible to prove or enforce before they outright overrule them,” Litman said.</p>



<h2><strong>Other civil rights could be pared back or transformed</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Over the years, Alito and Thomas have written many dissents on another topic: civil rights. In total, out of 413 cases on civil rights on which they’ve voted over the years, at least one of them has written dissents on 66 – 16 percent overall – but on close cases,<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cases with three or four votes in the minority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> that rises to 26 percent (34 out of 129). And if we look at close cases that were decided in a liberal direction, Thomas and Alito wrote dissents in a full 53 percent of them (32 out of 60).  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those dissents include some of the issues that Thomas mentioned in his concurrence in the abortion-rights decision, including the right to same-sex marriage. But it’s a much bigger category than just reproductive or gay rights.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Next term, for instance, Alito and Thomas seem poised to find themselves on the winning side of <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/essay/clarence-thomass-radical-vision-of-race" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a civil rights issue</a> they’ve <a href="https://www.motherjones.com/politics/2016/06/samuel-alito-fisher-v-texas-affirmative-action/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long complained about</a>: affirmative action. In 2016, <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/2012/11-345" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a divided court upheld</a> the University of Texas’s race-conscious admissions program, saying that it was not a constitutional violation to consider race as one factor among many. When the ruling came out, Alito read his dissent — which Thomas and Roberts joined — from the bench. The majority decision’s opinion, he said, was “remarkably wrong.” The university, in his view, was actually relying on damaging racial stereotypes in its quest for greater diversity, and helped wealthy Black students at the expense of Asian American applicants. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Soon, the court is hearing another case that could have a very different outcome. Earlier this year, <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2022/01/court-will-hear-challenges-to-affirmative-action-at-harvard-and-university-of-north-carolina/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the justices decided to hear</a> challenges to race-conscious admissions programs at Harvard University and the University of North Carolina. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/01/24/1003049852/supreme-court-adds-affirmative-action-to-its-potential-hit-list" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Harvard case contends</a> that the university discriminates against Asian American applicants by using admissions criteria designed to effectively create a cap on how many Asian students can be admitted, while the University of North Carolina case revolves around whether the university discriminated against white and Asian applicants. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/political-consequences-overturning-roe-wade-85819633</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Both Harvard and the University of North Carolina argued that their programs are constitutional under current Supreme Court precedents. But Alito and Thomas <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2022/3/8/scotus-affirmative-action-justices-opinions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">appear to think</a> those precedents were wrongly established — and the experts we spoke with said that it’s likely that at least three of the other conservatives agree. “Affirmative action in higher education is probably going to fall next year,” said Steve Vladeck, a professor at the University of Texas School of Law.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The fact that an affirmative action case is on the court’s docket for next year — along with several <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/moore-v-harper-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other high-profile</a> <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/merrill-v-milligan-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voting rights and election administrations cases</a> and a case about whether <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/supreme-court-to-hear-case-of-designer-refusing-to-offer-wedding-websites-for-gay-couples" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a website designer who opposes same-sex marriage</a> can post a message on her website saying she won’t do work for gay weddings — signals that many lines of precedent could be at stake. Other conservative victories could be coming — and the outcomes in those cases will likely be shaped by Alito and Thomas’s views, even if they aren’t the decisive votes. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Siegel said that Alito, in particular, will likely push for outcomes that benefit conservatives and the Republican Party. “He’s a conservative, traditionalist, culture warrior,” Siegel said. “With most justices, you’re able to identify cases where they’ve disappointed the party who appointed them — even if there aren’t many.” With Alito, he said, it’s difficult to find the situations where he broke with Republican orthodoxy. “He just never seems to disappoint the Republican Party,” Siegel said. “And now of course he’s writing majority opinions where he used to be in dissent.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 15:23:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658331002249775</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Abortion Vote In Kansas Looks Like It’s Going To Be Close</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-abortion-vote-in-kansas-looks-like-its-going-to-be-close/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Abortion Vote In Kansas Looks Like It’s Going To Be Close</h1>
																			<h2>A new poll shows that Democrats may be more energized than Republicans.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Nathaniel Rakich</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 20, 2022, at 9:33 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Value Them Both yard sign" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/USA-ELECTION-KANSAS-ABORTION-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/USA-ELECTION-KANSAS-ABORTION-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/USA-ELECTION-KANSAS-ABORTION-4X3.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/USA-ELECTION-KANSAS-ABORTION-4X3.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>REUTERS / Gabriella Borter</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">On June 24, the U.S. Supreme Court’s conservative majority overturned the constitutional right to abortion in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization, saying they were <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sending the issue of abortion back to the voters</a>. But voters don’t make their decisions in a vacuum, and we’re already seeing how the politics of abortion have changed in Kansas. On Aug. 2, Kansans will <a href="https://www.ksn.com/news/state-regional/whats-behind-the-value-them-both-amendment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vote on a state constitutional amendment</a> that would clarify that the state’s bill of rights does not protect Kansans’ right to an abortion. And even though <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the state leans Republican</a>, new polling and fundraising numbers suggest it’s a close race.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The proposed amendment, as its supporters are quick to point out, wouldn’t ban abortion, but it would remove one of the biggest obstacles to making abortion illegal in Kansas. In 2019, the state Supreme Court ruled that the right to bodily autonomy in the state’s bill of rights <a href="https://www.kscourts.org/Newsroom/News-Releases/News/2019-News-Releases/April-2019/Supreme-Court-announces-decision-in-Hodes-Nauser" target="_blank" rel="noopener">includes the right to abortion</a> — separate from any rights guaranteed (or not guaranteed) by the U.S. Constitution. So even if Kansas’s Democratic governor, Laura Kelly, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">loses in November</a>, the state’s Republican-controlled legislature wouldn’t be able to pass much anti-abortion legislation at all. And Kansas would continue to be an <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/us/abortion-laws-roe-v-wade.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">island of abortion access</a> as surrounding states ban abortion. If the amendment passes, on the other hand, the Kansas constitution would no longer protect abortion and <a href="https://www.kmbc.com/article/recording-sheds-light-on-kansas-legislation-if-value-them-both-amendment-passes/40645319#" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more restrictions are likely</a>, particularly if Republicans take back the governor’s mansion in the midterm elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The vote will be an early bellwether for how Americans are thinking about abortion in the lead-up to the midterms. According to the <a href="https://coefficient.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/KS-VTB-Amendment-7.18.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first publicly released poll of the campaign,</a> conducted by <a href="https://coefficient.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">co/efficient</a> and shared exclusively with FiveThirtyEight, 47 percent of likely primary voters say they plan to vote for the <a href="https://sos.ks.gov/elections/22elec/2022-Primary-Election-Constitutional-Amendment-HCR-5003.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">amendment</a>, while 43 percent say they plan to vote against it.<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This poll of 1,557 likely Kansas primary voters was conducted by mobile text response and automated landline interviews from July 17 to 18 and has a margin of error of ±2.78 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One quirk is that the proposed amendment is on the primary ballot, not the general election ballot, which means that voter turnout will almost certainly be lower. Normally, lower turnout would benefit the amendment’s supporters, who would likely be more motivated to vote since their side went to the trouble of getting this on the ballot in the first place. But the U.S. Supreme Court’s ruling on abortion appears to have scrambled that conventional wisdom. Most respondents (84 percent) in the co/efficient survey say the amendment has made them more likely to vote, and the poll finds that Democrats are more energized than Republicans by the issue: 94 percent of Democrats say the amendment has “increased the importance of voting in this upcoming election,” compared with 78 percent of Republicans. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-supreme-court-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86637136</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">“The decision was a wakeup call for a lot of moderate Kansans who weren’t engaged on this issue because they thought there was federal protection for abortion care,” said Ashley All, a spokesperson for <a href="https://kansansforfreedom.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kansans for Constitutional Freedom</a>, the main organization opposing the amendment. According to All, the group went from having about 44 volunteers sign up per week to more than 500 volunteers per week after the Dobbs decision, and they’ve made more than 140,000 phone calls to Kansans since then as well. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Money is pouring into the campaign, too. All said the campaign raised almost $100,000 on the day of the decision alone — more than three times what it had raised in the previous three weeks. In total, Kansans for Constitutional Freedom <a href="http://ethics.ks.gov/CFAScanned/ConstitutionalBallot/2022/202202/constfreedom_2207.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has raised more than $6.5 million</a> since the beginning of the year. By contrast, the coalition supporting the amendment — Value Them Both — has raised <a href="http://ethics.ks.gov/CFAScanned/ConstitutionalBallot/2022/202202/valuethem_2207.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">about $4.7 million</a>. Kansans for Life, one of the main groups in the coalition, did not respond when we asked whether they’ve noticed more engagement among their supporters, but Emily Massey, a spokesperson for the pro-amendment campaign, told us their strategy hadn’t changed since the Dobbs decision.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-energizing-abortion-evens-midterms-equation-silver-86558599</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">The competitiveness of this campaign may seem surprising given the state’s strongly Republican lean in partisan elections, but public opinion on abortion in Kansas is not absolute. In fact, this isn’t the first time the state has been at the center of the battle over abortion rights. In 1991, <a href="https://www.kake.com/story/46761088/1991-summer-of-mercy-protesters-forcefully-closed-wichita-abortion-clinics-thousands-arrested" target="_blank" rel="noopener">busloads of anti-abortion activists descended on Wichita</a> for six weeks in what they dubbed the “Summer of Mercy.” They blocked the entrances to abortion clinics throughout the city to prevent patients from getting in, leading to more than 2,000 arrests. Nearly two decades later, a Wichita doctor named George Tiller who performed third-trimester abortions <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/06/24/1107244499/storycorps-remembering-a-murdered-doctor-who-performed-abortions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was murdered</a> by an anti-abortion extremist while Tiller was working as an usher at church. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Today, because of the 2019 state Supreme Court decision, Kansas is one of the few Midwestern states where the Dobbs decision has essentially had no impact on the legality of abortion. “The court called [abortion] a fundamental right,” said Richard Levy, a professor of constitutional law at the University of Kansas, adding that the protection is even stronger than the federal constitutional right conferred by Roe v. Wade. As a result, <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/fact-sheet/state-facts-about-abortion-kansas" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abortion remains legal until 22 weeks of pregnancy</a> — with some restrictions like a 24-hour waiting period, a mandatory ultrasound and parental consent for minors — even though two of the four states bordering Kansas <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/us/abortion-laws-roe-v-wade.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have banned abortion</a> and a third <a href="https://www.wowt.com/2022/06/30/ricketts-says-he-would-consider-signing-nebraska-abortion-ban-with-exceptions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could soon follow suit</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dr. Christina Bourne, the medical director of Trust Women, an abortion clinic that <a href="https://trustwomen.org/about/history#:~:text=Tiller%20was%20one%20of%20the,after%20a%20nationwide%20capital%20campaign." target="_blank" rel="noopener">occupies the space where Tiller once worked</a>, said the state is an increasingly crucial access point for women in the South and Midwest: “The day the Dobbs decision came down, people in Mississippi and Louisiana were literally calling us from the waiting rooms of abortion clinics there, saying their appointment had just been canceled and could we fit them in.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/supreme-court-dealt-big-blow-separation-church-state-85886797</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">The future of abortion access in Kansas has been a big part of the debate over the constitutional amendment — and both supporters and opponents of abortion rights are trying to take advantage of the particular aspects of public opinion on their respective sides. For example, Kansans for Constitutional Freedom has argued that passing the amendment “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBXgGCK0R-c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could lead to a full ban</a> of any abortion in Kansas, with no exceptions for rape, incest or a mother’s life.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That would be extremely unpopular, even in Kansas: According to the co/efficient survey, only 5 percent of likely primary voters support a total ban on abortion. A ban like the ones that have passed in <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/05/26/1101428347/oklahoma-governor-signs-the-nations-strictest-abortion-ban" target="_blank" rel="noopener">neighboring</a> <a href="https://missouriindependent.com/2022/06/29/missouri-ag-says-state-abortion-ban-does-not-prohibit-plan-b-or-contraception/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">states</a> — with an exception only for the mother’s health — also wouldn’t be popular, since only an additional 7 percent support a ban with that single exception. More primary voters favor a ban with exceptions for rape, incest or the mother’s health (19 percent), although that support is still far from overwhelming. Other respondents favor a ban on abortion after a “<a href="https://www.factcheck.org/2019/07/when-are-heartbeats-audible-during-pregnancy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">heartbeat</a>” can be detected (6 percent) — cardiac activity usually happens around six weeks into a pregnancy — or after viability (16 percent). More than 2 in 5 (43 percent) said, however, that there should be no restrictions on abortion.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Kansans for Constitutional Freedom argues that the amendment’s wording is confusing and emphasizes that it would “chang[e] the constitution.” That’s a clever strategy given that voters are often hesitant to make big changes to policy and the law. This <a href="https://catalist.us/2021/05/yes-you-can-generally-trust-issue-polling-but-theres-a-catch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">status-quo bias</a> often makes ballot measures underperform their polling, and it could be another reason why this vote is closer than you might assume in such a red state.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the other side, Value Them Both has sought to stake out a middle ground. Their ads contend that the amendment itself <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z0SH-R0mmNg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would not actually ban abortion</a> but rather let the legislature impose “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A3oFN_FA_MU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">common-sense abortion limits</a>” like parental notification (although this is somewhat misleading, because parental notification is already the law in Kansas). They also argue that the 2019 decision “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nn4xAdGRVZE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">[made] it impossible to regulate abortion in Kansas</a>,” allowing “unlimited abortion.” That also isn’t quite true — some restrictions were struck down as a result of the decision, but many limitations are still in place, including a ban on abortion after 22 weeks of pregnancy. Proponents of the amendment have accurately pointed out, though, that Kansas is becoming a destination for women seeking abortion. One ad noted that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JBlZpkEbLAM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the number of abortions performed</a> in Kansas has <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/wireStory/patient-influx-states-increases-kansas-abortions-78027418" target="_blank" rel="noopener">increased in recent years</a> (due largely to Texas and Oklahoma residents who can no longer get abortions in their home states) and reached a <a href="https://www.cjonline.com/story/news/politics/2022/04/27/kansas-abortions-increase-despite-fewer-texas-oklahoma-patients-2021/9543419002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">10-year high in 2021</a>.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/overturning-roe-means-abortion-access-us-fivethirtyeight-85676655</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Both sides are also trying to make Kansas’s conservative inclination work to their advantage. In its advertising, Value Them Both has set itself up in opposition to the “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7cZPZV-eriY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">radical left</a>” and “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eVK15h0t63Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unelected liberal judges</a>,” unfavorably comparing abortion laws in Kansas to those in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=esiAi7H-Lx8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blue states like California</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nn4xAdGRVZE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York</a> — an apparent attempt to harden the race along ideological, if not outright partisan, lines. And several ads from Kansans for Constitutional Freedom have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Imr-3zMNsrQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">framed the amendment</a> as a “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhpX84FXQzM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">government mandate</a>,” a nod toward the state’s preference for small government. By 51 percent to 25 percent, Kansans told Fort Hays State University in December that the <a href="https://www.fhsu.edu/docking/Kansas-Speaks/2021-kansas-speaks-report-final_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state government shouldn’t place regulations</a> on the circumstances under which someone can get an abortion. The anti-amendment campaign has even <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhpX84FXQzM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">implicitly compared abortion regulations to mask mandates</a> — casting them both as an attack on Kansans’ personal freedom.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Regardless of the outcome, the vote in Kansas will tell us something important about how the public is reacting to the U.S. Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Americans’ constitutional right to abortion. The court’s decision wasn’t popular — but now we’ll get our first chance to see if the ruling will actually spur voters into action.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 14:33:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658326502745335</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What To Watch In The Maryland Primary</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-to-watch-in-the-maryland-primary/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Maryland Primary</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>What To Watch In The Maryland Primary</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 19, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Campaign signs compete for space during early voting in Maryland" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1407345278-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1407345278-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1407345278-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1407345278-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Chip Somodevilla / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">After a busy May and June, July is a lonely month for primaries. Maryland is the only state holding a primary election for Congress or a major statewide office this month, after its primary was delayed from June 28 due to <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/03/15/md-primary-pushed-back-to-july-19/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">redistricting litigation</a>. And a few races in the Old Line State follow some of the same storylines we’ve seen so far this year, including continued Democratic <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/9-democratic-primaries-to-watch-in-illinois-and-new-york/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">battles over race and ideology</a>, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/16/democrats-moderate-progressive-super-pacs-00032610" target="_blank" rel="noopener">impact of outside spending</a> in Democratic primaries and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-candidate-lost-in-nebraska-but-trump-is-still-winning-most-of-his-primaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s continued influence</a> in Republican intraparty contests. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here’s a look at the three contests we’re watching closely today, with interesting primaries in two U.S. House seats and competitive races in both parties’ primaries for governor.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch: 4th and 6th congressional districts; governor</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong><strong>8 p.m. Eastern</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republican Gov. Larry Hogan is term-limited, so the open-seat race for <strong>governor</strong> in this usually solid-blue state has attracted a total of nine Democratic contenders,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Rushern Baker &lt;a href="https://www.nbcwashington.com/decision-2022/rushern-baker-suspends-campaign-in-maryland-gubernatorial-primary/3074590/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;dropped out of the race&lt;/a&gt; in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>13</sup></a> as there’s a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-the-gop-could-make-or-break-its-chances-in-10-key-governors-races/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">good chance the party will be favored</a> in November. A range of candidates are running, too, with six notable Democrats in the mix — three of whom look poised to win the nomination.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of those three, Marylanders are probably the most familiar with four-term state Comptroller Peter Franchot. The political veteran has a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/07/04/primary-maryland-governor-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reputation as a populist</a> with a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/06/02/franchot-ad-maryland-governor-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">knack for garnering attention</a>, and since Hogan entered office, Franchot <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/md-politics/a-bipartisan-friendship-maryland-gov-hogan-and-comptroller-franchot/2016/08/14/b120b294-5f13-11e6-af8e-54aa2e849447_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has become close to the governor</a> despite their party differences because of their shared goal of reducing state spending and cutting taxes. Still, the 74-year-old Franchot, who is white, might face a tough sell in convincing Black Marylanders, who could make up 40 percent or more of the primary electorate, that he’ll build an economy with a “<a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/06/08/peter-franchots-100-day-plan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">level playing field</a>.” His running mate, former Prince George’s County Councilor Monique Anderson-Walker, is Black and has been prominently featured in his ad focused on <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/e1b22b06-f676-41c1-80ce-8226eeb10271/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">helping people build wealth</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Also in serious contention is Wes Moore, an author and former nonprofit CEO who has an impressive biography. Moore, who is Black, lost his father as a child and was sent off to military school, which he points to as a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6bBwkWHRJdU&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank" rel="noopener">catalyst for becoming an Army captain</a>, a Rhodes Scholar and, later, the CEO of an anti-poverty nonprofit. Moore also wrote a bestselling memoir and went on to host a show on the Oprah Winfrey Network (notably, <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/oprah-maryland-candidate-governor-wes-moore/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Winfrey has cut an ad for Moore</a>). But it’s possible that certain <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/04/13/politics/wes-moore-baltimore-origin-story-campaign-governor-maryland/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">elements of Moore’s profile are exaggerated</a>, in particular his connection to Baltimore; he didn’t actually grow up there despite coverage that suggests he did. Moore has also been <a href="https://foxbaltimore.com/news/local/bronze-star-recipient-wes-moore-appears-to-misrepresent-military-record-in-past-interview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accused of failing to correct</a> past interviewers who said he had earned a Bronze Star during his Army service. This hasn’t dissuaded notable Democrats from supporting him, however. In Moore’s camp is <a href="https://www.wypr.org/wypr-news/2022-06-21/ferguson-mfume-endorse-wes-moore-for-governor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rep. Kweisi Mfume</a>, who represents Baltimore, as well as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/04/28/hoyer-wes-moore-endorse-maryland-governor-00028745" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Majority Leader Steny Hoyer</a> and the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/05/07/jones-endorses-wes-moore-maryland-governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two Democratic</a> leaders in the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/06/21/moore-maryland-governor-ferguson-mfume/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state legislature</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the other top-tier contender is Tom Perez, former chair of the Democratic National Committee and a secretary of labor under President Barack Obama. Perez has built a national profile in the past decade, but he’s also been involved in Maryland politics, having served as a council president in Montgomery County in the early 2000s and then as Democratic Gov. Martin O’Malley’s labor secretary. The son of immigrants from the Dominican Republic, Perez is running on the message that he’ll “<a href="https://youtu.be/jPvNeI_fwp8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">get stuff done</a>,” and notably, he’s attracted primary endorsements from the state’s two main newspapers, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/07/11/maryland-governor-endorsement-perez-schulz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Washington Post</a> and <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/opinion/editorial/bs-ed-0626-endorsement-perez-governor-20220626-c4mhggfm4jgg7gv6xtf2gifgea-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Baltimore Sun</a>, which could provide a small boost in a highly competitive primary with a large number of undecided voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Three other candidates merit a mention, though. First, there’s former Secretary of Education John King, who served in Obama’s Cabinet and has <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2021/12/06/john-king-maryland-governor-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mounted a progressive campaign</a> that has gained the backing of the <a href="https://www.sierraclub.org/maryland/blog/2022/06/sierra-club-endorses-john-king-for-governor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sierra Club</a>, <a href="https://ourrevolutionmd.com/2022/06/17/4152/ormd-endorses-john-king-for-governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our Revolution</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/pcmaction/status/1532118045916790786" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pro-Choice Maryland</a>. Then there’s former Maryland Attorney General Doug Gansler, who is running as a <a href="https://youtu.be/OTvZaI-dxYk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tough-on-crime</a> moderate who also wants to <a href="https://www.msba.org/doug-gansler-discusses-plans-to-rebuild-economy-protect-environment-if-elected-governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">protect the environment</a>. But Gansler may be held back by scandals that upended his 2014 gubernatorial campaign, such as <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/dc-politics/attorney-general-gansler-depicted-as-reckless-passenger-by-md-troopers-who-drove-him/2013/10/12/3115487a-328f-11e3-9c68-1cf643210300_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">directing state troopers to speed</a> with their lights and sirens on so he could get to routine appointments and <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/bal-doug-ganslers-teen-party-controversy-20140909-storygallery.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attending a party</a> where underage drinking appeared to be happening. Lastly, nonprofit executive Jon Baron is in the mix, having <a href="https://www.thebaltimorebanner.com/article/jon-baron-pledges-to-do-what-works-if-he-becomes-maryland-governor-FVPH4A73Q5F5PE5CQGY4PHP54U/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">self-funded his campaign</a>, which pledges to take a more evidence-based approach to developing policy solutions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polls generally put Franchot, Moore and Perez in a three-way battle for first, although King’s polling suggests he’s also a contender. The most recent independent poll from <a href="https://www.goucher.edu/hughes-center/documents/Goucher-College-Poll-June-2022-Part-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Goucher College/The Baltimore Banner/WYPR</a> found in mid-June that Franchot was leading with 16 percent and Moore and Perez were tied for second with 14 percent. Meanwhile, the rest of the field was in the low-to-mid single digits. Two late June surveys sponsored by campaigns also showed a close race. A <a href="https://wesmoore.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/Garin-Hart-Yang-Research-Group-June-30-Survey-among-Maryland-Democratic-Primary-Voters.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Garin-Hart-Yang Research Group poll</a> for Moore’s campaign found Franchot and Moore running neck and neck at around 20 percent, with Perez at 16 percent, while a <a href="https://twitter.com/JohnBKing/status/1542923690903478272" target="_blank" rel="noopener">20/20 Insight survey</a> on behalf of King’s campaign found Perez leading with 22 percent and Moore, King and Franchot in a close fight for second in the mid-to-high teens.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With the race so tight, <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/politics/elections/bs-md-pol-july-2022-campaign-finance-analysis-20220710-lver3xgv5rfuzi2zeatq4mns6e-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">campaign spending</a> could make the difference. And it’s Moore who has led on this front: In tandem with his running mate, former Del. Aruna Miller, his campaign has attracted $7.9 million and had the most money for the final weeks of the campaign (about $810,000 as of July 3). Franchot and Anderson-Walker meanwhile have raised around $4.5 million. Although Franchot started the cycle with $977,000 in the bank from previous campaigns, he had about $630,000 left as of July 3. Close behind were Perez and his running mate, former Baltimore City Councilor Shannon Sneed, who brought in $4.4 million and had $645,000 remaining. King’s campaign has also raised a fair bit ($3.6 million), but only had about $208,000 left over. As for the other two candidates, they’ve largely self-funded, with Baron loaning his campaign $1.7 million out of $2.3 million raised, and Gansler loaning his campaign $800,000 of $1.3 million; as of July 3, Baron had $337,000 in the bank while Gansler had about $550,000.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile on the Republican side, the gubernatorial primary is a clash between a Hogan-backed candidate and a Trump endorsee. On Team Hogan is former Maryland Secretary of Commerce Kelly Schulz. Schulz served under Hogan and is now portraying herself as his natural successor, which could be smart as Hogan, who <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/03/22/hogan-endorses-schulz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has endorsed Schulz</a>, has proven to be <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/04/28/governor-approval-ratings-2022-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a popular GOP governor</a> in a blue state. On Team Trump, meanwhile, is state Del. Dan Cox, who is running as a vocal Trump supporter and <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2021/11/22/with-trumps-backing-dan-coxs-gubernatorial-bid-gains-national-exposure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has the former president’s endorsement</a>. But considering Maryland’s strong Democratic lean, a Cox victory might preclude a competitive race in the fall.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Schulz’s challenge, however, has been how to balance appealing to conservative primary voters while not repelling parts of the state’s Democratic-leaning electorate that she needs in the general. To that end, she has focused on <a href="https://youtu.be/dcrhzgdm-8c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">parental rights in education</a>, a topic that <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-aim-repeat-youngkins-schools-tactic-2022-elections-2021-11-04/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans believe boosted them</a> in 2021, as well as <a href="https://youtu.be/PlWN0IANexg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">opposing increased spending and higher taxes</a>, issues that helped Hogan <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/opinion/editorial/bs-ed-larry-hogan-20141105-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">achieve an upset win</a> in 2014. Her campaign <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/05/11/in-gop-governor-race-schulz-campaign-calls-cox-unstable-and-unfit-for-office/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has also hit Cox on his early stances</a> on COVID-19 preventive measures and ethics. And more recently, the Schulz campaign has attacked Cox, who is an attorney, for <a href="https://youtu.be/JeK-ui9efRI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defending an alleged child rapist</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For his part, Cox <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/politics/bs-md-pol-dan-cox-mastriano-20220621-y6pj5uhmdzcr5gcwm4x7gqfyiu-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has played to the GOP base</a> by opposing vaccine and mask mandates and abortion rights. Cox has also promoted the false claim that Trump won the 2020 election, and even <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2021/01/07/del-cox-arranged-buses-to-violent-trump-rally-calls-vice-president-a-traitor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chartered buses for Trump supporters</a> to attend Trump’s Jan. 6 rally, which later turned into a violent attack on the Capitol, during which Cox tweeted “Pence is a traitor” over then-Vice President Mike Pence’s refusal to stop the certification of the 2020 election results. More recently, Cox <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/03/03/house-rules-panel-rejects-coxs-attempts-to-impeach-hogan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sponsored legislation to impeach Hogan</a>, although it ultimately went nowhere. But this, in addition to Cox’s other hard-right positions and dalliances with QAnon conspiracists, has led Schulz’s campaign to call him “<a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/05/11/in-gop-governor-race-schulz-campaign-calls-cox-unstable-and-unfit-for-office/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unfit for office</a>.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Schulz has had the financial upper hand throughout the campaign, as she’s raised about $2.6 million to Cox’s $662,000. She also entered the final weeks with more in the bank, $734,000 versus Cox’s $189,000. However, in a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-20-california-primary-races-to-watch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">replay of what we’ve seen</a> throughout this <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/21-republican-primaries-and-a-special-election-to-watch-on-june-28/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">primary season</a>, Democrats have sought to boost Cox with outside spending: The Democratic Governors Association <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/02/dems-trump-hogan-maryland-00043837" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has reserved at least $1.2 million in ads</a> calling Cox “too conservative for Maryland,” which doubles as an attack ad (should Cox win) but also as a means to influence Republicans to support him.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The little polling we have suggests that the DGA’s investment could pay off, though. The most recent survey, that mid-June poll from Goucher College/The Baltimore Banner/WYPR, found Cox running just ahead of Schulz, 25 percent to 22 percent. But with 44 percent undecided, a lot of voters still remain on the fence. Notably, however, that same poll found that Schulz is far <a href="https://www.thebaltimorebanner.com/politics-power/state-government/national-democrats-could-be-trying-to-help-one-of-marylands-republican-candidates-for-governor-N37VQNIXAZFBTBUBNXJDIIBYWA/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to make November competitive</a> than Cox. The survey asked Democrats if they’d consider voting for either Republican, and while only 9 percent said they’d consider Cox, 34 percent said they’d potentially consider Schulz.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Turning to Maryland’s two congressional primaries of note, Democrats have a highly contested race in the majority-Black <strong>4th District</strong>, a deep-blue seat <a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/other/redistricting/sb1012-congress/SB1012-congress-%28032822%29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mostly centered on Prince George’s County</a>, outside of Washington, D.C. Democratic Rep. Anthony Brown is <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/07/06/brown-omalley-maryland-ag-attorney-general/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">running for attorney general</a>, so the open-seat race has attracted a bevy of Democrats, but <a href="https://wtop.com/maryland/2022/07/2-well-known-names-lead-race-for-marylands-4th-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two contenders seem to have risen above</a> the rest of the primary field: former Rep. Donna Edwards, who represented this seat from 2008 to 2017, and former Prince George’s County State’s Attorney Glenn Ivey (both candidates are Black). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Outside spending, driven largely by groups focused on Israel, is the main story here, though. The United Democracy Project, a super PAC partly funded by the bipartisan American Israel Public Affairs Committee, has invested heavily to defeat Edwards, whom AIPAC <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/politics/donna-edwards-glenn-ivey-maryland-israel" target="_blank" rel="noopener">views as anti-Israel</a>. In total, <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00799031/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">UDP has spent $4.2 million</a> opposing her and $1.7 million supporting Ivey, <a href="https://rollcall.com/2022/07/14/big-money-dominates-in-marylands-4th-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">running ads</a> dinging Edwards for a <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/9c07957d-079f-4f49-b80b-12cacccd8162/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poor record of constituent services</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/ijHIYvzduNU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">promoting Ivey’s record</a> on combating crime and police misconduct. The Democratic Majority for Israel <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00710848/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has also backed Ivey</a> with $426,000. Meanwhile, J Street, a more progressive Israel-focused group, <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00815753/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent $728,000</a> supporting Edwards or opposing Ivey. Overall, though, the nearly $8 million in spending by outside groups dwarfs the $940,000 and $737,000 spent by the Ivey and Edwards campaigns, respectively. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polling has been scarce, but the <a href="https://jewishinsider.com/2022/07/glenn-ivey-donna-edwards-poll-maryland-congress-democratic-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most recent survey</a> found Ivey just ahead of Edwards, 33 percent to 28 percent. However, that survey, which was conducted by Change Research on behalf of the <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00486845/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pro-Edwards</a> League of Conservation Voters Victory Fund, is from early June, before much of the spending by pro-Ivey groups took place. So, if there’s a favorite, it’s probably Ivey, although Edwards <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/07/03/donna-edwards-glenn-ivey-maryland-4th-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">does have backing</a> from House Speaker Nancy Pelosi, labor groups and EMILY’s List.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the <strong>6th District</strong> in western Maryland has a competitive GOP primary, with the winner set to face Democratic Rep. David Trone. The <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/maryland/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new congressional map</a> made the 6th District much more competitive, too, turning it into a seat that is 1 point more Republican than the country as a whole,<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> as opposed to the old D+16 boundaries. <a href="https://www.washco-mdelections.org/_files/ugd/70dc4f_3b920cb0c3c748568755bc20d0e57076.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Six Republicans are running</a>, but the two main contenders are state Del. Neil Parrott and Matthew Foldi, a former writer for the conservative Washington Free Beacon.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We haven’t seen any polling, so it’s hard to say who might come out on top. Only 25 years old, <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/campaigns/washington-free-beacon-reporter-files-bid-for-congress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Foldi entered the race</a> just before the April filing deadline but has <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/06/22/political-notes-dems-prepping-pitch-to-dnc-kevin-mccarthy-backs-kid-in-dist-6/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsements from House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/news/larry-hogan-endorses-matthew-foldi-congress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hogan</a>. Foldi also <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2MD06328/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raised about $223,000</a> in just one fundraising quarter of activity — a decent haul considering Parrott has <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/committee/C00691931/?cycle=2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">brought in $328,000</a> over a much longer period of time. Foldi’s <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/gop-hopeful-matthew-foldi-releases-first-tv-ad-dccc-prioritizes-david-trone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first ad highlighted</a> his background as a reporter and his exposés about Democratic offices, including Trone’s, closing due to COVID-19 concerns. Still, Parrott isn’t to be discounted, as he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/17/gop-endorsements-25-year-old-matthew-foldi-00046173" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may have a stronger base of local support</a> and name recognition from his work as a member of the state legislature and his <a href="https://elections.maryland.gov/elections/2020/results/general/gen_results_2020_4_00806.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">losing campaign against Trone in 2020</a> under the old lines. He also has backing from the Family Research Council and Rep. Andy Harris, currently the only Republican U.S. House member from Maryland.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Considering the potentially Republican-leaning environment and the purple nature of this seat, either Republican could give Trone trouble. But Trone will likely have more campaign cash at his disposal thanks to his personal wealth from his <a href="https://www.totalwine.com/about-us/our-leadership" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ownership of a wine store chain</a>; he’s already <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H6MD08549/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">given his campaign</a> almost $12.6 million.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Well, that’s the July primary picture for you. We won’t be live-blogging the Maryland primary, but if you’re monitoring the results (<a href="https://twitter.com/geoffreyvs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we will be</a>), remember that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/07/12/maryland-primary-results-may-be-delayed-mail-in-votes-are-counted/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state law prohibits</a> the counting of mail ballots before the Thursday after the election, meaning a sizable number of votes (particularly Democratic ones) will probably still need to be counted after Tuesday night.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658227501518538</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Americans Aren’t Happy With Biden. Or Republicans.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-americans-arent-happy-with-biden-or-republicans/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>New York Times</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<category>Polling Accuracy</category>
			<category>Senate</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-americans-arent-happy-with-biden-or-republicans/">
	<div data-podcast-id="339721" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Americans Aren’t Happy With Biden. Or Republicans.">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP8446259883.mp3?updated=1658191538">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Last week The New York Times and Siena College released their first round of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/16/upshot/poll-analysis-2022-midterms.html?name=styln-nyt-polling&amp;region=TOP_BANNER&amp;block=storyline_menu_recirc&amp;action=click&amp;pgtype=Article&amp;variant=show&amp;is_new=false" target="_blank" rel="noopener">midterms polling</a>. It covered a wide range of questions, from views on President Biden and former President Donald Trump to the state of the economy and our democracy. The poll showed broad pessimism about the country and the people leading both parties. Beyond the pessimism, the data also highlights how Americans want things to be different, with clues for future elections and how the two parties’ coalitions could continue to evolve.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Nate Cohn, the chief political analyst at The New York Times, joins the crew to discuss the results of the poll. They also consider whether a <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/13/recession-outlook-us-economy-data/?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult/Politico poll</a> asking Americans whether they think the U.S. is currently in a recession is a “good or bad use of polling.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 01:46:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658196001987762</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>At Least 120 Republican Nominees Deny The Results Of The 2020 Election</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/at-least-120-republicans-who-deny-the-2020-election-results-will-be-on-the-ballot-in-november/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich and Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>At Least 120 Republican Nominees Deny The Results Of The 2020 Election</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Kaleigh Rogers</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
							<p>Graphics by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/humera-lodhi/" rel="author">Humera Lodhi</a></p>
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 18, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Trump rally in Conroe" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1238075129-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1238075129-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1238075129-4X3.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1238075129-4X3.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Almost half the Republican candidates thus far for House, Senate, governor, attorney general or secretary of state who will appear on the ballot in November have either questioned or denied the legitimacy of the 2020 election.													<p>Sergio Flores/Anadolu Agency/Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Since the 2020 election, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/there-is-more-than-one-big-lie/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">millions of Republican voters</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-big-lie-voting-laws/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have accepted</a> former President Donald Trump’s false claim that the presidential election was stolen from him. And now, here in 2022, many Republican politicians have capitalized on this lie and have won elections of their own.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This election cycle, FiveThirtyEight is tracking the views of every Republican candidate for Senate, House, governor, attorney general and secretary of state on the legitimacy of the 2020 election. And now that we’re halfway through the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/primary-results/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">primary season</a>, we can say definitively that at least 120 election deniers have won their party’s nomination and will be on the ballot in the fall. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How did we arrive at that number?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Categorizing candidates’ stances on the legitimacy of the 2020 election is not a straightforward exercise. Sure, some Republicans openly state the race was stolen, while others (a much smaller number) have unambiguously accepted the legitimacy of President Biden’s victory. But many have tried to walk a fine line between the two — for example, by accepting the results but still expressing concern about mass voter fraud, or by winking at the idea that the election was stolen without saying so outright. So we’ve ended up putting candidates into one of six categories:</p>



<ol><li>Those who have explicitly said the 2020 election was illegitimate and/or took legal measures to try and overturn the election.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of the latter include members of Congress who &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2021/politics/congress-electoral-college-count-tracker/"&gt;voted against certifying election results&lt;/a&gt; or politicians who &lt;a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/22/22O155/163550/20201211132250339_Texas%20v.%20Pennsylvania%20Amicus%20Brief%20of%20126%20Representatives%20--%20corrected.pdf"&gt;signed an amicus brief for a Texas lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; that challenged election results in four states Biden won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>15</sup></a></li><li>Those who raised questions or concerns about the election but haven’t outright denied or affirmed it.</li><li>Those who have accepted Biden’s victory but have still raised questions or concerns about fraud.</li><li>Those who have accepted Biden’s victory without reservations.</li><li>Those who have refused or avoided directly answering questions about the election (e.g., by changing the subject when asked about it).</li><li>Those for whom no information is available.</li></ol><p data-paragraph="main">After doing that for all 1,148 Republican candidates for these offices in nominating contests through the end of June, here are four observations we have so far.</p>



<h2><strong>1. Half of Republican nominees have at least flirted with denying the election</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">As mentioned above, out of 340 Republican nominees for Senate, House, governor, attorney general and secretary of state so far, 120 are full-blown election deniers (35 percent).<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominees include anyone running in the general election, so candidates advancing out of party conventions or California’s top-two primary to a November “runoff” are included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> This includes people like Alabama Gov. Kay Ivey, who said in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xztJw19j-CY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">campaign ad</a> that “the fake news, big tech and blue-state liberals stole the election from President Trump,” and Indiana Rep. Greg Pence, who <a href="https://www.therepublic.com/2021/01/08/rep-greg-pence-votes-to-object-to-pennsylvania-electoral-college-results/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voted not to certify Pennsylvania’s electoral votes</a> (defying his brother, former Vice President Mike Pence) and hasn’t spoken out on the issue since. It also includes at least four people who attended the Jan. 6 riot at the U.S. Capitol: Pennsylvania gubernatorial nominee <a href="https://whyy.org/articles/new-video-appears-to-show-state-sen-mastriano-closer-to-capitol-riot-than-he-said/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Doug Mastriano</a>, Ohio 9th Congressional District nominee <a href="https://www.toledoblade.com/local/politics/2021/04/01/QAnon-linked-Ohioan-whose-Trump-lawn-went-viral-is-running-for-Congress/stories/20210331121" target="_blank" rel="noopener">J.R. Majewski</a>, Oregon senatorial nominee <a href="https://www.koin.com/news/ex-senate-candidate-jo-rae-perkins-among-trump-supporters-in-dc/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jo Rae Perkins</a> and North Carolina 1st Congressional District nominee <a href="https://twitter.com/SandySmithNC/status/1346886855250337793?s=20&amp;t=rU_StxcdrnrwmsJoLMrmTw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sandy Smith</a>.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/theview/video/election-deniers-dominating-primaries-colorado-fivethirtyeight-85874712</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">An additional 48 nominees (14 percent) have expressed doubts about the election despite the multitude of evidence that it was legitimate. This includes people like Nevada gubernatorial nominee <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/politics/2021/07/01/southern-nevada-sheriff-looks-north-first-bid-governors-office/7818738002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joe Lombardo</a> and Arkansas gubernatorial nominee <a href="https://www.texarkanagazette.com/news/2022/may/02/in-race-for-arkansas-governor-gop-hopefuls-differ/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah Huckabee Sanders</a>, who have both said some fraud took place but they’re not sure how much; Oregon 5th District nominee <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2022/04/leading-oregon-republican-candidates-for-congress-say-biden-was-in-fact-winner-of-2020-presidential-election.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lori Chavez-DeRemer</a>, who did not take a direct stance but used <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dog_whistle_(politics)" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dog-whistle</a> language that undermined faith in the election; and South Carolina Sen. <a href="https://www.live5news.com/2021/01/06/sen-tim-scott-propose-commission-examine-integrity-november-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tim Scott</a>, who gave credence to Trump’s false claims by proposing an “election integrity commission.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here’s a snapshot of the whole Republican primary field so far:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1326" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-final.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-final.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-final.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-final.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1658" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-mob-final.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-mob-final.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-mob-final.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/rakich.rogers.BIG-LIE.0718-1-mob-final.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In total, almost half of the GOP’s nominees for these offices have at least dabbled in false election claims. However, a lot of that is simply because the candidate pool overall was sympathetic to these claims, rather than primary voters going out of their way to elect election deniers. Thirty percent (346 out of 1,148) of all Republican candidates for those offices (winners <em>and</em> losers) explicitly denied the election’s legitimacy, and another 16 percent (185 out of 1,148) questioned it. To be sure, that leaves a lot of Republican candidates who didn’t fall into this camp, but it is still notable that such a large share of political hopefuls from one of our two main parties is not ready to accept the result of a fair democratic election.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-agree-disagree-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-85543538</p>


<h2><strong>2. And that’s almost certainly an undercount …</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Considering the 2020 election continues to be a major talking point in the Republican primaries, you may be surprised to learn that a sizable chunk of candidates haven’t publicly stated their opinion on the 2020 election either way. We were unable to find a stated position on the 2020 election for 37 percent of Republican primary candidates (421 out of 1,148) and a quarter of GOP nominees (84 out of 340). That means that our finding of the number of nominees so far who believe the 2020 election was fraudulent is almost certainly an undercount — it’s likely that a portion of the candidates for whom we can’t find a publicly stated opinion are, in fact, election deniers. We know this because when we follow up with these kinds of candidates, they often tell us they are — even if they aren’t serious contenders.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For example, when first researching Christopher Mann, the Republican nominee for Oregon’s 1st District, we couldn’t find any stated position on the 2020 election. His campaign website doesn’t say anything about voting, the 2020 election or Trump, and he hadn’t been asked about it in any local media reports or debates that we could find. But when we e-mailed him, his campaign wrote back and clearly stated that he <em>did</em> think the election was stolen. Listing off a number of debunked conspiracy theories about election fraud, including <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/factcheck-usa-mules/fact-check-does-2000-mules-provide-evidence-of-voter-fraud-in-the-2020-u-s-presidential-election-idUSL2N2XJ0OQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a reference to the bogus “documentary”</a> “2,000 Mules,” Mann’s campaign said he believes “the election was rampant with fraud,” and that “it is most likely that President Trump won the election by the largest margin in history, as well as gaining more votes than any sitting president in history,” a claim that is baseless. (It’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/oregon/1/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unlikely Mann will win</a> in the general election this fall.)</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/big-lie-believers-win-runoffs-georgia-alabama-fivethirtyeight-85532528</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">However, this doesn’t mean that <em>all</em> of the candidates who didn’t respond are secretly harboring election conspiracy beliefs. When candidates responded to our questions, they would also sometimes confirm that they believed the 2020 election was legitimate. Joe Pinion, the Republican nominee for Senate in New York, also didn’t have a public record on the 2020 election, but when we reached out he responded unequivocally: “The election was legitimate and certified. Joe Biden is the 46th President of the United States of America. Full stop.” So these “undeclared” candidates really can’t be presumed to represent either side, and likely include some candidates who deny the legitimacy of the 2020 election and some who don’t.  </p>



<h2><strong>3. Denying the election is most common in House races — and rarest in secretary of state races</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">While we analyzed candidates for five different offices, we found that nominees for the U.S. House were the likeliest to embrace Trump’s lies about the election. Full-blown election deniers constitute 40 percent (105 out of 263) of Republican nominees for the House thus far. By contrast, they constitute between just 18 and 22 percent of Republican nominees for the other four offices.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>How candidates for different offices view the 2020 election</h5>
 <p>Republican candidates running for Senate, House, governor, attorney general and secretary of state who either fully or partially deny the legitimacy of the 2020 election</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rogers-rakich.big-lie-halftime.2"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Candidates</th>
 <th colspan="2" scope="colgroup">Nominees</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Elected Office</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Fully Deny</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Partially Deny</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Fully Deny</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Partially Deny</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">% of NOMINEEs Who DENY</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Governor</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>21</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>7</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">55%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>House</td>
 <td>233</td>
 <td>136</td>
 <td>105</td>
 <td>36</td>
 <td>54</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Attorney general</td>
 <td>10</td>
 <td>6</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>33</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Senate</td>
 <td>44</td>
 <td>12</td>
 <td>4</td>
 <td>2</td>
 <td>27</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Secretary of state</td>
 <td>16</td>
 <td>10</td>
 <td>3</td>
 <td>1</td>
 <td>24</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>For all primaries through June 28, 2022, and for which results are available. There was not information available for 421 candidates’ positions. Thirty-nine candidates declined to share their position.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">When you add in the 14 percent (36 out of 263) of Republican House nominees who have questioned the election’s legitimacy, a total of 54 percent of Republican House nominees have publicly at least entertained the notion that the election was stolen. The only comparable office is governor; just 20 percent (four out of 20) of Republican gubernatorial nominees have fully embraced Trump’s false election-fraud claims. An additional 35 percent (seven out of 20) have flirted with them, though.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, unlike for the House, a sizable number of gubernatorial nominees have also accepted the 2020 election results — four with reservations, four without them, for a total of 40 percent. By contrast, only 18 percent (47 out of 263) of House nominees have acknowledged Biden’s win. (The remainder haven’t taken a position, as far as we could ascertain. This probably reflects how much higher-profile gubernatorial elections are than House elections; it’s easier for a House candidate to avoid taking a stance on this, or any, issue.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, Republican gubernatorial nominees <em>are</em> more conspiratorially minded than Republican Senate nominees, despite Senate elections being just as high-profile as gubernatorial elections. Only 18 percent (four out of 22)<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The denominator here includes Mark Meuser, who is the nominee in both the regularly scheduled and special U.S. Senate election in California, twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a> of the GOP’s Senate nominees so far have fully rejected the election’s legitimacy, and only 9 percent more (two out of 22) have questioned it (a total of 27 percent). On the other hand, 59 percent have accepted it, either with (six out of 22) or without (seven out of 22) reservations. This fits with the Senate’s <a href="https://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/minute/Senate_Created.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historical role</a> as the more temperate chamber of Congress than the more populist House.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/meet-nevada-gop-candidates-support-trumps-big-lie-85370871</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Arguably, though, a candidate’s position on election integrity is most important in secretary of state races, given that, in most states, the secretary of state is the state’s top election official and the one most involved in conducting elections in the state. But perhaps somewhat surprisingly given Trump’s interest in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-2022-endorsements-are-earlier-bolder-and-more-dangerous-than-when-he-was-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">installing loyalists as secretaries of state</a>, these nominees are the least likely to sympathize with election-fraud claims. Out of 17 Republican secretary of state nominees thus far, only three — <a href="https://www.detroitnews.com/story/news/politics/2021/09/07/donald-trump-backs-michigan-election-critic-secretary-state/5758348001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kristina Karamo</a> in Michigan, <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/in-debates-secretary-of-state-candidates-cast-wildly-different-visions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jim Marchant</a> in Nevada and <a href="https://twitter.com/AudreyT4NMSOS/status/1337184873186906116?s=20&amp;t=JeeMLQ9LxEeAl-zMh1LUZA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Audrey Trujillo</a> in New Mexico — have outright rejected the legitimacy of the 2020 election, while one other — <a href="https://www.al.com/news/2022/02/spotlight-shines-on-alabama-secretary-of-state-race-as-views-over-2020-election-and-trump-loom-large.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wes Allen</a> in Alabama — has nodded in that direction. That’s just 24 percent of secretary of state nominees. Of course, at least two of those states are crucial swing states, so these candidates may still pose a threat to democracy if they win.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s especially notable, however, about these differences from office to office is that they don’t show up when you look at candidates more broadly (so again, winners plus losers). Republicans who don’t accept Biden’s victory made up a similar share of House candidates as they did Senate, gubernatorial and secretary of state candidates. In fact, the share of total Senate (46 percent) and secretary of state (53 percent) candidates who questioned or denied the election was actually slightly higher than the share of House candidates (45 percent). And yet House <em>nominees</em> are still significantly more likely to entertain these conspiracy theories. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So there appears to be something about House primaries that’s producing more election deniers, and something about secretary of state and Senate races that’s holding them back. Some of this could have to do with the fact that secretary of state and Senate races are statewide affairs, while House races can be taking place in extremely conservative corners of a state. But it may also just be dumb luck. For example, in at least two Republican primaries for secretary of state so far this year (<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/05/10/us/elections/results-nebraska-secretary-of-state.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nebraska</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/05/17/us/elections/results-idaho-secretary-of-state.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Idaho</a>), a pro-democracy candidate prevailed, but only with a plurality of the vote. Both were running against two opponents who denied the legitimacy of the 2020 election, meaning that a majority of primary voters actually cast votes for an election denier, though they ultimately split the vote.</p>



<h2><strong>4. But denying the election isn’t a guaranteed win </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Being a candidate who claims the 2020 election was stolen is a bit like being endorsed by Trump (and, unsurprisingly, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-than-70-percent-of-trumps-endorsees-believe-the-2020-election-was-fraudulent/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">these two pools of candidates tend to overlap</a>) — it can help in the right race, but it’s not a guaranteed winning strategy. Often, other electoral factors override the appeal an election-denying candidate might have — especially when that’s all they really have to offer voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, in the 91 contests in which at least one candidate entertains stolen election conspiracy theories and at least one candidate has accepted Biden as president, Republican voters opted for the pro-democracy candidate 49 times out of 91 (54 percent). The election-denying candidate won just 33 times (36 percent).<a data-footnote-id="18" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-18" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remaining nine races were won by a candidate whose position is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>18</sup></a> In fact, candidates who accepted the election — either fully or while still raising questions about fraud — represent just 14 percent of total Republican primary candidates (winners and losers). Yet, these two groups were overrepresented in the primary winners: 22 percent of nominees (11 percent in each category) accepted the 2020 results.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This perhaps unexpected mismatch, given the prevalence of election-denying candidates this year, had a lot to do with incumbency. In many of the races where voters had a choice between a candidate who had denied the election results and one who accepted them, the latter was an incumbent facing a lesser-known, far-right challenger who was then predictably crushed in the primary. That was the case in the GOP primary for Texas’s 12th District, where Rep. Kay Granger (who <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/11/20/kay-granger-donald-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said it was time for Trump to “move on”</a> from the election way back in late November 2020) easily fended off Alysia Rieg, an EMT who called for “election integrity accountability” on her campaign website, a vague term often <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-big-lie-voting-laws/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">used as a dog whistle</a> to signal soft support for the stolen election conspiracy theories.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/half-gop-primary-winners-big-lie-fivethirtyeight-85234905</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Other electoral factors besides incumbency were at play here, too. In purple districts, for instance, Republicans sometimes decided that a GOP nominee who can potentially attract moderates from the other side in a general election is more appealing than one who can rile up the base. Take Iowa’s 3rd District, where Republicans are hoping to unseat the state’s lone Democratic representative, Cindy Axne. That might explain why voters ultimately nominated state Sen. Zach Nunn, who <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=606394250523133" target="_blank" rel="noopener">touted the security of Iowa elections</a> during his campaign, instead of a candidate who appealed more to the Republican base, like vocal election denier Gary Leffler, a retired farmer who attended Trump’s rally on Jan. 6 and then took photos from <a href="https://twitter.com/patrynard/status/1347282533491351558" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the steps of the U.S. Capitol building</a>. Similarly, in blue Oregon, the winner and runner-up for Republican nominee for governor both accepted the results of the 2020 election, while the <a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2022/05/09/trump-oregon-politics-governors-race-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vocal election denier</a> in the race <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/05/17/us/elections/results-oregon-governor.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attracted just 11 percent of the vote</a>.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, some election deniers also <em>won</em> nominations in purple districts, and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/2022-house-primary-elections-june-14-4da57bd07801cc9613227c2291f64e39" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even unseated incumbents</a>. Even races where the incumbent ultimately prevailed have sometimes been close. For instance, Rep. Nancy Mace, who voted to certify the 2020 election, had to fend off an election-denying challenger in South Carolina’s 1st District. It was a close election, too: Former state Rep. Katie Arrington, who <a href="https://www.thestate.com/news/politics-government/article258170953.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frequently said the 2020 election was stolen</a> from Trump, attracted 45 percent of the vote to Mace’s 53 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, questioning the results of the 2020 election might not be a surefire path to the nomination, but it hasn’t proven to be a dealbreaker for Republican voters, either. That speaks volumes as to the overall direction the Republican Party is moving in.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1658142002069424</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Americans Feel About Space</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/one-of-the-few-things-americans-agree-on-space-is-cool/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Space</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" name="">Pollapalooza</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Americans Feel About Space</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers and Zoha Qamar</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 15, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0414_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0414_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0414_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0414_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/0414_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Two of us are writing this week’s Pollapalooza, but I — Kaleigh Rogers — am taking this top bit since we’re focusing on the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/webbfirstimages/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first images from the James Webb Space Telescope</a> and space exploration is in my blood. During his time as a <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/9adbba/apollo-fire-feature" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quality-control inspector at NASA</a>, my grandfather worked on the Mercury, Gemini and Apollo missions, helping to put the first man on the moon and earning himself an Exceptional Bravery Medal. So when there are new discoveries from the great beyond, I tend to get a little emotional. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Cut to me audibly gasping and visibly tearing up as I saw those intergalactic images. The rich data and level of detail moved me and made me think about our infinitesimal place in the universe. It wasn’t just my fellow space nerds who were feeling the feels this week, either. Social media exploded with awe and wonder at the remarkable images (and <a href="https://twitter.com/JillKrajewski/status/1546626633054015490" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more</a> than <a href="https://twitter.com/_rallycap/status/1546890570815209477" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a few</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/dominicknero/status/1546846199151529987" target="_blank" rel="noopener">memes</a>). And while I’m not convinced the public’s enthusiasm for these deep-space delights indicates much about President Biden’s approval rating (unlike <a href="https://twitter.com/MarkJacob16/status/1546821979919073283" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some publications</a>), I was curious to find out what Americans think about NASA and space exploration in general.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It turns out, this is one of the few areas where Americans largely agree. In <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2021/07/16/americans-support-sending-astronauts-moon-and-mars" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a July 2021 poll from YouGov/The Economist</a>, a majority of Americans said the U.S. should send astronauts to the moon and Mars. This was true across political parties, with slim majorities for Democrats, Republicans and independents. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Most Americans are on the same page about funding space exploration, too. About a third of Democrats, Republicans and independents said government funding of space exploration should be kept the same, and about 40 percent of each group said funding should be increased. Find me another issue where roughly the same share of Republicans and Democrats agree that the government is not spending enough money. Grandpa Buck would be happy to know that about three-quarters of Americans across the political spectrum — 77 percent of Democrats, 76 percent of Republicans and 75 percent of independents — also agreed that the effort made to land the first astronauts on the moon was definitely or probably worth it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For me, one of the most exciting findings from the Webb telescope actually wasn’t one of the eye-popping images but a graph of atmospheric composition instead. That’s because the graph showed evidence of water vapor on an exoplanet called WASP-96b (cool name). We all know water is a key ingredient for life, so whenever we detect it on another planet, it tends to conjure up mental images of extraterrestrial life (though <a href="https://www.salon.com/2022/07/13/jwst-exoplanet-wasp-96b-water/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this particular planet</a> is very hot, doesn’t have a rocky surface and is missing a thin atmosphere, so experts don’t suspect it’s a great candidate to host life). On the question of alien lifeforms, Democrats and Republicans are also aligned. In <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/05/24132604/2205143_crosstabs_POLITICO_RVs_v2_SH_05-25-22.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a Morning Consult/Politico poll</a> from May, registered voters were asked whether they believed life exists outside of Earth. Roughly the same share of Democrats, independents and Republicans (28 percent, 25 percent and 23 percent, respectively) said “yes, definitely.” Another 40 percent of Democrats, 37 percent of independents and 32 percent of Republicans said “yes, probably.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Americans are also equally conspiratorial on this front. Seventy-nine percent of Democrats, 73 percent of independents and 84 percent of Republicans said the government has definitely or probably hidden evidence of UFOs from the public. I guess finding consensus among American voters isn’t that hard — you just have to look a little further.</p>



<h2>Other polling bites</h2>



<ul><li>Tampons have become increasingly expensive and difficult to procure, and younger voters are noticing. Forty-one percent of likely voters between the ages of 18 and 29 are “very” concerned about national tampon shortages, according to <a href="https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2022/7/7/young-voters-are-more-concerned-about-the-tampon-shortage">a poll conducted by Data for Progress</a> last month. Only 14 percent of likely voters of all ages, however, were very concerned about such a shortage. Supply chain bottlenecks and higher prices for materials have contributed to a nearly 10 percent rise in national average tampon costs since the start of 2022. The same survey also assessed attitudes toward the “pink tax,” or how products marketed toward women cost more than the same products marketed toward men. A sizable majority of likely voters (76 percent), regardless of age, said they would “strongly” (56 percent) or “somewhat” (20 percent) support legislative efforts to ban such discrimination in product prices.</li></ul><ul><li>Over half of Americans believe they are their harshest critic, per <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/veycmvelf3/toplines_Imposter_Syndrome_20220607.pdf">a June 7-10 YouGov survey</a> studying imposter syndrome. Fifty-three percent said they criticize themselves more than others criticize them, while only 11 percent thought others criticized them more. (Ah, to be one of those chosen few!) Only 10 percent thought they exaggerated their achievements, compared with 38 percent who said they downplayed achievements. Notably, 46 percent of Americans stated they would rather struggle alone than reach out for help. </li></ul><ul><li>A whopping 64 percent of Democratic primary voters do not prefer Biden as their party’s presidential candidate in 2024, <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071122/33ffa85627ee4648/full.pdf">according to a July 5-7 New York Times/Siena College poll</a>. A third of these naysayers cited his age as their primary concern, while another third referenced his job performance. Meanwhile, 77 percent of all voters said the United States was heading in the wrong direction. Though the exact figure varies slightly, a majority of voters across every party, race, age group, level of educational attainment, region and gender agreed that the nation’s trajectory was negative. That’s a second thing Americans can agree on, beside the stunning space photos: We’re all barreling toward something bad. Unity!</li></ul><ul><li>Eating just a little bit can’t hurt, right? Well, depends who you ask. Americans are split on whether certain foods, even when consumed in choice amounts, can be beneficial for a healthy diet, <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/health/articles-reports/2022/07/08/which-foods-and-drinks-do-americans-think-are-bad">per a survey conducted by YouGov last month</a>. While 23 percent said consuming salt in moderation was healthy, 44 percent thought it was detrimental to one’s health. The divide carries over to caffeinated beverages, as 36 percent of Americans said black coffee was good for one’s health, and 14 percent said it was not. Meanwhile, 37 percent said red meat was good for you, but 27 percent had beef with that take. </li></ul><ul><li>Forty-three percent of American adults under the age of 30 say they know people who use gender-neutral pronouns such as “they,” compared with just 27 percent of all adults, <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/lifestyle/articles-reports/2022/07/08/viewpoints-pronouns-yougov-poll-june-29-july-4-202?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_campaign=gender">according to a recent YouGov survey</a>. Interpersonal relationships seem to affect Americans’ feelings about using these pronouns: A majority of adults who personally knew someone who used gender-neutral pronouns said they’d feel “very” (43 percent) or “somewhat” (31 percent) comfortable using these pronouns for anyone who asked them to do so. To a certain degree, the converse was also true: Americans who did not personally know anyone who used gender-neutral pronouns were more likely to report feeling very (33 percent) or somewhat (28 percent) uncomfortable if asked to use them.</li></ul><h2>Biden approval</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="19" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-19" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>19</sup></a> 38.7 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 56.0 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -17.3 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-americans-dont-trust-institutions/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-americans-dont-trust-institutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 38.6 percent approved and 56.3 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -17.7 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 39.5 percent and a disapproval rating of 53.9 percent, for a net approval rating of -14.4 points.</p>



<h2>Generic ballot</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>20</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 1.8 points (44.8 percent to 43.0 percent). A week ago, Republicans led Democrats by 1.6 points (44.8 percent to 43.2 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 2.5 points (44.8 percent to 42.3 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657881001469716</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Biden Is Very Unpopular. It May Not Tell Us Much About The Midterms.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/biden-is-very-unpopular-it-may-not-tell-us-much-about-the-midterms/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Generic Ballot</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Biden Is Very Unpopular. It May Not Tell Us Much About The Midterms.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 15, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0715-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0715-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0715-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0715-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0715-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">This week, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/11/us/politics/biden-approval-polling-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a Siena College/New York Times poll</a> showed President Biden with just a 33 percent approval rating, a result so poor that it touched off speculation — including from <a href="https://twitter.com/NateSilver538/status/1546520924957990913?s=20&amp;t=jKKV0neUqZUotFWPk7xMBQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">yours truly</a> — about whether he would even run again in 2024. The Siena/New York Times number is on the low end of the polling consensus, but Biden’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approval rating in our polling average</a> — about 39 percent<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>21</sup></a> — is nonetheless a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-behind-bidens-record-low-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historically low number</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And yet, the same poll showed a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/13/upshot/poll-2022-midterms-congress.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">neck-and-neck race for Congress</a>. Democrats led by 1 percentage point among registered voters<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which makes for the most direct comparison with the poll’s Biden approval number, which was also taken among registered voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> on the question of which party voters preferred controlled Congress and trailed by 1 point among likely voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What to make of this seeming divergence? How much does the president’s approval rating <em>actually </em>matter for predicting congressional outcomes?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">From a zoomed-out perspective, the answer is that there’s a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democrats-in-congress-need-bidens-approval-rating-to-stay-in-the-mid-50s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reasonably strong relationship</a>. If you knew nothing else about the race for Congress, you’d expect an unpopular president’s party to lose seats. And indeed, that’s likely what will happen this year, too. Republicans are an 87 percent favorite to take over control of the House, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to the Deluxe version of our forecast</a>. The Senate <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remains much closer to a toss-up</a>, but that has <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-are-favored-to-win-the-house-but-not-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more to do with poor Republican candidates</a> than anything the Democrats are doing well.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-continue-win-georgia-2022-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86847505</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But predicting the number of seats lost in Congress based on the president’s approval rating is not <em>quite</em> the question we’re interested in from a forecasting standpoint. Rather, we want to know how much the president’s approval rating matters <em>given all the other information we have about the race</em>. In other words, is Biden’s poor approval already “baked in” to the congressional generic ballot polls and polls of individual House and Senate races? Or is there reason to think that the Democrats’ standing will get worse between now and November?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The statistical answer is that it’s <em>mostly</em> baked in. Warning: The following paragraphs are going to be a bit technical. If you want more of an intuitive answer, skip ahead to the bolded bullet points below.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">way our model addresses this</a> is by looking at every congressional race since 1990 and evaluating how predictable the movement in the generic ballot has been based on baseline conditions, which we sometimes refer to as the “fundamentals.” Specifically, the factors it looks at include the president’s approval rating, the result of the previous election for Congress, whether or not the election is a midterm and the degree of political polarization. (Times of high political polarization — like now — will tend to produce less dramatic swings in races for Congress because there are fewer swing voters.)</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-energizing-abortion-evens-midterms-equation-silver-86558599</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Right now, those “fundamentals” expect Democrats to eventually lose the House popular vote by about 8 points, which would be an awful result for the party and would very likely result in its loss of both chambers of Congress. By comparison, if Biden had a breakeven approval rating instead of being about 17 points underwater, the “fundamentals” would predict Democrats to lose the popular vote by around 4.5 points, which would still mean almost certain doom in the House but might be enough for them to save the Senate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, the model also weighs those “fundamentals” against the current state of affairs. Right now, Democrats <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trail in our generic congressional ballot polling average</a> — a proxy for the House popular vote — by about 2 points. But that’s actually more like a 4-point deficit among likely voters, since Republicans are likely to have a turnout advantage in November. Our model accounts for this, but the model also accounts for factors aside from the generic ballot in forecasting the House popular vote, and when we take into consideration those factors, our model predicts Democrats to lose the popular vote by almost 6 points, not that far from what the “fundamentals” show.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-supreme-court-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86637136</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Even if there were a bigger gap, though, the “fundamentals” ultimately do not get all that much weight in the model. The reason is simply that, even at this fairly early point in the cycle, the generic ballot (at least if you properly adjust it to account for likely voters) and other indicators directly related to the current election have historically been more reliable predictors than the “fundamentals.” The model does expect conditions to get a bit worse for Democrats, but really just a bit.<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specifically, at this point, the model regresses about one-sixth of the way toward the “fundamentals,” which means that it expects the House popular vote to swing about half of a point more toward Republicans between now and November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So what is the intuition behind this? Here are a few factors to keep in mind:</p>



<h2>1. <strong>Voters have good reasons to disapprove of Biden without wanting Republicans in Congress</strong> </h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">When your approval rating has fallen into the 30s, you’ve not only lost the confidence of most swing voters but also some members of your own party. The Siena/New York Times poll, for instance, showed Biden with <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071122/33ffa85627ee4648/full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only a 70 percent approval rating even among Democrats</a>. However, <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071322/a775fbafdcf9db9d/full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">90 percent of Democrats in that same poll</a> prefer Democratic control of Congress, compared to just 4 percent who want the GOP in charge.<br><br>One concern for Democrats is that those disaffected voters won’t turn out. Still, there’s no particular reason to expect them to vote Republican if they do. A <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/11/us/politics/biden-approval-polling-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lot of them think Biden is too old</a> — a concern also shared by many independent voters — but that’s more a factor for 2024 than in congressional preferences for 2022.<br><br>And on many issues — from <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-the-midterms-could-most-affect-abortion-access/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abortion</a> to <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/03/10/texas-trans-kids-abortion-lgbtq-gender-ideology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LGBTQ rights</a> to the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/the-election-deniers-dominating-the-primaries-in-colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">integrity of the 2020 vote</a> — Republicans are adopting highly right-wing, partisan positions that have little appeal to swing voters and might even motivate otherwise disaffected Democrats to turn out. Parties <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-strongest-house-candidates-in-2020-were-mostly-moderate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generally pay a penalty for ideological extremism</a>. In other words, although Democrats have also adopted <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/29/magazine/moderate-democrat.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpopular left-wing positions</a> on many issues, Republicans aren’t as poised to capitalize on a high inflation and poor electoral environment for Democrats as a more moderate, less Trumpian version of the party would be.</p>



<h2>2. <strong>It’s usually best to trust a direct measure over an indirect one</strong> </h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is just a good principle of statistical analysis. If you have a direct measure of the quantity that you’re interested in, there’s not much need for a proxy or an indirect one.<br><br>Suppose, for instance, that you’re trying to estimate the volume of home sales in — I don’t know — Indianapolis. You could imagine some clever ways to get at this. You could drive around town and count the number of “FOR SALE” signs. Or you could track the number of clicks on Zillow and other websites that list homes for sale. But all of that is beside the point because home sales can be <a href="https://indianarealtors.com/consumers/housing-data/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">directly measured</a>, albeit with something of a lag until reports are compiled.<br><br>Likewise, if you’re interested in races for Congress, and you ask voters how they’re going to vote for Congress and also how they feel about the president, voters’ preference for Congress is the direct measure and the one that should be more reliable. It’s presumptuous, frankly, to suggest otherwise and to disbelieve a voter who says she disapproves of Biden but also wants Democrats to stay in charge of Congress.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/political-consequences-overturning-roe-wade-85819633</p>


<h2>3. <strong>Biden and Democrats weren’t that popular to begin with</strong> </h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/election/2020/exit-polls/president/national-results" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national exit poll in November 2020</a>, 52 percent had a favorable opinion of Biden and 46 percent had an unfavorable opinion. That’s considerably better than his numbers now, and Biden won a fairly comfortable victory in the popular vote. But, it also wasn’t the sort of sweeping mandate that, say, former President Barack Obama had in 2008, which was accompanied by approval and favorability numbers that <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2009/04/23/obama-at-100-days-strong-job-approval-even-higher-personal-ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">initially soared into the 60s and 70s</a>. Moreover, Democrats rode into Obama’s first term with 257 House seats, far more than the 222 they held after the 2020 election.<br><br>Part of the reason that the 2010 midterms were so awful for Democrats was because they had a long way to fall from being about as popular as a party probably could be in modern American politics. In 2022, Democrats don’t have that problem because they weren’t very popular to begin with. They barely held onto the House.<br><br>So while goodwill toward Biden may have been just enough to get him over the hump in 2020 — and a lot of that goodwill has now evaporated — conditions aren’t necessarily <em>that</em> different than they were two years ago. The major parties are <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/355280/party-favorable-ratings-near-parity-viewed-negatively.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">both unpopular</a>, there are few if any nationally beloved political figures and the country is highly polarized. What’s more, with <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/favorability/donald-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpopular</a> former President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/07/14/trump-2024-announcement-fall/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">potentially set to declare a 2024 bid soon</a>, he could also be a factor in the race — maybe one that helps Democrats.</p>



<h2>4. So far, presidential approval and the race for Congress have diverged, not converged </h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, I’d note that if you had predicted some months ago that polls for Congress and Biden’s numbers would have converged toward one another, you would have been wrong. Since May 1, Biden’s approval rating has declined by about 9 points:</p>



<figure><img src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/biden-approval-rating-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/biden-approval-rating-2.png"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And yet, the generic ballot has been essentially unchanged:</p>



<figure><img src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/generic-ballot-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/generic-ballot-2.png"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Instead, as voters have gathered more information about the race, they have drawn more of a distinction between how they feel about Biden and what they’d like to see happen in Congress. Maybe this trend will reverse itself. But the “fundamentalists” — the analysts who think the races for Congress are predictable based on presidential approval and other baseline conditions — have been wrong so far.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (July 15, 2022, 11:06 a.m.):</strong> A previous version of this article calculated the change in Biden’s approval rating from May 1, 2021 — not May 1, 2022. That calculation has been updated to reflect the change in Biden’s approval since May 1, 2022.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><br><br></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657881001469715</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: How Democrats Flipped Georgia in 2020</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-democrats-flipped-georgia-in-2020/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Georgia</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Senate</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-democrats-flipped-georgia-in-2020/">
	<div data-podcast-id="339403" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: How Democrats Flipped Georgia in 2020">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP8373816509.mp3?updated=1657835183">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">In the 2020 election cycle, Georgia found itself at the center of the American political universe. Georgians handed control of the U.S. Senate to Democrats in a pair of dramatic runoffs and voted for a Democrat for president for the first time in 28 years. But just a few years before, it was hardly a battleground state. In 2016, Trump won the state without ever having visited a single time as the Republican presidential nominee. So how did Georgia find itself in such a prominent place in American politics?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In his new book, “Flipped: How Georgia Turned Purple and Broke the Monopoly on Republican Power,” Atlanta Journal-Constitution reporter Greg Bluestein writes about Democrats Jon Ossoff and Raphael Warnock and their successful elections to the U.S. Senate as well as Stacey Abrams and the Democratic coalition she helped turn out at the polls. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Galen Druke talks to Bluestein about his book and delves into how Georgia politics are evolving in the 2022 midterms.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 22:48:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657836001293280</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What’s Behind Biden’s Record-Low Approval Rating?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-behind-bidens-record-low-approval-rating/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/presidential-approval/" name="">Presidential Approval</a></p>
						
													<h1>What's Behind Biden's Record-Low Approval Rating?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 14, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="President Biden Delivers Remarks On The American Rescue Plan" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240645633-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240645633-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240645633-4X3.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1240645633-4X3.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Drew Angerer/Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">In games such as golf, you win by scoring lower than any of your opponents. But in the realm of presidential job approval, such an approach is a recipe for political upheaval, as President Biden has found over the past few months. Polls continue to show his approval rating in poor shape, and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/11/us/politics/biden-approval-polling-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even Democrats are asking questions</a> about his political future amid broad dissatisfaction with the current state of the country.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, Biden is dancing with a bleak bit of history: His <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approval rating of 39 percent</a><a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>24</sup></a> is now the worst of any elected president at this point in his presidency since the end of World War II, according to FiveThirtyEight’s historical presidential approval data. In other words, Biden is arguably in worse shape than any other elected president heading into his first midterm election, including his four most recent predecessors, who, like Biden, were operating in an increasingly polarized political climate.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Biden could have the lowest midterm approval rating" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/iIUGB/8/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="495" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">After entering office, most recent presidents see a decline in their approval ratings, but since Biden’s numbers peaked at 55 percent in March 2021, they have moved in only one direction: down. To some extent, President Barack Obama’s approval rating followed a similar trajectory, but he started off with better numbers than any of the other four most recent presidents and was still well above where Biden is at this point in his presidency. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/latest-jan-hearing-testimony-affect-midterm-elections-86274149</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">By comparison, President Bill Clinton actually mounted a comeback nearly a year into his presidency before his approval fell again in the latter part of 1994. Even President Donald Trump’s low approval rating ticked back up into the low 40s in 2018 after falling to 36 percent in December 2017. And, of course, President George W. Bush topped them all when his approval jumped to a record-high 88 percent in 2001 due to a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rally-around-the-flag-events-are-rare/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rally-around-the-flag moment</a> shortly after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why is Biden’s approval so low? For starters, Americans have a really dim view of how things are going in the U.S. For instance, about 75 percent believe the country is on the wrong track according to the <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/other/direction_of_country-902.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RealClearPolitics average</a> of recent polls, while only 18 percent say the country is moving in the right direction. To be sure, Americans have long held negative views about the direction the country is moving in — RCP’s average hasn’t been net positive once in the past 13 years — but this is still the highest level of dissatisfaction since 2011.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-americans-dont-trust-institutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Many factors</a> are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-feel-burnt-out-personally-and-politically/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">driving</a> this overall <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/are-americans-unhappy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">feeling of dissatisfaction</a> among Americans, but inflation is arguably the biggest reason. Inflation, which is at its <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/?g=rocU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">highest point since the early 1980s</a>, has <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/american-issues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">consistently ranked as the top issue</a> Americans are worried about in our polling with Ipsos. In the most recent <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-birth-control-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight/Ipsos</a> poll, 62 percent of Americans told us that inflation or increasing prices was one of the most important issues facing the country, ranking far ahead of any other topic we asked about. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-continue-win-georgia-2022-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86847505</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, too, inflation has soured Americans further on Biden’s job performance. For instance, an <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/three-in-five-americans-disapprove-of-bidens-handling-of-economic-recovery" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early June poll from Ipsos/ABC News</a> found that only 28 percent of Americans approved of Biden’s handling of inflation; along with his handling of gas prices (27 percent approved), inflation ranked lowest of any of the issues the poll asked about. This stacks up with what’s happened to past presidents, too, as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">notable upticks in inflation</a> have often coincided with sharp declines in presidential job approval. This is particularly true of rising gas prices, as studies have found that <a href="https://pprg.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/Presidential-Approval-and-Gas-Prices.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gas price increases</a> are linked to lower presidential approval — and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-may-or-may-not-blame-biden-for-higher-gas-prices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gas prices have soared</a> during this period of high inflation.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Recently, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-the-economy-still-the-most-important-thing-for-trumps-reelection/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">connection between economic perceptions and presidential standing</a> hasn’t been as strong, but political scientists John Sides and Robert Griffin found that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/07/12/biden-approval-economy-inflation-presidential-ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">falling consumer sentiment</a> is once again a useful indicator for understanding presidential approval, as it explains a lot of what we’re seeing with the decline in Biden’s approval.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Interestingly, that reconnection between the economy and presidential approval may be partly down to the decreasing confidence Democrats have in the state of the economy. In fact, even though Democrats are still more confident than Republicans or independents about the economy, we can see that Democrats’ opinions about economic conditions are actually worse now than at any time during Trump’s presidency, using consumer sentiment data from the <a href="https://data.sca.isr.umich.edu/reports.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Michigan’s Surveys of Consumers</a>.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Even Democrats are down on the economy" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ZsSD7/8/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="400" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The upshot is that this may have weakened Democratic loyalty to Biden. Just 69 percent to 76 percent of Democrats said they approved of Biden in polls from <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/ipsos-core-political-presidential-approval-tracker-07072022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ipsos/Reuters</a>, <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/sdsvy1azjc/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/The Economist</a> and <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/07/11135504/2206231_crosstabs_GEOPOLITICAL_RISK_RV_RVs_v1_LM.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult</a> conducted in early July. This sounds high, but it’s much lower than what <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2018-07/reuters-ipsos-data-core-political-2018-07-11.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">these pollsters</a> found for <a href="https://morningconsult.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/180708_crosstabs_POLITICO_v1_DK-2.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s approval rating among Republicans</a> during the same period <a href="https://d25d2506sfb94s.cloudfront.net/cumulus_uploads/document/j4bk4qaafk/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in 2018</a>, when it hovered between 84 percent and 88 percent. Of course, economic conditions were more favorable during Trump’s presidency, which may have helped keep Republicans firmly behind Trump, but regardless of party loyalty, the reality is that Biden has lost ground among pretty much every group we have numbers for, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/biden-has-lost-support-across-all-groups-of-americans-but-especially-independents-and-hispanics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">continuing a trend</a> we first observed in October. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Back then, close to 35 percent of independents approved of Biden, a figure that’s now sunk to around 30 percent. Meanwhile, Biden’s approval among Black Americans may have fallen even more, going from the high 60s to about 60 percent; among Latino Americans, his approval has gone from around 50 percent to the low-to-mid 40s. White Americans are more Republican-leaning, so Biden had less ground to lose with them to begin with, but even still, his numbers among them have slipped from the high 30s to the mid 30s.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One other group that has soured on Biden is younger Americans, especially considering they were <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Elections/exit-polls-2020-us-presidential-election-results-analysis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the most Democratic-leaning</a> age group in 2020 (and in most recent elections). The <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a> and the Cooperative Election Study suggest that around 60 percent or more of voters 18 to 29 backed Biden in 2020, yet <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/0atxy0xx1u/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent polls suggest</a> Biden’s approval among that age group has <a href="https://60p3co1nax34ovc830mr2sak-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/June-2022-Omnibus-External-Crosstabs.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fallen into the 30s</a>, or <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071122/33ffa85627ee4648/full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even lower</a> in some surveys.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-supreme-court-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-86637136</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Economic dissatisfaction certainly plays into the disillusionment that young people may have of Biden, but other reports suggest that some of that frustration may also lie in their anger over the Biden administration’s <a href="https://www.vox.com/23042037/joe-biden-young-voters-disapprove-progressive-gen-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener">limited progress on issues</a> like climate change and canceling student debt. Looking ahead to the midterm elections, the discontent young people feel toward the president could be a real problem, as it might dampen their enthusiasm to vote — that could be bad for Democrats since young voters are already <a href="http://www.electproject.org/home/voter-turnout/demographics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far less likely to turn out</a> in midterms than in presidential elections. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As it currently stands, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/394628/americans-intensity-running-high-midterms.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls suggest</a> that <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/economic-issues-top-publics-agenda-poll/story?id=85183412" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans as a whole are more enthusiastic</a> than Democrats about the <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/official-polls/fox-news-poll-more-voters-trust-republicans-handle-inflation-crime" target="_blank" rel="noopener">upcoming election</a>, although most recent surveys asking that question predate the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Roe v. Wade, the 1973 decision establishing abortion as a constitutional right. This is an issue that could be motivating for Democrats this fall, and in fact, we’ve already seen some movement toward Democrats in our generic ballot average. It remains to be seen, though, whether that’s a short-term blip or a more long-lasting change in the electoral environment, and of course someone who is unenthusiastic can still vote — an unenthusiastic vote counts the same as an enthusiastic one.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-energizing-abortion-evens-midterms-equation-silver-86558599</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Nevertheless, the historical relationship between presidential approval and the performance of the president’s party in midterm elections should scare Democrats. Generally speaking, the worse a president’s approval is, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-early-clues-about-how-the-midterms-will-go/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the more seats that party tends to lose</a> in the House.<a data-footnote-id="25" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-25" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This relationship is somewhat true for the Senate, too, but because only about one-third of Senate seats are up each cycle, it’s not a truly national election like it is for the House, where all 435 seats are up. For instance, while &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/election-results/2018/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Republicans lost control of the House&lt;/a&gt; in the 2018 election, they actually &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/election-results/2018/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;gained two seats&lt;/a&gt; in the Senate despite Trump’s approval rating sitting in the low 40s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>25</sup></a> Thinking back to that first chart, three of the four presidents preceding Biden saw their party <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lose at least 40 House seats</a> in their first midterm election. The exception was Bush, whose party actually gained six seats in the 2002 election, but he had an unusually high approval rating at the time of his first midterm. That’s still notable, though, because it means it has taken that kind of anomaly to see the president’s party suffer fewer losses — or even achieve gains — in House elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We can’t know for sure where Biden’s approval will go from here, but many of the factors playing into his approval rating don’t look likely to disappear anytime soon. And that could be a major anchor weighing down Democrats this fall.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657795502060563</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Jan. 6’s Salacious Details Are Beside The Point</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/jan-6s-salacious-details-are-beside-the-point/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Jan. 6 Investigation</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/january-6th-investigation/" name="">Jan. 6 Investigation</a></p>
						
													<h1>Jan. 6's Salacious Details Are Beside The Point</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 13, 2022, at 7:35 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="House Select Committee to Investigate the January 6th Presents Findings in Hearing" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1241866202-2-e1657711706340.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1241866202-2-e1657711706340.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1241866202-2-e1657711706340.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1241866202-2-e1657711706340.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Kent Nishimura / Los Angeles Times via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">During an hours-long meeting at the White House on Dec. 18, 2020, White House aide Cassidy Hutchinson fired off a text: “The west wing is UNHINGED” — emphasis hers. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The meeting Hutchinson was referring to that night involved then-President Donald Trump, White House attorneys and a coterie of outside influencers assisting in a crusade to overturn the election. At the meeting, voices grew so loud that staffers could hear shouting from down the hall. Eric Herschmann, then a senior adviser to Trump, nearly got in a fist fight with Michael Flynn, the retired general and former national security adviser. And Rudy Giuliani may or may not have <a href="https://twitter.com/therecount/status/1546917426863931392" target="_blank" rel="noopener">called Trump’s White House advisers</a> “a bunch of pussies.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some <a href="https://www.axios.com/2021/02/02/trump-oval-office-meeting-sidney-powell?utm_campaign=organic&amp;utm_medium=socialshare&amp;utm_source=twitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">details of this meeting</a> had already leaked, but the full scope of the tense evening was outlined in testimony during the Tuesday hearing held by the House Select Committee investigating the Jan. 6 attack on the U.S. Capitol. Unsurprisingly, these salacious details dominated the reactions following the hearings, both online and in media reports. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the true lurid details of the hearings are in the whole trying-to-overturn-democracy thing. Trump’s White House staff, his campaign and <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-bidens-washington/bill-barr-calls-bullshit-on-trumps-election-lies" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his own Justice Department</a> made clear to him there was no evidence of election fraud, but he continued to claim there was anyway. He continued to pressure election officials and then-Vice President Mike Pence to overturn the results. Trump <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/jan-6-panel-looks-trump-white-house-cassidy-hutchinson-testimony-rcna35550" target="_blank" rel="noopener">knew many of his supporters were armed</a> that day when he spoke to them, but he encouraged them to go to the Capitol anyway. He knew they had breached the Capitol, yet he <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trump-mob-failure/2021/01/11/36a46e2e-542e-11eb-a817-e5e7f8a406d6_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">waited hours to call off his supporters</a>.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/latest-jan-hearing-testimony-affect-midterm-elections-86274149</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">The Dec. 18 meeting, then, is important in how it augments <em>those</em> events. The committee took care to emphasize the timing: The meeting took place four days after the Electoral College vote, a deadline after which many in Trump’s inner circle believed (and logic would dictate) the fight over the results should have ended. This was made clear through testimony from former Attorney General Bill Barr, who said, “In my mind that was the end of the matter,” and former press secretary Kayleigh McEnany, who said once the litigation had concluded she started to plan for “life after the administration.” Even Trump’s daughter, Ivanka Trump, when asked <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/07/12/1111123258/jan-6-committee-hearing-transcript" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whether she thought the Electoral College vote marked the end</a> of the administration, said, “I think so, I think it was my sentiment probably prior as well.” Yet just days later, here was Trump hosting individuals who continued to claim there was a path to overturning the results. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The tension itself that night was also part of the broader story of Trump’s election fraud claims. Members of both the election-denying crew who visited the White House that night — which included Giuliani, Flynn, lawyer Sidney Powell and Overstock.com founder Patrick Byrne — and members of Trump’s staff testified in recorded depositions that the evening became heated because the outsiders continued to push the election fraud theory while the staffers reminded them that there was no evidence. Both sides said the animosity that night was because Trump’s closest advisers were pushing back against the baseless claims of fraud, yet in the wee hours of the next morning, Trump sent out a now-infamous tweet announcing the rally on Jan. 6 to his followers: “Be there, will be wild!”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Tuesday’s hearing wasn’t the first time titillating details were included in the testimony — sprinkled throughout the hearings were allegations such as Giuliani <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/donald-trump/rudy-giuliani-blasts-trump-aides-said-was-drunk-election-night-rcna33485" target="_blank" rel="noopener">getting hammered</a> on election night (a claim Giuliani has denied) and Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/06/28/january-6-hearings-cassidy-hutchinson-key-moments-video-analysis-00042914" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hurling a plate of ketchup</a> at the wall of the White House dining room (a claim <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/108568349673244821" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump has denied</a>). But while it’s easy to get distracted by these moments, the committee has kept its eye on the ball, unveiling exactly what the president knew and when he knew it. It’s not a crime to host a heated meeting or to smash a plate of food against the wall. It is a crime to mount an insurrection. The committee is more focused on trying to figure out whether the latter than the former happened, even if the headlines suggest otherwise.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 12:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657714501545851</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Limiting Access To Abortion Limits Access To Birth Control</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-limiting-access-to-abortion-limits-access-to-birth-control/</link>
						<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>Birth Control</category>
			<category>Planned Parenthood</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/birth-control/" name="">Birth Control</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Limiting Access To Abortion Limits Access To Birth Control</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/monica-potts/" title="" rel="author">Monica Potts</a></p>
							<p>Graphics by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/humera-lodhi/" rel="author">Humera Lodhi</a></p>
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 13, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Planned Parenthood birth control sign, Alexandria, Minnesota" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1355162625-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1355162625-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1355162625-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/GettyImages-1355162625-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Michael Siluk/UCG/Universal Images Group/Getty Images)</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Planned Parenthood has been controversial since its 1916 founding, but the latest wave of political battles against it <a href="https://www.vox.com/2016/7/14/12189446/mike-pence-planned-parenthood" target="_blank" rel="noopener">began in earnest in 2007</a>, when then-Rep. Mike Pence introduced an amendment to a House of Representatives’ appropriations bill to block federal funds from going to the organization’s nationwide network of reproductive health clinics.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Planned Parenthood was targeted because it’s the largest abortion provider in the United States, but it wasn’t its abortion services that were on the chopping block. Federal law already prohibits federal funds from being used for abortion services. Instead, the bill would have ended payments to Planned Parenthood for other health services, like cancer screenings, testing for sexually transmitted infections, regular reproductive health exams and contraception. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The goal of Republican pro-life lawmakers like Pence has long been to put abortion clinics out of business. But what the long-running fight against Planned Parenthood and other abortion providers shows is that access to abortion and birth control are often linked. In fact, almost <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/sites/default/files/pdfs/pubs/journals/j.contraception.2010.04.010.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all clinics that provide abortion services</a> also provide contraceptive services. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In many states, anti-abortion politics can limit patients’ access to contraception, especially low-income women who rely on publicly funded clinics. That could be even more true as some abortion clinics around the country <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/24/us/abortion-clinics-closing-roe-wade.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">start to close</a> following the Supreme Court’s ruling last month <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-argument-for-overturning-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overturning the constitutional right to abortion</a>. For many people worried about an unplanned pregnancy, all of the tools that they might use to prevent one — from birth control to abortion — are out of reach simply because of where they live.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“My biggest fear right now is the fact that, as we are heading into this post-Roe phase, is that red states — and especially red Southern states — where there are already so few Planned Parenthoods, are going to lose them and as those are in essence, the same place that people can even get contraception, it’s going to make all of this so much more dire,” said Robin Marty, director of operations for the West Alabama Women’s Center.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Planned Parenthood clinics are an important part of the reproductive health landscape. Currently, many low-income patients without private insurance access birth control through Medicaid or Title X, the latter of which funds clinics that provide birth control and other family-planning services. According to Planned Parenthood, in 2018 <a href="https://www.plannedparenthoodaction.org/issues/health-care-equity/medicaid-and-reproductive-health" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly half of its patients received Medicaid</a>, and according to the Kaiser Family Foundation, Planned Parenthood in 2019 served <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/issue-brief/financing-family-planning-services-for-low-income-women-the-role-of-public-programs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">32 percent</a> of the patients who sought contraceptives at safety-net clinics.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/overturning-roe-means-abortion-access-us-fivethirtyeight-85676655</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But more than that, Planned Parenthood and other clinics that offer abortions are often exclusively focused on reproductive care, which means <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/issue-brief/financing-family-planning-services-for-low-income-women-the-role-of-public-programs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">patients can sometimes obtain contraception faster and have a wider range of options</a> than other places, like <a href="https://www.hrsa.gov/opa/eligibility-and-registration/health-centers/fqhc/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Federally Qualified Health Centers</a> or through county health departments, that see other patients for needs beyond just reproductive health care.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Marty said, for instance, that in Alabama, most Title X funds are distributed through county health departments and there is often only one department per county, regardless of the population relying on that clinic for services. “Because of that, most people are waiting three months, four months in order to be able to get in for birth control,” she said. “I’ve been in Alabama for a little over a year now, and one of the things that has utterly blown me away is how little birth control access already exists in the state and in the South,” she said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And some states have already moved to further restrict access to these services. At least four states — <a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/planned-parenthood-st-louis-region-southwest-missouri/who-we-are/press-releases/missouri-just-became-fourth-state-to-approve-defunding-planned-parenthood-biden-administration-must-take-action-immediately" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arkansas, Texas, Mississippi and Missouri</a> — have attempted to block Planned Parenthood from receiving Medicaid funds. These bans have been challenged in court, but so far federal judges have allowed <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/08/16/543974021/federal-appeals-court-says-arkansas-can-block-medicaid-payments-to-planned-paren" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Arkansas</a> and <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/03/10/planned-parenthood-medicaid-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Texas bans</a> to stand. Karen Stone, vice president of public policy and government relations at Planned Parenthood Federation of America, said in a statement that Planned Parenthood is “urging the administration to enforce” a provision that says Medicaid recipients should be able to choose their own providers. “Right now, a number of the states that have or are attempting to ban abortion have also cut off Medicaid patients’ access to preventive care,” the statement said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even more fundamental, though, <a href="https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/status-of-state-medicaid-expansion-decisions-interactive-map/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">12 states have not expanded Medicaid</a> under the Affordable Care Act at all. And without Medicaid expansion, <a href="https://www.cbpp.org/research/health/medicaid-expansion-frequently-asked-questions#:~:text=The%20uninsured%20rate%20among%20low,to%2034%20percent%20in%202019." target="_blank" rel="noopener">uninsured rates remain higher in these states than the rest of the nation</a>, which means patients who want access to contraception don’t have the care that Medicaid guarantees. And as you can see in the map below, there’s a lot of overlap between the states that haven’t expanded Medicaid and those that have or plan to limit access to abortion. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1210" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/potts.BIRTH-CONTROL.0713.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/potts.BIRTH-CONTROL.0713.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/potts.BIRTH-CONTROL.0713.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/potts.BIRTH-CONTROL.0713.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That said, even in states where Medicaid has been expanded but abortion is banned or limited within a few weeks of conception, there are other barriers to receiving contraceptive care. A particular point of contention is emergency contraception, <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2013/02/22/172595689/morning-after-pills-dont-cause-abortion-studies-say" target="_blank" rel="noopener">which doesn’t end a pregnancy</a> but has come under fire from <a href="https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/research-and-analysis/blogs/stateline/2022/05/19/some-states-already-are-targeting-birth-control" target="_blank" rel="noopener">legislators who believe</a> it might prevent a fertilized egg from implanting in the uterus. (Studies have shown it works primarily <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2013/02/22/172595689/morning-after-pills-dont-cause-abortion-studies-say" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by preventing ovulation</a>.) “I think that has opened the door for politicians, particularly in these more hostile states to … think about using language that that exists in anti-abortion bills” to limit access to birth control, said Megan Kavanaugh, a principal research scientist at the Guttmacher Institute, a research organization that supports abortion rights.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Fifteen states and Washington, D.C., currently require emergency rooms to dispense emergency contraception on request, but many of those states have not restricted abortion rights since the Supreme Court decision, according to the Guttmacher Institute. (Additionally, Arkansas, Colorado, Virginia and Texas require emergency rooms to provide information about emergency contraception, while Ohio and Pennsylvania require emergency rooms to dispense emergency contraception but lack an enforcement mechanism or allow providers to opt out.) Thirteen other states allow doctors, hospitals, pharmacists and/or employers to refuse to administer or prescribe emergency contraception. And many of these states that allow providers to opt out of providing emergency contraception are also now banning abortion, or limiting it to very early in pregnancy.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Title X program is supposed to provide a backstop for uninsured patients to still have access to birth control, but how those funds are distributed and used is often political. For instance, in 2019, the Trump administration <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/article/2020/02/trump-administrations-domestic-gag-rule-has-slashed-title-x-networks-capacity-half" target="_blank" rel="noopener">instituted a rule</a> that clinics that provide or refer patients to abortion services couldn’t receive Title X funds, effectively blocking Planned Parenthood and other abortion clinics from receiving money from the program. Providers referred to it as <a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/about-us/newsroom/press-releases/in-huge-victory-for-sexual-and-reproductive-health-care-biden-harris-administration-announces-end-to-title-x-gag-rule" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a “gag” rule</a>, and Planned Parenthood <a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/about-us/newsroom/press-releases/trump-administration-gag-rule-forces-planned-parenthood-out-of-title-x-national-program-for-birth-control-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pulled out of some states</a> where they had been providing Title X-funded services because they refused to comply with the ban. (Six states — Hawaii, Maine, Oregon, Vermont, Utah and Washington — saw <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/article/2020/02/trump-administrations-domestic-gag-rule-has-slashed-title-x-networks-capacity-half" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all of their Title X clinics</a> pull out of the program.)</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/political-consequences-overturning-roe-wade-85819633</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, in the following years, 2.4 million fewer patients were served by Title X clinics, <a href="https://opa.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/2021-09/title-x-fpar-2020-national-summary-sep-2021.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to an analysis</a> from the federal Office of Population Affairs. While some of that was due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the OPA found that about two-thirds of the loss in clients was attributable to the Trump rules, versus about a third to the pandemic. The Biden administration reversed those rules <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/about/news/2021/10/04/hhs-issues-final-regulation-aimed-at-ensuring-access-to-equitable-affordable-client-centered-quality-family-planning-services.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in 2021</a>, but that only recently went into effect, and service levels haven’t bounced back. <a href="https://theintercept.com/2021/02/01/biden-title-x-reproductive-health/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Funding for the program has thus far remained relatively stagnant</a>, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even before 2019, though, access to Title X services depended on where patients lived. In a 2021 study, political scientists Candis Watts Smith, Rebecca Kreitzer, Kellen Kane and Tracee Saunders <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/jhppl/article/46/2/277/166722/Affordable-but-Inaccessible-Contraception-Deserts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">examined patient access to Planned Parenthood clinics in the Title X network</a> located within a reasonable distance.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Although the 10 states they studied distributed Title X funds in a variety of ways, overall, between <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/jhppl/article/46/2/277/166722/Affordable-but-Inaccessible-Contraception-Deserts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">17 and 53 percent of reproductive-age residents</a> lived in a contraception desert, meaning the nearest clinics were beyond what they classified a reasonable traveling distance.<a data-footnote-id="26" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-26" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The states studied included seven of the 10 most populous states. The researchers used a definition of “reasonable” which varied by where people lived: A 15-minute drive was considered reasonable for a densely populated area, for instance, while an hour’s drive was considered reasonable for people who live in an isolated community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>26</sup></a> Moreover, low-income people and people of color were disproportionately likely to live in a contraception desert, and they found that this problem would be made worse if Planned Parenthood were blocked from the program entirely.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, patients seeking abortions are already likely driving longer distances to receive care, further straining a system that also provides contraception care. “The health care centers located in what we’re calling surge states are going to necessarily need to be able to provide and meet these patients’ needs for abortion care, and that could very well impact their capacity to provide the other range of sexual reproductive health care needs that our patients have,” Kavanaugh said. They may need to focus on abortion care at the expense of other services in some instances, she said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s why as abortion clinics continue to close, an already strained system will now have to absorb all of the reproductive health care needs that will go unaddressed, especially if more pregnancies continue because of a lack of access to birth control and abortion. “Right now it’s important, it’s really important, to make sure that our family planning network is robust and well-funded across the country,” said Alina Salganicoff, director of women’s health policy at the Kaiser Family Foundation. “Particularly in places where abortion will no longer be available.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657710001617604</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Americans Feel About Abortion And Contraception</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-birth-control-poll/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>American Issues</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Americans Feel About Abortion And Contraception</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/holly-fuong/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 12, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="IPSOS-ISSUES-0708-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IPSOS-ISSUES-0708-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IPSOS-ISSUES-0708-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IPSOS-ISSUES-0708-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/IPSOS-ISSUES-0708-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">It’s been more than two weeks since the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-argument-for-overturning-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Supreme Court ruled in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health</a> that there is no consitutional right to abortion, overturning the precedent set in 1973’s Roe v. Wade decision. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/roe-v-wade-defined-an-era-the-supreme-court-just-started-a-new-one/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">This has set off</a> a scramble <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-the-midterms-could-most-affect-abortion-access/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">across the country</a>, as <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/interactive-map-shows-abortion-bans-effect-doctors-face/story?id=85881916" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some states move to restrict legal access to abortion</a> while others seek to expand it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polls show that Americans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-views-on-abortion-are-pretty-stagnant-their-views-on-the-supreme-court-are-not/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largely disapprove of the court’s decision</a>, and the latest <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/FiveThirtyEight-2022-midterm-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight/Ipsos survey</a> found that Americans are now more likely to prioritize abortion as a major issue — even if it still isn’t their top concern. Conducted shortly after the court overturned Roe,<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;June 27-July 5, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> FiveThirtyEight/Ipsos once again interviewed the same 2,000 or so Americans from our previous two survey waves using Ipsos’s <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/solutions/public-affairs/knowledgepanel" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KnowledgePanel</a>. And from a list of 20 topics, the more than 1,500 adults who responded ranked abortion as the fourth-most important issue facing the country, with 19 percent rating it as a leading concern.<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had 1,549 respondents in the third wave of the panel survey. As was the case in the previous waves of our survey, we asked respondents about the most important issues in three different ways: an open-ended question where they could write what issue or issues were most important to them, and then two multiple choice questions where respondents could choose up to three issues from a list of 20, including “other” or “none of these,” that they were either personally worried about or that they thought were most important to the country. Sample is weighted to match the general population. This poll’s margin of error is +/- 3.2 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a> This marked a notable increase from the 9 percent who ranked abortion as a top issue in our last survey released in early June. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="More Americans are now worried about abortion after Dobbs" aria-label="Range Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/pbyEu/3/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="603" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Despite the clear uptick in concern about abortion, however, the issue still substantially trailed three other issues: inflation or increasing costs, crime or gun violence and political extremism or polarization. Inflation is far and away Americans’ leading worry, as more than 60 percent named it as one of their top issues. Meanwhile, concern over crime and gun violence fell to 34 percent after <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/over-40-percent-of-americans-now-rate-gun-violence-as-a-top-issue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reaching the low 40s in June</a>, while concerns about <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/3-in-10-americans-named-political-polarization-as-a-top-issue-facing-the-country/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polarization and extremism grew to 33 percent</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats and independents were especially likely to say abortion ranked as a top issue for the country.<a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Independents included respondents who identified as “independent” or “something else,” or who skipped the question for party identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>24</sup></a> The share of Democrats who named abortion more than doubled, from 13 percent in our previous wave to 27 percent in our latest wave, while the percentage of independents who mentioned abortion jumped from 8 percent to 17 percent. Republicans, too, were more worried about the issue, but their share only increased from 8 percent to 13 percent.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/political-consequences-overturning-roe-wade-85819633</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">We asked these respondents why they listed abortion as a key issue, and many offered stark responses that showed the range of emotions that can accompany this issue — sometimes from unexpected sources. “Abortion is a personal topic for women. No one/no law should go against a woman's personal issue concerning this matter,” said a 60-year old Hispanic woman from New Jersey who identified as an independent but leaned Republican, while a 26-year old white woman in Colorado who identified as a Republican told us that “a nation that kills its babies cannot possibly survive as a strong, compassionate, cohesive nation.” A 20-year old Black man from California who identified as a Democrat wrote, “Women have less rights now than their mothers and grandmothers did.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Interestingly, most Americans supported the underlying argument for Roe — that there is a right to privacy established in the Constitution; only not everyone agreed that it applied to abortion. Overall, 65 percent of Americans said the Constitution contains a right to privacy; only 10 percent said “no,” with almost no differences across party lines. However, a plurality (39 percent) said there was no legal right to abortion in the Constitution, while 30 percent said there was, a split largely driven by Republicans (70 percent of whom said there was no legal right to abortion).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/overturning-roe-means-abortion-access-us-fivethirtyeight-85676655</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But the question now is where the fight over abortion will go next. For instance, the Dobbs decision <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/06/24/thomas-constitutional-rights-00042256" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may have opened the door</a> to future judicial rulings that threaten long-protected access to different forms of contraception. And some Republican-controlled state legislatures have even started <a href="https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/research-and-analysis/blogs/stateline/2022/05/19/some-states-already-are-targeting-birth-control" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trying to restrict access to</a> different forms of birth control with legislation. Our poll found, however, that such bills might be a bridge too far for most Americans, as there is overwhelming support for legal access to common forms of contraception across party lines. Strikingly, around 90 percent of Americans said condoms and birth control pills should be legal in “all” or “most” cases, and 81 percent said the same of IUDs (intrauterine devices). And, there is very little difference in support for the legality of each of these contraceptives across party lines.<a data-footnote-id="25" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-25" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The difference in support between Democrats and Republicans is at most 2 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>25</sup></a> </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Americans of all stripes support most forms of birth control" aria-label="Dot Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/Ln8zx/4/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="355" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Americans are more clearly divided over emergency contraception like Plan B pills, but 70 percent overall still said these methods should be legal, including 62 percent of Republicans, who were less supportive than Democrats or independents. But abortion itself brought out the sharpest partisan splits. At least 80 percent of Democrats said abortion in surgical or pill form should be legal, compared to about a third of Republicans. “I identify more with Republicans because the Democrats seem to be ‘everybody gets a free ride.’ But on this issue, I’m more with the Democratic Party,” said Debra W., an older white woman from Michigan. “Too many of [the Supreme Court justices] are too conservative. And they just are seeming to go back on a lot of rights.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, while Republicans were more likely to oppose abortion than Democrats or independents, they, like most Americans, rejected the idea of making abortion fully illegal, with no exceptions. This is notable because a number of almost entirely Republican-run states <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/09/health/abortion-bans-rape-incest.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could end up with abortion bans</a> that contain no allowances in cases of rape, incest or when the mother’s life is in danger. But in our poll, 81 percent of respondents opposed such a comprehensive ban, including 74 percent of Republicans.<a data-footnote-id="26" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-26" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respondents were asked whether they supported or opposed a series of items. We defined “support” as when respondents “strongly” or “somewhat” supported an item, and “oppose” as when respondents “strongly” or “somewhat” opposed an item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>26</sup></a> “I feel like a lot of the conservative views are a bit more extreme than they were before,” said Soledad Ramos, a 33-year old Hispanic woman from Texas who identified as independent but leaned Democratic. “Regardless how it happened, [women] may end up in a situation where they may decide that abortion is the better option for them. And I feel like they should have the say to decide that.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some GOP-controlled states <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/06/29/abortion-state-lines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are also looking to punish women</a> who seek abortions across state lines, yet 78 percent of respondents opposed making it illegal to cross state lines to obtain an abortion, including 73 percent of Republicans. And 76 percent overall opposed making it illegal to assist a woman seeking an abortion with money or transportation, including 61 percent of Republicans. More broadly, there just wasn’t much support for punishing those who violate laws against abortion, as only 18 percent of respondents supported criminally charging violators and having them face either jail time or a fine. By comparison, 13 percent supported them being charged with a misdemeanor and a fine, while 36 percent opposed any punishment at all (31 percent said they didn’t know).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans <a href="https://time.com/6191886/fetal-personhood-laws-roe-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are also pushing forward</a> controversial fetal personhood legislation — laws that could <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/states-say-abortion-bans-dont-affect-ivf-providers-lawyers-worry-rcna35556" target="_blank" rel="noopener">make in vitro fertilization illegal</a>. In our survey, we asked half our respondents whether <em>fetuses</em> should be given the same rights as children and adults, and the other half whether <em>fertilized eggs</em> should have those rights. Majorities opposed both proposals, but fetal personhood did receive a bit more support, especially among Republicans. Overall, 59 percent opposed making fetuses legal persons, while 36 percent supported the idea, including 66 percent of Republicans. By comparison, 62 percent opposed personhood for fertilized eggs, including 50 percent of Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Beyond what states are doing to restrict or expand abortion access, there’s also the question of the issue’s impact on the 2022 midterm election. It’s early yet, but we’ve noticed a small trend in the Democrats’ direction in our generic ballot question among likely voters, not unlike that seen <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maybe-dobbs-did-change-the-race-well-need-more-time-to-know-for-sure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in some other recent polling</a>. Back in early May, Republicans led by 5 points among likely voters (40 percent to 35 percent), but the GOP edge shrank to 2 points in early June (40 percent to 38 percent), and in our latest wave Democrats actually led by 1 point (39 percent to 38 percent). Because the FiveThirtyEight/Ipsos poll uses a panel, we’re talking about movement among largely the same group of voters, so this could be meaningful. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/supreme-court-dealt-big-blow-separation-church-state-85886797</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">However, we shouldn’t overstate the importance of this swing, as it’s only July and we know <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/our-best-tool-for-predicting-midterm-elections-doesnt-show-a-republican-wave-but-history-is-on-the-gops-side/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the generic ballot polling average tends to trend</a> toward the party not in the White House as we get closer to the election. Moreover, abortion (or any other issue, for that matter) doesn’t seem to have made people who weren’t likely to vote say they are <em>now </em>likely to vote. <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/majority-of-americans-think-supreme-court-overturning-roe-was-more-about-politics-than-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A lot of</a> coverage <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/3543477-nearly-4-in-10-say-roe-v-wade-overturning-made-them-much-more-interested-in-voting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has cited polls</a> that ask respondents whether the Supreme Court’s decision has made them more likely to vote, but respondents who were already likely to vote could still answer “more likely” in such surveys, so those figures don’t tell us that much about potential increases in voter engagement. Meanwhile, in our survey, the share who said they were likely to vote has hardly changed across the three waves — and there’s been little change by party, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, while about 1 in 5 respondents cited abortion as a top issue, 3 in 5 named inflation or rising prices. Moreover, higher prices, particularly higher gas prices, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">often correspond</a> with abysmal presidential approval ratings, which, of course, usually align <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-early-clues-about-how-the-midterms-will-go/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">with worse midterm performances</a> by the president’s party. We didn’t ask about job approval, but President Biden’s favorability numbers remained poor: Thirty-three percent registered a favorable opinion of him, compared with 59 percent who held an unfavorable view.<a data-footnote-id="27" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-27" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Favorable opinions were those that were “very,” “somewhat” or “lean” favorable. Unfavorable opinions were those that were “very,” “somewhat” or “lean” unfavorable. Respondents were also given the option of “don’t know” and skipping the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>27</sup></a> Those numbers were somewhat better among likely voters (40 percent favorable, 59 percent unfavorable), but still quite negative for Biden. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, abortion has become a more pressing topic in the midterms, but the fundamental worry about rising prices and Biden’s low standing could still be a major boon to Republican fortunes in the fall.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional reporting and research by Amelia Thomson-Deveaux. Art direction by Emily Scherer. Copy editing by Santul Nerkar. Graphics by Paroma Soni. Story editing by Sarah Frostenson.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657624502351362</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Americans’ Support For LGBTQ Rights Often Stops With Transgender Rights</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-support-for-lgbtq-rights-often-stops-with-transgender-rights/</link>
						<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<category>Discrimination</category>
			<category>Gay Rights</category>
			<category>LGBTQ</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<category>Transgender</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/lgbtq/" name="">LGBTQ</a></p>
						
													<h1>Americans’ Support For LGBTQ Rights Often Stops With Transgender Rights</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/natalie-jackson/" title="" rel="author">Natalie Jackson</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 12, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="LGTBQ-CROSSPRESSURES-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/LGTBQ-CROSSPRESSURES-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/LGTBQ-CROSSPRESSURES-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/LGTBQ-CROSSPRESSURES-4x3-1.png?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/LGTBQ-CROSSPRESSURES-4x3-1.png?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">In his <a href="https://thehill.com/regulation/court-battles/3535841-thomas-calls-for-overturning-precedents-on-contraceptives-lgbtq-rights/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://thehill.com/regulation/court-battles/3535841-thomas-calls-for-overturning-precedents-on-contraceptives-lgbtq-rights/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">concurring opinion</a> in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization, Justice Clarence Thomas wrote that he views not only abortion precedent as wrong but also precedents involving LGBTQ rights. Public opinion, however, is largely against restricting LGBTQ rights. Over the past few decades, these rights have steadily gained backing from the American public — for example, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/350486/record-high-support-same-sex-marriage.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">support for same-sex marriage has doubled</a> since the late 1990s. And laws intended to protect LGBTQ people from discrimination in jobs, <a href="https://adata.org/faq/what-are-public-accommodations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public accommodations</a> and housing garners the <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/americans-support-for-key-lgbtq-rights-continues-to-tick-upward/#page-section-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">support of about 8 in 10 Americans</a>, including majorities of Republicans and white evangelicals.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the same time, however, policies curbing certain aspects of LGBTQ rights — particularly those pertaining to transgender people — have gained traction in state legislatures across the nation. A number of states have already implemented <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/nbc-out/out-politics-and-policy/nearly-240-anti-lgbtq-bills-filed-2022-far-targeting-trans-people-rcna20418" target="_blank" rel="noopener">policies affecting transgender Americans</a>, and more states are introducing similar measures. And despite widespread support for general nondiscrimination policies, many Americans actually <em>do</em> support restricting rights for transgender people.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For example, the Public Religion Research Institute, where I’m the research director, found last year that <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/most-americans-support-pro-lgbtq-policies-but-are-more-divided-over-transgender-sports-and-bathroom-policies/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">47 percent of Americans favored “bathroom bills”</a> that would require transgender people to use the bathroom of their sex assigned at birth, not their gender identity.<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The poll was conducted Aug. 9-30, 2021, and has a margin of error of +/- 1.86 percentage points. If respondents skipped a given question, they were excluded from its analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>20</sup></a> Meanwhile, 52 percent of Americans said they were opposed to transgender boys’ participating in high school sports for their gender identity; 61 percent said the same of transgender girls.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For some Americans — especially members of the LGBTQ community — supporting restrictive bathroom bills and opposing participation in sports of one’s gender identity are forms of discrimination and should be incompatible with broader support for nondiscrimination protections. Yet in that same survey from PRRI, we found that a considerable share of Americans held seemingly opposing views. Forty-six percent of Americans, for instance, said they both supported general nondiscrimination protections <em>and </em>opposed allowing transgender girls to participate in girls’ sports. Meanwhile, 37 percent supported nondiscrimination protections <em>and</em> opposed allowing transgender boys to participate in boys’ sports. Finally, 36 percent supported nondiscrimination protections <em>and </em>supported bathroom bills requiring transgender people to use the bathroom of their sex assigned at birth.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Who are these Americans with mixed views? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In short, a little bit of everyone. By partisanship, Republicans and independents are much more likely than Democrats to hold opposing views, or be “cross-pressured,” on this issue, but at least one-quarter of Democrats also fall into this cross-pressured category in each of the three situations described above.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Cross-pressured opinions were most prominent among Americans age 50 to 64, with those 65 and older and those 30 to 49 being somewhat less likely to fall into this category. Americans age 18 to 29 were the least likely to be cross-pressured — although at least 30 percent of this age group fell into that category across all three situations. Americans with a college education were also less likely than those without a college education to be cross-pressured on the bathroom-use question, as were women compared with men on the issue of transgender girls participating in girls’ high school sports. Those who said they knew someone who is LGBTQ were also less likely to be cross-pressured on the bathroom-use question compared with those who do not know an LGBTQ person.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With the exception of Hispanic Catholics, most Christian groups were considerably more likely than non-Christians or religiously affiliated Americans to be cross-pressured on nondiscrimination protections and transgender participation in sports. On nondiscrimination protections and bathroom restrictions, however, all Christian groups we surveyed, including Hispanic Catholics, were more cross-pressured than those who weren’t Christian or religiously affiliated at all.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In general, those who are less likely to be cross-pressured are more likely to support all three pro-LGBTQ-rights positions we asked about. That includes Democrats and young people across all three situations, and those with a college education or higher and women on some of the questions — although, notably, at least one-fourth of each of these groups were still cross-pressured.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These same patterns hold for just about every demographic and attitudinal comparison that analysts typically use to explain differences in opinion — many people remain cross-pressured, even those who are typically on the progressive end of the political spectrum. The policies and questions surrounding transgender rights are clearly not tapping into the same sense of fairness and anti-discrimination sentiment as the nondiscrimination-laws question. So, what is it tapping into?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The clearest picture emerges when we look at beliefs about gender. As with abortion, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-real-dividing-line-on-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the true dividing line</a> seems to have more to do with how people think about gender. Among those who feel strongly that there is a range of many genders (versus only two — a man and a woman),<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Respondents selected whether they: 1) feel strongly that there is a range of many gender identities, 2) think there is a range of many gender identities but do not feel strongly about it, 3) think there are only two genders but do not feel strongly about it or 4) feel strongly that there are only two genders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>21</sup></a> just 20 percent are cross-pressured when it comes to transgender girls’ participation in sports, and that share drops to 13 percent for transgender boys’ participation. Meanwhile, 25 percent support general nondiscrimination laws and bathroom restrictions. These are relatively low rates of cross-pressured responses compared with those who think there are only two genders, regardless of whether they feel strongly about that belief. And among those who feel strongly that there are only two genders, more than half are cross-pressured on these questions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s important to remember that opinions on these issues can be complex — and genuinely cross-pressured. Sometimes people haven’t thought much about how these issues connect — meaning, it does not occur to them that bathroom bills or rules about sports participation could be discriminatory. Other times people have thought about these issues and still believe they are not discriminatory at their core. Either way, opinion on LGBTQ rights — as with everything — is more nuanced and complex than a single general survey question can show.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657624502351361</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: The Supreme Court Episode</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-supreme-court-episode/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Institutions</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Roe V. Wade</category>
			<category>Senate</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-supreme-court-episode/">
	<div data-podcast-id="339404" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: The Supreme Court Episode">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP5384614776.mp3?updated=1657577530">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">This past Supreme Court term featured the sharpest ideological divide in decades, with 21 percent of rulings seeing justices nominated by presidents of one party vote one way and justices nominated by presidents of the other party vote the opposite way. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew analyzes the rightward direction of the court this term and what the majority conservative court could have in store in the future. Then they break down the Democrats’ response and how the party could try to tip the balance of the court or limit the power of the justices.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But first the crew kicks off this SCOTUS-focused podcast by discussing a recent <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/394103/confidence-supreme-court-sinks-historic-low.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup poll</a> that found American confidence in the Supreme Court at a 50-year low. The poll has inspired political commentators to argue that the court is putting its legitimacy in danger by straying too far from national public opinion.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 23:11:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657579501907522</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Jan. 6’s Tangled Web Of Extremism</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/jan-6s-tangled-web-of-extremism/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers， Holly Fuong， Elena Mejía， Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</dc:creator>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<category>Right-wing Extremism</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/right-wing-extremism/" name="">Right-wing Extremism</a></p>
						
													<h1>Jan. 6's Tangled Web Of Extremism</h1>
																	</div>

					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="JAN-6-SOCIAL-NETWORKS-16×9" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/JAN-6-SOCIAL-NETWORKS-16x9-1.png?w=1024" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/JAN-6-SOCIAL-NETWORKS-16x9-1.png?w=1024" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/JAN-6-SOCIAL-NETWORKS-16x9-1.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/JAN-6-SOCIAL-NETWORKS-16x9-1.png?w=2048 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

							<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
									</figcaption></figure></div>

						<div>
				<div>
											<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers, Holly Fuong, Elena Mejía, Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/holly-fuong/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers, Holly Fuong, Elena Mejía, Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/elena-mejia-lutz/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers, Holly Fuong, Elena Mejía, Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/maya-sweedler/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers, Holly Fuong, Elena Mejía, Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/chadwick-matlin/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers, Holly Fuong, Elena Mejía, Maya Sweedler and Chadwick Matlin</a></p>
					<p>Graphics by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/elena-mejia-lutz/" rel="author">Elena Mejía</a></p>
					<p>
						<time>
							Jul. 11, 2022, at 6:00 AM						</time></p>

				</div>
				<div>
									</div> 
			</div>
			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Mike Jensen keeps a database of bad guys. As a senior researcher at the University of Maryland’s National Consortium for the Study of Terrorism and Responses to Terrorism (START), part of Jensen’s job is to identify violent events that occur in the U.S. and investigate whether the people involved have any ties to extremism. If they do, he adds them to his database. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In what he calls a “very active” year, Jensen says he might end up adding 300 individuals to the database. But after the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the U.S. Capitol, Jensen’s database grew dramatically. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We have three times that on one day that potentially qualify,” Jensen said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After the attack on the Capitol, Jensen started putting together a social network consisting of individuals who had been charged in relation to Jan. 6 and had existing ties to extremist organizations. He found many of the defendants had connections to extremist groups prior to Jan. 6, and that these groups were connected to one another. Relationships between defendants and a shared belief in the Big Lie forged new connections between these disparate groups. It’s not that your local Proud Boys chapter is regularly planning a bowling night with the neighborhood sovereign citizens collective. But when a lie about a stolen election aligns with their respective ideologies, they’ll be sure to show up in Washington, D.C., to riot together. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.insider.com/all-the-us-capitol-pro-trump-riot-arrests-charges-names-2021-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">More than 800 individuals</a> have been charged in relation to the Jan. 6 attack. To identify who had existing ties to extremist organizations, Jensen analyzed court filings, news reports and social media posts. He found roughly a third of those charged had preexisting ties to extremist groups<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of June 3, 2022. Jensen identified defendants as having extremist ties if they were a member of, self-identified as a member of, or praised an extremist group. He coded defendants as members if there was evidence that they had gone through a group’s established membership process, such as completing an application or paying dues. He coded defendants as praising or self-identifying with an extremist group if there was insufficient evidence that they had gone through the membership process despite expressing interest in joining; if the group or movement they praised does not have a membership process (like QAnon); or if they promoted the views of (i.e., publicly praised) the group. Public praise included publicly sharing or wearing the signs, symbols or slogans of a group or movement; publicly posting a movement’s ideology while attributing the ideas to said ideology; or sharing photos (including selfies) with group leaders or members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a> and nearly one in five also had verifiable contact with <em>other</em> defendants prior to Jan. 6. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A photo of a defendant on social media sporting a Proud Boys T-shirt (a group that has a formalized membership) wasn’t enough to consider them a member of that group, nor was simply retweeting or liking a post from a member of that group, according to Jensen. He looked for more substantial connections, such as direct messages, posting on each other’s social media pages, or having a conversation in the comments or replies of social media posts.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Jensen’s data reveals a tangled web of individuals with connections to other defendants, as well as to a number of extremist groups including the Proud Boys (<a href="https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/proud-boys" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a far-right extremist group</a> that is known for street violence and boasting about “Western chauvinism”), the Oath Keepers (a <a href="https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/oath-keepers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far-right anti-government militia</a>) and QAnon, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/qanon-has-become-the-cult-that-cries-wolf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the wide-ranging conspiracy theory</a> alleging that major Democrats and Hollywood figures are part of a secret cabal of Satanic pedophiles. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1410" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1608" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-1-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">These extremist organizations look isolated in the chart above, but it’s only because we’ve removed most of the person-to-person connections. “Normally [these groups] would not get along. You would not have this coalition force. But on Jan. 6, what you saw is this perfect storm that brought together each of those distinct, disparate groups and movements, to act as one cohesive group in engaging in these actions,” said Jon Lewis, a research fellow at the Program on Extremism at George Washington University. Certain ideology — like the unfounded belief that the 2020 election was stolen from former President Donald Trump — can thread together otherwise disparate groups of extremists on the right, and can mobilize members of these groups to act collectively. When this happens, a single extremist organization can reach beyond its small sphere of influence, and it can lead to deadly results, as we saw on Jan. 6. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here’s what it looks like when all the extremist defendants’ connections are visible:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1410" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1666" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-2-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In this database, Jensen has documented over 750 unique connections between defendants and between defendants and various groups. The resulting network is densely filled with connections between national leaders and lesser-known members of extremist groups. To understand how to parse it, let’s consider a couple of examples. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the time of the Jan. 6 attack, Enrique Tarrio was the national leader of the Proud Boys and Stewart Rhodes was the leader of the Oath Keepers. Unsurprisingly, these two individuals are found basically at the center of the web. Both the Proud Boys and the Oath Keepers had a large presence on Jan. 6, and the groups <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/29/us/politics/trump-flynn-stone-jan-6-extremist.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been accused</a> of plotting and coordinating ahead of the attack. Though Tarrio wasn’t at the Capitol on Jan. 6, <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/22053617-tarrio-et-al-superseding-indictment" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he is alleged to have been coordinating</a> the Proud Boys movements from Baltimore, and to have helped plan the attack ahead of time. Both Rhodes and Tarrio were <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/06/06/tarrio-proud-boys-seditious-conpiracy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recently charged with seditious conspiracy</a> (among other charges), a federal charge punishable by up to 20 years in prison. We reached out to Rhodes’s and Tarrio’s lawyers. Rhodes’s lawyer did not respond to a request for comment. Tarrio’s lawyer, Nayib Hassan, called the notion that the Proud Boys and the Oath Keepers were connected a “fictious lie” and referred to a motion filed in the case disputing claims that the two organizations coordinated ahead of the attack. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/happen-jan-hearings-change-minds-85225807</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">In the chart below, you can see how Tarrio and Rhodes link the different points in the web together. Through dozens of other defendants from whom they are separated by one or two degrees, Tarrio and Rhodes connect almost three-quarters of the known extremist organizations that were present on Jan. 6:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1410" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1510" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-3-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">But it’s not only the leaders of national right-wing extremist groups who were heavily connected prior to the attack. Let’s highlight two other individuals: Dominic Pezzola and Charles Donohoe. Both Pezzola — a 45-year-old small business owner from Rochester, New York — and Donohoe — a 34-year-old handyman from the suburbs outside Winston-Salem, North Carolina — were members of the Proud Boys. At the time of the attack, Donohoe was a chapter president in North Carolina, while Pezzola was a somewhat new but active member in New York. Though not national figures, both men were allegedly members of the “Ministry of Self Defense,” or MOSD — a chapter of the Proud Boys’ inner circle that planned national rallies. According to court filings, Donohoe was also a member of the MOSD Leaders Group, a chat group that was allegedly created by Tarrio where members of MOSD planned the Proud Boys participation on Jan. 6. Donohoe also has a connection to QAnon — he <a href="https://www.fayobserver.com/story/news/2020/08/29/fayetteville-downtown-businesses-advised-close-early-before-march/5668323002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">provided security</a> for a QAnon “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/qanons-obsession-with-savethechildren-is-making-it-harder-to-save-kids-from-traffickers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">save the children</a>” rally in Fayetteville, North Carolina, in August 2020.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/latest-jan-hearing-testimony-affect-midterm-elections-86274149</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Largely through their membership in these chat groups, even these lower-level Proud Boys end up deeply integrated into this web. Donohoe has direct contact with six other named defendants, while Pezzola has direct contact with eight others.<a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Including one another. Calculated as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrality#Degree_centrality" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;degree&lt;/a&gt;, which is the number of individuals that Jensen confirmed a person interacted with directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>24</sup></a> While Donohoe has many connections with other groups and quite a few direct connections to other defendants, Pezzola is one of the main links between highly connected defendants and defendants who have relatively few connections.<a data-footnote-id="25" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-25" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Calculated as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betweenness_centrality" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;betweenness centrality&lt;/a&gt;, the number of shortest paths between everyone in the network that includes the person of interest. Betweenness can be interpreted as how many indirect connections exist because a specific person links them together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>25</sup></a> </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1410" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4.png?w=2048 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1530" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/fuong.rogers.J6-SOCIAL-NETWORK-4-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Think of it like a chain of people holding hands. On one end, you have the Proud Boys, and on the other end, you have the Oath Keepers. In the middle of that chain is Pezzola, one of the links connecting the two groups. We reached out to the lawyers for both Pezzola (who has pleaded not guilty) and Donohoe (who has <a href="https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/leader-north-carolina-chapter-proud-boys-pleads-guilty-conspiracy-and-assault-charges-jan-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pleaded guilty</a>). Pezzola’s lawyer did not respond to follow-up requests for an interview. Donohoe’s lawyer, Ira Knight, sent a statement: “Charlie regrets his actions, and is remorseful for the conduct that led to these charges. He has accepted responsibility for his wrongs, and is prepared to accept the consequences.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The attack on the Capitol was the culmination of shared ideology — in this case, the belief in Trump’s false claims of a stolen election — mobilizing disparate groups into action. Soon after the attack on the Capitol, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/03/24/980754255/new-evidence-points-to-coordination-among-extremist-groups-ahead-of-capitol-riot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prosecutors claimed</a> that extremist groups like the Proud Boys and the Oath Keepers had coordinated ahead of Jan. 6. The alleged coordination and the relationships captured in Jensen’s data demonstrate how that shared ideology forged new connections between these groups.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-agree-disagree-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-85543538</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">“It’s really narratives that the bigger, radicalizing, conspiratorial networks can capitalize on at any given moment to facilitate offline organizing,” said Samantha Kutner, a researcher at the Khalifa Ihler Institute, a Sweden-based think tank that focuses on ending extremism worldwide. Kutner has conducted extensive research on the Proud Boys.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Jensen said he has a list of individuals with extremist ties who were at the Capitol on Jan. 6 but aren’t in his database yet because they haven’t been formally charged. If and when that happens, he says the web will only become more entangled. What’s most troubling about this web, he said, is that the kind of ideas that link and can mobilize these groups are becoming more commonplace. He said it’s the popularization of those ideas that should be raising alarm bells, more so than any individual group’s actions or organization.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We’re in an environment right now in this country where we are so politically divided and polarized that almost everything now seems like a mobilizing event,” Jensen said. “I think we’re going to see more of that.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Copy editing by Maya Sweedler. Story editing by Chadwick Matlin.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657534501603260</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Maybe Dobbs Did Change The Race. We’ll Need More Time To Know For Sure.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maybe-dobbs-did-change-the-race-well-need-more-time-to-know-for-sure/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 House Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Generic Ballot</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Maybe Dobbs Did Change The Race. We'll Need More Time To Know For Sure.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jul. 8, 2022, at 8:34 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0708-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0708-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0708-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0708-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0708-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It was a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">slow week of polling over the holiday weekend</a> — happy birthday, USA — and the FiveThirtyEight midterm election forecast hasn’t changed much since we launched it last week. Republicans have <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an 86 percent chance of winning control of the House in November</a> according to the Deluxe version of our model. But the Senate is <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">much closer to a toss-up</a>, with Republicans at a 53 percent chance of a takeover. Both of those numbers are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-are-favored-to-win-the-house-but-not-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pretty much the same as when we launched the model</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But we’ve seen some movement toward Democrats on the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>, which asks voters which party they would support in an election. Democrats now trail Republicans by 1.6 percentage points in the FiveThirtyEight average. That compares with a 2.3-point deficit on June 24, when the Supreme Court <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-argument-for-overturning-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health</a> that it would overturn Roe v. Wade.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why make a huge deal of the difference between 2.3 points and 1.6 points? Well, I’m not making a <em>huge</em> deal of it. But because of the way our polling average is designed, it’s a bigger deal than it might seem at first glance.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The truth is, when you design any sort of model, it’s rarely as simple as just following the data. Rather, you have a lot of choices to make. One of the most important ones is how sensitive a model or an average is to <em>new</em> data. It’s obviously possible to err in either direction. There’s a lot of noise in polling averages, and you don’t want a model that does acrobatics in response to every new poll, especially when it’s still many months out from the election and most voters are thinking more about what kind of meat to grill than about whom to elect to Congress.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But polls can and do change in response to big news, and Roe being overturned — probably the most well-known Supreme Court decision of the past 50 years — is big news.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/political-consequences-overturning-roe-wade-85819633</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Usually, the generic ballot is a noisy measure, and if you know nothing about what’s causing the changes, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/heres-a-new-less-volatile-version-of-our-generic-ballot-tracker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">best empirical strategy is to be quite conservative</a> in updating the average. If the polls move by several points and there’s no real underlying cause, it’s <em>probably</em> just noise.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After all, most people — even most people who vote in congressional elections — are not following the news intensely on a day-to-day basis. Cable news ratings, for instance, reflect a <em>tiny</em> fraction of the American population: The most-watched cable news program is seen by something like <a href="https://www.adweek.com/tvnewser/here-are-the-top-rated-cable-news-shows-for-q2-2022/510090/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1 percent of Americans on a typical night</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, in figuring out whether shifts in a polling average represent signal or noise, the model averages out <em>lots</em> of times when there’s nothing much going on and a <em>few</em> times when there is. The safe bet is usually “probably mostly noise, awaiting more evidence of signal.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/supreme-court-overturns-roe-wade-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-85666091</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But given that we do have a huge story on our hands, let’s do a direct before-and-after comparison. Six pollsters<a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;YouGov has released polls in partnership with both Yahoo News and The Economist, but because of a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gelliottmorris/status/1544674762332557313?s=20&amp;amp;t=svq7hp1sSmWNfnH0sWGzvw" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;technical issue with the YouGov/Economist polls&lt;/a&gt;, we’re using only the Yahoo News version here. Note, however, that the Economist polls have also shown a shift toward Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>24</sup></a> have released generic ballot polls both before and after the Dobbs decision.<a data-footnote-id="25" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-25" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By “after,” we mean that the poll went into the field on June 24 or later, and by “before,” we mean that the poll went into the field between May 15 and June 23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>25</sup></a> All six of those polling firms have shown a shift toward Democrats. On average, Democrats trailed by 1.3 points in the pre-Dobbs version of these polls but led by 1.5 points in the most recent ones, a shift of almost 3 points toward the party.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Since Dobbs, generic ballot polls have shifted toward Democrats</h5>
 <p>Generic ballot polls conducted before and after the Supreme Court’s Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health decision</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.eu070822.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Pollster</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Pre-Dobbs</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Post-Dobbs</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Shift</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Big Village</td>
 <td>D+1</td>
 <td>D+6</td>
 <td>D+5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Rasmussen Reports</td>
 <td>R+8</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Emerson College</td>
 <td>R+3</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>D+1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Harris Poll</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>EVEN</td>
 <td>D+2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>YouGov/Yahoo News</td>
 <td>D+4</td>
 <td>D+7</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Morning Consult/Politico</td>
 <td>EVEN</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Average</td>
 <td>R+1</td>
 <td>D+2</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>“Pre-Dobbs” polls include the pollster’s most recent poll conducted before June 24, and “Post-Dobbs” polls include polls that went into the field on June 24 or later. Pollsters with “Pre-Dobbs” polls conducted before May 15 were excluded.</p>
 <p>For pollsters that released results among both registered voters and all adults, the registered voter version of the poll is used.</p>
 <p>Source: POLLS</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">If this persists, then our generic ballot average — and also our midterm model — will eventually catch up and move toward Democrats. Of course, that might not happen. The change <em>could</em> still be a statistical quirk. Or it could be temporary, an <a href="https://agadjanianpolitics.wordpress.com/2017/07/02/possible-evidence-of-differential-partisan-nonresponse-in-trump-approval-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">artifact of partisan nonresponse bias</a>. That is, if Democrats are more engaged than Republicans by news of the Supreme Court’s decision — and there’s <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/3537982-democrats-more-likely-to-vote-in-midterms-after-abortion-ruling-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">evidence to suggest they are</a> — they may be more likely to respond to polls for some period of time, at least until the next news story takes hold. Then again, if Democrats are more motivated than Republicans to <em>vote</em> by the decision, that could help them in a real way in November, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Bottom line: Most of the time, polling averages are exceptionally useful, but be wary of using them in ways in which they weren’t intended. The FiveThirtyEight generic ballot polling average is designed<em> </em>to be conservative and slow-moving and not really equipped to deal with breaking-news developments.<a data-footnote-id="26" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-26" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-makes-our-new-2020-democratic-primary-polling-averages-different/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;experimented with techniques&lt;/a&gt; in our presidential polling averages that allow them to move rapidly in response to pre-scheduled news events such as conventions and debates, but there’s nothing like that for the generic ballot yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>26</sup></a> That our generic ballot polling average is steady in reaction to the news doesn’t really prove anything either way, then. But because of the Dobbs decision, there may be some electoral upside for Democrats beyond what our model currently shows.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 13:34:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1657287002070015</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
