<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 17:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 17:59:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Why Early Senate And Governor Polls Have Plenty To Tell Us About November</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-early-senate-and-governor-polls-have-plenty-to-tell-us-about-november/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley and Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Governor Polls</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<category>Senate Polls</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
						<h1>Why Early Senate And Governor Polls Have Plenty To Tell Us About November
</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Nathaniel Rakich</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 22, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-22T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Republican Senate candidate Herschel Walker" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1235507155-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1235507155-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1235507155-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1235507155-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Republican Herschel Walker leads Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock in early polls of the 2022 U.S. Senate race in Georgia.													<p>Sean Rayford / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">According to a <a href="https://blueprintpolling.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/BPP-Georgia.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent survey</a> from Blueprint Polling, Republican Herschel Walker is leading Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock 49 percent to 45 percent in Georgia’s 2022 Senate race. According to <a href="https://emersonpolling.reportablenews.com/pr/texas-2022-beto-and-abbott-matchup-likely-in-governor-s-race-ag-paxton-tries-to-avoid-runoff-in-republican-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">another</a> from Emerson College/The Hill/Nexstar, Texas Gov. Greg Abbott, a Republican, leads Democratic challenger Beto O’Rourke 52 percent to 45 percent. And according to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/pollster-ratings/john-zogby-strategies-emi-research-solutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">yet another</a> from John Zogby Strategies/EMI Research Solutions/Unite NY, New York Gov. Kathy Hochul, a Democrat, has 14-to-19-point leads over an array of possible Republican opponents.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These are surely good signs for Walker, Abbott and Hochul … or are they?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These polls, like <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all the others</a> you’ve seen of the 2022 general election so far, were conducted seven months or more before the general election. This means that there is still plenty of time for the trajectory of a race to change — whether due to news events, campaign strategy or shifts in the national environment. But while these polls are still from very early in the election cycle, they’re already pretty useful at this stage — you just have to bear in mind that, like all polls, they come with a margin of error.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s according to our analysis of general election polls for Senate and governor conducted in the first six months of every election year going back to 1998. Using over 2,000 polls, we built polling averages for 261 Senate races and 225 gubernatorial contests that had at least one survey in the first six months, finding that these polls have a fairly strong relationship to the final results in November, as the chart below shows.<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://sphweb.bumc.bu.edu/otlt/mph-modules/bs/bs704_multivariable/bs704_multivariable5.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;correlation between&lt;/a&gt; the Senate polling averages and results was .897, while the correlation between the gubernatorial polling averages and results was .839.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>1</sup></a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1072" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-desktop.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-desktop.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-desktop.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-desktop.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="750" height="1946" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-mobile.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/skelley-rakich.EARLY-SENATE-GOV-POLLS.0322-1-mobile.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">It’s important to note, though, that a “fairly strong relationship” is not the same as “every poll completely nailed the final margin.” Senate polls conducted during the first six months of an election year had a weighted average error of 8.2 percentage points — meaning the average polling margin between the Democratic candidate and Republican candidate was 8.2 points off the actual margin. Gubernatorial polls conducted during this span had a similar weighted average error of 8.6 points. That’s not super precise, but it’s also not much worse than polls conducted in the final three weeks of the 1998-2020 campaigns, which had a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-death-of-polling-is-greatly-exaggerated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">weighted average error of 5.4 points</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Early polls have also tended to “call” races correctly more often than not this far out, though that’s a bit of a quick-and-dirty way to understand polling accuracy. In a weighted average, early Senate polls have identified the eventual winner 76 percent of the time, while early gubernatorial polls have been right 78 percent of the time. This is only marginally worse than polls conducted in the last three weeks of the campaign, which averaged out to 81 percent for the Senate and 83 percent for governor races from 1998 to 2020.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But there’s a catch with the topline numbers for early surveys: Polls that show close races for Senate or governor — those with margins between 0 and 5 points — are essentially coin flips when it comes to being correct in November, as the table shows. The likelihood that polls nailed the eventual winner in races where the candidate has a 5-to-10 point edge or a double-digit lead is much higher, though, at roughly 75 percent and 90 percent of the time, respectively.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Early surveys often miss the mark in close races</h5>
 <p>Weighted average share of polls that correctly identified the winner in the first six months of the election year, by how close the poll showed the race to be, 1998-2021

 </p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley-rakich.early-senate-gov-polls-0322.3"><thead><tr><th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="2">Share of correct calls in races for …</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1">Poll margin</th>
 <th colspan="1">Gov.</th>
 <th colspan="1">Senate</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>0 to 5 points</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">54%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">51%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>5 to 10 points</td>
 <td>76</td>
 <td>73</td>
 </tr><tr><td>10+ points</td>
 <td>91</td>
 <td>92</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Pollsters get half-credit if they showed a tie for the lead and one of the co-leading candidates won.</p>
 <p>Excludes polls sponsored by organizations that operated on behalf of a candidate, party, campaign committee, PAC, super PAC, hybrid PAC, 501(c)(4), 501(c)(5) or 501(c)(6) organization that conducted a large majority of its political activity on behalf of one political party. Also excludes polls of races that featured jungle primaries or where the Democratic and Republican candidates didn’t finish first and second. For relevant races that went to runoffs, we compared non-runoff polls to the general election outcome before the runoff. To avoid giving a more prolific pollster too much influence, polls were weighted by 1 divided by the square root of the number of polls each pollster conducted.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">One more point in early polls’ favor: We found that they did not consistently overestimate either party — i.e., their weighted average bias was not disproportionately skewed toward Democrats or Republicans. Overall, early Senate polls conducted in the first six months of all races from 1998 to 2021 had only a 0.1-point weighted average bias toward Republicans, while early gubernatorial surveys had just a 0.02-point lean toward the GOP.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This doesn’t mean that some <em>individual</em> cycles didn’t have significant biases — only that early polls in those cycles weren’t any more biased than polls later in those cycles. (If you’re a regular FiveThirtyEight reader, you’re probably already familiar with the fact that the late polls overestimated Democrats in both 2016 and 2020; well, it turns out the early polls did, too.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the two tables below, we lay out the weighted average bias, weighted average error and weighted average correct-call percentage for every election cycle since 1998:</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Most govs. are elected in midterms, when bias has varied a lot</h5>
 <p>Weighted average error, bias and share of correct calls in polls of gubernatorial races conducted in the first six months of every election year, since 1998</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley-rakich.early-senate-gov-polls-0322.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1">Cycle</th>
 <th colspan="1">No. of polls</th>
 <th colspan="1">Avg. Error</th>
 <th colspan="1">Avg. Bias</th>
 <th colspan="1">Correct Calls</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1998</td>
 <td>38</td>
 <td>12.8</td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">85%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2000</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>5.7</td>
 <td>D+4.3</td>
 <td>88</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2002</td>
 <td>94</td>
 <td>9.9</td>
 <td>D+0.5</td>
 <td>79</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2004</td>
 <td>14</td>
 <td>8.2</td>
 <td>D+2.0</td>
 <td>63</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2006</td>
 <td>193</td>
 <td>10.2</td>
 <td>R+5.2</td>
 <td>82</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2008</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>5.6</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>88</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2010</td>
 <td>213</td>
 <td>7.0</td>
 <td>R+0.3</td>
 <td>80</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2012</td>
 <td>30</td>
 <td>8.0</td>
 <td>R+2.1</td>
 <td>60</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2014</td>
 <td>160</td>
 <td>9.1</td>
 <td>D+6.9</td>
 <td>73</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2016</td>
 <td>24</td>
 <td>4.5</td>
 <td>D+2.5</td>
 <td>77</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2018</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>6.0</td>
 <td>R+1.4</td>
 <td>84</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2020</td>
 <td>27</td>
 <td>8.9</td>
 <td>D+7.4</td>
 <td>100</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1998-2021</td>
 <td>994</td>
 <td>8.6</td>
 <td>R+0.02</td>
 <td>78</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Pollsters get half-credit if they showed a tie for the lead and one of the co-leading candidates won.</p>
 <p>Excludes polls sponsored by organizations that operate on behalf of a candidate, party, campaign committee, PAC, super PAC, hybrid PAC, 501(c)(4), 501(c)(5) or 501(c)(6) organization that conducts a large majority of its political activity on behalf of one political party. Also excludes polls of races that featured jungle primaries or where the Democratic and Republican candidates didn’t finish first and second. For relevant races that went to runoffs, we compared non-runoff polls to the general election outcome before the runoff. To avoid giving a more prolific pollster too much influence, polls were weighted by one divided by the square root of the number of polls each pollster conducted.</p>
 <p>Relevant off-year gubernatorial elections from 2003 to 2021 were included in the overall analysis, but those cycles are excluded from the table due to small sample sizes. Data from 1999 and 2001 was unavailable. A total of 91 early polls were conducted in those 10 odd-year cycles.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>

<div>
<section><header><h5>Most govs. are elected in midterms, when bias has varied a lot</h5>
 <p>Weighted average error, bias and share of correct calls in polls of gubernatorial races conducted in the first six months of every election year, since 1998</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley-rakich.early-senate-gov-polls-0322.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1">Cycle</th>
 <th colspan="1">No. of polls</th>
 <th colspan="1">Avg. Error</th>
 <th colspan="1">Avg. Bias</th>
 <th colspan="1">Correct Calls</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1998</td>
 <td>38</td>
 <td>12.8</td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">85%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2000</td>
 <td>8</td>
 <td>5.7</td>
 <td>D+4.3</td>
 <td>88</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2002</td>
 <td>94</td>
 <td>9.9</td>
 <td>D+0.5</td>
 <td>79</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2004</td>
 <td>14</td>
 <td>8.2</td>
 <td>D+2.0</td>
 <td>63</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2006</td>
 <td>193</td>
 <td>10.2</td>
 <td>R+5.2</td>
 <td>82</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2008</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>5.6</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>88</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2010</td>
 <td>213</td>
 <td>7.0</td>
 <td>R+0.3</td>
 <td>80</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2012</td>
 <td>30</td>
 <td>8.0</td>
 <td>R+2.1</td>
 <td>60</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2014</td>
 <td>160</td>
 <td>9.1</td>
 <td>D+6.9</td>
 <td>73</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2016</td>
 <td>24</td>
 <td>4.5</td>
 <td>D+2.5</td>
 <td>77</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2018</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>6.0</td>
 <td>R+1.4</td>
 <td>84</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2020</td>
 <td>27</td>
 <td>8.9</td>
 <td>D+7.4</td>
 <td>100</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1998-2021</td>
 <td>994</td>
 <td>8.6</td>
 <td>R+0.02</td>
 <td>78</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Pollsters get half-credit if they showed a tie for the lead and one of the co-leading candidates won.</p>
 <p>Excludes polls sponsored by organizations that operate on behalf of a candidate, party, campaign committee, PAC, super PAC, hybrid PAC, 501(c)(4), 501(c)(5) or 501(c)(6) organization that conducts a large majority of its political activity on behalf of one political party. Also excludes polls of races that featured jungle primaries or where the Democratic and Republican candidates didn’t finish first and second. For relevant races that went to runoffs, we compared non-runoff polls to the general election outcome before the runoff. To avoid giving a more prolific pollster too much influence, polls were weighted by one divided by the square root of the number of polls each pollster conducted.</p>
 <p>Relevant off-year gubernatorial elections from 2003 to 2021 were included in the overall analysis, but those cycles are excluded from the table due to small sample sizes. Data from 1999 and 2001 was unavailable. A total of 91 early polls were conducted in those 10 odd-year cycles.</p>
 <p>Source: Polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But good luck guessing the direction of the bias of early 2022 polls. True, in the last four cycles, early Senate polls have been about 3 to 6 points too good for Democrats. But in three of the four cycles before that, early Senate polls had overestimated Republicans — and early gubernatorial polls overestimated Republicans in 2018, too. Moreover, as the 2018 cycle showed, one set of polls could be skewed toward one party, while surveys for another office could end up biased toward the other party. Though the 2022 electoral environment <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is shaping up</a> to be <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">advantageous for the GOP</a>, just how accurately the polls gauge races remains to be seen. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Looking ahead to the 2022 election, though, there are still some takeaways for us based on our analysis of early polls in previous cycles. For instance, there’s not much we can say about Georgia’s Senate race, as Walker leads Warnock by about 2 points, on average; we found in previous cycles that when a candidate led by 0 to 5 points, the accuracy of polls was essentially a coin flip. We likely have a better sense of the ultimate outcome in Texas’s governor’s race, though, as Abbott currently leads O’Rourke by about 6 points, on average, which has historically given candidates a 3-in-4 shot at winning. Finally, in New York’s gubernatorial contest, we don’t know for sure whom each party will nominate, but assuming the apparent frontrunners do meet in November — Hochul and GOP Rep. Lee Zeldin — the early polls definitely point toward a Hochul victory, as she leads Zeldin by about 13 points, which is the sort of advantage that historically has signaled a candidate has a 9-in-10 chance of victory.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So can you trust the polls this far out? Sure you can, but be careful about how you interpret them. Polls are not a precise measurement of where a race will end up, even in the final days of an election. That said, they’re pretty telling, even many months before the general election.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647944101631080</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Ketanji Brown Jackson’s Nomination May Not Be Enough To Turn Out Black Voters For Democrats</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ketanji-brown-jacksons-nomination-may-not-be-enough-to-turn-out-black-voters-for-democrats/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>Black Voters</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Ketanji Brown Jackson</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>Supreme Court Nominees</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/black-voters/" name="">Black Voters</a></p>
						
						<h1>Ketanji Brown Jackson’s Nomination May Not Be Enough To Turn Out Black Voters For Democrats</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Alex Samuels</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 22, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-22T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="President Biden Announces Nomination Of Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson To Serve As Associate Justice Of Supreme Court" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238757597-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238757597-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238757597-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238757597-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Al Drago / Bloomberg / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">It was a promise Joe Biden made during a low point in his presidential campaign, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/joe-biden-suffers-huge-2020-loss-in-new-hampshire-primary-2020-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after he lost both</a> the Iowa caucus and the New Hampshire primary. Just <a href="https://apnews.com/article/stephen-breyer-joe-biden-us-supreme-court-campaign-2016-south-carolina-3a36206929862d7c06293a5724eff2fd" data-type="URL" data-id="https://apnews.com/article/stephen-breyer-joe-biden-us-supreme-court-campaign-2016-south-carolina-3a36206929862d7c06293a5724eff2fd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">days before the South Carolina primary</a>, when Black voters would <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2020/3/1/21160030/biden-black-vote-south-carolina-results" target="_blank" rel="noopener">effectively hand him</a> the Democratic nomination, Biden said at the end of a debate that if he were elected, he would nominate the first Black woman to the U.S. Supreme Court.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s a promise that some Republicans have since <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/law/2022/feb/20/ted-cruz-biden-promise-black-woman-supreme-court" target="_blank" rel="noopener">derided as discriminatory</a> or <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/supreme-court/gop-sen-wicker-compares-biden-s-supreme-court-pledge-affirmative-n1288211" target="_blank" rel="noopener">akin to affirmative action</a>, but the president’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nomination of Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson</a> to fill the seat of retiring Justice Stephen Breyer, is the one notable promise to Black voters — perhaps the only one — that Biden has managed to uphold. And according to political science research and experts I spoke to, this promise of appointing the nation’s first Black woman to the Supreme Court <em>is</em> important to Black voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In February, political scientists <a href="https://profiles.rice.edu/faculty/jaclyn-kaslovsky" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jaclyn Kaslovsky</a> of Rice University and <a href="https://www.andrewrstone.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Andrew R. Stone</a> of Washington University in St. Louis published a piece in <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/02/15/biden-supreme-court-nominee-black/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Washington Post</a> about their research showing that Black Americans place a high value on what’s called “descriptive representation.” In other words, having someone who looks like them in a position of power — particularly in the judiciary — is very important to Black Americans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Kaslovsky told me one reason why Black Americans may want more Black people in positions of power is that they’ve been historically underrepresented in politics. “There’s research arguing that group consciousness matters for how people evaluate political institutions,” she said. “So, as Black Americans become more represented in the judiciary, they may feel like their voices are legitimated by that institution.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Jackson’s confirmation process comes at an important time, too, as Black Americans have soured on Biden in the past six months, according to a FiveThirtyEight analysis of presidential approval polls going back to October. But while it’s possible that Jackson’s nomination offers the president a lifeline with Black voters, who overwhelmingly want to see her confirmed, there are also many reasons why Biden’s nomination of Jackson won’t be enough. Although research shows that a diverse judiciary is important to some Black voters, it’s unlikely that Jackson’s nomination will erase <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-democrats-failure-to-pass-a-voting-rights-bill-fits-a-pattern-of-failing-voters-of-color/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden’s longstanding problem</a> of failing to address and implement policies that would benefit <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2019/03/07/african-americans-are-the-democrats-most-loyal-constituency" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats’ most loyal base</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Biden dropped the ball on so many things, and not just things that people hoped for or expected he’d do, but promises he made to the American public, like <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/12/07/1062070001/student-loan-forgiveness-debt-president-biden-campaign-promise" target="_blank" rel="noopener">restructuring student loan debt</a> or <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2021/03/11/fact-sheet-president-biden-to-announce-all-americans-to-be-eligible-for-vaccinations-by-may-1-puts-the-nation-on-a-path-to-get-closer-to-normal-by-july-4th/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">managing the pandemic better</a> or <a href="https://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/biden-promise-tracker/promise/1583/offer-8000-tax-credit-child-care/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">implementing the child tax credit</a>,” said <a href="https://liberalarts.utexas.edu/sociology/faculty/rlr3462" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Robert L. Reece</a>, a professor of sociology at the University of Texas at Austin. “I’d bet that type of stuff starts to become more and more prominent as the election becomes closer, especially given that Jackson’s nomination has less of an immediate impact on people’s lives.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s working in Biden’s favor is that polls suggest that Black voters <em>really </em>want<em> </em>Jackson to make it through the nomination process and that her appointment is motivating them ahead of what’s expected to be a grueling midterm cycle for Democrats. While surveys on midterm enthusiasm among Black Americans are generally sparse, at least one survey from <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/09/black-voters-midterms-ketanji-brown-jackson-survey/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult/Politico</a> shows that Black voters became more enthusiastic for the midterm elections in late February — right around the time Biden <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/kbj/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">made Jackson’s nomination public</a>. Other polls similarly show Black Americans’ eagerness to get Jackson through the nomination process. According to <a href="https://navigatorresearch.org/most-americans-support-judge-kentanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-to-the-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Navigator Research</a>, 89 percent of Democratic voters and 88 percent of Black voters said they trusted Biden’s judgment on who should be the next Supreme Court justice. In fact, among all races and ethnic groups, Black voters were the most likely to say they would support the Senate’s confirmation of Jackson, at 71 percent; only 11 percent of Black voters said they would oppose the confirmation, for a net support of 60 percentage points. Asian American and Pacific Islander voters had the second-highest level of support for Jackson’s confirmation: 58 percent would support her confirmation, for a net support of 51 points. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But enthusiasm for Biden’s Supreme Court pick hasn’t translated to support for Biden himself so far. In fact, disillusionment with his administration has increased in the past six months. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1036" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="750" height="1282" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1m.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1m.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1m.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.KBJ-BLACK-VOTERS.0322-1m.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Of course, Biden’s approval ratings started to nose-dive last summer, as my colleague Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and I <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-have-been-souring-on-biden-since-last-summer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported in February</a>, but they are more fluid now, as he got a slight bump in the past several weeks. Still, Biden’s approval is down overall, and the dwindling support among Black Americans is particularly notable given that this <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/02/08/black-voters-helped-biden-get-elected-his-presidency-will-be-defined-by-how-he-acts-racial-equity/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bloc helped clinch</a> the presidency for Biden in 2020. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, not only are Biden’s struggles with Black voters now part of a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/one-year-in-bidens-approval-rating-is-in-troubleonly-trumps-was-lower/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">larger trend</a> in his <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abysmal approval ratings</a>, but, according to Reece, other frustrations are likely playing a role, too — for instance, a lack of movement on critical policy concerns like <a href="https://time.com/6051071/george-floyd-biden-police-reform/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">police reform</a>, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/08/01/1023393344/black-leaders-question-whether-biden-will-fulfill-campaign-promises-to-black-vot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voting rights legislation</a>, COVID-19 rates and inflation, which still <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/inflation-is-taking-biggest-toll-on-nonwhite-voters-wsj-poll-shows-11647255601?mod=hp_lead_pos12" target="_blank" rel="noopener">disproportionately affect</a> Black Americans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the short term at least, it’s possible that Jackson’s confirmation — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-racism-and-sexism-could-define-ketanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-hearings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">assuming it goes through smoothly</a> — will galvanize some Black voters. But, Reece warned me, if this is the <em>only </em>thing the Biden administration is banking on to court the Black vote, it’s probably not going to be enough. “People need tangible things. Not just symbolic representation to get out and vote, especially in the midterms,” he said. “Not only do <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2014/07/24/voter-turnout-always-drops-off-for-midterm-elections-but-why/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less people typically vote</a>, but <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/do-republicans-really-have-a-big-turnout-advantage-in-midterms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans tend to vote</a> in higher shares.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, while the historic nature of Jackson’s nomination shouldn’t be dismissed, the Biden administration should not discount the fact that appointments and platitudes alone may not be enough to persuade Black voters to turn out in droves this year the same way <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/large-racial-turnout-gap-persisted-2020-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they did in 2020</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats have long struggled with engaging Black voters, though, and this is a symptom of a larger problem, as former FiveThirtyEight senior writer Farai Chideya <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/black-voters-are-so-loyal-that-their-issues-get-ignored/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">explained ahead of the 2016 presidential election</a>. Because Black Americans reliably vote Democratic, they are treated somewhat as a “captured” voting bloc: That is, they’re often ignored by Republicans but taken for granted by Democrats. As a consequence, Democrats in power, including Biden and current members of Congress, tend to not address or prioritize many of the policy concerns Black communities have.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, Jackson’s nomination is pretty far away from the midterms, and there’s still plenty of time for voters to either forget Biden took this step or<em> </em>warm up to him before November. As the Morning Consult/Politico poll shows, along with tracking polls from <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/trackers/president-biden-job-approval-rating?crossBreak=black" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov</a>, Biden’s standing among Black Americans has the potential to rebound. But, as Reece told me, “Biden will have to rely on something else to motivate Black people come November. I’m not sure if Jackson’s nomination will be the thing that gets people out of their seats for a midterm election.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647944101631079</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: The Most Consequential Governor’s Races</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-most-consequential-governors-races/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Daylight Saving Time</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Virginia Governor</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-most-consequential-governors-races/">
	<div data-podcast-id="329709" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: The Most Consequential Governor's Races">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6375111248.mp3?updated=1647903654">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Thirty-six governors’ seats are up for election in November. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew looks at the states where full control of the government may be decided by these races. They also assess whether narratives from the 2021 Virginia gubernatorial election hold up in light of <a href="https://insights.targetsmart.com/did-education-sway-the-va-election-maybe-but-probably-not.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new data</a> and debate the hottest legislative topic in Washington: making daylight saving time permanent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647903601523310</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How White Victimhood Fuels Republican Politics</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-white-victimhood-fuels-republican-politics/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels and Neil Lewis Jr.</dc:creator>
			<category>Political Science</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<category>Race</category>
			<category>Race and Ethnicity</category>
			<category>Race Relations</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/race-and-ethnicity/" name="">Race and Ethnicity</a></p>
						
						<h1>How White Victimhood Fuels Republican Politics</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Alex Samuels and Neil Lewis Jr.</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/neil-lewis-jr/" title="" rel="author">Alex Samuels and Neil Lewis Jr.</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 21, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-21T17:19:09+00:00">1:19 PM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="A woman sits at a school board meeting with a sign against the teaching of Critical Race Theory" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1236621187-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1236621187-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1236621187-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1236621187-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Robert Gauthier / Los Angeles Times via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">On Nov. 4, 2008, Barack Obama, then <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/05/us/politics/05campaign.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a senator from Illinois</a>, was elected the first Black president of the United States. His election was seen as a hopeful moment in America and <a href="https://www.americanbar.org/groups/crsj/publications/human_rights_magazine_home/human_rights_vol36_2009/fall2009/on_celebrating_an_election_as_racial_progress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ushered</a> in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/05/us/politics/05elect.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lots</a> of <a href="https://www.forbes.com/2008/12/30/end-of-racism-oped-cx_jm_1230mcwhorter.html?sh=267378f349f8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">think pieces</a> and <a href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/opinion-la/la-oe-steele5-2008nov05-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reporting</a> that his presidency was the start of a new “post-racial” society. At long last — in the eyes of many, at least — there was hope that the racial wounds that have long divided Black and white Americans would heal.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That, of course, never happened. Even at the time, <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2008/08/racism-is-the-only-reason-obama-might-lose.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">certain white voters</a> refused to vote for Obama because of his race, and a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-obama-hatecrimes/election-of-obama-provokes-rise-in-u-s-hate-crimes-idUSTRE4AN81U20081124" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rise in hate crimes</a> followed his win. Moreover, in the lead up to Obama’s first election, some <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/images/PollingUnit/1065a4RaceandPolitics.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls showed that</a> only about one-third of white Americans (38 percent) thought Obama would help race relations, compared with 60 percent of Black Americans. Moreover, a plurality of white Americans thought (or, perhaps, hoped) that his candidacy would have no impact on race relations, essentially upholding the status quo. What’s more, some white voters during this period <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/rise-white-identity-politics-didn-t-start-trump-explains-michael-ncna926191" target="_blank" rel="noopener">started to become resentful</a> of a Black man ascending to the highest political office. And <a href="https://www.niskanencenter.org/how-racial-stereotypes-impacted-voting-for-obama-and-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that backlash</a>, in part, spurred the election of former President Donald Trump eight years later. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump’s election killed any illusions anyone might have had about a “post-racial” America. Indeed, Trump was successful in finding a predominately white audience who lapped up his overt racism toward people of color and who were eager to embrace a rising sense of <a href="https://theconversation.com/trump-tapped-into-white-victimhood-leaving-fertile-ground-for-white-supremacists-150587" target="_blank" rel="noopener">white victimhood</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump may be out of power, but those feelings aren’t. They may even be growing. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With President Biden having just passed one full year in office, public opinion research shows that white Americans — and especially Republicans — see whites as victims of discrimination more than, say, Hispanic or Black Americans. According to a 2021 survey by the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/03/18/majorities-of-americans-see-at-least-some-discrimination-against-black-hispanic-and-asian-people-in-the-u-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a>, for example, only 17 percent of Republican and Republican-leaning Americans said there is “a lot” of discrimination against Black people in today’s society. That number rose to 26 percent when Republicans were asked whether they believed <em>white</em> people faced “a lot” of discrimination. And intense <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/white-backlash-is-a-type-of-racial-reckoning-too/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">white racial resentment</a> remains present both among Trump’s base and in our politics today. Case in point: Trump, who’s a (<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/a-majority-of-republican-voters-actively-want-trump-to-run-for-president-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">very, very early</a>) favorite to win the 2024 Republican presidential nomination, is still hitting that same drum; during a recent political event, the former president went so far as to <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/arizona-rally-trump-claims-covid-19-treatment-is-anti-white-people-2022-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">falsely claim</a> that white people were currently being discriminated against and sent to the “back of the line” when it came to receiving COVID-19 vaccines and treatment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump is not the first white person to feel like a victim of discrimination or to make claims in that spirit. This phenomenon started long before him. But in the U.S., if we look at things like the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-many-americans-dont-see-the-racial-wealth-gap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racial wealth gap</a>, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2022-wells-fargo-black-home-loan-refinancing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mortgage denial rates</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-fewer-black-americans-are-getting-the-covid-19-vaccine-no-its-not-hesitancy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID-19 vaccination and illness rates</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-black-women-are-often-missing-from-conversations-about-police-violence/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">police violence rates</a> or myriad other data sets, we quickly see plenty of systemic biases against Black Americans and other minority groups (such as increasing <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/asian-america/anti-asian-hate-crimes-increased-339-percent-nationwide-last-year-repo-rcna14282" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hate crimes against Asian Americans</a>). You can’t, however, find such widespread evidence for anti-white discrimination. So why have many white Americans started to see themselves<em> </em>as the victims of racial discrimination?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Back in 2011, Harvard Business School professor <a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/profile.aspx?facId=326229" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Michael Norton</a> and Tufts University professor <a href="https://as.tufts.edu/psychology/people/faculty/samuel-sommers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Samuel Sommers</a> published <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1745691611406922" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a study</a> showing that white Americans perceived bias against whites as increasing from the 1950s to the 2000s. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to Sommers, it’s hard to pinpoint just <em>one </em>factor driving this feeling of white victimhood among white Americans. “There’s this sense that there’s only so much of anything to go around, so more of something for other groups or entities might mean less of something for me and my group,” he told us. “That makes a lot of sense when you’re talking about food at the table in front of you, but it feels like it’s getting applied to things like equal rights — or respect and status.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These feelings <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2008/08/racism-is-the-only-reason-obama-might-lose.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were especially prevalent in the late 2000s</a>, when white people saw a Black man rising to the nation’s highest office. But today, beyond Obama, other perceived “threats” to white Americans — such as an increasingly <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/who-the-census-misses/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">multiracial nation</a> that could eventually lead to the U.S. becoming <a href="https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2017/1/26/14340542/white-fear-trump-psychology-minority-majority" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a “majority-minority” society</a>, or<a href="https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2017/1/26/14340542/white-fear-trump-psychology-minority-majority" target="_blank" rel="noopener"></a> <a href="https://theconversation.com/trump-tapped-into-white-victimhood-leaving-fertile-ground-for-white-supremacists-150587" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s loss in 2020 to Biden</a> — likely fueled existing beliefs and feelings of inadequacy and victimhood among white Americans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The same is likely true of the discussions about “racial reckonings” following the murder of George Floyd, coupled with a few high-profile examples of Black people breaking barriers. Indeed, <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2016/06/27/on-views-of-race-and-inequality-blacks-and-whites-are-worlds-apart/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previous polling</a> has documented that white Americans — and especially white Republicans — largely think too much attention is paid to race and racial issues. And, as we wrote about in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-helped-build-the-social-safety-net-why-are-many-now-against-expanding-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our last article</a>, there are additional concerns about racial minorities getting more than they deserve. Kamala Harris’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/kamala-harris-biden-vice-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ascendance to the vice presidency</a> as well as the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nomination of U.S. Circuit Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson</a> to replace retiring Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer, for example, likely further stoked white Americans’ existing hatred against Black people and other marginalized groups. To use the language of Ohio State University professor <a href="https://english.osu.edu/people/mitchell.717" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Koritha Mitchell</a>, “Black success beckons the mob.” There is a phenomenon Mitchell calls “<a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/715439" target="_blank" rel="noopener">know-your-place aggression</a>” whereby U.S. culture celebrates the success of straight white men (regardless of their merit) but discourages, diminishes or destroys the achievements of members of other groups. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This phenomenon is related to one of the other things Sommers told us about:<strong> </strong>jockeying for stigma. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Maybe that’s a more general human phenomenon that transcends race and racism,” Sommers said, “but now we’re talking about it on a much more serious and problematic level.” When white Americans see minorities succeed, it threatens them in a way that makes them feel like victims. As Sommers puts it: “It seems like there’s some kind of status, attention or special treatment that certain white people think will be bestowed on them if they make the claim that they’ve been treated unfairly.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, for a “post-racial” America to exist, white people would need to see people of color ascending to higher political offices and an increasingly multiracial nation as a win for <em>all </em>of America. Instead, many take these things as a personal attack and view it as a loss of their <em>own</em> status at the top of America’s racial hierarchy. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We see evidence for this in public opinion data, too. With the help of Kathleen Weldon and Jacob Harris of the <a href="https://ropercenter.cornell.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Roper Center for Public Opinion Research</a> — a research center that has one of the largest archives of public opinion datasets (and where one of us, Neil Lewis Jr., is a faculty affiliate) — and Natalie Jackson from the <a href="https://www.prri.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Public Religion Research Institute</a> (PRRI), we looked at perceptions of discrimination against white Americans over time, and how those perceptions vary by both partisanship and race.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since at least the year 2000, polling firms have been asking Americans questions about how much discrimination they perceive is faced by white Americans, asking respondents to place that discrimination on a scale or to compare it to other racial and ethnic groups. And our analysis of the Roper Center’s data shows that before Obama’s first election, roughly half of Republicans perceived there to be at least some discrimination against white people. Specifically, according to a 2000 poll from Princeton Survey Research Associates/The National Conference for Community and Justice, 56 percent of Republicans said that white Americans faced at least some discrimination, and by 2005, when the organizations asked the question again, that number dipped slightly to 47 percent. However, toward the end of Obama’s first term, other polling found the share of Republicans answering a similar question to be higher, as can be seen for the years 2011 and 2012 on the chart below, which uses data from PRRI.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">PRRI has asked a slightly different question — to what extent respondents agree that discrimination against white Americans is now as significant of an issue as discrimination against Black Americans and other minorities — almost yearly between 2011 and 2020. The trend across that timespan is a bit messier, but the share of Republicans who “completely agreed” or “mostly agreed” with the statement was mostly higher during Trump’s time in office than during Obama’s. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="877" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-desktop@2x_EDIT.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-desktop@2x_EDIT.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-desktop@2x_EDIT.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-desktop@2x_EDIT.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="621" height="1146" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-mobile@2x_EDIT.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-mobile@2x_EDIT.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-mobile@2x_EDIT.png?w=621 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-1-mobile@2x_EDIT.png?w=1242 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">It is noteworthy that Democrats saw things quite differently than Republicans — indeed the clearest trend in the chart above is the polarization of views on this question along party lines. The percentage of Democrats who say there is at least “some” discrimination against whites has steadily decreased since the turn of the century, and this trend is consistent across both Roper and PRRI datasets. These trends are also consistent with new research that builds on Norton and Sommers’s initial work. In a <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/e6dar/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">forthcoming paper</a> in the journal <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/home/pps" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Perspectives on Psychological Science</a><em>, </em>a team of researchers from Tufts, Harvard and the VA Bedford Healthcare System found that race and partisanship shape perceptions of racism as a zero-sum game. “Liberal White Americans saw racism as a zero-sum game they were winning by a lot, moderate White Americans saw it as a game they were winning by only a little,” the researchers wrote, “and conservative White Americans saw it as a game they were losing.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, race and partisanship are intertwined: The <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-republican-choice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vast majority of Republicans are white</a>, and indeed, if we look at the same question by race, we see similar patterns:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="864" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-race-hires.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-race-hires.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-race-hires.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-race-hires.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="621" height="1089" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-2-mobile@2x.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-2-mobile@2x.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-2-mobile@2x.png?w=621 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Samuels.Lewis-WHITE-RACISM-VICTIMS.0318-2-mobile@2x.png?w=1242 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Worryingly, these trends may be <em>increasing </em>after Biden’s inauguration. PRRI didn’t ask the same question again in 2021, so we can’t make an apples-to-apples comparison there. But according to Pew’s 2021 survey, the share of Republicans — including “leaners,” i.e., Americans leaning toward one party or the other — who said there is at least “some” discrimination against white people was 63 percent. This includes 26 percent who said there is “a lot” of discrimination against white people, which <em>looks</em> like an all-time high. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We say “looks” because the polling data we have is messy. If we compare the Pew data to past Pew data (so that the methodology and question wording is consistent), we see an increase from <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/11/01/democrats-far-more-likely-than-republicans-to-see-discrimination-against-blacks-not-whites/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2019</a> (16 percent) to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/03/18/majorities-of-americans-see-at-least-some-discrimination-against-black-hispanic-and-asian-people-in-the-u-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2021</a> (26 percent) for the share of Republicans saying white Americans face “a lot” of discrimination. Those are only two data points, of course. We’ll need more polling to know how to interpret that result for sure.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, other recent polls have yielded similar findings with different questions. <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/articles/project-home-fire-center-for-politics-research-reveals-outsized-role-immigration-plays-in-fueling-our-national-divide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sabato’s Crystal Ball</a>, using a summer 2021 poll conducted by Project Home Fire and InnovateMR, found that only 38 percent of Trump voters either somewhat or strongly agreed that white people have advantages over people of color (compared with 87 percent of Biden voters). Moreover, 84 percent of Trump voters expressed concern that bigotry against white people will surge in the coming years. Meanwhile, only 38 percent of Biden voters felt the same way.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s striking is how these perceptions persist even in the face of extraordinary evidence to the contrary. We have already discussed some domestic evidence about the persistence of racial discrimination against minority groups. Additionally, on the international stage, we see anti-Black racism manifesting even during a war: Journalists <a href="https://twitter.com/Sifill_LDF/status/1498512483690102784?s=20&amp;t=MeCWB6dPrSMtQuc56eZcpA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">monitoring the invasion in Ukraine</a> have reported that <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/nbcblk/open-door-die-africans-report-racism-hostility-trying-flee-ukraine-rcna17953" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Black people are being violently removed</a> from <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/juliareinstein/african-students-racism-ukraine-invasion" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trains trying to get people to safety</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What could be fueling an increase in these views? Following Trump’s loss in 2020, the Republican Party leaned further into messages that paint Republicans and white people as victims of an overzealous movement for racial justice. For example, Fox News coverage of critical race theory — a decades-old framework for legal scholarship — surged during the Virginia gubernatorial campaign, according to a <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/fox-news-critical-race-theory-glenn-youngkin-1650208" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Newsweek analysis</a>, only to quickly and starkly dip following Republican Glenn Youngkin’s win. And several pundits pointed to education and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/04/opinion/crt-backlash-du-bois.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">critical race theory</a> as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-virginias-electorate-shifted-toward-republicans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reasons for his success</a>. Republicans have also<em> </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-attacking-cancel-culture-and-woke-people-is-becoming-the-gops-new-political-strategy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found a seemingly successful political strategy</a> in attacking and amplifying race-related buzzwords, such as “woke,” once used in activist circles. And as FiveThirtyEight contributors Hakeem Jefferson and Victor Ray pointed out on the anniversary of the Jan. 6 insurrection at the Capitol, the current narratives of victimization and the associated backlash to racial progress are some white people’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/white-backlash-is-a-type-of-racial-reckoning-too/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">way of reckoning</a> with the changing times. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Sommers underscored the gravity of leadership’s role in these processes when we talked with him: “If we’ve learned nothing else in the last five or so years, it’s just how influential top-down attitudes are. When leaders around the country and at a regional level are using racist or vulgar language themselves, that seems to move the needle on what’s considered normative and acceptable behavior in our society.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If we want to address the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-reminded-us-of-just-how-unequal-america-is/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">inequities that continue to plague and divide our society</a>, white Americans — and in particular, white Republicans — will need to move away from the victimhood narrative and acknowledge our current reality. And the extent that the inequities can be muted or even mitigated depends heavily on what politicians choose to emphasize in the narratives that they construct about the state of our union. The success of minorities does not mean victimization for white Americans. Without recognition that we can all succeed — and that the nation will be better off for it — the patterns of disparities we have discussed throughout will continue to persist, and we will all be worse off for it.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 17:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647894601578725</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What To Expect From Ketanji Brown Jackson’s Confirmation Hearings</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-to-expect-from-ketanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-hearings/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Ketanji Brown Jackson</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/supreme-court/" name="">Supreme Court</a></p>
						
						<h1>What To Expect From Ketanji Brown Jackson’s Confirmation Hearings</h1>

													<h2>Note: We probably won’t learn much.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 21, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-21T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Supreme Court Nominee Ketanji Brown Jackson Meets With Senators On Capitol Hill" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1383496687-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1383496687-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1383496687-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1383496687-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Anna Moneymaker / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Here we go again. For the fourth time in five years, the strange rituals of the Supreme Court confirmation process have overtaken the Capitol. In the weeks since U.S. Circuit Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/kbj/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was formally named</a> as President Joe Biden’s nominee to fill a soon-to-be-vacant spot on the high court, she has been <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/03/02/ketanji-brown-jackson-senators-confirmation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paying courtesy visits</a> to the senators who will vote on her confirmation. Now she’s made it through the gauntlet of private chitchat and is heading into an onslaught of public questions, none of which anyone really expects her to answer.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Supreme Court confirmation hearings have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/kavanaugh-was-quietly-conservative-on-day-2-of-his-hearing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a predictable rhythm</a>, and this one doesn’t look like it will be an exception. Jackson will face a several-day barrage of broad and complex questions about her background, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democrats-were-willing-to-break-the-rules-on-kavanaugh-day-3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">her philosophy as a judge</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-battle-lines-are-set-after-the-first-day-of-the-amy-coney-barrett-hearings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">her stance on hot-button issues</a>. Democrats will grandstand and lob her softballs. Republicans will grandstand and try to paint her as a radical. Jackson will smile and offer a series of polite nonanswers. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These hearings feel like they should be consequential — after all, Jackson is up for a lifetime seat on the country’s most powerful court. But the process of confirming a Supreme Court justice has mostly become just another partisan performance. Barring a last-minute surprise, the outcome is already sealed, and everyone knows it. Democrats have the votes, so Jackson is almost certain to be confirmed within a matter of weeks. Her presence on the court — while historic — won’t do anything to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-roberts-court-vs-the-trump-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">change its conservative tilt</a>. The main question is whether a Republican or two, sensing a low-cost opportunity to make a gesture toward bipartisan harmony, will cross the aisle to vote for her. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As I said, strange rituals.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The task of confirming would-be justices wasn’t always so drawn out, or so political. Early in the nation’s history, it might only take a couple of days for a Supreme Court nominee to be confirmed once they were named by the president. As the Supreme Court has grown more powerful and high-profile, the process has gotten longer and talkier. Since the mid-20th century, when the high court began to wade deeper into contentious battles over civil rights, the length of time between a justice being nominated and confirmed <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/02/07/up-until-the-postwar-era-u-s-supreme-court-confirmations-usually-were-routine-business/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has grown dramatically</a>, in large part because of the addition of public hearings. Jackson’s confirmation process may end up looking short compared to other modern justices, but that’s only because it’s taken months for many recent justices to be confirmed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Senators have also grown more eager to publicly weigh in on nominees’ qualifications. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/supreme-court-confirmation-hearings-have-more-questions-and-fewer-answers-than-ever-before/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to a FiveThirtyEight analysis from 2018</a>, the number of issues that were covered during the hearings has increased in recent years too, with a special focus on topics that have gotten more politically important, like civil rights and judicial philosophy. But that doesn’t mean nominees are sharing more about their actual views on the issues voters care about — in fact, when they’re asked about issues that could come before the Supreme Court in the future, they <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/classroom/2020/10/why-do-supreme-court-nominees-avoid-answering-so-many-questions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">routinely refuse to say anything</a>. “He has responded to many questions over the course of these hearings but he has adequately answered far too few of them,” <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/15/weekinreview/alito-vs-roberts-word-by-word.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Patrick Leahy complained</a> after three days of back-and-forth with now-Justice Samuel Alito.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/14/ketanji-brown-jackson-supreme-court-confirmation-00016594" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans have promised</a> Jackson a “respectful” back-and-forth. Whether that actually happens, of course, remains to be seen. It might not seem worthwhile to turn these hearings into a partisan bloodbath — after all, Jackson’s nomination won’t shift the ideological balance of the court, which will retain a 6-3 conservative majority. But <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-racism-and-sexism-could-define-ketanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-hearings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as I wrote earlier this month</a>, it’s possible that racist or sexist lines of questioning could filter into the hearings in subtle or explicit ways, and raise the temperature of the interrogations. Jackson is pretty popular overall, which makes this strategy risky — <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/03/08161506/2203034_crosstabs_POLITICO_RVs_v1_SH.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several</a> <a href="https://s.wsj.net/public/resources/documents/WSJPOLL032022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent</a> <a href="https://navigatorresearch.org/most-americans-support-judge-kentanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-to-the-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls</a> have found that about half of Americans want the Senate to confirm her to the Supreme Court, and only around 30 percent are opposed to her confirmation. (The rest said they didn’t know.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are certain aspects of Jackson’s background that the senators seem likely to linger on. Her supporters will highlight the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/25/politics/supreme-court-ketanji-brown-jackson/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historic nature of her nomination</a>, as the first Black woman and <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2022/03/15/ketanji-brown-jackson-would-first-federal-defender-supreme-court/9424483002/?gnt-cfr=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public defender</a> to be tapped for the Supreme Court. They’ll also emphasize her impeccable qualifications. On the other hand, her detractors are likely to seize on her career as a public defender as evidence that her ideology is too extreme, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/16/us/politics/ketanji-brown-jackson-criminal-defense.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">particularly on issues like crime</a>. Republican Sen. Josh Hawley previewed a potential line of attack in a Twitter thread last week where <a href="https://twitter.com/HawleyMO/status/1504221927665250305?s=20&amp;t=tXLuj3W9RcrHOhdCJGAi7Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he claimed</a> that Jackson had a “pattern of letting child porn offenders off the hook.” The Republican National Committee, meanwhile, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/16/us/politics/ketanji-brown-jackson-criminal-defense.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">criticized her work</a> representing detainees at Guantánamo Bay.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And depending on their mood, other Republican senators may argue that she has the wrong qualifications for the job — in the past few weeks, conservatives have implied both that she’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2022/mar/04/tucker-carlson-ketanji-brown-jackson-lsat-scores-credentials" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not qualified</a> and that she’s <a href="https://twitter.com/LindseyGrahamSC/status/1497218325394374709?s=20&amp;t=ClLfsxf5qWp63pX_i52eaQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">too qualified</a>. Alternatively, opponents may hone in on the cases where her decisions as a trial court judge were reversed by higher courts. That line of attack might not be very fruitful, though; According to an analysis of Jackson’s record as a trial court judge by law professors Josh Fischman and Kevin Cope, her reversal rate is low, like most of the other judges in the District of D.C. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These hearings, then, are really about politics, not Jackson herself. We already have a pretty good idea of where Jackson would land, and Republicans are unlikely to ferret out anything new. Over the years, as control of the Supreme Court has become an increasingly high-stakes political issue, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/bidens-supreme-court-pick-thrills-progressives-looking-win-rcna17429" target="_blank" rel="noopener">advocacy groups</a> have <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/15/us/politics/severinos-amy-coney-barrett.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pushed presidents</a> to nominate justices who are <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2018/07/09/david-souter-the-supreme-court-justice-who-built-the-trump-court-218953/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ideologically predictable</a>. Jackson is no exception. It’s true that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">based on the empirical metrics we have</a>, it’s not clear exactly where she’d fall on the court’s left wing, but she would almost certainly be a reliable liberal vote.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For that reason, Jackson will be lucky to get even a sliver of bipartisan support. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-harder-than-ever-to-confirm-a-supreme-court-justice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">As my colleague Geoffrey Skelley wrote in February</a>, successful Supreme Court nominees used to get the overwhelming support of senators in both parties, but those days have been over for a while. All of Trump’s nominees were confirmed with very narrow margins. Jackson <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/senate/595822-the-three-republicans-who-voted-to-confirm-brown-jackson-for-appeals-court" target="_blank" rel="noopener">did get three Republican votes</a> when she was nominated to the D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals last year — but there’s no guarantee those senators will remain on her side now that a Supreme Court seat is up for grabs.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But unless a moderate Democrat unexpectedly defects, which seems unlikely right now, Jackson’s path to the Supreme Court looks smooth. Occasionally, big and important issues do come up that pose a real threat to the nominee’s confirmation — <a href="https://www.npr.org/2018/09/27/652309743/christine-blasey-ford-describes-alleged-sexual-assault-by-kavanaugh-before-senat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the allegations that Justice Brett Kavanaugh attempted to rape a woman in high school</a> are a notable recent example. For the most part, though, Supreme Court confirmation hearings have become very similar to other televised congressional spectacles — an opportunity for senators to advertise their own ideological sentiments in viral soundbites. This time, the fact that control of the court isn’t at stake isn’t likely to stop senators from seizing the spotlight, and it certainly won’t speed the hearings along. At worst, that could mean the next few days descend into ugly race-baiting rhetoric — and at best, it could make the process feel pretty empty.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647858601095854</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Do Americans Really Want Permanent Daylight Saving Time?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/do-americans-really-want-permanent-daylight-saving-time/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Daylight Saving Time</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>State Legislatures</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" name="">Pollapalooza</a></p>
						
						<h1>Do Americans Really Want Permanent Daylight Saving Time?</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Jean Yi</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/jean-yi/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Jean Yi</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 18, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-18T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0318_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/0318_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/0318_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/0318_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/0318_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY FIVETHIRTYEIGHT / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Congress can’t agree on much lately — except, apparently, their hatred of changing the clocks twice a year. On Tuesday, just after Americans set their clocks an hour forward over the weekend, the Senate <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/15/us/politics/daylight-saving-time-senate.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unanimously passed a bill</a> that would make daylight saving time permanent (although they still have to send it to the House for consideration). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Supporters of the bill presented it as a gift for a groggy country struggling to get its sleep back on track. And it’s true that the annual clock-changing ritual is not especially popular. A <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_031522/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monmouth University poll</a> conducted March 10-14 found that only 35 percent of Americans wanted to keep resetting their clocks every fall and spring, while a <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/03/16/1742a/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> conducted March 16 found that 59 percent of Americans wanted to see daylight saving time made permanent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, putting the whole country on daylight saving time year-round seems like a no-brainer. But we’ve been there before, and it’s still unclear whether Americans would actually like permanent daylight saving time if they got it. Because while longer afternoons and a consistent schedule are appealing, there’s a tradeoff — dark winter mornings.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the past four years, support for making daylight saving time permanent has really gained steam, and not just in Congress. According to the <a href="https://www.ncsl.org/research/transportation/daylight-savings-time-state-legislation.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Conference of State Legislatures</a>, 18 states have passed legislation or enacted resolutions that would switch to permanent daylight saving time if Congress allowed it (and in some cases, if surrounding states also made the change).</p>


<div><iframe title="More than a third of states want DST year-round" aria-label="Map" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/zADPk/6/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="640" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, federal law doesn’t currently allow for permanent daylight saving time, so Congress has to take the lead, which is why the bill that just passed is a big step for proponents of daylight saving time.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Originally, daylight saving time was implemented during World War I as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/14/climate/daylight-saving-time-electricity.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a way to conserve energy</a>. The idea was that changing the clocks during the months with the most sunlight would encourage people to use less electricity. That <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/11/01/1050492391/daylight-saving-time-history-what-you-need-to-know" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doesn’t seem to be the case</a>, though. Instead, the real winners of daylight saving time are <a href="https://www.convenience.org/Media/Daily/2022/Mar/14/1-Daylight-Saving-Time-Is-Good-for-Business_GR" target="_blank" rel="noopener">businesses</a>, since people are <a href="https://www.wnycstudios.org/podcasts/takeaway/segments/who-really-benefits-daylight-savings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to go out and shop</a> when they have an extra hour or two of sunlight after work. So, a switch to permanent daylight saving time would be <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/11/01/1050492391/daylight-saving-time-history-what-you-need-to-know" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a boon</a> for lots of industries — especially those for outdoor activities like sports and gardening.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What everyday people actually want, though, isn’t as clear. Polling shows that people generally don’t like the disruption of gaining or losing an hour twice a year, although their feelings might not be as strong as politicians make it out to be. In an <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/xtubiu759r/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economist/YouGov poll</a> conducted days before the clocks changed in November, for instance, only 21 percent of Americans said they were looking forward to the end of daylight saving time coming up, while 34 percent said they weren’t looking forward to it; 38 percent said they didn’t care. But there was more consensus on the concept of changing the clocks than on the solution: Among the 63 percent of people who wanted to eliminate the practice of gaining or losing an hour, 48 percent said they wanted permanent daylight saving time, 29 percent said they wanted permanent standard time and 21 percent had no preference.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Older Americans, it turns out, are also much more likely than younger Americans to dislike the time changes. The Economist/YouGov poll found that an overwhelming majority of respondents 65 and over (77 percent) wanted to eliminate the twice-yearly time change compared with less than half of respondents age 18 to 29 (42 percent). To be clear, those younger people aren’t strongly in favor of keeping the clock change: They were just about as likely to say they didn't want to change the clocks (27 percent) as they were to say they weren't sure (31 percent). But they were also less in favor of permanent daylight saving time than older people were, by 30 percent to 54 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This division could hint at one of the big reasons why people really don’t like changing the clocks: It can be physically disruptive. Messing with sleep patterns can affect our <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/daylight-savings-shows-how-your-metabolism-works-on-a-clock" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eating habits</a> or <a href="https://utswmed.org/medblog/daylight-saving-time-sleep-health/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mental functioning</a> throughout the day. And an abrupt shift like adding or losing an hour can be especially troublesome for <a href="https://www.agingcare.com/articles/daylight-saving-time-health-156410.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">older people</a>, who may already have more fragmented sleep. It can also upset bedtimes and nap routines for <a href="https://www.happiestbaby.com/blogs/parents/daylight-saving-time-sleep-schedule" target="_blank" rel="noopener">small children</a>, and even <a href="https://mashable.com/article/pets-dogs-cats-daylight-savings-time" target="_blank" rel="noopener">make pets fussy</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But in exchange for later sunsets, people have to be OK with dark mornings. And that’s not a universally popular tradeoff. Americans actually experimented with permanent daylight saving time starting in January 1974, and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/03/15/no-more-changing-clocks-history-says-be-careful-what-you-wish-daylight-saving-time/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it didn’t go well</a>. As reported in The Washington Post, support for year-round daylight saving time fell from a majority in late 1973 to around 30 percent in February and March 1974. According to Louis Harris polling that March, people were much more likely to say the change was a bad idea (43 percent) than a good one (19 percent). Parents who found themselves sending their children to school on pitch-black, cold winter mornings were particularly upset.<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The experiment ended that fall, when the &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1974/10/01/archives/senate-votes-return-to-standard-time-for-four-months-and-sends-bill.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Senate agreed&lt;/a&gt; to scrap permanent daylight saving time and &lt;a href="https://www.fordlibrarymuseum.gov/library/document/0055/1668702.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;President Gerald Ford signed&lt;/a&gt; the bill into law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>2</sup></a> But anyone who wakes up on the early side — <a href="https://www.edisonresearch.com/wake-me-up-series-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">which many Americans do</a> — might also dislike slogging through an extra hour of darkness as they begin their day. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/get-ready-to-spring-forward-into-daylight-saving-time-and-longer-days/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sleep scientists</a> have argued that permanent standard time is <a href="https://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2022/03/12/daylight-saving-time-spring-forward-fall-back-change-clocks-sleep-science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more in sync</a> with our body’s natural rhythms. We might like an extra hour of light at the end of the day, their argument goes, but we <em>need</em> that extra hour of morning light. And regional differences play a role, too. It’s probably no coincidence that one of permanent daylight saving time’s biggest boosters is Florida Sen. Marco Rubio, since states farther south <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/@3558773?month=1&amp;year=2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aren’t running the risk</a> of a 9 a.m. sunrise, even at the darkest times of year. But <a href="https://www.wxyz.com/news/what-would-happen-if-michigan-kept-daylight-saving-time-all-year" target="_blank" rel="noopener">northern states</a>, and states on the <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/nation/how-daylight-saving-time-poses-a-host-of-health-concerns-according-to-a-neurologist#:~:text=The%20%E2%80%9Cwestern%20edge%E2%80%9D%20effect,edge%20of%20a%20time%20zone." target="_blank" rel="noopener">western edges of time zones</a>, would face longer stretches of morning darkness.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Another possibility, of course, is to stop putting all the weight of adjusting to the seasons onto the clocks and instead tweak our own schedules to gradually move the start time of our day. But that’s harder to legislate, so we’re left with some pretty unsatisfying options. We can keep dealing with the hassle of changing the clocks — or we can accept that, for a few months at least, we’ll either start or end our days in the dark. Which would you choose?</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-economic-impact/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-economic-impact/">Lower-income workers, in particular, have faced difficulties during the omicron surge</a> of the coronavirus, according to a Feb. 9-21 poll from the Kaiser Family Foundation. In the KFF COVID-19 Vaccine Monitor, 60 percent of workers living in a household making less than $40,000 annually said they had missed work in the past three months due to concerns over COVID-19, versus 33 percent of workers whose households earned between $40,000 and $89,999 annually and 43 percent of workers whose households made $90,000 or more annually. Moreover, just 32 percent of workers in lower-income households received paid time off if they got sick from COVID-19, compared with 57 percent of workers in households making $40,000 or more per year. Because these lower-income workers lack paid time off, a greater share came to work sick — 29 percent of workers in households making less than $40,000 annually said they went to work while symptomatic or after exposure to COVID-19 because they couldn’t afford to take time off; just 6 percent of workers in households making $40,000 or more said they had to do the same.</li></ul><ul><li>The <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/15/f1-fandom-netflix/">share of Americans who call themselves fans of a motorsport has revved up</a> in the past two years, according to polls from Morning Consult conducted Feb. 20-23, 2020, and March 5-7, 2022. While NASCAR still had the greatest share of fans, at 40 percent, Formula 1 saw its fan base increase the most (from 21 percent in 2020 to 28 percent in 2022), though MotoGP’s increase was a close second, at 6 percentage points. NASCAR, IndyCar and NHRA all gained fans, too, though by a more modest amount. The Netflix documentary series “Formula 1: Drive to Survive,” which chronicles the <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/how-drive-to-survive-remade-formula-1">annual struggle for the Formula One World Championship</a>, seems to be driving this boost in popularity. More than half of self-identified Formula 1 fans in the U.S. (53 percent) said the show, which <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2021/10/formula-1-drive-to-survive/619814/">developed a cult following</a> since its debut in 2019, was a major or minor reason why they became a fan.</li></ul><ul><li><a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/03/14/most-climate-scientists-expect-catastrophe">Climate scientists sound far more pessimistic than the American public</a> about the consequences of climate change, according to a September 2021 survey by Nature that polled authors and review editors of the latest report by the U.N.’s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change and a March 10-13 U.S. News Poll of American adults by YouGov that asked the same questions. For example, while just 25 percent of Americans said they thought they would see catastrophic impacts of climate change in their lifetimes, 66 percent of the climate scientists who responded to the Nature survey said the same. Meanwhile, just 35 percent of Americans said they felt anxiety, grief or other distress due to concerns about climate change, versus 61 percent of the experts polled. That said, as to whether climate-related concerns might overrule one’s desire to have children, climate scientists were roughly in line with the general public, even though research has found that having one fewer child is <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2017/jul/12/want-to-fight-climate-change-have-fewer-children">the most effective thing you can do to reduce your carbon footprint</a>. Just 17 percent of the climate scientists who answered the question said global warming has made them reconsider having children, versus 18 percent of the general public.</li></ul><ul><li>According to a March 3-7 poll from Navigator, <a href="https://navigatorresearch.org/most-americans-support-judge-kentanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-to-the-court/">President Biden and the Democratic Party have an edge over the GOP</a> when it comes to which party Americans trust more to “put the right people on the Supreme Court.” Forty-six percent of registered voters said they trusted Biden and the Democrats more, while 39 percent said they trusted Republicans more. A slight majority (51 percent) of voters said they would support the Senate confirming Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson, including 73 percent of voters who said they were familiar with her, while 27 percent of all voters were undecided and 22 percent opposed the confirmation.</li></ul><ul><li><a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/03/15/public-expresses-mixed-views-of-u-s-response-to-russias-invasion-of-ukraine/">Democrats and Republicans are largely united</a> on U.S. economic and military strategy toward Russia, but they seem more divided on accepting Ukrainian refugees, according to a March 7-13 poll from the Pew Research Center. For instance, Pew found that an overwhelming majority of Democrats (88 percent) and Republicans (85 percent) supported “keeping strict economic sanctions on Russia,” while just over a third (35 percent of Democrats, 36 percent of Republicans) supported “taking military action even if it risks a nuclear conflict with Russia.” But the parties sharply diverged when asked about “admitting thousands of Ukrainian refugees into the U.S.” — 80 percent of Democrats supported this policy versus 57 percent of Republicans, a 23-point gap.</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> 42.2 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 52.9 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.7 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-war-in-ukraine-might-change-putins-popularity-among-russians/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.5 percent approved and 51.6 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -9.1 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 41.4 percent and a disapproval rating of 53.0 percent, for a net approval rating of -11.6 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 2.2 percentage points (44.8 percent to 42.7 percent). <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-war-in-ukraine-might-change-putins-popularity-among-russians/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A week ago</a>, Republicans led Democrats by 2.1 points (44.8 percent to 42.7 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 2.1 points (44.8 percent to 42.6 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647602101643196</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What Is Ron DeSantis’s Vision For The GOP?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-is-ron-desantiss-vision-for-the-gop/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Florida</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Ron DeSantis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-is-ron-desantiss-vision-for-the-gop/">
	<div data-podcast-id="328744" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What Is Ron DeSantis's Vision For The GOP?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP5945696587.mp3?updated=1647553015">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">The conventional wisdom is that if former President Donald Trump wants the GOP presidential nomination in 2024, it’s his. But some Republicans are still jockeying for position to be the next leader of the party, the most prominent of which may be Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis. He is considered to be in the political mold of Trump, just more disciplined. And this week DeSantis closed out a state legislative session full of conservative culture-war priorities that may well be geared toward a national audience. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Galen Druke speaks with Florida reporters <a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/profile/244900712" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ana Ceballos</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/staff/matt-dixon" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.politico.com/staff/matt-dixon" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matt Dixon</a> about where DeSantis falls ideologically, how he’s shaped state politics and how he could shape the Republican Party.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 21:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647557101439379</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How This Redistricting Cycle Failed To Increase Representation For People Of Color — And Could Even Set It Back</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-this-redistricting-cycle-failed-to-increase-representation-for-people-of-color-and-could-even-set-it-back/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Black Voters</category>
			<category>Latino Voters</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/redistricting/" name="">Redistricting</a></p>
						
						<h1>How This Redistricting Cycle Failed To Increase Representation For People Of Color — And Could Even Set It Back

</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 17, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-17T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="A woman walks to a polling station to cast her ballot in the Texas 2022 primary election" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238867262-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238867262-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238867262-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GettyImages-1238867262-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Nick Wagner / Xinhua via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">It may get the most attention, but partisanship is not the only way to measure how fair <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the country’s new congressional maps</a> are. Equally important is how well they represent communities of color. And on this front, the congressional lines that will be used in the 2022 election leave a lot to be desired.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In theory, under the <a href="https://www.justice.gov/crt/section-2-voting-rights-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Voting Rights Act</a>, every racial group must be given equal opportunity to elect candidates of their choice. When it comes to <a href="http://www.publicmapping.org/what-is-redistricting/redistricting-criteria-the-voting-rights-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">redistricting</a>, this means drawing districts where nonwhite voters are the dominant voting bloc — enough to reasonably ensure they can elect their preferred candidate — <a href="https://www.justice.gov/crt/case-document/file/1429826/download" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whenever possible</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But this interpretation of the Voting Rights Act has been under siege lately by conservatives who believe it is <a href="https://electionlawblog.org/?p=127399" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unconstitutional</a>. And with the current conservative makeup of the U.S. Supreme Court, Republican legislatures have shown a willingness to push the boundaries of the law, minimizing the number of nonwhite districts (which usually vote Democratic) in order to maximize the number of Republican ones. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To complicate matters further, there is no agreed-upon standard for how diverse a district needs to be in order to elect a minority’s preferred candidate; even those who support the broader goal of more nonwhite representation often disagree. (For example, if Black voters constitute a majority of the primary electorate in a heavily Democratic district, that district could still elect Black voters’ candidate of choice even if Black voters are a minority of the district as a whole.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In practice, this means states often end up drawing fewer predominantly nonwhite districts than are possible. Just look at the most recent redistricting cycle’s report card. On the one hand, nonwhite Americans — namely Latinos — did gain clout in some states, but they lost it in others. And most importantly, racial minorities didn’t gain representation in several states where they easily could have.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s start with a positive development for nonwhite representation: Several new predominantly Hispanic congressional seats were created this redistricting cycle. (This makes sense, given that the Hispanic population of the U.S. increased by at least 11.6 million people between the <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0100000US&amp;y=2010&amp;tid=DECENNIALPLNAT2010.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2010</a> and <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0100000US&amp;y=2020&amp;tid=DECENNIALPL2020.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020</a> censuses, accounting for more than 51 percent of the country’s growth on net during that period — and the fact that <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/03/10/1083732104/2020-census-accuracy-undercount-overcount-data-quality" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Latinos were undercounted</a> could mean they accounted for even more.) For example, the voting-age population<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I.e., the population age 18 or older. All district demographics for the remainder of the article are based on VAP rather than total population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> of Illinois’s 3rd District, which was previously 58 percent white and 31 percent Hispanic, is now 44 percent Hispanic and 43 percent white, giving the Chicago area two seats now where Latinos are the biggest racial group.<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this article, we’re considering Hispanic or Latino ethnicity to be a race to make an apples-to-apples comparison with white, Black and Asian American populations. As a result, the terms “white,” “Black” and “Asian American” on their own refer specifically to non-Hispanic white, non-Hispanic Black and non-Hispanic Asian American.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But by far the biggest source of new Hispanic seats was California, whose redistricting commission appeared to <a href="https://twitter.com/Redistrict/status/1472965510748950534?s=20&amp;t=DSLVdnDj8Z1iY88M-MNzNg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">go out of its way</a> to create new opportunities for the state’s <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0400000US06&amp;y=2020&amp;tid=DECENNIALPL2020.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largest racial group</a>. California’s old congressional map had 13 districts where Latinos constituted a majority of the VAP; the new one has 18 (despite the fact that California lost a seat overall due to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reapportionment</a>!). This was accomplished by spreading the state’s Hispanic population more evenly among districts.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>California added several majority-Hispanic districts</h5>
 <p>Districts where Latino Americans make up a majority of the voting-age population under California’s new congressional map, including the change in Latino population between the old and new districts</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.redistricting-poc.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="2"><b>Old District</b></th>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="2"><b>New District</b></th>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="1">Hispanic VAP</th>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="1">Hispanic VAP</th>
 <th colspan="1">Change</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CA-19</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">36%</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-18</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">61%</td>
 <td>+25</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-10</td>
 <td>41</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-13</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>+20</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-36</td>
 <td>45</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-25</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td>+15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-37</td>
 <td>35</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-37</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>+15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-43</td>
 <td>44</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-43</td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>+10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-31</td>
 <td>51</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-33</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>+8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-34</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-34</td>
 <td>62</td>
 <td>+6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-16</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-21</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-41</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-39</td>
 <td>59</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-46</td>
 <td>62</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-46</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-32</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-31</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-38</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-38</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-29</td>
 <td>63</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-29</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-21</td>
 <td>72</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-22</td>
 <td>69</td>
 <td>-3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-35</td>
 <td>67</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-35</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>-6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-44</td>
 <td>68</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-44</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>-10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-51</td>
 <td>68</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-52</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>-11</td>
 </tr><tr><td>CA-40</td>
 <td>86</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>CA-42</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>-25</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Bolded districts have new Hispanic majorities. Old and new district numbers do not match because many districts in California were renumbered; new districts are paired with the old district that they most closely resemble.</p>
 <p>Sources: U.S. Census Bureau, The Upshot, Voting Election and Science Team, Ryne Rohla/Decision Desk HQ</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">True, Latinos were already a <em>plurality</em> of the VAP in most of the districts that have become majority Hispanic (all but the new 13th District), but in many cases the shift was still meaningful. For example, Latinos were 36 percent of the VAP in the old 19th District, but Asian Americans and whites were not far behind at 31 percent and 26 percent, respectively. In other words, Latinos were hardly guaranteed to get their preferred representative. However, the new version of this seat (renumbered the 18th District) is now 61 percent Hispanic, giving Latino Americans a much better shot at electing the candidate of their choice. It’s a similar story in the new 25th, 37th and 43rd districts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That was the extent of the gains, however. On the flip side, there are also several districts where the ability of nonwhite people — especially Black people — to elect the candidate of their choice has been thrown into question. For example, the two districts covering Detroit (Michigan’s 13th and 14th districts) were each formerly 53 percent Black by VAP. But their successors (renumbered the 12th and 13th districts, respectively) are significantly less so. The 13th District is 45 percent Black and 40 percent white, while the 12th District is 47 percent white and just 44 percent Black. While it’s still possible that these districts will elect Black voters’ preferred candidates, it’s less likely than it was before. (In fact, voting-rights advocates filed a lawsuit over the map earlier this year for this very reason, but <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/news/local/michigan/detroit/2022/02/03/michigan-supreme-court-upholds-redistricting-commission-maps/9226313002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it was dismissed</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Something similar happened with Georgia’s 2nd District and North Carolina’s 1st District. These districts, which have historically elected Black candidates, got ever so slightly less Black (Georgia’s 2nd went from 49 percent Black and 41 percent white to 48 percent Black and 43 percent white; North Carolina’s 1st went from 48 percent white and 41 percent Black to 50 percent white and 40 percent Black). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This may not seem like a big deal, but because voting in the South is so polarized by race, this was enough to make each district a few percentage points more Republican; Georgia’s 2nd went from a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> of D+6 to D+4, while North Carolina’s 1st went from a partisan lean of D+7 to D+5. In other words, they are competitive enough that it’s possible that Republicans will win them in 2022, which is already shaping up to be a good midterm environment for the GOP. If so, these districts will have failed to elect Black voters’ preferred candidate for the first time in decades.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Latinos weren’t immune from being squeezed by redistricting, either. For example, Nevada’s 1st District used to have a Hispanic plurality (41 percent, vs. 32 percent white). But Democrats redrew <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada’s congressional map</a> to maximize the number of seats they would win, which required “unpacking” the 1st District and its Hispanic community. As a result, the new 1st District is 44 percent white and only 32 percent Hispanic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The worst news for nonwhite representation this cycle, however, was the progress that was not made. In several states, people of color did not gain electoral control of seats that have historically been denied to them or that they were arguably entitled to because of population growth.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Texas is the canonical example of the latter. The Lone Star State grew by 4 million people between the <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0400000US48&amp;y=2010&amp;tid=DECENNIALPLNAT2010.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2010</a> and <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0400000US48&amp;y=2020&amp;tid=DECENNIALPL2020.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020</a> censuses — earning the state two more congressional districts — and <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/08/12/texas-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">95 percent of that growth was, on net, due to people of color</a>. However, the state went from 18 majority-minority districts to … 18 majority-minority districts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s more, Latinos alone accounted for almost half of the state’s net growth, yet the number of districts with a Latino majority or plurality actually decreased from 12 to 11. Rather than gaining congressional districts of their own, <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/12/13/latinos-texas-redistricting-dallas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">burgeoning nonwhite communities in places like Dallas</a> were <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/10/15/texas-redistricting-dallas-fort-worth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">carved up and parceled out to predominantly white, rural districts</a> in order to protect Republican incumbents from the forces of demographic change.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Similarly, people of color made up 68 percent of Colorado’s growth, on net, between the <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0400000US08&amp;y=2010&amp;tid=DECENNIALPLNAT2010.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2010</a> and <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?t=Hispanic%20or%20Latino&amp;g=0400000US08&amp;y=2020&amp;tid=DECENNIALPL2020.P2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020</a> censuses, and many advocates were hoping that this would finally be the year that Colorado <a href="https://apnews.com/article/entertainment-denver-colorado-redistricting-race-and-ethnicity-f70b53cc580c16c3ab3014ece268a22b" target="_blank" rel="noopener">drew a predominantly Latino district</a>. It didn’t happen, however: The state’s least white district (the new 8th District) is 56 percent white and only 35 percent Hispanic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, in the South, Black people have <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2015/7/15/1383616/-Nearly-every-Southern-state-could-have-drawn-another-congressional-seat-that-would-elect-a-minority" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long been underrepresented in the House</a>, and their situation did not improve during this round of redistricting. In Arkansas, Democrats <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/arkansas/hb1962/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">proposed a map</a> that would have made the 2nd District 53 percent white and 37 percent Black, which might have been enough to elect Black voters’ preferred candidate. Similarly, Georgia Democrats <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/georgia/dem_proposal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">proposed a map</a> that would have turned the 10th District into a 41 percent Black, 39 percent white seat closer to Atlanta. Neither map, however, passed the states’ Republican-controlled legislatures, and the Arkansas 2nd that ended up passing is 69 percent white and 19 percent Black, while the Georgia 10th is 66 percent white and 21 percent Black.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Arkansas and Georgia maps are currently subject to <a href="https://arktimes.com/arkansas-blog/2022/03/07/federal-suit-challenges-arkansas-congressional-districts-over-racial-gerrymandering-of-2nd-district" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racial-gerrymandering</a> <a href="https://www.gpb.org/news/2021/12/31/lawsuits-claim-georgias-redistricting-maps-ignore-black-population-growth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lawsuits</a>, but they’re unlikely to be overturned given what transpired in voting-rights advocates’ legal quest to add another Black seat in Alabama. After Alabama passed a congressional map that, like its old one, featured six majority-white seats and only one majority-Black seat, advocates sued, arguing that the Voting Rights Act required the state to have two Black districts. (Remember, the act theoretically requires states to draw districts where nonwhite voters are the dominant voting bloc whenever possible — and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/plaintiffs_plan_a/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">maps</a> drawn by the plaintiffs <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/plaintiffs_plan_b/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">showed</a> that such a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/plaintiffs_plan_c/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">configuration</a> was <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/plaintiffs_plan_d/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">indeed very possible</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A panel of three federal judges <a href="https://www.montgomeryadvertiser.com/story/news/2022/01/24/alabama-congressional-map-blocked-federal-court/9205925002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">agreed</a>, but after Alabama appealed their ruling, the U.S. Supreme Court <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/07/1078292766/supreme-court-lets-alabama-use-gop-backed-map-of-the-states-congressional-distri" target="_blank" rel="noopener">determined</a> it was too close to the 2022 election for the map to be overturned. This extinguished hopes not only that Black Alabamians would gain another seat in Congress, but also that courts would pave the way for drawing <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-court-ruling-in-alabama-could-boost-black-political-power-throughout-the-south/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">additional Black districts in states like Louisiana and South Carolina</a>, which, like Alabama, each have only one majority-Black seat but could support one more.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Supreme Court will issue a final decision on the Alabama case as part of its 2022-23 term, but given the court’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">history of weakening the Voting Rights Act</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/01/24/1003049852/supreme-court-adds-affirmative-action-to-its-potential-hit-list" target="_blank" rel="noopener">willingness to consider other challenges to civil-rights policies</a>, it is unlikely to err on the side of more nonwhite representation. More likely, it will change the historical interpretation of the Voting Rights Act and water down the act’s protections of minority districts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In this way, the legacy of this redistricting cycle for people of color could be even worse than not giving them more representation; it could undermine the very law designed to ensure their enfranchisement.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647512100974377</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Is Biden’s Approval Rating Really Rebounding?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-bidens-approval-rating-really-rebounding/</link>
						<dc:creator>Sarah Frostenson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</dc:creator>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>Slack Chat</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/presidential-approval/" name="">Presidential Approval</a></p>
						
						<h1>Is Biden’s Approval Rating Really Rebounding?

</h1>

											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p><span>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</span></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>Mar. 16, 2022</time>,
								at
								<time title="2022-03-16T10:00:00+00:00">6:00 AM</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="SlackChat_0316-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/SlackChat_0316-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/SlackChat_0316-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/SlackChat_0316-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/SlackChat_0316-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
						
		</figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/slack-chat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politics chat</a>. The transcript below has been lightly edited.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/sarah-frostenson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah Frostenson</a>, politics editor): In the last two weeks or so, President Biden’s approval rating has ticked up from 41.1 percent to 42.9 percent, according to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s presidential approval tracker</a>.<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> The share of Americans who disapprove of the job he’s doing has ticked down, too, from 53.6 percent to 52.3 percent.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2046" height="904" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.02.09-PM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.02.09-PM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.02.09-PM.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.02.09-PM.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Historically, State of the Union addresses <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-bidens-first-state-of-the-union-might-not-change-much/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">haven’t moved the needle much</a>, but Biden seems to have benefited at least a little bit from his March 1 address — perhaps in large part because it allowed him to once again address Russia’s ongoing invasion of Ukraine and the U.S.’s response.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard to know whether this current bump will last, but let’s tackle Biden’s approval rating in two parts. First, what do we know about why his approval rating has ticked up? Can we point to certain issues or groups where his standing has improved? Second, how should we think about this uptick? Is it a sign of things turning around for Biden, or is it more of a blip?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">OK, first up, why do we think Biden’s approval rating is inching up?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich</strong> (<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nathaniel Rakich</a>, senior elections analyst): It’s impossible to totally disentangle all the events of the past month or so, but I think the simplest answer (which is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occam%27s_razor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">usually the right one</a>) is the crisis in Ukraine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/polls/npr-pbs-newshour-marist-national-poll-bounce-for-biden-following-state-of-the-union-march-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to Marist/NPR/PBS</a>, Biden’s approval/disapproval spread on the issue of Ukraine shot up from 34/50 in mid-February to 52/44 in early March. His overall approval/disapproval increased from 39/55 to 47/50. And <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/08/biden-approval-improves-state-of-the-union-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to Morning Consult/Politico</a>, his approval/disapproval on Ukraine went from 42/45 in late February to 46/42 in early March. His overall approval/disapproval went from 41/56 to 45/51 over that same span. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a>, senior writer): At the start of the Ukraine crisis, Americans were on board with the steps that Biden was taking but still <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t approve of his handling of the crisis</a>. It now seems, though, that some folks are giving him credit. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Exactly, Amelia. And I think overall media coverage has had more to do with that than the State of the Union. Cable news has <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-care-about-the-invasion-of-ukraine-but-that-doesnt-mean-they-will-rally-around-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">covered the war in Ukraine very intensely</a>. For example, on Feb. 24, the day after Russia started its invasion,<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia actually started to invade early on the morning of Feb. 24 in Ukraine, but it was still late on Feb. 23 in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> <a href="https://api.gdeltproject.org/api/v2/summary/summary?d=iatv&amp;t=summary&amp;k=Ukraine&amp;ts=custom&amp;sdt=20220101000000&amp;edt=20220313235959&amp;fs=station%3ACNN&amp;fs=station%3AFOXNEWS&amp;fs=station%3AMSNBC&amp;fcs=comb&amp;fdn=raw&amp;fdr=day&amp;fdt=-05%3A00&amp;svt=zoom&amp;svts=zoom&amp;swvt=zoom&amp;ssc=yes&amp;sshc=yes&amp;swc=yes&amp;stcl=yes&amp;c=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ukraine was mentioned in 3,095 15-second clips on CNN, Fox News and MSNBC</a>. To put that in perspective, on Election Day 2020, former President Donald Trump was mentioned by name in <a href="https://api.gdeltproject.org/api/v2/summary/summary?d=iatv&amp;t=summary&amp;k=trump&amp;ts=custom&amp;sdt=20201101000000&amp;edt=20201108235959&amp;fs=station%3ACNN&amp;fs=station%3AFOXNEWS&amp;fs=station%3AMSNBC&amp;fcs=comb&amp;fdn=raw&amp;fdr=day&amp;fdt=-05%3A00&amp;svt=zoom&amp;svts=zoom&amp;swvt=zoom&amp;ssc=yes&amp;sshc=yes&amp;swc=yes&amp;stcl=yes&amp;c=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only 2,675 clips</a>.<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ran a search of CNN, Fox News and MSNBC coverage so far this year in the Television News Archive using the GDELT Television API. In that database, daily news footage is split into 15-second clips, and searches return the clips that contain a mention of our search query (“Ukraine”). The cutoff for measuring coverage for any given day is midnight Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a></p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Ukraine is dominating cable news" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nbA1g/9/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="575" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That level of media coverage matters, especially when Americans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generally approve of the actions Biden is taking</a> with regard to Ukraine, and is likely more responsible than the State of the Union address for the uptick we see in his approval rating.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> Although in fairness, Biden <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/01/us/politics/biden-sotu-transcript.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">talked a lot about the war in Ukraine</a> in his State of the Union address, which may have contributed to some of that coverage.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The bigger question for me, though, is who is changing their minds on Biden? Last month, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-have-been-souring-on-biden-since-last-summer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alex<strong> </strong>Samuels and I wrote a story</a> documenting how Biden seemed to have lost his shine among some Democrats starting last summer. If what we're seeing is mostly just Democrats coming back into the fold, that's not as dramatic as a shift among independents (or even — in a crazy world — Republicans!).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geoffrey Skelley</a>, elections analyst): Right, I don't think we have quite enough data yet to declare that it's down to Democrats supporting Biden more, but that would make the most sense. If Biden's approval ticks up further, that's what I'm mainly watching for. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> A recent Morning Consult poll indicated Democrats and independents were driving <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/08/biden-approval-improves-state-of-the-union-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the shift in Biden's approval</a>, but as you said, Geoffrey, it's early days.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> What do we see in the data we have so far? After all, a 2-point bump from March 1 <em>isn't</em> a huge shift.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> No, Sarah, it's not a huge shift, and I think that's reflective of the fact that Biden is facing very real headwinds such as inflation. Americans still say <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/wsj-poll-biden-ukraine-inflation-midterms-11646975533" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the economy is their top — or one of their top — issues</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> It’s really hard to say. Some polls have shown Biden gaining, while others have shown his approval largely unchanged. For instance, CBS News/YouGov put Biden's approval at 44 percent <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/russia-ukraine-biden-state-of-the-union-opinion-poll-2022-02-29/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in late February</a>, and at 43 percent (so basically the same) <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/russia-ukraine-sanctions-gas-prices-opinion-poll-2022-03-13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a week and a half into March</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, Quinnipiac also found his overall approval/disapproval mostly unchanged, <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3835" target="_blank" rel="noopener">from 35/55 in mid-February</a> to <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3838" target="_blank" rel="noopener">38/51 in early March</a>, even as Americans warmed to his handling of Ukraine, which went from 34/54 to 42/45. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> So ... maybe Biden's approval rating isn't rebounding?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> Well, I think it's important to remember that this is happening in the context of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-may-or-may-not-blame-biden-for-higher-gas-prices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a big spike in gas prices</a> — which would normally be terrible news for a president's approval rating.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Our colleague Santul Nerkar wrote in December <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">why inflation is such a powerful political issue</a>, and as you can see in the chart below, inflation often coincides with a sharp drop in a president’s approval </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1538" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214a.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214a.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214a.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214a.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="4604" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214-mobile.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/nerkar.INFLATION.1214-mobile.png?w=1240 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">So even though Biden’s approval rating hasn’t improved by much, it’s notable that it hasn’t gotten worse given how bad inflation is right now. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/10/us/politics/biden-putin-inflation.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Some people seem inclined to blame Russian President Vladimir Putin</a> for the current surge in gas prices, but it's not clear how long that will last. It could be a short-lived buffer for Biden if the war drags on and gas prices keep going up.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Biden’s approval rating has more or less ticked up to where it was in January, but it’s still a <em>very</em> small shift.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the one hand, that isn’t that surprising given just how polarized our politics are; <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-you-should-still-pay-attention-to-joe-bidens-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">small shifts in presidential approval are the order of the day</a> now.<strong> </strong>Rather, what has been surprising about Biden’s approval rating is how much <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-behind-bidens-declining-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it dropped in the late summer and early fall</a>, around the time of the messy withdrawal of U.S. troops from Afghanistan and the surge in the delta variant of the coronavirus in the U.S. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Biden’s approval rating declined by nearly 8 points from late July to early September last year, which marked a sharp drop over a fairly short period. Such a sizable and quick swing is unusual in our day and age, in which presidential approval has <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-approval-rating-is-incredibly-steady-is-that-weird-or-the-new-normal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tended to be pretty stable</a>. This may have partly been due to Biden’s “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-should-we-expect-of-bidens-approval-rating-in-the-first-few-months/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">honeymoon period</a>” ending pretty quickly, but it was still a precipitous slide: In our historical approval data, Trump’s approval rating never dropped that much in any month-and-a-half period, and former President Barack Obama’s did just once.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> Do you think we're in a situation, Geoffrey, where presidential approval no longer rebounds quickly? Compared to past periods, it seems easier in our gloomy political era for voters to quickly turn on a president than it is to suddenly decide he's doing OK after all.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Amelia, I would not rule it out entirely, but it would probably take fairly special circumstances, like a particularly strong rally-’round-the-flag moment — a stronger one than we're in now. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Ah, Geoffrey, you’ve stumbled onto one of my pet peeves! To paraphrase <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vimZj8HW0Kg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LL Cool J</a>, don’t call it a rally-’round-the-flag effect!</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As I wrote earlier this month, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-care-about-the-invasion-of-ukraine-but-that-doesnt-mean-they-will-rally-around-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a rally-’round-the-flag effect has two specific causes</a>: heightened patriotism and a lack of criticism from opposition parties. But I’d argue neither condition is met in the U.S. right now. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Instead, I would say what we’re seeing is a very rational public reaction to Biden's handling of the crisis. This may seem like an academic distinction, but I think it's an important one. After all, rally-’round-the-flag effects are about emotion: “I love America, and therefore I love our president!” But Americans’ response to what’s happening in Ukraine has been more rational: “I approve of the president's actions, and therefore I like our president (marginally) more.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> One thing that is shifting, though, is that Americans are <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/03/12/upshot/ukraine-russia-ally-enemy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to see Russia as an enemy</a> and more likely to see Ukraine as a friendly country or an ally. Interestingly, that shift is happening among both Republicans and Democrats, which could explain why we’re not seeing more of a shift in Biden’s approval rating. People are having a reaction to the war — maybe even an emotional one — but it's dampened by partisanship. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Not to mention, there are so many other factors weighing Biden down, such as inflation, the COVID-19 pandemic, supply chain issues, gas prices, etc. If the status quo of any of those issues suddenly improved, Biden's approval would likely improve, too. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Put another way, you need a <em>real</em> rally-’round-the-flag effect to overshadow those issues now, which, to Nathaniel's point, hasn’t happened. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Speaking of which … Americans still generally don’t approve of how Biden is handling the economy and/or the pandemic, right? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Well, his approval rating on the pandemic has actually improved. In fact, in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/coronavirus-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our coronavirus presidential approval tracker</a>, he rose above water in early March for the first time since early January. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2018" height="750" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.00.27-PM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.00.27-PM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.00.27-PM.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Screen-Shot-2022-03-15-at-6.00.27-PM.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">This could reflect the fact that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/us/covid-cases.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">case counts are way down again</a> as the omicron surge has faded — which, of course, could be another reason why Biden’s overall approval rating has ticked up.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> At the same time, though, Americans aren’t quite as concerned with the coronavirus as they once were. According to Gallup, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1675/most-important-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">13 percent of Americans</a> said it was the country's most important problem in February, which is not low in the grand scheme of things, but it is <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/354026/satisfaction-drops-covid-resurges-top-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">notably less important to Americans than it has been over the past two years</a>. For much of 2021, around 20 percent or more named the coronavirus as the country’s top challenge, and 45 percent <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/349205/fewer-cite-coronavirus-important-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">answered that way in April 2020</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> There’s also some evidence that Americans don’t trust Democrats to handle the pandemic as much as they once did. A recent <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/wsj-poll-biden-ukraine-inflation-midterms-11646975533?mod=djemalertNEWS" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wall Street Journal poll</a> found that voters thought Democrats were best able to handle the pandemic — compared to Republicans — by an 11-point margin, but that’s down 5 percentage points from mid-November. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, as Geoffrey said, the pandemic isn’t the key issue it once was for voters; instead, it’s the economy. And on that issue, Biden gets abysmal ratings. Sixty-three percent of voters said they “somewhat” or “strongly” disapproved of Biden’s handling of inflation and rising costs in that Wall Street Journal poll, with 47 percent saying they thought Republicans were best equipped to handle inflation, versus 30 percent who preferred Democrats. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> There are just so many forces working against Biden right now. People are <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/02/politics/unhappiness-americans-gallup-analysis/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">super unhappy</a> in general. It's not hard to see why they'd blame the president for that unhappiness — fairly or unfairly.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> The buck stops here, as former President Harry Truman <a href="https://www.trumanlibrary.gov/education/trivia/buck-stops-here-sign" target="_blank" rel="noopener">famously noted</a>, and that's how it goes as president — you get to enjoy the good, but you have to suffer the bad, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> What should we make of Biden's approval rating, then? Is it showing signs of rebounding? Or not really?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> I think it's a good sign for Biden that he's getting some Democratic enthusiasm back. He's also on track to appoint <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the first Black woman to the Supreme Court</a> — that's a campaign promise he's making good on. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Maybe things are going from really dire to only kinda sorta dire? That’s, of course, based on my very scientific direness scale. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Biden’s approval has ticked up, but I'm not sure I would call it a rebound. I think we have to wait and see whether his approval rating climbs a bit more. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And to Amelia's point, perhaps that happens due to other factors, like his Supreme Court pick, although I think it’s safe to assume that what’s happening in Ukraine will continue to overshadow most things besides inflation. Still, Biden could benefit if people continue to be OK with his handling of the crisis. Of course that could change, too. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd:</strong> I also think we'll have to see how things go. If the war in Ukraine slogs on and prices keep going up, people might stop giving Biden so much credit for his handling of the war — and blame him even more for the economic fallout of the conflict. That's not where we're at right now, obviously, but I could see us getting there in the future.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> On "The Bachelor," contestants often say “I'm falling in love with you” instead of “I love you” because, well, they've only known these people for a few weeks. In the same vein, yes, Biden's approval rating is “showing signs of rebounding,” but it certainly hasn't “rebounded.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647426601508013</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Republicans Are Thinking About Trumpism Without Trump</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-republicans-are-thinking-about-trumpism-without-trump/</link>
						<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Republican Party</category>
			<category>Trumpism</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Like most presidents, Donald Trump changed the political party he led. But Trump was hardly a normal president.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That was apparent <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/lifestyle/magazine/trump-presidential-norm-breaking-list/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">while Trump was president</a>, but in many ways that’s even easier to understand now that he is out of office. Unlike previous presidents, Trump has refused to take a step back from the limelight. Instead, he has continued to try and be the party’s kingmaker, playing a far more active role in the 2022 primaries than he did in 2018 and 2020. His <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-2022-endorsements-are-earlier-bolder-and-more-dangerous-than-when-he-was-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsements have gotten bolder</a> and more aggressive down ballot, and he’s often used them to root out those who oppose him or <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/30/us/politics/election-deniers-secretary-of-state.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his false claims about the 2020 election results</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">He also still commands <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2022/02/02/trump-desantis-close-2024-florida/9302491002/?gnt-cfr=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">considerable personal loyalty</a> among <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/a-majority-of-republican-voters-actively-want-trump-to-run-for-president-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voters within the party</a>. But as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-gop-might-still-be-trumps-party-but-that-doesnt-mean-theres-room-for-him/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I’ve written before</a>, there is evidence that the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-trumps-hold-on-the-gop-still-strong/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">alliance</a> between Republicans and Trump is uneasy, and it could test how much clout he carries in the party. To be sure, that doesn’t mean we should <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/if-republicans-ever-turn-on-trump-itll-happen-all-at-once/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expect Republicans to break from Trump en masse</a>, but nevertheless, there are signs that both Trump’s style and ideas are evolving as other politicians take them up and inevitably change them.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the last few years, a number of ambitious politicians have established a national name for themselves by claiming the Trumpist mantle — all while offering voters their <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2021/10/06/nikki-haley-plots-republican-party-future-with-without-trump/6001710001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">own interpretations of Trump-style conservatism</a>. This group includes governors like Ron DeSantis of Florida and Glenn Youngkin of Virginia; senators like Ted Cruz of Texas and Josh Hawley of Missouri; and even erstwhile members of the Trump administration like former Vice President Mike Pence and former U.S. ambassador to the United Nations Nikki Haley. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Though a few of these figures, like Cruz and Haley, had national ambitions prior to the Trump era, many became national figures starting in 2016 and thus created political profiles inextricably linked to Trump. Let’s take a look, then, at how these aspiring GOP leaders are reinventing — or resisting — Trumpism and what this might mean for the future of the Republican Party.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The first category of note is politicians who have tried to distance themselves from Trump’s political style without really rejecting any of his views. The most prominent example of a GOP politician in this group is probably Youngkin, whose November 2021 victory in the Virginia gubernatorial race could serve as a model for <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/virginia-politics/glenn-youngkin-virginia-governor-republican/2021/10/08/f4fa9cc2-2566-11ec-8d53-67cfb452aa60_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump-style candidates running in purple states</a>. What remains to be seen is whether this type of Trumpian politician will be any more successful at governing than Trump was. Youngkin’s administration so far has veered to the right and relied heavily on culture war tactics like going after <a href="https://www.nbc12.com/2022/01/25/gov-youngkin-sets-up-tip-line-report-divisive-teaching-practices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">critical race theory</a> in schools, which hasn’t <a href="https://www.wusa9.com/article/news/local/virginia/poll-shows-many-virginia-voters-disagree-with-governor-youngkin-on-masks-critical-race-theory/65-9e1360c5-bdf9-4f86-af4a-6859812dcdc2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">proved popular among voters</a> in the state. It’s possible that this approach isn’t a political winner in a purple state, even when the Democratic brand is struggling. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some Republicans have gone further than Youngkin, though, explicitly trying to separate loyalty to Trump and his policy positions from believing in the Big Lie, the false claim that the 2020 election was stolen from him. Former New Jersey Gov. and Trump transition leader Chris Christie, who has also criticized Trump’s general approach to politics, has said, for instance, that the Republican Party needs to <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/chris-christie-urges-republicans-to-drop-election-lies-conspiracies-this-has-to-stop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">move on from false beliefs</a> about the last presidential election. He also recently <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/07/politics/chris-christie-trump-republicans-january-6/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told conservative talk show host Hugh Hewitt</a> that Trump incited the Jan. 6 riot. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Pence has <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/09/politics/pence-trump-rebuke-response/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also publicly contradicted</a> Trump, suggesting that Trump was wrong to claim that the vice president could “overturn” the results when Congress met to count the Electoral College votes. He’s also <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/pence-hits-trump-room-gop-apologists-putin-83258089" target="_blank" rel="noopener">repudiated Trump’s embrace</a> of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Meanwhile, Haley has tried to strike more of a middle-of-the-road approach, <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/video/nikki-haley-calls-pence-saying-021027757.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">criticizing Pence’s rebuke of Trump</a> while maintaining publicly that Biden won the <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/nikki-haley-embraces-trump-in-her-vision-of-gop-future-11633424400" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election</a>. In other words, there’s a not-so-insubstantial faction of Republicans trying to split the difference when it comes to Trumpism. They derive some of their national stature from their affiliation with Trump but disavow some of his more extreme positions. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some Republicans, though, have broken even more decisively with Trump. Members of this group vary in their relationship to Trump’s legislative agenda — some actually backed core components of his policy goals — but they’re nonetheless distinct from others in the party in that they’re not trying to reinterpret Trumpism; rather, they’re aiming  to distance themselves from it. Some prominent Republicans who fall into this group include Reps. <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/republican-liz-cheney-calls-trump-unfit-future-office/story?id=82039304" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Liz Cheney of Wyoming</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/10/29/1050454729/gop-rep-adam-kinzinger-who-voted-to-impeach-trump-wont-run-for-reelection" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Adam Kinzinger</a> of Illinois and <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/congress-electoral-college-tally-live-updates/2021/01/06/953945397/called-a-traitor-by-trump-supporters-romney-says-president-disrespected-voters" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sens. Mitt Romney</a> of Utah, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/02/05/ben-sasse-2024-466424" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ben Sasse of Nebraska</a> and <a href="https://www.adn.com/politics/2021/01/08/alaska-sen-lisa-murkowski-calls-on-president-trump-to-resign-questions-her-future-as-a-republican/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A key distinction, though, between these figures and Republicans like Christie, Pence or Haley is that it’s even harder to imagine any of the former entering or gaining traction in a GOP presidential primary. The presence of a more outwardly anti-Trump faction is still significant, though, as it raises questions about the viability of the larger party coalition. Currently, it appears that members of this group will be ostracized. For instance, Cheney and Kinzinger have been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/04/us/politics/republicans-jan-6-cheney-censure.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured by the Republican National Committee</a>. Cheney also <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-there-no-place-for-liz-cheney-in-the-modern-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lost her leadership position</a> for her comments about the 2020 election and support for Trump’s second impeachment, and Kinzinger, who also supported Trump’s second impeachment, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/10/29/rep-adam-kinzinger-wont-seek-reelection-next-year-517599" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t seeking reelection</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the polar opposite of the firmly anti-Trump group are those in the party who seem to be trying to out-Trump Trump, or leaning into the most bombastic reimagining of Trumpism possible. This group most prominently includes DeSantis, who has tried to establish himself as the 2024 front-runner of this wing of the party. As such, he has positioned himself as a leading figure in the <a href="https://www.flgov.com/2021/12/15/governor-desantis-announces-legislative-proposal-to-stop-w-o-k-e-activism-and-critical-race-theory-in-schools-and-corporations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GOP’s fight</a> to curtail <a href="https://www.tallahassee.com/story/news/local/state/2022/03/08/florida-abortion-law-ban-hb-5-florida-abortion-clinic/9414123002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abortion rights</a> and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/dont-gay-bill-passes-florida-senate/story?id=83301889" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LGBTQ rights</a> and voting rights. He has even criticized Trump from his right, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/01/14/politics/desantis-trump-covid-response/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saying in January</a> that he regretted not speaking out in 2020 against Trump’s COVID-19 recommendations. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Congress, this group includes legislators like <a href="https://www.wpr.org/us-sen-ron-johnson-continues-push-state-lawmakers-take-over-federal-elections-wisconsin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Ron Johnson</a> and Reps. <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2021/02/18/marjorie-taylor-greene-won-conservative-views-and-donald-trump/4411352001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marjorie Taylor Greene</a>, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/11/30/politics/lauren-boebert-ilhan-omar-video-comments/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lauren Boebert</a>, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/rep-madison-cawthorn-says-there-will-be-bloodshed-if-us-elections-continue-to-be-rigged/2021/08/30/297a9fa2-09c8-11ec-aea1-42a8138f132a_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Madison Cawthorn</a> and <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/mccarthy-mtg-marjorie-taylor-greene-paul-gosar-white-nationalist-conference-191118196.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paul Gosar</a>. Trying to out-Trump Trump has a lot of different expressions, but among this group of Republicans, it broadly refers to their attitudes toward <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/02/technology/marjorie-taylor-greene-twitter.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID-19</a>, the 2020 election and <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/163487/madison-cawthorn-beach-ferrara-midterms" target="_blank" rel="noopener">electoral democracy</a> in general. This group’s rise to prominence illustrates the appeal of a constituency for an even more extreme version of Trumpism. That said, it’s not clear how broad the appeal is — Greene faces <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/corner/new-poll-shows-the-challenge-and-opportunity-of-a-primary-of-marjorie-taylor-greene/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several primary challengers</a> (though she is likely to <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/hopefuls-line-up-to-challenge-marjorie-taylor-greene-but-shell-be-hard-to-beat/LETWBNUQ6VF4HDZYSLDHGHNVBU/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">keep her seat</a>) and is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-do-americans-think-of-marjorie-taylor-greene-liz-cheney-josh-hawley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpopular nationally</a>. Meanwhile, Johnson’s popularity in his home state of Wisconsin has <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/01/25/ron-johnson-unpopular-in-wisconsin-can-he-win-anyway/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">declined since 2020</a>, and he is up for reelection in November. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, there is a lot of uncertainty about what the post-Trump Republican coalition will look like moving forward. It’s possible that the GOP is now completely dominated by one individual, as evidenced by the purge of those who pushed back on the 45th president’s fraudulent claims that the election was stolen from him. But there are still other voices in the party, including some that have pushed back on some aspects of Trumpism. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, if the largest group of Republicans prove to be that which seeks to reinterpret Trumpism in some way, it’s possible it’ll end up wielding a lot of influence in the party. The key question here is whether these Republicans can carve out their own political identities while still drawing on the past president, as Trump and Trumpism now define the the party’s factions. This is a <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/video/castro-says-he-not-biden-is-the-true-heir-to-obamas-legacy-015755071.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">common dilemma</a> for politicians after an <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2015/09/15/politics/ronald-reagan-republicans-2016/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">influential presidency</a>. And it still remains to be seen whether Trumpism is open to reinterpretation by others, or whether, as is often the case in highly personal political movements, the ideology proves impossible to separate from the leader.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In 2021, political scientist <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/01/even-now-republicans-will-stick-together/617803/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hans Noel wrote</a> that Republicans could “agree to disagree about democracy,” citing the need for parties to form broad coalitions in the U.S. political system and the many historical examples of such coalitions exiting despite deep differences within them. But disagreeing over the basic tenets of democracy might prove too much of an intra-party fissure for Republicans to overcome to form a coalition. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The fact, too, that it is so hard to imagine a post-Trump Republican Party speaks to just how successful Trump has been in seizing control of the party, whether it’s from election officials at the state and local level or <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/republican-national-committee-sues-jan-6-panel-salesforce-subpoena-rcna19427" target="_blank" rel="noopener">from the RNC</a>. And it’s perhaps the biggest reason why in 2024, as was the case in 2016, a well-known but divisive figure — including Trump himself — might once again step in and fill the void.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647341100980494</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: The Political Price Of Gas</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-political-price-of-gas/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Gas Prices</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-political-price-of-gas/">
	<div data-podcast-id="328091" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: The Political Price Of Gas">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6040850116.mp3?updated=1647294694">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Who gets blamed when gas prices go up? And what are the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-may-or-may-not-blame-biden-for-higher-gas-prices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political consequences</a>? Last week, President Biden announced that the U.S. would ban imports of Russian oil and warned that it would mean higher prices at the pump. That comes after a year of rising prices already. The average cost in the U.S. today is $4.33 per gallon. A year ago, it was $2.86, <a href="https://gasprices.aaa.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to AAA</a>. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses what high gas prices have meant for politics historically and outlines the debates in Washington over how to bring those prices down.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The crew also explores some of the ways <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZbUbaroCZgs&amp;t=20s" target="_blank" rel="noopener">American life has changed</a> in the two-plus years since the U.S. started introducing measures to fight the coronavirus pandemic. And they ask whether polling accuracy can be improved by asking respondents to <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-coin-flipping-can-make-polls-more-accurate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">flip a coin</a> before answering.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 21:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647296100843939</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Americans May — Or May Not — Blame Biden For Higher Gas Prices</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-may-or-may-not-blame-biden-for-higher-gas-prices/</link>
						<dc:creator>Santul Nerkar</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Santul Nerkar</dc:creator>
			<category>Gas Prices</category>
			<category>Inflation</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">When President Biden <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-announces-ban-russian-oil-imports-energy-products/story?id=83315763" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced last week</a> that he was banning Russian oil imports to the United States to retaliate against Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, he conceded that Americans would pay more for gas as a result. “Defending freedom is going to cost,” Biden said. “It’s going to cost us as well.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But higher prices at the pump and elsewhere aren’t new. For nearly a year now, Americans have faced sharply rising inflation, and the latest numbers were further confirmation of that reality: U.S. prices last month rose 7.9 percent year-over-year, the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/03/10/economy/us-consumer-price-inflation-february/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largest such increase since 1982</a> and a continuation of a worrying trajectory as the country recovers from the pandemic recession and a beaten-down supply chain.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible that this trajectory worsens, too, as the global economic outlook has gotten a lot more uncertain following Russia’s invasion late last month. Prices for <a href="https://apnews.com/article/russia-ukraine-business-asia-tokyo-sydney-1ac7c193d204266b2901fe420d32c2c2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">oil</a>, <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/wheat-continues-surge-toward-all-time-high-as-russian-invasion-of-ukraine-shuts-down-exports-11646664524" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wheat</a> and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2022/mar/08/carmakers-face-higher-costs-and-supply-issues-as-price-of-nickel-soars" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other resources</a> have skyrocketed as countries around the world impose harsh sanctions against Russian industries, and U.S. gas prices have ticked all the way up to <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/03/07/energy/record-gas-price/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$4.17 per gallon</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s a precarious situation for Biden because inflation and, in particular, higher gas prices — including those spurred by overseas oil crises — have been shown to drag down presidential approval. At the same time, presidents haven’t always experienced lower approval as a result of these conflicts, so it’s possible that, given the situation in Ukraine, Americans won’t blame Biden for higher gas prices as they have blamed past presidents.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Higher gas prices are hardly the only result of inflation, but they are one of the most visible and visceral realities of inflation for Americans. Scholarship has found that consumer sentiment gets <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3267721" target="_blank" rel="noopener">significantly more pessimistic</a> in response to rising gas prices, and that Americans form higher inflation expectations and change their spending habits <a href="https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w26237/w26237.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when they see higher gas prices</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Higher gas prices have also been shown to drag down presidential approval. As <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">I wrote back in December</a>, overall inflation has been associated with several periods of downturn in presidential approval, and research has also found that higher gas prices typically have a <a href="https://pprg.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/Presidential-Approval-and-Gas-Prices.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">significant and negative effect on presidents’ approval ratings</a>. But it’s not as simple as higher gas prices meaning lower presidential approval, according to <a href="https://politicalscience.stanford.edu/people/jon-krosnick" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jon Krosnick</a>, a social psychologist at Stanford University who has researched the link between presidential approval and economic indicators. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Namely, situations like Russia’s invasion of Ukraine can play a role in whether Americans blame Biden — or something or someone else, like Russia and Vladimir Putin — for inflation, according to Krosnick. And in this particular situation, it’s possible many Americans will tolerate higher gas prices as a result of sanctions against Russia, according to recent surveys from <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/omtmdczu48/econToplines.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/The Economist</a> and <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3838" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac University</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The impact of economic indicators on presidential approval depends upon the attribution that the public makes for the cause of economic indicators getting better or worse,” said Krosnick. “In other words, what matters here is whether the president can reasonably be held responsible for what happened to gas prices, or anything else [can].”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, higher gas prices resulting from foreign oil shocks haven’t always worsened presidential approval ratings. Take, for example, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/16/business/economic-scene-the-broad-impact-of-the-gulf-war.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the 1990 oil shock</a>, which was caused by Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2 of that year. Even as the price of oil spiked, former president George H.W. Bush’s approval jumped over 16 percentage points in less than a month as the international community swiftly condemned Iraq’s actions, and it rose again after the U.S.-led intervention in early 1991. Moreover, the price of oil <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111114053633/http://www.brookings.edu/economics/bpea/~/media/Files/Programs/ES/BPEA/2009_spring_bpea_papers/2009_spring_bpea_hamilton.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">returned to roughly prior levels</a> in less than a year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s unlikely that Biden will see this kind of upswell in his presidential approval rating, but it is true that we haven’t yet seen a drop in his presidential approval to accompany the <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/costco-sams-club-lines-as-gas-fuel-prices-soar-2022-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long lines at the pump</a> — in fact, we’ve seen the opposite. <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden’s approval today</a> is about the same as it was at the start of the Ukraine crisis and has actually rebounded since the initial days of the invasion, a period of time over which prices have risen considerably. He could be seeing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/08/biden-approval-rating-ukraine-00015065" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a bump</a> from his State of the Union address and from the Ukraine crisis itself, and as Krosnick noted, U.S. presidential approval often responds positively to international conflicts — even if big swings in approval are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/bidens-approval-rating-isnt-bouncing-back/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mostly a thing of the past</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One other factor working in Biden’s favor is that the U.S. is far less dependent on foreign oil than it was during the 1973 and 1979 energy crises. “At the time, if OPEC countries decided that they wanted to reduce production, that was it,” said <a href="https://www.bc.edu/bc-web/schools/carroll-school/faculty-research/faculty-directory/francesco-dacunto.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Francesco D’Acunto</a>, a professor of finance at Boston College. “Even if we see that prices are increasing [right now], we haven’t yet observed anything close to what was happening in the late ’70s,” he added. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Biden is still walking a tightrope on inflation. Inflation was high even before a foreign conflict pumped more uncertainty into the U.S. economy, and most Americans disapproved of Biden’s handling <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1fMLXPDp_XAlU4X-vC3Q5qSRcle8g245Q/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of inflation prior to the Ukraine crisis</a>. Moreover, as with much polling on foreign policy, voters <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-2508.2007.00602.x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">often take their cues from elites</a> on which policies to support, and it’s quite possible that they’ll end up <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-care-about-the-invasion-of-ukraine-but-that-doesnt-mean-they-will-rally-around-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reflecting partisan loyalties</a> when evaluating how Biden has handled what’s happening in Ukraine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All of that could lead Americans to rate the economy more poorly and, thus, hurt Biden’s political prospects. But it is still far too early to tell whether the conflict’s potentially negative effects on the U.S. economy will be just another economic issue Americans blame him for — or one that they’re willing to tolerate.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647255601602464</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How An Uptick In Censures Among Local Republicans Signals A Growing Radicalism</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-an-uptick-in-censures-among-local-republicans-signals-a-growing-radicalism/</link>
						<dc:creator>Seth Masket</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Seth Masket</dc:creator>
			<category>2020 Election</category>
			<category>Censures</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Republican Party</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">The Republican National Committee’s <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/gop-censures-cheney-kinzinger-moves-pull-debates-82678331" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censure last month of GOP Reps. Liz Cheney and Adam Kinzinger</a> was a historical rarity — national parties almost never reprimand their own officeholders. But in many ways it was the culmination of what’s been happening at the state level. State and local parties are increasingly disciplining their officeholders, and it’s mostly happening on the Republican side.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s typical for the losing party in a presidential race to undergo some sort of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Learning-Loss-Democrats-Seth-Masket/dp/1108482120/ref=sr_1_6?crid=2WHSGBSS8GIZI&amp;keywords=Masket&amp;qid=1641421903&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=maske%2Cstripbooks%2C208&amp;sr=1-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">period of self-reflection after its loss</a>, trying to come up with a narrative that will help guide it in future elections. But what Republicans have gone through since 2020 is something of a departure, with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/01/07/republicans-big-lie-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many in the party</a> <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/01/05/1070362852/trump-big-lie-election-jan-6-families" target="_blank" rel="noopener">arguing</a> that former President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/12/08/politics/perdue-kemp-ga-governor-trump-big-lie/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t actually lose</a>. Moreover, these election deniers haven’t just tried to delegitimize the 2020 election results, they’ve also spearheaded an effort to <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/heeding-steve-bannons-call-election-deniers-organize-to-seize-control-of-the-gop-and-reshape-americas-elections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rebuke Republicans who have said Trump lost</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One of the key tools these Trump supporters have used is the censure. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/what-is-censure-congress-/2021/11/18/20245326-4889-11ec-b8d9-232f4afe4d9b_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A censure</a> is something governing bodies (often legislatures) use to issue official statements of condemnation or disapproval. Censures have a long history in this country. The U.S. Senate, for example, <a href="https://www.senate.gov/about/origins-foundations/parties-leadership/censure-president-jackson.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured President Andrew Jackson in 1834</a> for effectively shuttering the Bank of the United States. The Senate has also <a href="https://www.senate.gov/about/powers-procedures/censure.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured nine of its own members</a>, and in 2021, the U.S. House of Representatives <a href="https://history.house.gov/Institution/Discipline/Expulsion-Censure-Reprimand/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured its 24th member</a>, Rep. Paul Gosar of Arizona, for, among other things, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republicans-house-gosar-ocasio-cortez/2021/11/17/4e012bb4-47b9-11ec-b8d9-232f4afe4d9b_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">posting an anime video of himself killing a fellow member</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Yet the censure is, by definition, a symbolic act: It does not actually remove anyone from office or strip anyone of power. In fact, the censure has <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/what-does-it-mean-to-censure-a-politician" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historically carried little weight</a>, although it can signal to the officeholder that they are losing standing with their party and that their renomination is likely in jeopardy. And until recently, censures were also relatively rare.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">State parties <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-trumpiest-republicans-are-at-the-state-and-local-levels-not-in-d-c/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have issued a number of censures</a> since the beginning of 2021. Take Arizona, a state that has made headlines for its <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/post-election-audits-are-normal-whats-happening-in-arizona-is-anything-but/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frivolous investigations into the accuracy of the 2020 presidential election</a>. In early 2021, Republicans in the state <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/01/23/politics/arizona-gop-censure-mccain-flake-ducey/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured three Republicans</a> for, among other things, failing to support Trump: former Sen. Jeff Flake, Gov. Doug Ducey and Cindy McCain, the widow of the late Sen. John McCain. Democrats in the state haven’t been as quick to censure as Republicans, but in January 2022, the Arizona Democratic Party <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/22/us/politics/sinema-censure-arizona-democrats.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured Sen. Kyrsten Sinema</a> for her refusal to change filibuster rules in order to pass voting rights measures. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not just state parties, either. Censures aren’t as well documented at the county level, as  there are more than 3,000 counties in the U.S. versus just 50 states, but I found in a search of nearly 7,000 newspapers using <a href="https://www.newsbank.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NewsBank</a>, a news research database, an explosion of censures, especially in 2021, at the county level.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1210" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/masket.CENSURES.0309-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/masket.CENSURES.0309-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/masket.CENSURES.0309-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/masket.CENSURES.0309-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The pattern is pretty striking. Censures by county parties were until recently a rare event, affecting somewhere between zero and three people per year, I found. Most were issued over relatively modest local or factional party disputes. Republicans in Bexar County, Texas, for example, <a href="https://www.mysanantonio.com/news/local/article/Straus-censured-by-Bexar-County-GOP-12425417.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured then-state House Speaker Joe Straus</a> for blocking a number of conservative bills in 2017. In Mohave County, Arizona Republicans <a href="https://www.havasunews.com/news/paul-mosley-censured-by-county-gop/article_0a05e526-87f0-11e8-993f-f3735fa604c0.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">censured state Rep. Paul Mosley</a> in 2018 for “conduct unbecoming” after he tried to abuse his position as a state legislator in order to get out of a traffic ticket. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But starting in 2020, the types of censures county parties issued shifted — both censures issued in 2020, for instance, had to do with COVID-19 mask mandates. In 2021, I found, there was just a dramatic increase in county-level censures, especially among Republican county parties. Republican county parties censured 23 GOP officeholders in 2021 compared to Democrats’ five, and what’s more, most Republican censures were tied in some way to the 2020 election, the subsequent Jan. 6 insurrection or the ensuing fallout.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, I have organized the county censure data by the number of individuals censured, which can be tricky. There are only five Democratic censures here, for example, and four of them were actually done in the same resolution, passed by the Democratic Party of Palm Beach County, Florida, to &lt;a href="https://www.palmbeachpost.com/story/news/education/2021/06/04/pbc-dems-censure-school-board-members-over-white-advantage-reversal/7541548002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;chastise four school board members&lt;/a&gt; for removing the phrase “white advantage” from a statement about equity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>11</sup></a>Although censures are still relatively rare events — I found just 34 of them in more than 3,000 counties over the past seven years — the uptick in the last year signals a growing form of radicalism among local party committees. All of this points to yet another signal of a Republican Party undergoing a purge. Parties often wage ideological fights in their primary contests, but primaries take time. In this rash of recent censures, we’re seeing county party leaders trying to more emphatically assert which faction of the party is in charge, and as I’ve documented above, that could dramatically reshape the GOP at its most fundamental levels of government</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1647255601602463</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How The War In Ukraine Might Change Putin’s Popularity Among Russians</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-war-in-ukraine-might-change-putins-popularity-among-russians/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers and Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<category>Vladimir Putin</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard to fathom what’s happening in Ukraine right now. Schools <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/video/20220306-war-in-ukraine-school-bombed-by-russian-army" target="_blank" rel="noopener">being bombed</a>. Civilians <a href="https://www.reuters.com/news/picture/from-molotov-cocktails-to-anti-tank-barr-idUSRTS62SIY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">forming militias and making</a> molotov cocktails. Millions of <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-60555472" target="_blank" rel="noopener">people displaced</a>, and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2022/03/04/ukraine-russia-casualties-kyiv/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an unknown number</a> of deaths. But perhaps equally difficult to fathom is the fact that, as recently as last month, the man behind this war, Russian president Vladimir Putin, was enjoying his highest approval ratings in nearly four years. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In February, Putin <a href="https://www.levada.ru/en/ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had a 71 percent approval</a> rating and a 27 percent disapproval rating among the Russian public, the highest it’s been since May 2018 (though it’s never dipped below 59 percent according to the Levada-Center). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the one hand, it’s natural to question the accuracy of public opinion polling under an authoritarian regime, but there are actually a number of reasons to believe those approval ratings represent genuine Russian sentiment. For one, the polling comes from the Levada-Center, a respected, independent pollster. And if you’re suspicious that Russians aren’t being totally honest about their feelings with pollsters due to fear of retribution, <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1060586X.2016.1144334" target="_blank" rel="noopener">research to control for this phenomenon</a> has found this isn’t the case — the polls are capturing true Russian opinions on Putin. Sure, there is likely some bias, but the bottom line is that Putin’s popularity at home is real. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Other recent polling suggests that many Russians view the war in Ukraine differently from those in the West. A <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2022/03/08/russia-public-opinion-ukraine-invasion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll conducted in Russia last week</a> by a group of independent survey research organizations (who have remained anonymous in order to avoid backlash from the Kremlin), found that about 58 percent of Russians approve of the invasion of Ukraine, while 23 percent oppose it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One reason Russians still support Putin and the war in Ukraine has to do with the propaganda and disinformation being sown by the Kremlin. Last week, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/04/world/europe/russia-censorship-media-crackdown.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Putin banned the spreading</a> of “false information” about the war — including calling it a war. He also <a href="https://apnews.com/article/russia-ukraine-vladimir-putin-business-europe-germany-d15ca4ed450d9ca67f43d3b1ac27294d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blocked Facebook and Twitter</a>, as well as a number of Western news outlets including the BBC, making it even harder for Russians to get outside information. And among state-sponsored media in Russia, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/08/world/europe/russia-ukraine-media.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the war is downplayed and cast</a> as a peacekeeping mission designed to liberate Ukraine from Nazis and drug-addled dictators.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a result, it’s not surprising that the Russian public has a very different view of the war: When asked <a href="https://www.levada.ru/en/2022/03/04/ukraine-and-donbass/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in a poll by the Levada-Center</a> in late February who they thought was the initiator of the escalations in Ukraine, 60 percent of Russians said the U.S. and NATO members were to blame — just 3 percent said Russia was the initiator. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But there are some realities of the war that can’t be ignored or downplayed, and they impact Russians’ views, too. For instance, as international sanctions place increased pressure on Russia’s financial sector, the ruble, Russia’s official currency, has plummeted, and <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/world/russians-line-up-at-banks-as-currency-plummets-in-face-of-sanctions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Russians have been lining up at banks</a> trying to withdraw cash. As a result, consumer confidence in Russia has taken a hit, dipping to its lowest point this year. On March 2 it dropped to 98.4, a 5.6 percent drop from four days prior, according to Morning Consult’s Russia Index <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/03/russian-consumers-are-feeling-the-impact-of-sanctions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of Consumer Sentiment</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also clear from <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2022/03/06/protest-arrests-russia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the public protests by Russians against the war</a>, which have resulted in thousands of arrests, that many are not buying the official Kremlin line. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/video/2022/mar/02/ukrainians-are-our-friends-the-young-russian-anti-war-protesters-defying-putin-video" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Many of those protestors</a> are young Russians, among whom support for the war was lower in the anonymous poll released last week: Among 18- to 24-year-olds, 29 percent supported the war, and 39 percent opposed it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As the war rages on, Putin’s popularity may become more precarious, too, if history is any indication. Russians have tended to <a href="https://theconversation.com/putins-public-approval-is-soaring-during-the-russia-ukraine-crisis-but-its-unlikely-to-last-177302" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lose faith in Putin</a> when faced with ongoing war, economic uncertainty or public protest against the leader.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“While examining hundreds of thousands of Russian public opinion survey responses from 2003-19, I have found that merely being exposed to public protest depresses approval of Putin and his regime,” Noah Buckley, a political science professor at Trinity College Dublin, wrote in <a href="https://theconversation.com/putins-approval-has-stayed-strong-over-the-years-war-in-ukraine-could-change-that-178179" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent op-ed</a> for The Conversation. “Members of the general public learn about regime misdeeds from these protests, and discover that there are more dissenters in their society than they may have previously assumed. In other ongoing research, my co-authors and I have found that when Russians find out that Putin’s approval levels are not as sky-high as they thought, their own feelings towards him sour substantially.”</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>On Tuesday, President Biden announced <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-announces-ban-russian-oil-imports-energy-products/story?id=83315763">a ban on Russian oil and energy imports</a>, and it turns out that many Americans support this decision, even if this results in higher gas prices. When asked directly if they would support imposing sanctions on Russian oil even if it led to higher fuel prices, <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3838">71 percent</a> of Americans (from a Mar. 4-6 Quinnipiac University poll) and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/russia-ukraine-latest-news-2022-03-08/card/wsj-poll-79-of-americans-back-ban-on-russian-oil-even-if-energy-prices-rise-niT9f6YRH5wRWe4pbhNv">79 percent</a> (from a Mar. 4-7 Wall Street Journal/Fabrizio, Lee &amp; Associates/ALG Research poll) said yes. When some pollsters included the option to support sanctions but<em> not</em> if they increased oil prices, support for sanctions was less consistently high. Sixty-nine percent of Americans supported sanctions even if they increased U.S. energy prices, and 12 percent supported sanctions as long as they <em>didn’t</em> increase prices, according to <a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/NPR_PBS-NewsHour_Marist-Poll_USA-NOS-and-Tables_202203010901.pdf">a Mar. 1-2 poll</a> from Marist College/NPR/PBS NewsHour. However, <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/nnyqh3ib1d/econToplines.pdf">a Mar. 5-8 The Economist/YouGov poll</a> of Americans found much lower support (46 percent supported sanctions regardless of their effect on U.S. gas prices, but 27 percent supported sanctions only if they didn’t raise prices) as did a <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/03/07/russian-oil-embargo-polling-ukraine-crisis/">Mar. 5-7 Morning Consult poll</a> of registered voters (49 percent supported sanctions regardless of their effect on U.S. gas prices, but 28 percent supported sanctions only if they didn’t raise prices).</li><li>A plurality of Americans (42 percent) felt that <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/omtmdczu48/econToplines.pdf">parents should have the final say</a> over whether K-12 students are required to wear masks in school, according to a Feb. 26-Mar. 1 poll from The Economist/YouGov. Twenty-two percent said it should be up to school administrators, 14 percent were unsure and 13 percent said the government, while just 7 percent said this responsibility should fall to teachers.</li><li><a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/curiosity/lat-mlb-lockout/">The Major League Baseball lockout is dampening interest</a> in the season among baseball fans, though most aren’t following the dispute closely, according to a Mar. 3-7 poll from the Los Angeles Times/SurveyMonkey. Sixty percent of fans said the dispute had caused them to lose interest in the season, but 78 percent said they weren’t closely following the lockout. In terms of who to blame for the dispute, baseball fans were split between blaming the lockout on both the players and the owners (49 percent) and blaming just the owners (31 percent).</li><li>Over three-quarters of European women<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defined as women aged 15 and older who live in one of the 27 member countries of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> thought that <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2022-03/Women_in_times_of_Covid19_2022_ep_eb_fl_report_en.pdf">the COVID-19 pandemic had led to at least a small increase of violence against women</a> in their country, according to a Jan. 25-Feb. 3 poll from Ipsos European Public Affairs, commissioned by the European Parliament. Women from Greece (93 percent) and Portugal (90 percent) were the most likely to say the pandemic had increased violence against women in their country, while less than half of Finnish (48 percent) and Hungarian (47 percent) women said the same.</li><li>Though it’s hardly a resounding vote of confidence, Americans seem to be giving <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/">Biden better marks for how he is handling the crisis in Ukraine</a>. According to the aforementioned Marist College/NPR/PBS NewsHour poll from Mar. 1-2, 52 percent now said they approved of Biden’s leadership in Ukraine, versus <a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/polls/npr-pbs-newshour-marist-national-poll-the-biden-administration-heading-into-the-state-of-the-union-address-february-2022/">34 percent in a Feb. 15-21 poll</a>. Polls from Morning Consult/Politico showed a similar but less pronounced trend: A Mar. 4-6 poll found <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/03/08161506/2203034_crosstabs_POLITICO_RVs_v1_SH.pdf">47 percent of registered voters approved of Biden’s handling of the crisis in Ukraine</a>, versus <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/02/22150612/2202139_crosstabs_POLITICO_RVs_v1_SH.pdf">40 percent from Feb. 19-21</a>.</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> 42.5 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 51.6 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -9.1 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-still-unsure-how-the-u-s-should-respond-to-the-invasion-of-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 41.6 percent approved and 52.9 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -11.3 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 41.3 percent and a disapproval rating of 52.6 percent, for a net approval rating of -11.3 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 2.1 percentage points (44.8 percent to 42.7 percent). A week ago, Republicans led Democrats by 2.2 points (44.8 percent to 42.6 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 2.0 points (44.4 percent to 42.4 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646999101235527</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: How To Think About The Risk Of Nuclear War</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-to-think-about-the-risk-of-nuclear-war/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Nuclear Weapons</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-to-think-about-the-risk-of-nuclear-war/">
	<div data-podcast-id="327975" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: How To Think About The Risk Of Nuclear War">

					<span>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/galen-druke/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke</a></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6979399475.mp3?updated=1646953601">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">As the war in Ukraine enters its third week, the threat of a nuclear conflict hangs in the balance. NATO has said it will not send troops to Ukraine or, despite repeated calls from Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy, enforce a no-fly zone over the country. Doing so, NATO says, risks escalating the situation to a direct conflict between nuclear powers. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Galen Druke speaks with James M. Acton, the co-director of the Nuclear Policy Program at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, about how leaders and experts quantify the risks of such a catastrophe.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 23:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646954101997644</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why It’s Important To Debate Foreign Policy Even In Times Of Conflict</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-its-important-to-debate-foreign-policy-even-in-times-of-conflict/</link>
						<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<category>Barack Obama</category>
			<category>Foreign Policy</category>
			<category>George W. Bush</category>
			<category>Iraq War</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>Vietnam War</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Americans are divided on most issues these days. But the Russian invasion of Ukraine might be an exception — sort of. In recent polling, <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2022/03/03/the-invasion-of-ukraine-unites-a-divided-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">both Democrats and Republicans</a> say they support Ukraine over Russia, approve of economic sanctions against Russia and its president, Vladimir Putin, and agree that the U.S. should send money and weapons — but not troops — to Ukraine. Calls for sanctions have received <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/03/04/ukraine-congress-bipartisan-trump-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bipartisan support</a> in Congress as well. Yet <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/russia-stefanik-biden-weakness-world-less-safe" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prominent Republicans</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2022/02/24/media-fox-biden-blame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conservative media figures</a> have criticized President Biden’s handling of the situation, and some, like former President Donald Trump, have <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2022/feb/25/tucker-carlson-fox-news-russia-putin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gone as far</a> as to <a href="https://www.kansascity.com/news/politics-government/article258638383.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">praise Putin</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a result, many Americans have <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/22/us/politics/congress-ukraine-russia.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expressed nostalgia</a> for a time when politics stopped at the water’s edge, a phrase attributed to Republican Sen. Arthur Vandenberg of Michigan, who urged his Republican colleagues to work with President Harry Truman, a Democrat, on postwar national-security issues despite their differences on domestic policies.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But was there ever a time when our country wasn’t divided, even on questions of foreign policy? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Conflicts that we now think of as uniting the country were still political. Americans were torn over what to do in World War II, for example. Congress <a href="https://millercenter.org/president/fdroosevelt/foreign-affairs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">passed a series of neutrality acts</a> in the 1930s, and these isolationist policies were responsible for America’s late entry into the war. And, of course, unity sometimes came at a price. The U.S. government’s <a href="https://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/disp_textbook.cfm?smtID=2&amp;psid=3479" target="_blank" rel="noopener">steps to punish anti-war speech during World War I</a>, for instance, are good examples of going too far with the idea that dissent is inherently harmful to war efforts.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The reality is that foreign policy has always been contested — and, more often than not, linked to questions of <a href="https://www.archives.gov/education/lessons/japanese-relocation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">identity</a> and <a href="https://millercenter.org/the-presidency/educational-resources/age-of-eisenhower/mcarthyism-red-scare" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ideology</a>. But debates about war are so interwoven with our larger culture-war politics now that most questions of how to handle military conflict have been largely reduced to partisan scoring. And that’s a problem — not because we need to get back to some bygone bipartisan era, but because real dissension is vital in a democracy, especially in matters of foreign policy. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The seeds of war politics’ merging with culture-war politics arguably date back to the late 1960s, when anti-Vietnam War protests overlapped with civil rights protests and other social movements that challenged the existing social order. Over time, conservatives and liberals <a href="http://www.uky.edu/AS/PoliSci/Peffley/pdf/Zaller%201991%20APSR%20Information%20Values%20Opinion.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">diverged in their attitudes</a> toward the war, especially as liberal elites began to criticize it. Starting with the <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/10/1968-election-won-by-nixon-still-haunts-our-politics.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1968 presidential election</a>, being anti-war became more closely associated with being a liberal Democrat. And the accusation that George McGovern, <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/108977/acid-amnesty-and-abortion-unlikely-source-legendary-smear" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the 1972 Democratic presidential nominee,</a> was all for “<a href="https://kansaspress.ku.edu/978-0-7006-1650-3.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">acid, amnesty</a><a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amnesty for ‘draft dodgers.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> <a href="https://kansaspress.ku.edu/978-0-7006-1650-3.html" data-type="URL" data-id="https://kansaspress.ku.edu/978-0-7006-1650-3.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and abortion</a>” helped solidify this cultural connection.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And this larger cultural split between the two parties came to a head during the Iraq War. In many ways, it’s connected to the political discourse we’re seeing with Russia and Ukraine now. Unlike now, though, the discourse during the Iraq War — in the beginning at least — exemplified the idea that politics stops at the water’s edge. Critics of then-President George W. Bush rallied behind him after the 9/11 terrorist attacks, and public opinion on the war was <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/19/iraq-war-continues-to-divide-u-s-public-15-years-after-it-began/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">initially quite favorable</a>, even though <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/107-2002/s237" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats</a> were far more<a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/107/hjres114" target="_blank" rel="noopener"></a> split than <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/107/hjres114" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That national unity turned out to be short-lived, though. As <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/195620/summary?casa_token=O_d704mGPBsAAAAA:UckFyFpiFQlwqyFbPW22bqyHw-tKcsXLwooH45fIJIl1EtkJSqNc4E1bvNjpSQDXSXc4jLhqrA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political communications scholar Mary Stuckey</a> has observed, it was during the Iraq War that the two parties began to make very distinct arguments about what it meant to be an American in relation to the war. Bush, for instance, often framed the war on terror, including the <a href="https://www.cfr.org/timeline/iraq-war" target="_blank" rel="noopener">U.S. invasion of Iraq</a>, in terms of <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/42940574.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">good and evil</a> as he tried to establish the GOP as the party of faith and strength. Democrats, meanwhile, in their 2004 party platform accused Bush and the Republicans of having an “<a href="https://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/documents/2004-democratic-party-platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">insufficient understanding of our enemy</a>” and a failure to comprehend the complexity of the situation in the Middle East.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">While the Iraq War was not directly related to Bush’s religious faith, both supporters and opponents alike depicted his <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna6371594" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approach to war</a> as reflective of his <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bs-xpm-2004-08-29-0408290144-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overall philosophical approach</a>: The president relied on gut and instinct, not expertise, to make decisions. Likewise, Bush’s 2004 presidential campaign portrayed his Democratic opponent, then-Sen. John Kerry of Massachusetts, as a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2QpS2Am51Wo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">waffling intellectual</a> who lacked conviction and patriotic dedication. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, the debate over the Iraq War quickly became an extension of the debates Democrats and Republicans were already having in the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/22/us/2000-campaign-matters-faith-bush-uses-religion-personal-political-guide.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2000 presidential election</a> — and <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2013/11/dukakis-and-the-tank-099119/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even earlier</a> — about religion, culture and Bush’s intellect and qualifications.   </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, the Bush administration’s justification for the Iraq War became the subject of widespread criticism across the ideological spectrum since the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2019/03/22/iraq-war-wmds-an-intelligence-failure-or-white-house-spin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rationale for invasion</a> was shaky at best. But the narratives Democrats and Republicans employed during the invasion of Iraq and the war on terror were still powerful for the ways in which they preyed on domestic and cultural disagreements and anxieties.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These arguments also had important implications for debates over presidential war powers. While many Republicans embraced an expansive role for the president — a strong leader asserting U.S. dominance on the world stage — Democrats said in their 2008 presidential platform that they “<a href="https://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/documents/2008-democratic-party-platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reject[ed] the sweeping claims of ‘inherent’ presidential power</a>,” and that their candidate, then-Sen. Barack Obama of Illinois, would better grasp intercultural nuance and policy detail. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But as president, Obama struggled with questions of war and war powers as well. Although his administration was committed to a less interventionist approach, world events still demanded attention. There were new questions to answer about American intervention in the Middle East and North Africa, as civil wars broke out in <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2011/03/24/obamas-unconstitutional-war/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Libya</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2018/04/02/what-policy-lessons-are-there-from-the-war-in-syria/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Syria</a>. And like Bush, Obama often found himself the subject of criticism — first for <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/what-exactly-is-the-war-powers-act-and-is-obama-really-violating-it" target="_blank" rel="noopener">going too far in Libya</a> and then for <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-mideast-crisis-syria-obama-analysis/syrias-civil-war-to-mar-obama-legacy-idUSKBN14228S" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not going far enough in Syria</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, the debate around the Iraq War didn’t help either Democrats or Republicans create a coherent set of ideas about how to engage with foreign conflict, how to prepare for the aftermath of one, or when it makes the most sense to avoid getting involved at all. Obama was different from Bush, but the foreign-policy questions he faced were still difficult — and domestic culture-war disputes were not especially useful in resolving them. Yet, because of the Iraq War, the country was now set on a political course that undermined the goal of meaningful, reasoned dissent on foreign policy. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Figuring out the role the U.S. should play following the Russian invasion of Ukraine requires answering a completely different set of questions than the global war on terror or the U.S. response to the war in Syria required, but as we saw in Vietnam, Iraq and elsewhere, culture-war politics are once again overshadowing the discussion of what to do. Instead of debating the extent to which Americans should intervene in Ukraine, Republicans have attacked Biden as a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-target-biden-blame-over-putins-ukraine-invasion-2022-02-24/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">weak leader</a> — and that’s the PG-rated stuff: Many attacks from the far right have veered into even <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/01/31/1077064951/global-culture-wars-some-far-right-groups-in-the-u-s-are-taking-a-pro-russia-sta" target="_blank" rel="noopener">uglier culture-war territory</a> and <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/former-trump-adviser-steve-bannon-backs-anti-woke-vladimir-putin-1682122" target="_blank" rel="noopener">praise for the Russian president</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, most rank-and-file Republicans have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-gop-is-still-largely-skeptical-of-putin-for-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unfavorable views of the Russian invasion</a>, not sympathy toward Putin. (Instead, a partisan divide is emerging over whether the U.S. should be “<a href="https://poll.qu.edu/images/polling/us/us02282022_umex87.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doing more</a>.”) Still, it’s not hard to figure out why the discussion of whether and how America gets involved in armed conflict has devolved into partisan point-scoring. Nearly everything has. But this has a real cost, and the answer isn’t for politics to stop at the water’s edge. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Dissenting viewpoints and serious debate are crucial in a democracy, and foreign policy is not an exception. Politics can and should be a place for real debate and multiple viewpoints. It is imperative to hold public officials accountable for their decisions. When we treat foreign policy as an extension of domestic cultural politics, we lose almost as much as we do when we act as though it’s not up for debate at all.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646913601600107</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>More States Are Proposing Single-Payer Health Care. Why Aren’t They Succeeding?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-states-are-proposing-single-payer-health-care-why-arent-they-succeeding/</link>
						<dc:creator>Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<category>Health Care</category>
			<category>Medicare for All</category>
			<category>Public Option</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">The Democratic presidential primary might feel like a lifetime ago, but one <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2019/12/19/21005124/2020-presidential-candidates-health-care-democratic-debate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">important storyline in that race</a> was health care — specifically single-payer health care, or the policy that the government should offer universal health insurance to everyone in the country. The nomination of now-President Biden, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2020-election/coronavirus-crisis-hasn-t-changed-joe-biden-s-mind-medicare-n1172361" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who opposed single-payer health care during the primary</a>, has put single-payer health care on the backburner nationally. But that hasn’t stopped the issue from impacting state legislators, who have introduced more single-payer health care bills in the last few years than ever before. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Health care policy researchers Erin C. Fuse Brown and Elizabeth McCuskey <a href="https://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=9687&amp;context=penn_law_review" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tracked the number of unique single-payer bills</a> introduced in state legislatures across the country from 2010 to 2019, finding a sharp uptick in bills introduced since 2017. During each of those three years, at least 10 single-payer proposals were introduced, according to Brown and McCuskey’s research, for the first time since 2013. In total, state legislators proposed more single-payer bills from 2017 to 2019 than in the previous seven years combined. And for 2021, we’ve identified 10 single-payer bills that legislators introduced across the country, from liberal states like <a href="https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=202120220AB1400" target="_blank" rel="noopener">California</a> and <a href="https://malegislature.gov/Bills/192/S766/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Massachusetts</a> to more conservative ones including <a href="https://www.legis.iowa.gov/legislation/BillBook?ga=89&amp;ba=HF55" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Iowa</a> and <a href="https://www.ohiosenate.gov/legislation/GA134-SB-253" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ohio</a>.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be sure, it’s possible this tally includes repeats of past years’ bills or bills that are not truly single-payer — Fuse Brown and McCuskey touch on some of the challenges of tracking this in their methodology — but the number of bills introduced last year shows that single-payer is still a popular legislative issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What do all these proposals have in common? They’ve all universally failed. In fact, Vermont, the only state that managed to pass single-payer health care in 2011, ended up <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/why-vermonts-single-payer-effort-failed-and-what-democrats-can-learn-from-it/2019/04/29/c9789018-3ab8-11e9-a2cd-307b06d0257b_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shelving its plan three years later</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It makes sense why single-payer advocates have tried to take these fights to the states. States have traditionally been seen as the “<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5594285/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">laboratories of democracy</a>,” and some advocates of single-payer health care have argued that liberal states <a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2021/10/state-federal-medicare-for-all-single-payer-health-care" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could provide unique opportunities</a> to advance single-payer health care. But as I’ll explain, passing single-payer health care at the state level is next to impossible, as states are particularly limited in how they can allocate federal and private health care funds. There is, however, evidence that Americans may have an appetite for a public option, or government-run health insurance that people can opt into at the state level. <a href="https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/research-and-analysis/blogs/stateline/2021/07/22/3-states-pursue-public-option-for-health-coverage-as-feds-balk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Three states</a> (Colorado, Nevada and Washington) have already passed a public option. It’s not single-payer health care reform, but it’s possible that we might see more states adopt their own public-option reforms.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One big reason single-payer proposals haven’t caught on at the state level is because finding a reliable way to pay for such a program is challenging. Single-payer advocates originally envisioned a federal proposal that would cover all Americans under <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/what-medicare-all-how-would-it-work-n1014256" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a more generous version</a> of a preexisting program — that is, Medicare, but now for all. Doing this state-by-state would require each state <a href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/forefront.20190717.466249/full/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to apply for waivers</a> to divert federal funds used for Medicare, Medicaid and Affordable Care Act exchanges to be used for their own single-payer plans. And that’s tricky because the Department of Health and Human Services has wide discretion to approve or deny states’ requests, which makes any proposal highly dependent on the national political climate. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This isn’t just a theoretical debate either: Trump’s administrator for the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services Seema Verma said in 2018 that she would <a href="https://www.modernhealthcare.com/article/20180725/NEWS/180729942/verma-will-reject-any-single-payer-state-waivers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">deny waivers from states to create single-payer systems</a>, while Biden’s Health and Human Services Secretary Xavier Becerra <a href="https://khn.org/news/article/fact-check-xavier-becerra-opposition-ads-single-payer-insurance-health-care-coverage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has expressed more favorable sentiments</a>. Almost all single-payer proposals depend on these waivers and states don’t often have fallback plans for if this federal funding gets denied.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Employer-sponsored health insurance plans, which <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/publications/2021/demo/p60-274.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cover 54 percent of Americans</a>, are another hurdle for states trying to pass single-payer health care. Federal law <a href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/forefront.20190717.466249/full/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largely prevents states from regulating</a> employer-provided health insurance, so states can’t just stop employers from offering their own health care benefits. The exact scope of this law has been <a href="https://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=9687&amp;context=penn_law_review" target="_blank" rel="noopener">litigated for decades</a>, but suffice it to say that it’s successfully put the kibosh on many statewide health care reforms. Single-payer health insurance is particularly tricky as there’s no way to get everyone onto the plan without first changing how private insurance works. States have tried to address this through measures like increasing payroll taxes or restricting providers’ ability to accept reimbursement from private insurance plans. But the more elaborate these mechanisms get, the more complicated it becomes to implement — and the more people that could slip through the cracks.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, another big financial barrier is that state governments <a href="https://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/what-are-state-balanced-budget-requirements-and-how-do-they-work" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have far less leeway than the federal government</a> to increase budgetary spending. That means tax increases, which come with their own political challenges, are often necessary for states to secure the funding they need.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Take California’s single-payer proposal, <a href="https://calmatters.org/politics/2022/02/california-single-payer-legislature/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">which failed in</a> late January. It would have required two-thirds of voters to pass <a href="https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billTextClient.xhtml?bill_id=202120220ACA11" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a separate constitutional amendment</a> to implement the necessary tax increases to pay for it. Concerns over tax increases also contributed to the demise of single-payer proposals <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2017/9/14/16296132/colorado-single-payer-ballot-initiative-failure" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in Colorado</a> and <a href="https://www.vox.com/2014/12/22/7427117/single-payer-vermont-shumlin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vermont</a>. It’s true that a recent analysis of New York’s single-payer health care plan found that it would lower overall health care spending <a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_reports/RR2424.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by 3 percent</a> by 2031, but it would also require additional state tax revenue of $139 billion in 2022 — over 150 percent of the current state budget. Politicians facing the next election cycle may be leery of proposing short-term tax increases, even if the end result is long-term savings.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All of this creates a daunting picture for statewide single-payer health care. But the failures of single-payer doesn’t entirely close the door on health care reform, especially if these reforms are supplementing the existing system instead of entirely replacing it. Colorado and Nevada, for instance, <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/22535267/public-option-health-insurance-nevada-colorado-washington" target="_blank" rel="noopener">successfully passed a public option</a> in 2021, joining Washington, which passed one in 2019. Colorado’s success in advancing a public option is particularly striking, given that almost 80 percent of people <a href="https://www.coloradoindependent.com/2016/11/08/coloradocare-amendment-69/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voted against</a> its single-payer proposal in 2016.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, though, efforts to implement a public option aren’t without their own challenges. In 2021, during its first year of implementation, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/03/22/health-202-states-are-eyeing-public-option-health-plans-many-obstacles-stand-way/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Washington state’s public option struggled</a> to enroll people and get health care providers to agree to lower payment rates. State lawmakers have tried to fix this problem by introducing legislation that would require more providers to participate and bring down premiums by increasing subsidies. Proponents have also cautioned that it might take years before the public option really gains a foothold with Washington state residents.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not clear yet how successful these state-run public option plans will be, but it is possible that a public option may prove more popular than single-payer. For starters, while single-payer health care is popular among Democrats, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=00000178-6298-d5c9-ab7c-e79a8aa50000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the public option still polls much better</a> among Republicans and independents. According to a Morning Consult/Politico poll from March 2021, the public option was roughly as popular as Medicare for All among Democrats — about 80 percent said they supported each. But support for the public option was much higher than support for Medicare for All among both Republicans and independents. Just 28 percent of Republicans and 50 percent of independents supported Medicare for All versus 56 percent of Republicans and 63 percent of independents who supported a public option. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, a public option may align more naturally with Americans’ existing views on the role of government in health care. Polls have long found that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/medicare-for-all-isnt-that-popular-even-among-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Americans still want a choice in their health care</a>, even though they believe that providing health insurance to the uninsured <a href="https://cdn1.sph.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/94/2021/05/RWJF-Harvard-Report_FINAL-051321.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is the government’s responsibility</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, any health care reforms would be easier to implement on a federal level than a patchwork, state-by-state approach. But Washington, Colorado and Nevada <a href="https://time.com/6077007/states-public-option-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remain important tests</a> of state governments’ ability to implement a public option in lieu of action by the federal government. It’s not single-payer, but it’s still some of the most consequential health care reforms in decades — and a potential sign of where the debates over health care are heading.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646828101299173</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Would It Take For Americans To Support War Against Russia?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-would-it-take-for-americans-to-support-war-against-russia/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Foreign Policy</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Poll after poll makes it clear: Americans don’t want to go to war with Russia over Ukraine. In an <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/three-quarters-americans-support-us-taking-ukrainian-refugees" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ipsos/Reuters poll</a> from March 3-4, adults opposed sending troops to Ukraine, 61 percent to 39 percent. In a <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/russia-ukraine-biden-state-of-the-union-opinion-poll-2022-02-29/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/CBS News poll</a> from Feb. 24-28, Americans opposed sending U.S. troops to defend Ukraine, 71 percent to 29 percent. In a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/aa58ig9d3b/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/The Economist poll</a> from Feb. 26-March 1, they thought sending soldiers to Ukraine to fight Russian soldiers was a bad idea, 54 percent to 19 percent. And a <a href="https://www.filesforprogress.org/datasets/2022/2/dfp_ukraine_a_toplines.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 25-27 poll</a> from Data for Progress found that likely voters opposed taking military action against Russia in response to the invasion of Ukraine, 64 percent to 23 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These numbers are hardly surprising in a country not far removed from <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-are-unlikely-to-support-a-war-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two unpopular, drawn-out foreign wars</a> in Afghanistan and Iraq. What’s more of a surprise, though, is that Americans are actually open to going to war with Russia under different circumstances: namely, if Russia continues its aggression and invades one of the U.S.’s fellow members of NATO.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Under <a href="https://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/topics_110496.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Article 5 of the North Atlantic Treaty</a>, NATO members are pledged to each other’s collective defense — if one of them is attacked, the others must respond. And Americans want the U.S. to stick to this obligation. Sixty-one percent of respondents to a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/e1pqcsj7ov/tabs_Russia_and_Ukraine_20220224.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> from Feb. 24-28 said the U.S. should maintain its commitment to defend NATO allies, while only 13 percent said this commitment was no longer necessary. A <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3838" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac University poll</a> from March 4-6 put it even more bluntly and got an even more emphatic answer: 79 percent of its respondents supported a U.S. military response to a hypothetical Russian attack on a NATO country.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that same YouGov poll suggested that, in reality, Americans’ appetite for war would vary depending on which NATO country is attacked. According to the poll, adults supported using military force to defend Great Britain, 58 percent to 14 percent, and France, 55 percent to 15 percent. But they were less supportive of using force to defend other NATO members, such as Latvia (35 percent to 18 percent) and Croatia (34 percent to 21 percent).</p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h5>Americans have a mixed view of helping NATO allies</h5>
 <p>Share of Americans who said the U.S. should be willing to use military force to defend various countries against a hypothetical Russian attack</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.support-escalation.1">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1">Country</th>
 <th colspan="1">NATO member?</th>
 <th colspan="1">Should</th>
 <th colspan="1">Should not</th>
 <th colspan="1">Don’t know</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Great Britain</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">58%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">14%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">28%</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>France</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>15</td>
 <td>29</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Germany</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>51</td>
 <td>19</td>
 <td>30</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Poland</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>18</td>
 <td>34</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Greece</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>19</td>
 <td>35</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Sweden</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>45</td>
 <td>21</td>
 <td>34</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Finland</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>21</td>
 <td>37</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Romania</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>37</td>
 <td>20</td>
 <td>42</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Latvia</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>35</td>
 <td>18</td>
 <td>46</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Croatia</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>34</td>
 <td>21</td>
 <td>46</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Turkey</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 <td>33</td>
 <td>27</td>
 <td>40</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Ukraine</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>31</td>
 <td>31</td>
 <td>37</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>Based on a survey of 1,000 adults conducted Feb. 24-28, 2022.</p>
 <p>Source: YouGov</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">This raises the possibility that Americans are passing judgment on individual countries’ worthiness of having the U.S. rush to their defense. While some of this is probably due to Americans’ unfamiliarity with certain countries (46 percent said they didn’t know if the U.S. should defend Latvia or Croatia), it is still notable that just 14-15 percent opposed intervening if Russia attacked Great Britain or France, while about 20 percent opposed it for most Eastern European countries, and an even higher share (27 percent) opposed it for Turkey. Therefore, even in the nightmare scenario where Russia pushes beyond Ukraine and invades another country, we shouldn’t assume that Americans will automatically favor going to war over it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There is, however, one set of poll questions that suggests Americans want to use military force against Russia <em>right now</em>. Multiple polls show support for a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/05/world/europe/what-is-no-fly-zone.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no-fly zone</a> over Ukraine. In the Ipsos/Reuters survey, 74 percent of adults said the U.S. and NATO should impose a no-fly zone above Ukraine. And in the YouGov/The Economist poll, 45 percent of adults thought enforcing a no-fly zone was a good idea, while just 20 percent thought it was a bad idea. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It seems likely, though, that many Americans aren’t aware that enforcing a no-fly zone would mean <a href="https://www.crisisgroup.org/europe-central-asia/eastern-europe/ukraine/no-fly-zone-ukraine-war-russia-another-name" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shooting down Russian airplanes</a> that violate Ukrainian airspace (which, of course, could escalate into a greater, possibly nuclear conflict with Russia). In the YouGov/The Economist poll, a significant number of respondents (35 percent) said they weren’t sure whether a no-fly zone was a good or bad idea. And notably, Ipsos/Reuters didn’t even give respondents a “not sure” option, which could explain why it pegged support so high. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible that a no-fly zone sounds to many Americans like a happy medium between two extreme options that we know from polling are both unpopular — going to war with Russia and doing nothing — and that’s why support initially registers so high. It’s impossible to know for sure, though, without more probing from pollsters. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A separate <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/03/04/britons-oppose-ukraine-no-fly-zone-39-28" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> from the United Kingdom (conducted March 3-4) gives us an idea of what more detailed polls might find, however. The poll explained, “Some are calling for a NATO ‘no-fly zone’ over Ukraine. This would mean that NATO countries like Britain would commit to shooting down any military aircraft attempting to fly over Ukraine. This could force the Russian military to stop launching air attacks against Ukraine, but it could also trigger an armed conflict between Russia and NATO countries if Russia chooses to ignore the no-fly zone.” Given this information, Britons said they opposed a no-fly zone, 39 percent to 28 percent (one-third were undecided).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, the U.K. isn’t the U.S., but the poll demonstrates how American support for a no-fly zone may be soft. After all, we already have plenty of clues that Americans may not fully grasp the gravity of a no-fly zone. According to a <a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/NPR_PBS-NewsHour_Marist-Poll_USA-NOS-and-Tables_202203010901.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marist College/NPR/PBS NewsHour poll</a> from March 1-2, 70 percent of American adults were concerned (including 36 percent who were “very” concerned) that the conflict between Russia and Ukraine would lead to the use of nuclear weapons. And according to a <a href="https://www.marugroup.net/public-opinion-polls/us/the-us-stands-with-ukraine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 25-28 poll</a> from Canadian consumer-research firm Maru Public Opinion, 61 percent of Americans thought there was a real chance that Russia would use nuclear weapons against countries that interfered in Ukraine. Although Americans are certainly not immune to holding contradictory opinions, that doesn’t sound like a country that’s ready and willing to shoot down Russian airplanes.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 19:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646769601845096</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>All But One House Republican Who Voted To Impeach Trump Faces A Trump-Endorsed Challenger</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/all-but-one-house-republican-who-voted-to-impeach-trump-faces-a-trump-endorsed-challenger/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>House Republicans</category>
			<category>Impeachment</category>
			<category>Infrastructure</category>
			<category>Primary Challenges</category>
			<category>Republican Party</category>
			<category>Trump Endorsements</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">With <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/texas-election-biden-state-of-the-union/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Texas’s primary on March 1</a>, the 2022 primary election season has officially begun. For most incumbents, that means working to win renomination by appealing to their party’s supporters and fending off any serious primary challengers. But for a small group of House Republicans, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/9-of-the-10-house-republicans-who-voted-for-impeachment-already-have-primary-challengers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their primary campaigns are complicated</a> by their vote to impeach then-President Donald Trump in January 2021, a move that outraged many Republican voters and <a href="https://www.wyff4.com/article/scgop-votes-to-censure-rep-tom-rice-for-voting-to-impeach-donald-trump/35371761" target="_blank" rel="noopener">earned condemnations</a> from <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/rep-herrera-beutler-censured-over-trump-impeachment-vote/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many local and state Republican officials</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of the 10 House Republicans who voted to impeach Trump in 2021, three have retired instead of running again, while all but one of the other seven has a Trump-endorsed primary opponent.<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be sure, the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1xPpzTTGOK_UAl1BGLW3ATw4VycJdsDArkgaZ4lV486s/edit#gid=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;candidate filing deadlines&lt;/a&gt; haven’t yet passed for these seven incumbents, so they could all still theoretically change their minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>16</sup></a> That means primary voters in nearly all of these districts will be able to choose whether they want to punish disloyalty to Trump and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-trumps-hold-on-the-gop-still-strong/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">move the GOP into even closer alignment</a> with Trumpism.</p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h5>Republicans who voted to impeach face primary challenges</h5>
 <p>The 10 House Republicans who backed impeachment, including whether they’re retiring, have a Trump-endorsed primary challenger and/or face another Republican incumbent in the primary by the partisan lean of their new congressional district</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.gop-challengers.7">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="3"></th>
 <th colspan="2">In primary, faces …</th>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1">Representative</th>
 <th colspan="1">District</th>
 <th colspan="1">Retiring</th>
 <th colspan="1">… Trump- endorsed opponent</th>
 <th colspan="1">… Fellow GOP incumbent</th>
 <th colspan="1">Partisan Lean</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Liz Cheney</td>
 <td>WY-AL</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>R+49.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Tom Rice</td>
 <td>SC-07</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>R+25.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Dan Newhouse</td>
 <td>WA-04</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>R+24.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Jaime Herrera Beutler</td>
 <td>WA-03</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Fred Upton</td>
 <td>MI-04</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td>R+8.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Peter Meijer</td>
 <td>MI-03</td>
 <td></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>D+2.5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>David Valadao</td>
 <td>CA-22</td>
 <td></td>
 <td></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>D+10.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Anthony Gonzalez*</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>–</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Adam Kinzinger*</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>–</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>John Katko*</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td><span>✓</span></td>
 <td></td>
 <td></td>
 <td>–</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>*Retiring and did not specify which district they might have run in.</p>
 <p>Sources: News reports, U.S. House of Representatives</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Opposition to these incumbents ramped up in February, most notably when Trump decided to put his stamp of approval on primary challengers in two of the three reddest districts represented by pro-impeachment Republicans: South Carolina’s 7th Congressional District and Washington’s 4th Congressional District. Trump’s endorsement <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-2022-endorsements-are-earlier-bolder-and-more-dangerous-than-when-he-was-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t guaranteed to make someone a winner</a>, but there is reason to think it can be helpful: Republican pollster Echelon Insights <a href="https://twitter.com/EchelonInsights/status/1499081885485514756/photo/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found in February</a> that an endorsement by Trump without support from local GOP leaders would give a Republican primary candidate a narrow edge of 3 percentage points, for instance. And while that was far weaker than a candidate who had backing from both Trump <em>and</em> local party leaders (+29 points), Trump’s support by itself was valuable, as candidates backed by only local officials (-10 points) or by neither Trump nor local leaders (-22 points) performed notably worse.<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Per Echelon, this question was conducted via conjoint analysis. Respondents of each party were given five matchups between hypothetical candidates assigned a series of attributes, such as age, professional background, endorser or political approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s start with South Carolina’s 7th District. At the start of February, <a href="https://wpde.com/news/local/former-president-donald-trump-endorses-russell-fry-calls-tom-rice-a-coward" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump endorsed</a> state Rep. Russell Fry in his bid to take down Rep. Tom Rice. Trump was likely attracted to Fry in part because the state legislator <a href="https://www.postandcourier.com/myrtle-beach/politics/donald-trump-endorses-russell-fry-in-primary-challenge-to-sc-congressman-tom-rice/article_863bba62-8387-11ec-ab26-63ae4d94c45d.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has backed Trump’s false claim</a> that the 2020 election was illegitimate. But Fry may also be best positioned to challenge Rice: He has outraised all the other challengers <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/SC/07/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still in the race</a>, and he came in third in a <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mq0hidvbl0dklfm/PollingProfessor-MemoFiveRaceSynopsis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">primary poll conducted by SoCo Strategies</a> back in early December. (Moreover, in a boon to Fry, the second-place candidate <a href="https://www.myrtlebeachonline.com/news/politics-government/article257828103.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropped out</a> just before Trump announced his support for Fry.) As such, Trump’s endorsement could help opposition to Rice consolidate around Fry in the <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/SC/07/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still-crowded primary field</a>, improving Fry’s chances of advancing to a possible runoff against Rice, as South Carolina is <a href="https://www.ncsl.org/research/elections-and-campaigns/primary-runoffs.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of seven states</a> that requires a candidate to win a majority of the primary vote to capture a party’s nomination.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then, about a week after backing Fry, <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/trump-endorses-loren-culp-in-challenge-to-wa-rep-dan-newhouse-who-voted-for-impeachment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump endorsed</a> Loren Culp, the former police chief of a small Washington town, in Washington’s 4th District against Rep. Dan Newhouse. Culp isn’t as strong of a pick as Fry — he’s struggled with fundraising, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/WA/04/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raising less than $150,000</a> through the end of 2021 — but he may have caught Trump’s eye in his 2020 gubernatorial bid when he <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/loren-culp-refusing-to-concede-washington-gubernatorial-race-turns-on-top-republicans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">refused to accept defeat</a>, citing unsubstantiated claims about election irregularities. He <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/state.php?year=2020&amp;fips=53&amp;f=0&amp;off=5&amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lost by 13 percentage points</a>. It remains to be seen whether Culp will gain more traction with Trump’s endorsement. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Washington has its own primary wrinkle, though. It uses a top-two system in which candidates from all parties run on the same ballot and the top-two finishers advance to the general election, regardless of party. This could potentially help Newhouse, as it’s not just Culp running against him. Jerrod Sessler, a former NASCAR driver, has thrown down about $350,000 <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2WA04165/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of his own money</a> and could attract some Republican-leaning support in the primary, too. But if Culp and Sessler are able to split the GOP voting base while Democrats largely back one candidate, it’s possible Culp or even Sessler edge out Newhouse for one of the two spots and join the Democrat in the general. Still, this district <a href="https://results.vote.wa.gov/results/20161108/congressional-district-4-us-representative_bycounty.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has sometimes sent</a> two Republicans to the November election, so it’s possible that it ends up being Newhouse and one of his GOP challengers.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Another endorsement raised eyebrows in February, but this one wasn’t from Trump. House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/17/politics/kevin-mccarthy-harriet-hageman-endorsement/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced his support for former Republican National Committee member Harriet Hageman</a>, the most prominent opponent of Wyoming Rep. Liz Cheney (who has been a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republican-voters-say-they-dont-mind-trump-critics-but-liz-cheneys-ouster-says-otherwise/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vocal critic of Trump</a>). Trump <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/09/09/politics/trump-endorses-harriet-hageman-cheney-challenger/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had already backed Hageman</a> in September, but it’s still highly unusual for a party’s legislative leader to endorse a colleague’s primary challenger. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Wyoming GOP appears to be done with Cheney, too, having <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/rep-liz-cheney-ousted-wyoming-gop/story?id=81206853" target="_blank" rel="noopener">passed a resolution</a> in November that essentially excommunicated her from the party. Helpfully for Hageman, most other high-profile Republicans <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/572403-third-republican-drops-out-of-race-to-replace-cheney-after-trump-endorses" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have left the race</a>, which should make it easier for anti-Cheney forces to coalesce around a challenger. Cheney already looks to be in real trouble. The early December <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mq0hidvbl0dklfm/PollingProfessor-MemoFiveRaceSynopsis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SoCo Strategies poll</a> found Hageman leading Cheney 39 percent to 19 percent, and prior surveys <a href="https://twitter.com/IAmNickReynolds/status/1420482244334952448" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found Cheney struggling</a>. Cheney does have a massive financial advantage, though: By the end of 2021, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/WY/00/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">she had raised</a> $7.2 million and had $4.7 million in the bank. By comparison, Hageman had garnered roughly $750,000 and had around $380,000 cash on hand. Cheney also appears set on staying in the race despite her difficulties, and some observers have speculated that <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/liz-cheneys-re-election-prospects-doubt-national-profile-grows-rcna17265" target="_blank" rel="noopener">she may even be looking</a> to take on Trump and his supporters nationally in 2024.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Cheney isn’t alone in having to push back against fierce intraparty opposition, though. While he hasn’t officially announced that he’s seeking reelection, Republican Rep. Fred Upton’s campaign <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/news/politics/elections/2022/02/22/fred-upton-running-congress-tv-ads/6898798001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">began running ads at the end of February</a>, so it looks like he’s angling to run again, or at least testing the waters. <a href="https://youtu.be/UMnMComd6SM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In the ad</a>, Upton told the camera, “If you want a rubber stamp as your congressman, I’m the wrong guy,” and Upton isn’t kidding: He’s likely to be the only pro-impeachment House Republican seeking reelection <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-house-republicans-who-voted-for-bidens-infrastructure-bill-could-face-serious-primary-challengers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who also voted</a> for the $1.2 trillion bipartisan infrastructure package — the other three have announced their retirements — which has <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/criticism-gop-infrastructure-bill-backers-grows-louder-mccarthy-stays-quiet-n1283759" target="_blank" rel="noopener">made him a target of the right</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But while Upton has given his opponents plenty of ammunition, he might also be in a better position than Cheney thanks to the particulars of his primary race in Michigan’s new 4th District. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-house-republicans-who-voted-for-bidens-infrastructure-bill-could-face-serious-primary-challengers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Upton faces fellow</a> Rep. Bill Huizenga, a more conservative incumbent who opted to run here after <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/michigan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his old district was carved up in redistricting</a>. This makes Upton the only pro-impeachment Republican also running against another incumbent, but both Upton and Huizenga must face Trump-endorsed state Rep. Steve Carra, <a href="https://www.detroitnews.com/story/news/politics/2021/09/07/trump-endorses-michigan-primary-challenger-u-s-rep-upton/5757497001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who has pushed Trump’s fraudulent claims that the 2020 presidential election was stolen</a>. Provided Trump sticks with Carra, whom <a href="https://www.sturgisjournal.com/story/news/politics/2021/09/08/donald-trump-has-endorsed-steve-carra-bid-unseat-u-s-rep-fred-upton/5762731001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he endorsed before Huizenga also challenged Upton</a>, that could actually make it easier for Upton to win a plurality if opposition to Upton splits between his two challengers.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As for the other three pro-impeachment Republicans who are running again, two of them face potentially competitive primary contests. In Michigan’s 3rd District, freshman Rep. Peter Meijer must contend with John Gibbs, a former Trump administration official who <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-congress-michigan-grand-rapids-impeachments-bfbb4564f73f2afdda6c5dbcb969c4ac" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has the former president’s backing</a>. Meijer has <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/MI/03/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dominated Gibbs in fundraising</a>, but a <a href="https://twitter.com/allymutnick/status/1496198857323069444" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll sponsored by EMILY’s List</a> found Meijer only leading Gibbs 26 percent to 13 percent, and trailing once voters were told that Trump supported Gibbs. This survey could definitely point to potential danger for Meijer, although we need to treat it with caution considering EMILY’s List, as an organization that backs female Democratic candidates who support abortion rights, would like to see Meijer lose his primary to improve the Democrats’ chance of winning the swingy 3rd District. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Washington’s 3rd District, meanwhile, Rep. Jaime Herrera Beutler faces veteran Joe Kent, who has Trump’s endorsement. This is another top-two primary, but there’s already reason to think Herrera Beutler might find herself coming up short, as a <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/WA03-22Primary-Feb-Poll-Report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">February poll</a> from GOP pollster Trafalgar Group found her running close to even with Kent in the low-to-mid 20s while Democrat Brent Hennrich led with 33 percent. If Hennrich does win most Democratic support in the top-two race, Herrera Beutler will have a challenging time finishing in the top two, as <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mq0hidvbl0dklfm/PollingProfessor-MemoFiveRaceSynopsis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other polling</a> has also shown her struggling to keep up with Kent among Republican voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Lastly, Republican Rep. David Valadao is the only pro-impeachment Republican in the House who lacks a Trump-endorsed primary challenger, and it’s unclear whether Trump will wade into this race. (Like Washington, California also uses the top-two primary system.) That may be in part because Valadao looks to have the toughest general election path, as California’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/california/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new 22nd District</a> is notably bluer than any of the other districts discussed here. Still, Valadao has previously won <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VfkHtzBTP5gf4jAu8tcVQgsBJ1IDvXEHjuMqYlOgYbA/edit#gid=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on Democratic-leaning turf</a>, so it could be Valadao who faces the least amount of electoral danger compared to the other House Republicans who voted to impeach Trump last year.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/trump-prosecuted-jan-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83309234</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646738101478150</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What Americans Want The U.S. To Do Next On Ukraine</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-make-of-polls-that-suggest-americans-want-a-no-fly-zone-over-ukraine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-make-of-polls-that-suggest-americans-want-a-no-fly-zone-over-ukraine/">
	<div data-podcast-id="327746" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What Americans Want The U.S. To Do Next On Ukraine">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP7366277998.mp3?updated=1646694436">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">A week and a half after Russian troops invaded Ukraine, we look at how Americans view the U.S. response so far. They overwhelmingly approve of the sweeping economic sanctions the U.S. has imposed, and a significant share support going further. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew analyzes new polling suggesting that Americans support enforcing a no-fly zone over Ukraine and banning the purchase of Russian oil even if that increases gas prices at home. They also discuss the accuracy of opinion polling conducted in Russia and Ukraine, and senior writer Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux discusses the possible legal case against former President Donald Trump for his role in the Jan. 6 insurrection.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 23:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646697601434850</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
