<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 06:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 06:59:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>We’re Hiring A Social Video Intern For Summer And Fall</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/were-hiring-a-social-video-intern-for-summer-and-fall/</link>
						<dc:creator>Meena Ganesan</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Meena Ganesan and Anna Rothschild</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Internships</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Jobs</category>
			<category>Housekeeping</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight is seeking an intern to work with our video and social teams during the summer of 2022. We’re looking for a current student journalist or recent graduate who is enthusiastic about accuracy, clarity, video production and storytelling; who is adept at building and cultivating communities on platforms like TikTok or Instagram; and is interested in sharing our wonky, data-driven approach to sports and political journalism with those audiences.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The intern’s main role will be to build up FiveThirtyEight’s video presence, engagement and following on social platforms. This means pitching and executing short social videos while developing and refining FiveThirtyEight’s cross-platform voice and tone. Should they have interest, the intern might narrate or host videos. The intern will also help with general video audience strategy and work with our senior designer and video journalists to repurpose existing assets for distribution on our website and other platforms, including Instagram, YouTube and Twitter.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Journalism experience (whether from a journalism class, school paper, job or internship) is a must, as is some experience reporting on politics. But “politics” doesn’t just mean electoral politics — it could mean you have experience reporting on policy issues, social movements, how polarization affects your community or something else.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The social/video intern will report to the senior editor for social and audience and the senior video producer but will also have the opportunity to work with reporters across the newsroom.<br><br>Applicants should be able to commit to a full-time schedule from May or June through August. They must be a current student or have graduated in the past 18 months. This is a paid position and can be done remotely.</p>



<h2><strong>Basic qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Some journalism experience</li><li>A solid understanding of U.S. politics and a prolific consumption of news</li><li>Enthusiasm for FiveThirtyEight and the kind of journalism we create</li><li>Demonstrated experience creating compelling social videos</li><li>Some experience with Adobe Premiere. Applicants should be able to cut clips and add music</li><li>Experience writing scripts and storyboarding</li><li>Experience behind a camera (a smartphone camera counts)</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Preferred qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Experience writing social copy</li><li>Experience using WordPress or a similar CMS to publish articles </li><li>Experience in front of the camera (a smartphone camera counts)</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Additional information</strong>:</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">If you don’t check every box, that’s OK — we’d still like to hear from you. <a href="https://xjobs.brassring.com/TGnewUI/Search/home/HomeWithPreLoad?PageType=JobDetails&amp;partnerid=25348&amp;siteid=5039&amp;Areq=939783BR#jobDetails=944582_5039" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Apply here with a résumé and brief cover letter.</a> Please include links in your cover letter or résumé to three social videos you’ve produced. They can be personal projects and don’t necessarily need to be journalistic.<strong><br><br></strong>At the time of application, the applicant must be enrolled in an accredited college/university and taking at least one class in the semester/quarter prior to participation in the internship program, or the applicant must have graduated from a college/university within six months.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This internship is a paid, remote internship and will run May/June 2022 through January 2023. Candidate must be available to work 40 hours/week on Eastern Time for the duration of the internship.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">ABC News and FiveThirtyEight are equal-opportunity employers. Applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, religion, sex, national origin, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability or protected veteran status.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 19:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646422202047625</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We’re Hiring An Art And Design Intern For Summer And Fall</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/were-hiring-an-art-and-design-intern-for-summer-and-fall/</link>
						<dc:creator>Emily Scherer</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Emily Scherer</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Internships</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Jobs</category>
			<category>Housekeeping</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight is hiring an <strong>Art and Design Intern</strong> for the summer and fall. Are you someone who loves using photography, illustration and design to tell a compelling story? Are you considering a career in visual journalism? The Art and Design Intern will work with FiveThirtyEight’s Senior Designer and story editors to make our stories as visually compelling as they are well-researched and written. It’s an exciting opportunity for someone with an interest in editorial design to have an outsize impact on a small team.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This paid internship will run from approximately May/June 2022 through January 2023 and can be fully remote if you live outside the New York City area. Current students at accredited colleges or universities are eligible, as are recent graduates who were enrolled in at least one course in the semester before the internship starts.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Art and Design Intern may work up to 40 hours per week (with some flexibility in schedule, as needed).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To apply, please send a cover letter, résumé and link to your website or portfolio through the <a href="https://xjobs.brassring.com/TGnewUI/Search/home/HomeWithPreLoad?partnerid=25348&amp;siteid=5039&amp;PageType=JobDetails&amp;jobid=944581" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Disney Careers portal</a>. Even if you don’t check all the boxes below, we encourage you to apply as soon as possible! If you have any questions about this role, please email <a href="mailto:emily.scherer@abc.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emily Scherer, Senior Designer</a>. </p>



<h2><strong>Responsibilities:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Researching, cropping and writing photo captions for stories</li><li>Applying stylistic treatments to photos to create visually consistent art elements for stories in a series (for example, World Cup updates)</li><li>Thinking through the order and pacing of images within a story to find the best way to keep our readers engaged throughout</li><li>Creating custom illustrations to lead daily and feature stories</li><li>Helping assemble stories in WordPress and contributing ideas for headlines and other display text to make sure all elements of the piece work well together</li><li>Collaborating with other FiveThirtyEight teams on video and interactive projects</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Basic Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Interest in pursuing a career in graphic design, art direction, photo editing and/or illustration</li><li>Experience in visual arts or photojournalism at the college level</li><li>Proficiency in Adobe Photoshop and Illustrator</li><li>Kindness and enthusiasm for collaborating</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Preferred Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Familiarity and interest in U.S. politics, sports and/or science</li><li>Proficiency in Adobe InDesign, After Effects and/or WordPress</li></ul>



<p data-paragraph="main">ABC News and FiveThirtyEight are equal-opportunity employers. Applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, religion, sex, national origin, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability or protected veteran status.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 16:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646413201497486</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Americans Are Still Unsure How The U.S. Should Respond To The Invasion Of Ukraine</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-still-unsure-how-the-u-s-should-respond-to-the-invasion-of-ukraine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>Foreign Policy</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">The ongoing war in Ukraine appears to have Americans in a bind: While roughly half of U.S. adults want to impose some type of punishment on or sanction against the Russian government for waging a war on Ukraine, another chunk of the country thinks it’s best for President Biden and others in power to stay out of European affairs.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">My colleague <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geoffrey Skelley previously documented</a> the sort of quandary many Americans are in regarding the war. And recent polling suggests that most voters are on the fence on where to go from here. That said, certain things <em>are</em> clearer based on recent polling: For starters, Americans are still <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">somewhat dissatisfied with Biden’s response</a> to the crisis. As my colleague <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nathaniel Rakich wrote</a> the day after Russia invaded Ukraine, Biden already had <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">low approval ratings</a>, including on his handling of foreign policy. Unfortunately for the president, though, his numbers haven’t significantly improved on the issue since. According to a <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/two-five-americans-approve-president-biden-handling-russia-ukraine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reuters/Ipsos</a> poll fielded in late February and early March, only 40 percent said they approved of the way Biden has handled Russia, while 43 percent said the same about how he’s handled Ukraine. Moreover, per the same survey, most Americans (63 percent) are against sending the U.S. military to Ukraine to help defend them against Russian forces — a reality <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-60499385" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden has said is off the table</a>. Other polls yield a similar finding: According to an early February <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/international/articles-reports/2022/02/11/americans-want-support-ukraine-not-us-troops" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economist/YouGov</a> survey, 55 percent of Americans said that sending troops to Ukraine to fight Russian soldiers was a bad idea.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Beyond that, though, public opinion is a bit murky, and the data suggests that Americans have mixed feelings on the U.S. response — whether that’s things like imposing sanctions on Russia (which experts warn <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/03/02/politics/russia-oil-exports-sanctions-ukraine-cnntv/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could raise gas prices here</a>), <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/International/natos-article-pull-us-allies-russia-ukraine-conflict/story?id=83108600" target="_blank" rel="noopener">allowing Ukraine to join NATO</a> or sending U.S. troops to NATO countries in Eastern Europe. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to that Reuters/Ipsos survey, roughly one-third of Americans (34 percent) said Ukraine’s current problems should stay their own. And per the Economist/YouGov survey, adults were split on a number of potential courses of action. On imposing economic sanctions on Russia, a bare majority (50 percent) thought this was a good idea, while 20 percent disagreed. Meanwhile, allowing Ukraine to join NATO earned the support of 43 percent of adults, compared with 15 percent who said that was a bad idea. And 42 percent of citizens said they wanted the U.S. to send financial aid to Ukraine; 24 percent did not. What’s somewhat striking from YouGov’s survey, though, is that large shares of Americans are simply unsure how the U.S. should respond. Thirty-one percent and 42 percent of respondents, respectively, said they didn’t know whether it was a good or bad idea for the U.S. to impose economic sanctions on Russia or let Ukraine join NATO. But, to some extent, these numbers should be expected, as Americans often <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Origins-Opinion-Cambridge-Political-Psychology/dp/0521407869" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t know a lot about foreign policy</a> and <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-2508.2007.00602.x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">look to political elites</a> to signal what to do. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the situation in Europe is fluid, so these numbers could change with time. Greater media coverage of the war will likely shape Americans’ opinions on the issue, but it’s also possible that more people will begin paying attention if things start to affect them personally — or if they start to feel even more strongly about Biden’s inability to handle international affairs. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/russia-waging-war-ukraine-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83167916</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, there’s already evidence that public opinion on the crisis in Ukraine has changed — particularly on the question of whether what’s happening overseas will increase the cost of goods and services, like <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/energy/ukraine-crisis-led-gas-price-surge-revives-demand-inflation-hedges-2022-02-28/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gas prices</a>. On imposing additional sanctions against Russia, 69 percent of Americans said they were in favor, according to a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/broad-majority-americans-support-russia-sanctions-poll-2022-02-24/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reuters/Ipsos</a> poll that was conducted in the <a href="https://www.usnews.com/news/best-countries/articles/2022-02-24/explainer-why-did-russia-invade-ukraine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two days prior to the invasion</a> on Feb. 24. But despite widespread support, only about half of the public said those sanctions were worthwhile if they led to more expensive gas prices. A <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/28/politics/cnn-poll-russia-ukraine-us-aid/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CNN/SSRS</a> poll fielded just after the invasion began found a similar result: Per the survey, 71 percent of Americans agreed that the U.S. should consider gas prices when deciding its actions toward Russia, a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/oil-natural-gas-prices-vault-as-sanctions-threaten-russias-commodity-exports-11646049246" target="_blank" rel="noopener">major oil and natural gas producer</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Beyond that, it’s hard to tell just how much Americans’ views on the war could change, especially given how volatile the situation is. But, so far, evidence suggests that as time goes on, <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/poll-74-percent-of-americans-call-russias-ukraine-invasion-unjustified-142128676.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the public is paying more attention</a> to European affairs. The CNN/SSRS poll found that 79 percent of adults were following the war at least somewhat closely, though only 3 in 10 said they were watching it <em>very </em>closely. Here at FiveThirtyEight, we’ll continue to cover what’s happening in Europe, but unless the war <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/26/1083283294/americans-react-to-how-the-russian-invasion-of-ukraine-could-impact-them" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has a more direct effect</a> on Americans’ day-to-day lives, it’s possible that the public won’t have strong opinions on this conflict moving forward. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>According to recent polling by <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/28/ketanji-brown-jackson-supreme-court-nomination-poll/">Politico/Morning Consult</a>, almost a majority of voters (46 percent) are in favor of the Senate confirming U.S. Circuit Court Judge Ketanji Brown Jackson <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/">to replace retiring</a> Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer. What’s more, the survey suggests that appointing Jackson to the high court garnered more initial support than that of any of President Donald Trump’s Supreme Court nominees. Morning Consult asked voters about the prior three nominees (Amy Coney Barrett, Brett Kavanaugh and Neil Gorsuch) when they were nominated as well and found that Jackson netted the most initial support overall, although Gorsuch came in a close second at 43 percent. Kavanaugh, meanwhile, whose confirmation was <a href="https://time.com/5677929/new-york-times-brett-kavanaugh-sexual-misconduct/">mired in allegations</a> of sexual misconduct and sexual assault, ranked third at 40 percent, while Barrett, whose confirmation was <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/10/amy-coney-barrett-supreme-court-gop/616727/">rushed by Republicans</a> in the weeks leading up to the 2020 presidential election, earned the support of 37 percent of voters at the time of her nomination.</li></ul><ul><li>As new COVID-19 case numbers <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/covid-data/covidview/index.html">decrease nationally</a>, some polling suggests that Americans are less willing to take the necessary safety precautions to protect themselves and others from spreading the coronavirus. Per a recent survey from <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/declines-in-covid-concerns-and-mask-mandate-support/">The Associated Press-NORC Center for Public Affairs Research</a>, just a bare majority of Americans (50 percent) approve of mask mandates — down 5 percentage points from August and 25 points from December. Republicans, many of whom <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-and-democrats-see-covid-19-very-differently-is-that-making-people-sick/">were against mask mandates</a> to begin with, were much less likely (22 percent) to say they were in favor of mask mandates compared with independents (43 percent) and Democrats (77 percent). Part of what’s driving the downtick in taking more precautions is that many Americans aren’t as worried about COVID-19 now as they were in December — at the time, 36 percent said they were extremely or very worried about it versus 24 percent who said the same in February — but Democrats and Republicans still have very different ideas about the types of precautionary measures needed.</li></ul><ul><li>A majority of U.S. adults said they believe that younger generations face more challenges than their parents did, according to polling from the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/02/28/most-in-the-u-s-say-young-adults-today-face-more-challenges-than-their-parents-generation-in-some-key-areas/">Pew Research Center</a> released late last month. Per the survey, issues involving money and savings were top-of-mind. A whopping 72 percent and 71 percent, respectively, said that things like saving for the future and paying for college are harder for young adults today. </li></ul><ul><li>At one point, it seemed like conservative Americans were <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/11/27/politics/republicans-leaving-fox-news-trump-analysis/index.html">abandoning Fox News</a>, opting instead for <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extremes-of-the-gop-have-moved-beyond-fox-news/">more right-wing outlets</a> like One America News Network and Newsmax. The reason for the switch? Last year, some GOPers reportedly <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2020/12/27/fox-news-viewers-switch-to-newsmax/">started to feel</a> as though Fox News wasn’t doing enough to address Trump’s false claims that the 2020 election was stolen and that its coverage was becoming too similar to that of other mainstream media outlets. February polling from <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/28/cable-news-credibility/">Morning Consult</a>, however, suggests that Fox News’s credibility is improving among rank-and-file Republicans. According to the survey, 69 percent of Republicans now say they find the outlet “credible,” compared with 59 percent who felt the same in May. Moreover, the share of Republicans who said they trust Fox News a lot or some also jumped 10 percentage points since May — from 60 percent to 70 percent. Of course, that doesn’t mean the party’s voters are abandoning Newsmax and OANN. Morning Consult found that two-fifths of Republicans ranked Newsmax as credible, while 31 percent saw OANN in the same light.</li></ul><ul><li>According to a February <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/70et3512ml/tabs_Life_and_Society_20220222.pdf">YouGov</a> survey, 37 percent of Americans believe demons exist, and 36 percent believe in ghosts. There was little confidence among the general public that werewolves and vampires exist, however; only 7 percent were firm in their belief that each of those entities exist. One fascinating find: Republicans were much more likely than Democrats to believe in demons. Half of Republicans (50 percent) said demons are real, compared with 3 in 10 Democrats (29 percent) who said the same. Republicans were slightly more likely than Democrats to believe in other supernatural beings (37 percent to 26 percent) and ghosts (38 percent to 33 percent). </li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval </strong></h2>



<figure><img width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a><sup></sup>41.6 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 52.9 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -11.3 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/stop-using-the-midterms-to-predict-presidential-elections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.1 percent approved and 52.5 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -10.4 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 41.5 percent and a disapproval rating of 53.0 percent, for a net approval rating of -11.5 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/generic-ballot-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 2.2<strong> </strong>points (44.8 percent to 42.6 percent). A week ago, Republicans led Democrats by 2.6 points (45 percent to 42.5 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 1.9 points (44.3 percent to 42.4 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646395201604877</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Americans Care About The Invasion Of Ukraine — But That Doesn’t Mean They Will Rally Around Biden</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-care-about-the-invasion-of-ukraine-but-that-doesnt-mean-they-will-rally-around-biden/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Foreign Policy</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">It was long thought that most Americans <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/01/26/will-foreign-policy-be-a-major-issue-in-the-2016-election-heres-what-we-know/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shrugged their shoulders at foreign policy</a>. Some political scientists posited this was because Americans saw international affairs as distant events that didn’t affect their daily lives; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_Almond#Almond%E2%80%93Lippmann_consensus" target="_blank" rel="noopener">others</a> believed it was because the public didn’t know enough about foreign policy to react intelligently to it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Americans’ overwhelming response to Russia’s invasion of Ukraine seems to fly in the face of that belief. Instead, it’s consistent with <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev.polisci.9.111605.105008?journalCode=polisci" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more recent research</a> that citizens not only have opinions on foreign policy, but also assess their leaders based on it. It turns out, research suggests, that not all foreign-policy issues are created equal: Most Americans may not concern themselves with day-to-day international relations, but acute international crises often do grab their attention.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev.polisci.11.060406.214132" target="_blank" rel="noopener">multiple</a> <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0022002701045005006" target="_blank" rel="noopener">studies</a>, one thing that can make Americans care more about foreign affairs is heavy media coverage of a given issue. And the media is heavily covering the war in Ukraine right now. According to <a href="https://api.gdeltproject.org/api/v2/summary/summary?d=iatv&amp;t=summary&amp;k=Ukraine&amp;ts=custom&amp;sdt=20220101000000&amp;edt=20220228235959&amp;fs=station%3ACNN&amp;fs=station%3AFOXNEWS&amp;fs=station%3AMSNBC&amp;fcs=comb&amp;fdn=raw&amp;fdr=day&amp;fdt=-05%3A00&amp;svt=zoom&amp;svts=zoom&amp;swvt=zoom&amp;ssc=yes&amp;sshc=yes&amp;swc=yes&amp;stcl=yes&amp;c=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">closed-captioning data</a> from the Internet Archive’s <a href="https://archive.org/details/tv" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Television News Archive</a>, from Feb. 22-28, the three major cable-news networks (CNN, Fox News and MSNBC) mentioned Ukraine in an average of 2,478 15-second clips per day.<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ran a search of CNN, Fox News and MSNBC coverage from Jan. 1 to Feb. 28 in the Television News Archive using the GDELT Television API. In that database, daily news footage is split into 15-second clips, and searches return the clips that contain a mention of our search query (“Ukraine”). The cutoff for measuring coverage for any given day is midnight Eastern Time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> On Feb. 24, the day after Russia started its invasion,<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia actually started to invade early on the morning of Feb. 24 in Ukraine, but it was still late on Feb. 23 in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> Ukraine was mentioned in a whopping 3,095 clips. To put this in perspective, during January, the word “COVID” was mentioned in an average of <a href="https://api.gdeltproject.org/api/v2/summary/summary?d=iatv&amp;t=summary&amp;k=COVID&amp;ts=custom&amp;sdt=20220101000000&amp;edt=20220228235959&amp;fs=station%3ACNN&amp;fs=station%3AFOXNEWS&amp;fs=station%3AMSNBC&amp;fcs=comb&amp;fdn=raw&amp;fdr=day&amp;fdt=-05%3A00&amp;svt=zoom&amp;svts=zoom&amp;swvt=zoom&amp;ssc=yes&amp;sshc=yes&amp;swc=yes&amp;stcl=yes&amp;c=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only 482 clips per day</a>. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Ukraine is dominating cable news" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nbA1g/9/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="575" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">Heck, on Election Day 2020, former President Donald Trump was mentioned by name in <a href="https://api.gdeltproject.org/api/v2/summary/summary?d=iatv&amp;t=summary&amp;k=trump&amp;ts=custom&amp;sdt=20201101000000&amp;edt=20201108235959&amp;fs=station%3ACNN&amp;fs=station%3AFOXNEWS&amp;fs=station%3AMSNBC&amp;fcs=comb&amp;fdn=raw&amp;fdr=day&amp;fdt=-05%3A00&amp;svt=zoom&amp;svts=zoom&amp;swvt=zoom&amp;ssc=yes&amp;sshc=yes&amp;swc=yes&amp;stcl=yes&amp;c=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only 2,675 clips</a>. In other words, Ukraine is utterly dominating the news.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And Americans say they’re watching. According to a <a href="https://www.filesforprogress.org/datasets/2022/2/dfp_ukraine_a_toplines.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 25-27 poll</a> from Data for Progress, 63 percent of likely voters said they have read or heard a lot about Russia invading Ukraine. And a <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/two-five-americans-approve-president-biden-handling-russia-ukraine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 28-March 1 poll</a> from Ipsos/Reuters found that 85 percent of adults said they were either very or somewhat familiar with the conflict between Ukraine and Russia. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And just as political science would predict, all that coverage is making Americans prioritize the issue. In a <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/poll-74-percent-of-americans-call-russias-ukraine-invasion-unjustified-142128676.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/Yahoo News poll</a> from Feb. 24-27, 86 percent of adults said the situation with Russia and Ukraine was either very or somewhat important. Of course, it’s easy to say an issue is important in the abstract, but even when respondents were asked to choose only one issue to be President Biden’s top priority, Russia and Ukraine came in first place with 23 percent (though it was tied with inflation). </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/russia-waging-war-ukraine-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83167916</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Similarly, 58 percent of adults polled by <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/russia-ukraine-biden-state-of-the-union-opinion-poll-2022-02-29/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/CBS News</a> on Feb. 24-28 said Russia’s invasion matters a lot to the interests of the U.S. And among Americans who planned to watch or listen to the State of the Union, more respondents (73 percent) said it was important for Biden to talk about Russia and Ukraine in his address than said so about any other issue, including the economy (67 percent), inflation (61 percent) and the coronavirus pandemic (52 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In sum, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/foreign-policy-doesnt-usually-affect-elections-could-iran-be-different/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first question we often have</a> when there is major news abroad — will Americans care about this? — has been answered. The public is clearly reacting strongly to the war. But that raises a second question: Will the crisis then affect how Americans feel about their president?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Immediately after Russia’s invasion, <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/white-house/596030-biden-shows-decisive-leadership-on-ukraine-itll-get-tougher" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some commentators</a> speculated that Biden could experience a surge in his job-approval ratings as a result of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rally_%27round_the_flag_effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rally-’round-the-flag effect</a>, or the tendency for presidents to get more popular in times of war. But so far, that hasn’t happened. According to the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight average</a>, Biden ended March 3 with a 41.6 percent approval rating, one of the lowest numbers of his presidency. There is no sign of a rally even in polls conducted entirely after Russia’s invasion: For example, Ipsos/Reuters gave him a 43/54 approval/disapproval spread, little changed from his 43/53 rating in their pre-invasion poll.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This isn’t surprising when you consider the actual mechanisms behind the rally-’round-the-flag effect. Political scientists have offered <a href="https://oxfordre.com/politics/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228637.001.0001/acrefore-9780190228637-e-518" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two causes of the phenomenon</a>: an upswell of patriotism in response to the crisis and a lack of criticism of the president that accompanies the crisis, as opposition politicians either show solidarity with him or keep their mouths shut. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Neither condition is met in the U.S. right now. Sure, Americans are showing a lot of solidarity — but with Ukraine, not their fellow Americans. After all, it has been Ukrainian flags, not American flags, adorning <a href="https://www.chroniclelive.co.uk/news/uk-news/add-ukraine-flag-facebook-profile-23235639" target="_blank" rel="noopener">social media</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/25/world/empire-state-building-eiffel-tower-ukraine-russia.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prominent buildings</a> over the last few days. According to a <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5a17333eb0786935ac112523/t/621ed33945b290698a3910e5/1646187323364/Ukraine+US++02+03+22+F.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 25-28 poll</a> from Canadian consumer-research firm Maru, 89 percent of Americans said they stood with the people of Ukraine against Russia. But since Biden isn’t the president of Ukraine, there’s little reason to expect this would help him.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And Republicans certainly <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-target-biden-blame-over-putins-ukraine-invasion-2022-02-24/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aren’t holding back</a> from criticizing Biden amid the crisis. The official Twitter account of House Republicans last week <a href="https://twitter.com/HouseGOP/status/1496206645919105031" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tweeted</a> a photo of Biden with the caption, “This is what weakness on the world stage looks like.” After the invasion, Sen. Ted Cruz <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/ted-cruz-russia-invaded-ukraine-because-of-catastrophic-mistakes-made-by-biden-administration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said on Fox News</a>, “The reason Russia has invaded Ukraine is because of catastrophic mistakes made by President Biden.” And Trump himself has <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/news/news-wg223arwqz1663" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said</a> Biden failed “terribly” in allowing the war to start.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, it takes a lot to trigger a rally-’round-the-flag effect. (Just think about how big a crisis would have to be to get Republicans to stop attacking Biden.) Indeed, <a href="https://oxfordre.com/politics/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228637.001.0001/acrefore-9780190228637-e-518" target="_blank" rel="noopener">research has shown</a> that international crises, and even small deployments of American troops, historically have given the president only a small boost in the polls, or none at all. Only all-out wars or large-scale terrorist attacks produce the kind of emotional response required for a significant rally-’round-the-flag effect — and of course, Biden <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/24/politics/us-troops-ukraine-russia-nato/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has pledged</a> that the U.S. will not go to war with Russia over Ukraine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, Biden’s approval rating could still increase as a result of Ukraine — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-explains-the-bump-in-trumps-approval-ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not because of the rally-’round-the-flag effect</a>, but simply because people like what he’s done to address the crisis. Last week, I identified a paradox in the polling on Ukraine: Americans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">disapproved of Biden’s handling of the situation</a> but <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">agreed with the specific actions he’s taken</a>, like imposing sanctions and not using military force. That’s still the case after the invasion: In the aforementioned YouGov/CBS News poll, 76 percent of adults said the U.S. should place economic sanctions on Russia, and 71 percent thought the U.S. should not send troops to Ukraine. But respondents still disapproved of the way Biden was handling the situation with Russia and Ukraine, 59 percent to 41 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible that, as time wears on, Americans will start to give Biden credit for his popular policies on Ukraine and that those numbers will come into closer alignment. According to Ipsos/Reuters, Biden’s approval/disapproval rating on Ukraine improved from 34/49 before the invasion to 43/47 after it. His State of the Union address on Tuesday could also hasten that along, given that he started the speech by talking about Ukraine (although historically, any boosts presidents have received from State of the Union addresses <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-bidens-first-state-of-the-union-might-not-change-much/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been short-lived</a>). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it’s also possible that the paradox is, in fact, a feature and not a bug. Political science tells us that people <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-2508.2007.00602.x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">turn to trusted political elites</a> to tell them what to think about foreign policy. And as long as Republicans keep telling their voters that Biden is mishandling Ukraine — while not opposing (even <a href="https://www.vox.com/2022/2/24/22948900/russia-sanctions-democrats-republicans" target="_blank" rel="noopener">supporting</a>!) his actual policy on it — partisan polarization may prevent Biden from reaping any political benefit.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646395201604876</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We’re Hiring An Associate Visual Journalist</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/were-hiring-an-associate-visual-journalist/</link>
						<dc:creator>Christopher Groskopf</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Christopher Groskopf</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Jobs</category>
			<category>Housekeeping</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight is seeking a kind and creative <strong>Associate Visual Journalist</strong> to join our Interactives and Graphics team. This entry-level position is ideal for recent graduates and career switchers, as it offers immediate access to the experience and mentorship necessary to become a thriving member of the Interactives team. Day-to-day work primarily involves creating static charts, but the Associate Visual Journalist will also have opportunities to work on interactives and occasionally pitch their own work.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Associate Visual Journalist will report to either the <strong>Deputy Editor, Interactives and Graphics</strong>, or the <strong>Senior Editor, Interactives</strong>, and work closely with the rest of the Interactives team, as well as with reporters and editors across the newsroom. This full-time role with benefits is a U.S.-based position. As our offices are in New York, we prefer candidates based in the New York area, but full-time remote work may be considered.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If you have questions, please email Deputy Editor <a href="mailto:chris.groskopf@abc.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chris Groskopf</a>. To apply, please submit a cover letter and résumé through the <a href="https://jobs.disneycareers.com/job/new-york/associate-visual-journalist-fivethirtyeight-abc-news/391/24578398160" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Disney Careers portal</a>. </p>



<h2><strong>Responsibilities:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Crafting static and bespoke charts to accompany daily and feature stories under the supervision of editors or more senior visual journalists</li><li>Contributing code and design to minor components of interactive projects as a sole contributor or to larger components when working in close collaboration with more senior visual journalists</li><li>Proactively learning whatever new technical skills and domain knowledge are necessary to succeed on each project</li><li>Collaborating with the Interactives team and the rest of the newsroom by actively engaging in routine workflow, such as copy editing, story check-ins and project retrospectives</li><li>Communicating project status, including unexpected roadblocks or delays, to collaborators and stakeholders in a timely fashion</li><li>Giving and receiving candid feedback to peers, colleagues and managers</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Basic Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>A passion for data visualization and crafting graphics that tell a clear story</li><li>Proficiency in Adobe Illustrator</li><li>Some experience using front-end web-development technologies, such as HTML, CSS and JavaScript</li><li>The ability to balance deadlines with opportunities to experiment and create new ways to visualize sports and politics data</li><li>Enthusiasm for collaborating with other FiveThirtyEight journalists on their beats</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Preferred Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>A solid understanding of U.S. politics, particularly electoral politics, major U.S. sports and/or science</li><li>Fluency in basic statistics</li><li>Fluency in at least one programming language, ideally JavaScript</li></ul>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is an entry-level position so if you don’t check every box but still feel like this would be a great role for you, please apply!</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">ABC News and FiveThirtyEight are equal-opportunity employers. Applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, religion, sex, national origin, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability or protected veteran status.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 15:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646323201172730</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>COVID-19 Has Left Millions Of Students Behind. Now What?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-has-left-millions-of-students-behind-now-what/</link>
						<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Education</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">If a kid isn’t keeping up with peers academically, summer school seems like a no-brainer. Instead of forgetting what they learned during the school year while they’re on vacation for two months, they’re catching up and getting ahead. Which is why it was a surprise when a <a href="https://www.rand.org/education-and-labor/projects/national-summer-learning-project.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rand Corporation study of summer school programs</a> in five urban school districts<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Boston; Dallas; Duval County, Fla; Pittsburgh; and Rochester, N.Y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> found that this common-sense solution … didn’t really solve the problem. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Rand’s study found that summer school offered modest, short-term improvements in math scores at best, but those improvements faded by the fall. Other metrics — performance in language arts, student attendance and overall grades — showed no meaningful link to summer school. “The effects were pretty underwhelming,” said Megan Kuhfeld, a senior research scientist with NWEA, a nonprofit educational testing and research organization.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Overall, summer school programs didn’t deliver on their promises. But some subgroups did benefit: the students who regularly attended the programs that were better at navigating hurdles like student retention. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s perhaps never been so urgent to make educational interventions like summer school work for kids. Two years into the pandemic, children across the nation are behind where they would have been academically if the pandemic hadn’t happened. To help bridge the gap, educational theories will have to adapt to the unique realities of actual kids’ lives and families’ needs. If they don’t, even the best ideas, with tons of evidence behind them, won’t work in the real world.   </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Kids learned plenty during the pandemic, Kuhfeld told me. The problem, she said, is that they aren’t learning as much or as quickly as they were each year before the pandemic. Nationally, third-graders in fall 2021 were, on average, testing significantly below where third-graders were testing in fall 2019 in reading and math. The NWEA assessments showed these declines extended across third-graders through eighth-graders, too.<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s judging by their percentile ranking relative to students who were in those grades several years before the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="863" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-desktop@2x.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-desktop@2x.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-desktop@2x.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-desktop@2x.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="621" height="1412" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-mobile@2x.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-mobile@2x.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-mobile@2x.png?w=621 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/koerth-learningloss-1-mobile@2x.png?w=1242 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Most of the experts I spoke to said the popular term “learning loss” is a misnomer — it’s not that kids have lost ground, they’re just not progressing as fast. But the slower progression is real, and there are patterns to it. The effects were particularly pronounced among Black, Hispanic and American Indian and Alaska Native students.  </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1872" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-desktop@2x.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-desktop@2x.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-desktop@2x.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-desktop@2x.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="621" height="4881" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-mobile@2x.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-mobile@2x.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-mobile@2x.png?w=621 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Koerth-learningloss-2-mobile@2x.png?w=1242 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In the NWEA data, the median percentile ranks for Black third-graders went down 10 points in reading and 14 points in math. For white third-graders, the median percentile ranks declined by exactly half of that (5 points in reading and 7 in math), while the median percentile ranks for Asian American third-graders fell by 3 points in both subjects. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In addition, there’s evidence of declines in attendance and high school graduation rates, something that could signal a broad sense of emotional disconnection from school. Which, in turn, could help explain slowed learning — or exacerbate it, said Dan Goldhaber, director of the National Center for Analysis of Longitudinal Data in Education Research.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Slowed learning during the pandemic doesn’t necessarily mean kids are doomed, however. In fact, other researchers like Torrey Trust, a professor of learning technology at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, said kids actually learned a lot of things during the pandemic that they might not have learned otherwise. For many, virtual classes meant more time with family, more skills with technology, and for some, even better educational experiences, free from bullying. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The other good news: Research shows that the slower progress documented by these test scores should be able to be fixed with small-group tutoring. “It’s not rocket science,” said Thurston Domina, a professor of educational policy and organizational leadership at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. “You get the kids in small groups and you can really give them customized instruction and focus on them.” When Matthew Kraft, a professor of education and economics at Brown University, reviewed several <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/23328584211042858" target="_blank" rel="noopener">meta-analyses of the effectiveness of various educational interventions</a> in 2021, he found that tutoring in small groups had a significantly greater effect on student test scores than changes in class size, longer school days or summer-school-type programs. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But while it’s relatively simple for researchers to run studies on classrooms or schools and figure out which interventions produce the best results, it’s hard for educators to take those findings and put them to work across America. The evidence doesn’t produce a solution — it just shows you how hard it’s going to be to craft a wide-reaching solution. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Case in point: those summer school studies. One of the biggest factors affecting the overall failure of summer school programs in the Rand analysis was that only around half the kids who attended one year didn’t come back for the next — and some kids didn’t even attend each day the first year. The kids who attended summer school habitually, for both years, did improve their math and language skills in ways that lasted all school year. But that group represented only <a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_briefs/RB9924.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">about 35 percent of all the kids</a> involved in the study. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So summer school works just fine — if you can get kids to actually go. And that sets up a whole other set of logistical complications that have to be studied and analyzed and implemented. It takes hiring the right teachers who have the motivation and specific interest in teaching summer school, Kuhfeld said. It also takes long-term dedicated recruitment of kids into the programs. Unlike with regular school, students don’t have to attend summer school, so getting them and their families to choose the programs means you have to build both interest and trust — neither of which is a given. And all of this takes money. “There’s a big gap between what should work in theory and what works in practice,” Kuhfeld said. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This kind of effect is depressingly common. When the George W. Bush administration set up a program to compile evidence-based educational resources in 2002, education specialists told me they’d hoped this program — the What Works Clearinghouse — would bridge the gap between academia and classrooms. They envisioned it as a way for teachers to get a better handle on how to use evidence-based interventions in the classroom. “We thought we would punch in third-grade math and get an answer,” said Rachael Gabriel, a professor of literacy education at the University of Connecticut.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it never worked out to be that simple. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In many cases, researchers I spoke to found that teachers — the people tasked with educating students and bringing those test scores up — didn’t have much control over which interventions they could use and how. Those decisions were made higher up in the chain of administration. A teacher might want to try something and not be allowed. Or they might be excited to try something that was allowed but not be given the funding or staff or bus transport to make it happen effectively. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Making things work in a classroom is different from making things work in a whole district or a whole state or the whole country. That’s something Domina learned when California’s State Board of Education tried to mandate all eighth-graders to take and be tested on algebra. The idea was very much based on evidence, he said. Studies showed that separating some kids into elite math and others into remedial math served to widen inequality and narrow kids’ futures. Giving kids higher expectations leads them to do better. So expanding access to algebra for all should have reduced test-score gaps between rich and poor, white and Black. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it didn’t. In fact, the opposite happened. Domina sees problems of scale — particularly staffing issues — at the heart of that failure. Offering algebra to everyone meant that schools needed a lot more algebra teachers, and quickly. But there were only so many fully qualified, highly skilled algebra teachers. A lot of kids, particularly the ones in lower-income schools, ended up with teachers who didn’t have as much experience and weren’t as effective at teaching the material, he said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That story is particularly poignant now. Small-group tutoring can help students catch up on what they didn’t get a chance to learn during the pandemic. But small-group tutoring takes staff — and schools are one of many industries suffering from staffing shortages. Experts like Kraft are concerned that <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/brown-center-chalkboard/2020/05/21/getting-tutoring-right-to-reduce-covid-19-learning-loss/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">schools might create failing tutoring programs</a> by using irregular volunteers or older students in place of dedicated staff. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Much like students, schools themselves aren’t necessarily functioning at a neutral, pre-pandemic state, either. “The biggest trend I’ve seen in the last 6-12 months is that schools are struggling to get the basics down. Staying open is hard,” said Chase Nordengren, the principal research lead for Effective Instructional Strategies at NWEA. He’s seen many cases where federal funds, which otherwise may have been spent on staffing tutoring programs to mitigate learning loss, were spent instead on things like better ventilation, personal protective equipment and substitute teachers. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“I think tutoring is a really promising initiative,” Goldhaber said. “But we have never tried to do tutoring at the scale that we are trying it today.” Because of that, he said, parents should be advocating for real-time evaluation and course-correction to go along with these learning-loss interventions. There should be tools in place to help teachers know when something isn’t working for their specific school and allow them to make the kind of personalized adjustments we know are necessary to make any intervention effective. But that, again, takes resources. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the end, it’s not kids’ pandemic test scores that really make researchers feel gloomy about the future of education. Instead, it’s the way educational systems have been set up to fail those kids. Schools have been running with limited resources and little wiggle room for change for at least the past decade, Domina said. “And now we’ve hit a crisis. And they’re not resilient.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646305288680624</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Do Americans Think About War?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-americans-are-unlikely-to-support-a-war-in-ukraine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<category>Afghanistan</category>
			<category>Iraq War</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Russia Invasion</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard to remember now that it’s over, but the war in Afghanistan was overwhelmingly popular when it began. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Merely a week after Sept. 11, then-president George W. Bush <a href="https://www.cfr.org/timeline/us-war-afghanistan" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed a joint resolution from Congress authorizing the use of force</a> against those responsible, and the U.S. and British, with international support, began bombing Taliban and Al-Qaeda forces Oct. 7. The American public almost universally approved this rush to war: A Gallup poll <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/208334/support-syria-strikes-rates-low-historical-context.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conducted soon after found</a> that 90 percent supported the war and only 5 percent opposed it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The circumstances, of course, were very particular: There had been an attack on American soil. When Bush’s war on terror expanded to Iraq in 2003, more Americans questioned the reasoning behind going to war — <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna7634313" target="_blank" rel="noopener">skepticism that turned out to be justified</a> — and there were <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/what-happened-to-the-antiwar-movement_n_5a860940e4b00bc49f424ecb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">high-profile protests</a> against the Bush administration, but still an overwhelming majority supported the effort: About 76 percent approved and 20 percent disapproved, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/208334/support-syria-strikes-rates-low-historical-context.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to Gallup</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With time, though, both wars became less popular. A Pew Research Center survey conducted last August, after the U.S. had fully withdrawn from the country, found that a <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/08/31/majority-of-u-s-public-favors-afghanistan-troop-withdrawal-biden-criticized-for-his-handling-of-situation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">majority of Americans supported the decision to leave Afghanistan</a>, even as a plurality thought the Biden administration had handled the withdrawal badly, while a July 2021 Gallup poll found that 47 percent of Americans <a href="https://news.gallup.com/opinion/polling-matters/354182/american-public-opinion-afghanistan-situation.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">thought the war had been a mistake</a>. Many younger Americans had grown up entirely during the war’s 20-year duration and so hadn’t formed an opinion at the war’s inception, while many older Americans had changed their minds as its costs multiplied over time.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/russia-waging-war-ukraine-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83167916</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Now, as the U.S. faces the question of how involved to be in Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, we can look back at these experiences of war, still not fully reckoned with, and consider how they might have shifted Americans’ understanding of the role U.S. foreign policy plays around the world. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To begin with, Americans seem more skeptical of more recent wars than those of the past. According to a 2019 YouGov poll, World War II was the most recent war in which a majority of Americans, about two-thirds, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-americans-agree-that-wwii-was-justified-recent-conflicts-are-more-divisive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said the United States’ role was at least “somewhat” justified</a>. Respondents said America’s role was less justified in every subsequent war the pollster asked about, with America’s involvement in Vietnam representing a low point of support, at just 22 percent. But of course, these assessments are made in hindsight, when the costs, successes and failures have been made clear.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are a few other hints that the American public may be war weary, though. In 2017, Gallup asked Americans whether they approved of the airstrikes the <a href="https://www.vox.com/2017/4/6/15215132/us-syria-bombing-trump-assad-chemical-weapons" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump administration launched against Syria</a> because of its use of chemical weapons; only 50 percent approved, a relatively low number. Sixty percent of Americans had approved of previous actions against the Islamic State group in Iraq and Syria in 2014, although only 47 percent of Americans approved of actions taken against Libya during the 2011 Arab Spring uprising. Before that though, a majority of Americans in Gallup’s polling on the question, which goes back to the U.S. invasion of Grenada in 1983, supported American military force, especially once the president had taken action. “Americans weren’t really enthusiastic about going into other countries after the other engagements we’ve had recently,” said <a href="https://www.gallup.com/people/100180/jeffrey%20m.-jones,%20ph.d..aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jeffrey M. Jones</a>, Gallup’s senior editor.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Iraq War may have made a lasting impression on whether the U.S. should attack a country preemptively: In 2020, 65 percent told Gallup that the U.S. shouldn’t attack unless it was attacked first, up from a range of 51 to 57 percent when the question was asked from 2002 to 2006, according to Jones.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it’s also true that Americans support defending their allies against nations they see as threats, according to <a href="https://www.thechicagocouncil.org/sites/default/files/2021-10/ccs2021_fpmc_0.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent survey from the Chicago Council on Global Affairs</a>. “What a lot of people always assume about the American public is that the American public is isolationist, is tired of wars and doesn’t want to get involved in the world, especially not militarily,” said <a href="https://www.thechicagocouncil.org/about/staff/dina-smeltz" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dina Smeltz</a>, a senior fellow on public opinion and foreign policy at the Chicago Council. But the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq haven’t dulled support for military involvement. “Instead of seeing a shrink back from getting involved, especially when there’s an ally involved, we’ve actually seen somewhat of an increase in support for using the military,” Smeltz said. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, Americans broadly back economic sanctions against Russia, but fall short of supporting military action. <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1BR8Cq98JXoKFaaBmfRD-7Cf_eOqmk8dV/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A recent CBS/YouGov poll found</a> that 82 percent of Americans were worried that the war could spread to the rest of Europe, but 71 percent were against sending troops. Americans also told CBS/YouGov that they wanted Biden to address the situation in his State of the Union speech Tuesday, even more so than the pandemic and the economy. And Biden <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/01/us/politics/biden-sotu-transcript.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spent over 10 minutes</a> at the beginning of his address on the crisis, saying that the American people stood with Ukraine and promising forceful action against Russia, including continued economic sanctions and creating a Department of Justice task force to pursue action against Russian oligarchs. “But let me be clear: Our forces are not engaged and will not engage in the conflict with Russian forces in Ukraine,” he added. “Our forces are not going to Europe to fight in Ukraine, but to defend our NATO allies in the event that Putin decides to keep moving west.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Typically, several factors determine the level of American support — whether the nation we’d theoretically be fighting against is seen as a threat to American interests, whether we’re allies with the country we’d be supporting and whether respondents feel the war would be successful with few casualties, Smeltz said. Americans see Russia as a threat and Ukraine as an ally, but it seems that many Americans think a war with Russia would not be quick and easy, which could explain many Americans’ hesitancy over sending troops.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Americans also typically support actions like diplomacy and air strikes more than sending troops to war. Other factors, like where in the world a conflict is, or which party the sitting president belongs to, don’t register as important in polls, Smeltz said. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But whether and how Americans favor U.S. involvement in foreign conflicts aren’t the only lessons from Afghanistan and Iraq. <a href="https://cla.umn.edu/about/directory/profile/fazal007" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tanisha Fazal</a>, a political scientist at the University of Minnesota, said modern military medicine has also altered how we should calculate the cost of war. More soldiers <a href="https://academic.oup.com/isq/article-abstract/65/1/160/5905233?redirectedFrom=fulltext&amp;login=false" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are surviving battlefield injuries</a>, but they’re coming home wounded. Fazal said that hasn’t changed how most Americans think about sending troops abroad — except for people who are caretakers of those who came home wounded. “They know that they’re going to be paying the cost of war,” she said. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646305288680623</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Unity From Biden, Disunity In Texas</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-unity-from-biden-disunity-in-texas/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>State of the Union</category>
			<category>Texas</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main"></p><p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/unity-biden-disunity-texas-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83199577</p>



<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-unity-from-biden-disunity-in-texas/">
	<div data-podcast-id="327518" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Unity From Biden, Disunity In Texas">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9171410373.mp3?updated=1646203196">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">It was a night of firsts: the first midterm primary of the year, in Texas, and President Biden’s first official State of the Union address. The <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a> crew discussed the key takeaways in Biden’s optimistic speech and analyzed the outcomes of the Texas primaries as results came in.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646237701608162</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Racism And Sexism Could Define Ketanji Brown Jackson’s Confirmation Hearings</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-racism-and-sexism-could-define-ketanji-brown-jacksons-confirmation-hearings/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Ketanji Brown Jackson</category>
			<category>SCOTUS</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">On Feb. 25, shortly after President Biden’s Supreme Court nominee became public, <a href="https://twitter.com/LindseyGrahamSC/status/1497218325394374709?s=20&amp;t=JJ9UXZnL7nPRsguZszodzQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican Sen. Lindsey Graham tweeted</a> that he expects a “respectful but interesting” hearing before the Senate Judiciary Committee. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If history is any guide, Graham’s right about it being interesting — but likely wrong about it being respectful. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden’s nominee is Ketanji Brown Jackson</a>, the first Black woman to be nominated to the Supreme Court. Jackson is highly qualified for the role — she has two Harvard degrees, nearly 10 years of experience as a federal judge and once clerked for Stephen Breyer, the justice she’s been tapped to replace. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But research suggests that despite that stellar résumé, her identity as a Black woman — plus her professional background as a former public defender — means that she’s likely to be described less glowingly, interrupted more frequently and asked more questions about her qualifications than another nominee would be. That means we could be heading for an ugly political spectacle, with Republicans attacking Jackson’s background and grilling her about how race might inform her work.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The vast majority of Supreme Court justices <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/01/politics/black-woman-scotus-nomination-diversity-what-matters/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been white men</a>. (The first Black man on the court, Thurgood Marshall, was confirmed nearly 55 years ago, and the first woman on the court, Sandra Day O’Connor, was confirmed just over 40 years ago.) So, for that matter, were <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/01/28/racial-ethnic-diversity-increases-yet-again-with-the-117th-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the vast majority of the senators</a> tasked with deciding whether to confirm those nominees. Perhaps as a result, researchers who study the Supreme Court confirmation process have found that when people of color and women began to be nominated to the high court, they were met with more skepticism — and treated with less courtesy — at their Senate confirmation hearings.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/sites/default/files/Boyd%20Collins%20Ringhand%202018%20-%20Paul%20Collins.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mining a painstakingly assembled database</a> of every transcribed statement made in every Supreme Court hearing held before the Senate Judiciary Committee between 1939 and 2010, political scientists <a href="http://clboyd.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christina Boyd</a> and <a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/people/paul-m-collins-jr" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paul Collins Jr.</a> and law professor <a href="http://www.law.uga.edu/profile/lori-ringhand" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lori Ringhand</a> found that although the sample size was small, there were noteworthy differences in how women and nonwhite nominees were treated.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In their sample, there are three nonwhite nominees (Justices Thurgood Marshall, Clarence Thomas and Sonia Sotomayor) and four female nominees (Justices Sandra Day O’Connor, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Sotomayor and Elena Kagan). Since the data goes through only 2010, this does not include the confirmation hearings for Justices Neil Gorsuch, Brett Kavanaugh, and Amy Coney Barrett.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> “We find that female nominees are asked more questions of competence,” Collins said. “We also find that female nominees and nominees of color are interrupted more and described in less stellar terms — words like ‘exceptional’ and ‘outstanding.’”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Usually, this treatment comes from senators of the party opposite of the president who nominated the justice. The researchers found that female nominees were <a href="https://theconversation.com/interruptions-at-supreme-court-confirmation-hearings-have-been-rising-since-the-1980s-104357" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than twice as likely to be interrupted</a> by senators of the opposite party. At some confirmation hearings, senators banter about scheduling or the nominee’s family, but <a href="https://digitalcommons.wcl.american.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1612&amp;context=aulr" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the senators dispense with that earlier</a> for female and minority nominees, which means those candidates are asked more substantive questions. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Women and minority nominees <a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/sites/default/files/Boyd%20Collins%20Ringhand%202018%20-%20Paul%20Collins.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are also pressed more heavily</a> on their judicial philosophy, which is often a coded way of questioning their competence to serve on the court. And there’s evidence that they are particularly likely to face skeptical queries about their outlook. For instance, during Justice Sonia Sotomayor’s confirmation hearings, the researchers found that nearly 20 percent of the questions asked were about her judicial philosophy — higher than any other nominee in the data except for Justice Samuel Alito and Justice Sandra Day O’Connor.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Embedded in those questions is often an assumption that female nominees and nominees of color will be biased — particularly on issues like sex-based discrimination and civil rights. During the 1967 confirmation hearings for Marshall, who would eventually become the first Black justice to serve on the Supreme Court, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/20/books/review/wil-haygoods-showdown-thurgood-marshall-and-the-supreme-court-nomination-that-changed-america.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">senators needled him</a> about recent Supreme Court decisions expanding rights for criminal defendants, heavily implying that they had contributed to rising crime, and targeted his record as a celebrated civil rights attorney, suggesting that he couldn’t apply the law impartially. One southern senator <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=NVZFAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA161&amp;lpg=PA161&amp;dq=%E2%80%9CAre+you+prejudiced+against+white+people+in+the+South?%E2%80%9D&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=yeAkja2Ljl&amp;sig=ACfU3U2VXGikn4ql3kj3VfB8xrGLec6hOg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjq17OfjaP2AhX7knIEHZe1AFEQ6AF6BAgCEAM#v=onepage&amp;q=%E2%80%9CAre%20you%20prejudiced%20against%20white%20people%20in%20the%20South%3F%E2%80%9D&amp;f=false" target="_blank" rel="noopener">asked him bluntly</a>, “Are you prejudiced against white people in the South?”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s no reason to think that the appeal of racist dog whistles has diminished over time. The professional and personal experiences that make Jackson an appealing nominee for liberals could easily be weaponized against her by the Republicans on the committee — not just her race and gender, but her career as a public defender and <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2022/02/profile-of-a-potential-nominee-ketanji-brown-jackson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">work on federal sentencing</a>. In January, during confirmation hearings for Andre Mathis, a Black lawyer nominated to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 6th Circuit, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/01/12/politics/andre-mathis-blackburn/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican senators tried to make hay</a> out of three traffic tickets — all more than 10 years old — that the nominee had apparently failed to pay, claiming that he had a “rap sheet.” And in a recent hearing for Nina Morrison, a white female lawyer for the Innocence Project who had been nominated to a district-court judgeship in New York, a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/02/17/nina-morrison-nomination-cruz-hawley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican senator argued</a> that Morrison would be more likely to “let more violent criminals go.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Other elements of the hearings could be just as much of a no-win situation for Jackson. Republicans may also try to use her credentials against her. <a href="https://twitter.com/LindseyGrahamSC/status/1497218325394374709?s=20&amp;t=K8HLMk3vUb5q9gyz4lhT6Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Graham has already commented</a> that “[t]he Harvard-Yale train to the Supreme Court continues to run unabated.” It’s true that most of the current Supreme Court justices have degrees from Harvard or Yale. And it’s also true that Biden’s Black female judicial appointees <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-bidens-appointees-can-tell-us-about-his-supreme-court-nominee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tend to have even more highly burnished résumés</a> than his average nominee. But while it’s certainly possible to argue that the court would benefit from more educational and socioeconomic diversity, it’s a new line for Republicans. Trump, for instance, appointed two white men <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/10/08/politics/supreme-court-elite-harvard-yale-clerks/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who didn’t just attend Harvard and Yale</a> — they also went to the same <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/07/10/us/kavanaugh-gorsuch-georgetown-prep.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exclusive Washington, D.C., prep school</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-biden-is-reshaping-the-courts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one expert pointed out</a> in a story I wrote last year, Biden may be leaning toward Black women with unimpeachable résumés in an attempt to mitigate racist criticisms about their qualifications. And it’s hard to imagine that Republicans would be any more likely to fall in line behind Jackson if she didn’t have two degrees from Harvard.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So it’s possible that Republicans could turn Jackson’s nomination — which will have no immediate impact on conservatives’ control of the court — into a racist spectacle. That might be red meat for their base of white conservatives since, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-oppose-bidens-promise-to-nominate-the-first-black-woman-to-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as FiveThirtyEight contributor Michael Tesler wrote last month</a>, GOP politics is increasingly energized by fears of anti-white discrimination. Biden’s approach to selecting a nominee makes that only more likely, since he guaranteed that he would select a Black woman. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But some research suggests that racist attacks on the first Black woman to be nominated to the Supreme Court could mobilize another important political group — Black Democrats. <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/political-science-research-and-methods/article/descriptive-representation-and-public-support-for-supreme-court-nominees/4044D595EFB6E1EC361314BF3319DB1A" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to a study published in 2019</a>, Black Democrats are particularly likely to prioritize having Black Supreme Court justices, perhaps because they’ve had so little representation on the court throughout its history. There’s evidence that Justice Brett Kavanaugh’s contentious confirmation hearing <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-kavanaugh-helping-republicans-midterm-chances/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">boosted Republicans in the lead-up</a> to the 2018 midterms. It’s not inconceivable that the same thing could happen for Democrats in November, depending on what happens next.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the meantime, the bleak reality is that Jackson could be in for a very tough confirmation process. But as a Black woman lawyer who’s risen to the height of her profession in spite of all the obstacles in her way, she’s probably pretty well prepared to deal with it.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/liberal-judge-ketanji-brown-jackson-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-83167862</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646219701647212</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Went Down At Biden’s State Of The Union And Texas’s Primary Election</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/texas-election-biden-state-of-the-union/</link>
						<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Economy</category>
			<category>Election Administration</category>
			<category>Election Results</category>
			<category>Inflation</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Live Blog</category>
			<category>Pandemic</category>
			<category>Politics</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>Sotu</category>
			<category>State of the Union</category>
			<category>Texas</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>White House</category>
			<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646183700838082</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Biden’s First State Of The Union Might Not Change Much</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-bidens-first-state-of-the-union-might-not-change-much/</link>
						<dc:creator>Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>State of the Union</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">This year’s State of the Union will be — believe it or not — the first since the beginning of the pandemic in the United States. And unlike last year’s speech (which was technically a speech to a joint session of Congress, not a State of the Union), attendance will not be capped this year and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/535-members-congress-invited-bidens-state-union-address/story?id=82981127" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all members of Congress are invited</a>, though guests still aren’t allowed. With both Russia’s ongoing invasion of Ukraine and President Biden’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historic Supreme Court pick in Ketanji Brown Jackson</a>, this year’s event is sure to cover a lot of important ground. But as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-state-of-the-union-doesnt-have-a-big-political-impact/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we’ve long documented at FiveThirtyEight</a>, the State of the Union (capitalized title and all) is more symbolic than anything else.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, Biden’s speech will still be an opportunity for him to introduce his legislative priorities to the public and to Congress. While the war in Ukraine <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/02/28/biden-state-of-the-union/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is poised to overshadow things</a>, Biden will also surely talk about domestic policy matters, such as <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/meet-the-press/ukraine-presents-biden-challenge-ahead-his-state-union-address-n1289895" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID-19, inflation and the economy</a>. But simply being a topic included in the State of the Union is no guarantee that Congress will act. From 1965 to 2020, political scientists Donna Hoffman and Alison Howard, who <a href="https://www.dominican.edu/news/news-listing/state-union" target="_blank" rel="noopener">track presidents’ policy requests</a> in State of the Union addresses, found that only 25 percent of requests presidents made of Congress were completely successful. Another 14 percent were partially successful, but a whopping 62 percent were entirely unsuccessful. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, as you can see in the chart below, some presidents have been more successful than others in getting their speech’s agenda through Congress. The number of requests has varied by president, too. Former President Bill Clinton made by far the most requests on average (57 per speech), including the most requests in one address (87 in 2000), whereas former President Jimmy Carter averaged around 16 requests per speech.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Presidents' requests have scattered success with Congress" aria-label="Stacked Column Chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/EZdqr/5/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="600" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">Congress also isn’t acting on as many presidential requests as it once did. The share of requests fully enacted by Congress peaked in the first year we have data for — in 1965, under former President Lyndon Johnson. And it’s mostly been downhill ever since, especially in recent years as Congress has <a href="https://www.axios.com/congress-legislation-covid-19-2020-28a81b79-8cfc-4fc6-8fa6-e1758dd5f81f.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struggled to pass all kinds of legislation,</a> thanks to <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-congress-stopped-working" target="_blank" rel="noopener">growing political polarization and gridlock</a>. The share of unsuccessful requests has steadily grown, and former Presidents Barack Obama and Donald Trump each had one year where Congress didn’t pass a single piece of their State of the Union agenda. It’s possible, too, that Biden won’t risk overpromising ahead of what’s expected to be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a tough midterm election for Democrats</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Regardless of how many requests he makes of Congress, Biden will probably be addressing a heavily Democratic audience. The audience for a president’s State of the Union is usually skewed toward the president’s party, as you can see in the chart below. Consider, too, that in Trump’s last State of the Union, 61 percent of Republicans said that <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2020/02/03/state-of-the-union-2020-poll" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they planned to watch</a>, whereas majorities of independents and Democrats said they didn’t plan to. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Partisanship drives State of the Union viewership" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/uFDxs/16/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="400" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that few people will tune in tonight. About 27 million people watched Biden’s joint address last year, which was <a href="https://apnews.com/article/entertainment-state-of-the-union-address-arts-and-entertainment-government-and-politics-b17d3b474c509d91bd97bf5bbc2f256f" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the lowest rating</a> for a State of the Union or joint address since Nielsen, a research firm, started tracking viewership numbers in 1993. (This viewership is especially meager when compared with Biden’s predecessor, who <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-donald-trump-hacked-the-media/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">often dominated media coverage</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So let’s say the audience tonight is small and already friendly toward the president. That’s not ideal for making up ground with the public at large. Indeed, that’s what Gallup’s polling of presidents’ approval ratings shows as well. Because Gallup’s polling goes back decades, we can look at presidential approval ratings before and after a president’s speech, and what we’ve found is little to no improvement in a president’s approval rating. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">State of the Union addresses coincided with an average improvement of just 0.4 percentage points, and a median change of 0 points. In fact, a president’s approval rating is just as likely to go down as it is up after an address (the average movement in any direction is 2.6 points).</p>


<div>

<section>
 <header>
 <h5>How the State of the Union affects presidential approval</h5>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.sotu-won-t-do.2" data-expandable-rows="20">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="2"></th>
 <th colspan="3">Approval rating before and after the State of the Union</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1">Year</th>
 <th colspan="1">President</th>
 <th colspan="1">Before</th>
 <th colspan="1">After</th>
 <th colspan="1">Change</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>1998</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">59%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">69%</td>
 <td>+10</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1996</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>+6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2005</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>51</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>+6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2019</td>
 <td>Trump</td>
 <td>37</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>+6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1994</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>+4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>45</td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>+4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1984</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>+3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2015</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>45</td>
 <td>48</td>
 <td>+3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1980</td>
 <td>Carter</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1995</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>Trump</td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>48</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2012</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>44</td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2018</td>
 <td>Trump</td>
 <td>38</td>
 <td>40</td>
 <td>+2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1988</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>+1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1992</td>
 <td>H.W. Bush</td>
 <td>46</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>+1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2003</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>+1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2014</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>41</td>
 <td>42</td>
 <td>+1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1982</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1999</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>69</td>
 <td>69</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>34</td>
 <td>34</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2010</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>48</td>
 <td>48</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2011</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1979</td>
 <td>Carter</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>42</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1986</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>64</td>
 <td>63</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1991</td>
 <td>H.W. Bush</td>
 <td>83</td>
 <td>82</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>64</td>
 <td>63</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2006</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>42</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1983</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>37</td>
 <td>35</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2002</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>84</td>
 <td>82</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2013</td>
 <td>Obama</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>50</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1978</td>
 <td>Carter</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>-3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1997</td>
 <td>Clinton</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>-3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1985</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>64</td>
 <td>60</td>
 <td>-4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2004</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>53</td>
 <td>49</td>
 <td>-4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2007</td>
 <td>W. Bush</td>
 <td>36</td>
 <td>32</td>
 <td>-4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1987</td>
 <td>Reagan</td>
 <td>48</td>
 <td>43</td>
 <td>-5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1990</td>
 <td>H.W. Bush</td>
 <td>80</td>
 <td>73</td>
 <td>-7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td colspan="3">Average change</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>+0.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td colspan="3">Median change</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td colspan="3">Average absolute change</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>2.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td colspan="3">Median absolute change</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>2</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <div><a>Show more rows</a></div>
 <footer>
 <p>Source: Gallup</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, there have been some big swings in presidents’ approval ratings following the State of the Union. Consider Clinton’s 1998 speech. At the time, he was mired in scandal because he had lied to the country about the sexual nature of his relationship with Monica Lewinsky, a then-24-year-old White House intern. But <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/02/05/opinions/state-of-the-union-donald-trump-bill-clinton-1998-avlon/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after a measured State of the Union speech</a> that never mentioned the scandal, but instead touted bipartisan accomplishments like a national budget surplus, he gained 10 points in his approval rating. Likewise, in 2019, Trump’s approval rating had fallen to 37 percent largely because he had just <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/government-shutdown-ends/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overseen the longest government shutdown</a> in history. But similar to Clinton, Trump tried to tout a bipartisan message, <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/4-takeaways-from-trumps-2019-state-of-the-union" target="_blank" rel="noopener">emphasizing cooperation and unity</a> on issues like infrastructure and cancer research, and afterward, his approval ratings recovered to his usual low 40s.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Biden’s circumstances are different, but like Clinton and Trump, his <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approval rating is quite low</a>, so the State of the Union could be a much-needed popularity boost for Biden. At the very least, it will be an opportunity for Biden to once again outline how he plans to handle <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/24/politics/us-troops-ukraine-russia-nato/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Russia’s invasion of Ukraine</a>, an issue that Americans so far <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">haven’t graded him too highly on</a>. And given the audience will likely lean heavily Democratic, it may even be a chance for Biden to rebuild his standing with Democrats whose views of him <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-have-been-souring-on-biden-since-last-summer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been faltering since last summer</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As is true for every president, the State of the Union is one of Biden’s best opportunities to tout his administration’s achievements, detail a plan for his administration in the upcoming months and communicate as directly to the public as he can. But ultimately, it’s the 500-some legislators in Congress who will be responsible for passing or not passing most of his agenda — and their minds probably won’t be swayed by a speech.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646134201869898</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Americans Are Unified Against Russia’s Invasion Of Ukraine</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-americans-are-unified-against-russias-invasion-of-ukraine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>Supreme Court Nominees</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-americans-are-unified-against-russias-invasion-of-ukraine/">
	<div data-podcast-id="326992" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Americans Are Unified Against Russia's Invasion Of Ukraine">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6020894661.mp3?updated=1646089267">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">On Thursday, Russian President Vladimir Putin declared a “special military operation” in Ukraine, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/24/world/europe/why-russia-attacked-ukraine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">launching an invasion</a> that has caused a humanitarian crisis and reshaped world affairs. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, host Galen Druke talks to Samuel Charap, an expert on Russia and Eurasia from the Rand Corporation, about the ongoing war and how tensions between Russia and Western nations came to a head in Ukraine. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The podcast crew also explains how the war is affecting American politics, and senior writer Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux joins to discuss President Biden’s nomination of Ketanji Brown Jackson to the U.S. Supreme Court and the impact she could have on the nation’s highest court if she’s confirmed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 22:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646089201244624</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Where Ohio Republicans’ Attacks On Dr. Fauci Came From</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-ohio-republicans-attacks-on-dr-fauci-came-from/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Anthony Fauci</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Ohio Primary</category>
			<category>Say What?</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main"><em>This is the latest edition of </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/say-what/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>our column</em></a><em> that excavates the origins of public figures’ extreme comments. We explain what their claims are referring to, the evidence (or lack thereof) behind them and where they sprang from in the first place.</em><em></em></p>



<h2><strong>Who said what …</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The race for the Republican nomination for Senate in Ohio is hotly contested, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2021/10/27/path-ahead-gop-runs-through-ohio-senate-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">closely watched</a> and full of candidates who more or less believe the same things — including that Dr. Anthony Fauci, the White House’s chief medical adviser, is a bad dude.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Each of the leading Republican candidates in Ohio’s Senate race have piled on the top doc throughout the campaign. Josh Mandel, a former state treasurer, <a href="https://twitter.com/joshmandelohio/status/1424560420128542720?lang=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tweeted last year</a> that the founding fathers would have “tarred and feathered Dr. Fauci.” Former Ohio GOP chair Jane Timken <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/577955-timken-rolls-out-six-figure-ad-campaign-hits-fauci-in-ad?rl=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rolled out a six-figure ad campaign</a> where she proposed to “fire Fauci.” Mike Gibbons, an investment banker, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MikeGibbonsOH/photos/a.471671659878827/1451800795199237/?type=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has called</a> Fauci a “liar” whose “credibility is shot.” And “Hillbilly Elegy” author J.D. Vance has called Fauci <a href="https://www.cincinnati.com/story/news/politics/2022/01/30/marjorie-taylor-greene-rallies-crowd-j-d-vance-ohio-senate-race/9252491002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a tyrant</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/JDVance1/status/1490030328525869058/photo/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pledged to reduce</a> Fauci’s salary to zero dollars and <a href="https://twitter.com/JDVance1/status/1435232117869490183" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accused him</a> of committing perjury. And while the Republican pile-on of Fauci goes <a href="https://www.wptv.com/news/political/gov-ron-desantis-sells-spoof-fauci-can-pound-sand-flip-flops" target="_blank" rel="noopener">beyond Ohio</a> — in fact, there was <a href="https://cpac.conservative.org/full-agenda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a series of speeches</a> under the title “Fire Fauci” at the Conservative Political Action Conference on Feb. 26 — it’s a recent case study that shows just how popular the hate for Fauci is on the right.</p>



<h2><strong>Some background …</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The COVID-19 pandemic thrust Fauci into the spotlight in an unprecedented way, and amid the partisan conflict over how best to handle the pandemic, he became <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/04/fauci-attacks-personal-conspiratorial-491896" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a target for right-wing critics</a> who blamed him for both the Trump and Biden administrations’ pandemic responses. These attacks preceded a change in public trust of Fauci. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In April 2021, the <a href="https://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/confidence-declines-in-cdc-and-dr-anthony-fauci/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Annenberg Public Policy Center</a> at the University of Pennsylvania found that 71 percent of Americans said they were confident Fauci was providing trustworthy advice on COVID-19, with 47 percent of Republicans saying so. By January 2022, 65 percent of Americans said they were confident in Fauci, while just 36 percent of Republicans did. </p>



<h2><strong>Where the comment came from …</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The most obvious source of the attacks on Fauci is the soured relationship between him and former President Donald Trump, who have a long, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2020/10/28/president-donald-trump-anthony-fauci-timeline-relationship-coronavirus-pandemic/3718797001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">well-documented history of conflict</a>. Being anti-Fauci is an easy proxy for politicians and candidates to convey that they are pro-Trump and anti-mandates (vaccine, mask or otherwise). And given GOP voters’ waning trust in the doctor, dunking on Fauci is an easy win for Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But whether or not they realize it, they’re also taking advantage of simmering conspiracy theories on the far right. Take, for example, Vance’s claims that Fauci perjured himself when he <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/05/18/fact-checking-senator-paul-dr-fauci-flap-over-wuhan-lab-funding/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told Congress the National Institutes of Health</a> does not fund gain-of-function research — research where an <a href="https://www.virology.ws/2021/09/09/gain-of-function-explained/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">organism, such as a virus, is altered</a> to give it a new property or to enhance an existing one — at the Wuhan Institute of Virology.<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Fauci made this statement, &lt;a href="https://theintercept.com/2021/09/09/covid-origins-gain-of-function-research/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;The Intercept obtained internal documents&lt;/a&gt; about research the NIH funded that some experts argue meets the definition of gain-of-function, though it &lt;a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/02/09/1044985/shi-zhengli-covid-lab-leak-wuhan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;remains a matter of scientific debate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>8</sup></a> Such a claim taps into a layered conspiracy theory that COVID-19 was intentionally created at the WIV. While the possibility of an accidental lab leak is <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2021/10/13/1045647249/who-covid-investigation-china-wuhan-lab-leak" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still being investigated</a>, there is so far no evidence the virus was created on purpose. On top of that, some conspiracy theorists believe it was intentionally created <em>by</em> the NIH, under Fauci’s direction, to facilitate the need for vaccines, which the conspiracists believe either kill you, give you AIDS, are the mark of the beast or play into various other colorful fantasies. These conspiracy theorists believe Fauci is a satanist, a member of the “deep state” and a pedophile who is responsible for the entire pandemic. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“IF we ever get the truth (bahahahahaha) we’ll find Fauci gave us AIDS, HEP C, certain CANCERS and other diseases,” wrote a user in a QAnon chat group on the messaging app Telegram, on Feb. 3. “So the Satanic forces in OUR Government is responsible for MILLIONS of deaths.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“[F]auci created AIDS to kill the homosexual community he created the MRNA vaccine to depopulate the world steal our children and get his adrenonachrome,” another user posted in the same Telegram chat, on Feb. 1, referring to <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/opinion-the-dark-virality-of-a-hollywood-blood-harvesting-conspiracy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the conspiracy theory</a> that elites torture children to elicit a fear response in the children’s bodies, thus creating a chemical called adrenochrome, which the elites then harvest and consume to become immortal. (The theory, so far as we can tell, is false.) “Trump learned about this and changed the vax to kill the population of the elite everyone who dies of covid after having the vax is of satanic bloodlines everyone else will get sick from it but should survive[.]”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be clear, neither Vance nor the other Ohio candidates have explicitly advanced these specific conspiracy theories, but the attacks on Fauci are red meat for individuals who believe them. The more vague and overarching the criticism of Fauci — such as calling him a “liar” or calling for him to be fired without specifying why he deserves to lose his job — the more easily they can be transposed onto the wildest conspiracy theories the internet has to offer.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 16:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646066701039743</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How To Watch Texas’s Primaries Like A Pro</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-watch-texass-primaries-like-a-pro/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Texas Politics</category>
			<category>Texas Primary</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Texas has found itself making headlines pretty frequently these days. Last fall, it dominated much of the news cycle with back-to-back stories about the state’s heavily <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/texass-new-congressional-map-could-give-a-huge-boost-to-gop-incumbents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gerrymandered congressional map</a>, coupled with a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-texass-abortion-law-may-go-too-far-for-most-americans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stringent abortion law</a>. And, just last week, the governor made headlines after he announced an order that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/23/science/texas-abbott-transgender-child-abuse.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would effectively penalize</a> people who provide gender-affirming medical care to transgender children, in addition to <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2022/02/23/greg-abbott-gender-affirming-care-child-abuse-directive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">classifying gender-affirming care as child abuse</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But now, the Lone Star State has another reason to stay in the limelight: After months of campaigning and prognostisticating, Texas’s primary <a href="https://apps.texastribune.org/features/2022/texas-2022-election-ballot-primary/?_ga=2.218788825.1111587308.1641394127-124119358.1641394127" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Election Day is finally (almost) here</a>. Texas is not only the first state to hold its primary election this year, but <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/36-states-are-electing-governors-this-year-here-are-the-races-to-watch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it’s also one of 36 states</a> hosting a gubernatorial race in 2022. And — to no one’s surprise — former President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.houstonpublicmedia.org/articles/news/politics/2022/01/30/418018/donald-trump-endorses-texas-republicans-at-conroe-rally-ahead-of-march-primaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hasn’t shied away from endorsing</a> a number of Republican candidates in the traditionally red state. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, there’s a lot to keep an eye out for, but here are the five main threads we’ll be tracking as results trickle in tomorrow evening: </p>



<h2><strong>Can Abbott beat opponents on his right flank? </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republican Gov. Greg Abbott is running for what on paper should be an <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/01/06/greg-abbott-2022-primary-campaign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">easy third term</a>: He has a <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/01/greg-abbott-beto-orourke-fundraising/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">colossal war chest</a>, the <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/06/01/texas-greg-abbott-donald-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsement of the Republican Party’s</a> current kingmaker (Trump), and an incumbency advantage. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, there are a few wrinkles in his plans for reelection.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For starters, he has a handful of Republican opponents on his right flank. And Abbott’s <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/07/04/allen-west-greg-abbott-texas-governor-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two most formidable challengers</a> — former Texas GOP Chairman Allen West and former state Sen. Don Huffines — have arguably <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/23/texas-primary-governor-don-huffines-allen-west-greg-abbott/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pushed the governor further right</a>, forcing him to confront questions about whether he’s the right fit to lead Texas. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/texas-worst-gerrymander-country-fivethirtyeight-83120405</p>


<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2020-swing-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In the last two presidential elections</a>, Texas has inched toward Democrats, but this hasn’t stopped Abbott from signing a number of <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/06/15/abbott-critical-race-theory-law/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racist</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2021/09/20/texas-state-politics-shifts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">illiberal</a> bills into law since 2020 that restrict everything from what is taught in the classroom to the manner in which Texans can vote. Yet this might not be enough for some conservatives in the state. The Texas Tribune reported in February that some Republican voters have begun to question whether Abbott has <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/03/texas-republicans-abbott-primary-votes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">done enough to deliver</a> on his initial campaign promises. And if that wasn’t enough to cast doubt on Abbott’s reelection chances, it’s possible that a local man challenging Abbott <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/12/13/rick-perry-texas-governor-springtown/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">named Rick Perry</a> — no, not the state’s former governor — will distract voters on the ballot who mistake him for the wrong person.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s arguably more working <em>in </em>Abbott’s favor, though. Since late last year, he’s led in every reputable, public statewide poll we could find that measured him against his Republican opponents — and by wide margins, too. According to an October 2021 <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/11/05/texas-poll-greg-abbott-beto-orourke/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Texas/Texas Tribune</a> poll, 58 percent of the state’s Republican voters said that Abbott would get their vote for governor. West, meanwhile, netted 12 percent of the vote, while Huffines received 7 percent. Chad Prather, a conservative commentator, earned 4 percent. And since then, Abbott’s standing among voters has only improved. Per a January and February <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zD7C_I4RR6loXEZMaJDouNOi0IpeAFBC/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Texas/Texas Politics Project</a> statewide survey, Abbott led all<em> </em>of his Republican challengers with 60 percent of the vote. No other Republican — including West, Huffines, Prather or Perry — received more than 15 percent of the vote among likely GOP primary voters. Moreover, in a recent <a href="https://www.uttyler.edu/politicalscience/files/dmn-uttyler-jan2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Texas at Tyler/Dallas Morning News</a> survey, a majority of Republicans indicated they like the way Abbott is handling his job as governor. Per the survey, 80 percent of Republicans said they either “strongly approve” or “approve” of how Abbott is doing his job. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Beyond the Republican primary, all eyes on the Democratic side will be on former presidential candidate Beto O’Rourke, who entered the gubernatorial primary <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/nov/15/beto-orourke-texas-governor-greg-abbott" target="_blank" rel="noopener">with a splash last fall</a>. Given O’Rourke’s initial <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/01/18/beto-orourke-fundraising-governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fundraising haul</a>, high name recognition and <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zD7C_I4RR6loXEZMaJDouNOi0IpeAFBC/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling advantage</a>, winning the Democratic nomination should be an easy feat. But in 2018, the last time O’Rourke ran a statewide race in Texas, <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2018/03/08/texas-primary-democrat-beto-orourke-confronts-hispanic-surname-advanta/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he fell short of expectations</a> during the Democratic primary — especially around the state’s border area counties. Plus, the dynamics this time around are much different: In the past four years, O’Rourke has run in — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-most-candidates-dont-run-again-after-losing-twice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and lost</a> — two high-profile races. And during his presidential run, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/09/12/politics/beto-orourke-hell-yes-take-ar-15-ak-47/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he took controversial stances</a> that could hurt his political standing in Texas. O’Rourke’s run for governor still tests a somewhat interesting proposition, however: Can a politician whose <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/02/11/beto-orourke-supporters-texas-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shine has dulled considerably</a> over the last few years salvage his reputation enough to not only clear the Democratic field — something that is still <a href="https://www.elpasotimes.com/story/opinion/2022/01/21/cristina-tzintzun-ramirez-column-how-can-beto-orourke-flip-texas-young-voters-color/6599184001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an open question</a> — but <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/01/greg-abbott-beto-orourke-fundraising/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also win a general election</a> in a state that hasn’t elected a Democrat to a <a href="https://www.politifact.com/article/2012/sep/26/texas-democrats-have-lost-statewide-elections-long/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">statewide office since 1994</a>? </p>



<h2><strong>Can Trump save Paxton from a runoff?</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">As we’ve documented previously, Trump has issued a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-2022-endorsements-are-earlier-bolder-and-more-dangerous-than-when-he-was-president/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">number of endorsements</a> for this year’s midterm primaries — including <a href="https://www.houstonchronicle.com/politics/texas/article/Donald-Trump-Texas-endorsements-16782422.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at least 20 Republicans</a> in Texas. For the most part, many of these statements of support have gone to sitting members of Congress (with a few notable exceptions). There is one race, however, where Trump’s endorsement will really be put to the test. In the race for attorney general, <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2017/01/12/tracker-attorney-general-ken-paxton-coverage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">embattled incumbent</a> Ken Paxton (who is<em> </em><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/26/trump-endorses-paxton-500804" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed by Trump</a>) faces a number of challengers that could make his reelection bid more difficult. Arguing he’s unfit for office <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/news-politics/the-republican-race-for-attorney-general-will-be-the-weirdest-wildest-and-most-telling-texas-election-in-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">due to his ethical and legal baggage</a>, there are three Republicans challenging Paxton this year: Land Commissioner George P. Bush, former Texas Supreme Court Justice Eva Guzman and Rep. Louie Gohmert (who, for what it’s worth, is one of the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/11/22/politics/louie-gohmert-texas-attorney-general-election/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fiercest Trump supporters</a> on Capitol Hill).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">While Paxton has <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1496476595124641795" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the largest war chest</a>, according to various reports, polls suggest a close race among the four Republicans, and it’s not clear whether Paxton can make it through tomorrow without avoiding a runoff (a reality <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1493235635909500932" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even he’s acknowledged</a>.)<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If no candidate in a Texas primary receives at least 50 percent of the vote, plus at least one additional vote, the top two vote-getters advance to a head-to-head runoff election &lt;a href="https://www.sos.state.tx.us/elections/voter/important-election-dates.shtml" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;on May 24&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>9</sup></a> Per a February <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/news/politics/2022/02/20/texas-gov-greg-abbott-up-7-points-over-beto-orourke-ag-ken-paxton-likely-headed-to-runoff/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Texas at Tyler/Dallas Morning News</a> poll, Paxton led Bush, 39 percent to 25 percent. Guzman landed in third with 13 percent of the vote, while Gohmert netted 7 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump, of course, is no stranger to butting into competitive elections and calling out Republicans he deems insufficiently loyal to him, especially those who <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democracy-is-on-the-ballot-in-these-11-secretary-of-state-and-attorney-general-elections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">haven’t vocally accepted</a> his false claims that the 2020 election was unfairly stolen from him. What’s interesting in this race, however, is that <a href="https://www.statesman.com/story/news/2021/07/27/trump-rewards-texas-ag-ken-paxton-key-endorsement-gop-primary/5388330001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paxton</a> isn’t <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/news-politics/louie-gohmert-ken-paxton-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the only Republican</a> to have the former president’s back. So, it’ll be especially interesting to see whether Trump’s endorsement is enough to save the incumbent from a runoff. And while we shouldn’t put too much stock in Trump’s standing in the GOP based on the results of just <em>one</em> Texas race, remember: The former president already <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-special-election-in-texass-6th-district-will-test-trumps-influence-on-the-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">suffered a small setback last year</a> when Republican Susan Wright — his choice candidate for a special election in Texas’s 6th Congressional District — narrowly lost her race in July to Rep. Jake Ellzey.</p>



<h2><strong>Who will win control of Texas’s newest districts? </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Thanks to Texas’s population growth over the last decade, the state gained two additional congressional seats — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than any other state</a> — during the reapportionment process. The question now, though, is: Who will win control of these new districts? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As my colleague Geoffrey Skelley and I <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/texass-new-congressional-map-could-give-a-huge-boost-to-gop-incumbents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wrote in September</a>, the two new seats (one in Austin’s metropolitan area, another in Houston’s) aren’t that competitive. In fact, following the redistricting process, there’s only one competitive seat left, near the border. This is in large part because legislators made a number of Republican incumbents’ seats even <em>redder</em>,<em> </em>while Democrats were packed into traditionally liberal — or once competitive — enclaves, like Austin and Dallas. <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">As a result</a>, the newest seat in Austin will be bright blue, while the Houston seat was intentionally drawn so that it’s favorable for a Republican. </p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h5>GOP incumbents are protected in Texas’s new proposed map</h5>
 <p>Change in partisan lean in Texas congressional districts held by Republicans, from the current map to the new plan for 2022 to 2030</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="samuels-skelley.texas-redist.4">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="2">DISTRICT</th>
 <th colspan="3">PARTISAN LEAN</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1">GOP INCUMBENT</th>
 <th colspan="1">OLD</th>
 <th colspan="1">NEW</th>
 <th colspan="1">OLD</th>
 <th colspan="1">NEW</th>
 <th colspan="1">CHANGE</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Dan Crenshaw</td>
 <td>TX-02</td>
 <td>TX-02</td>
 <td>R+9.1</td>
 <td>R+29.7</td>
 <td>R+20.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Beth Van Duyne</td>
 <td>TX-24</td>
 <td>TX-24</td>
 <td>R+3.5</td>
 <td>R+22.3</td>
 <td>R+18.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>John Carter</td>
 <td>TX-31</td>
 <td>TX-31</td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 <td>R+27.3</td>
 <td>R+16.1</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Troy Nehls</td>
 <td>TX-22</td>
 <td>TX-22</td>
 <td>R+8.3</td>
 <td>R+23.7</td>
 <td>R+15.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Michael McCaul</td>
 <td>TX-10</td>
 <td>TX-10</td>
 <td>R+9.2</td>
 <td>R+23.7</td>
 <td>R+14.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Chip Roy</td>
 <td>TX-21</td>
 <td>TX-21</td>
 <td>R+10.2</td>
 <td>R+24.4</td>
 <td>R+14.2</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Roger Williams</td>
 <td>TX-25</td>
 <td>TX-25</td>
 <td>R+16.4</td>
 <td>R+30.0</td>
 <td>R+13.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Jake Ellzey</td>
 <td>TX-06</td>
 <td>TX-06</td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 <td>R+24.2</td>
 <td>R+13.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Van Taylor</td>
 <td>TX-03</td>
 <td>TX-03</td>
 <td>R+10.5</td>
 <td>R+23.0</td>
 <td>R+12.5</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Randy Weber</td>
 <td>TX-14</td>
 <td>TX-14</td>
 <td>R+24.6</td>
 <td>R+35.2</td>
 <td>R+10.6</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Pete Sessions</td>
 <td>TX-17</td>
 <td>TX-17</td>
 <td>R+18.2</td>
 <td>R+27.1</td>
 <td>R+8.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Tony Gonzales</td>
 <td>TX-23</td>
 <td>TX-23</td>
 <td>R+5.1</td>
 <td>R+12.8</td>
 <td>R+7.7</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Michael Burgess</td>
 <td>TX-26</td>
 <td>TX-26</td>
 <td>R+23.3</td>
 <td>R+26.1</td>
 <td>R+2.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Jodey Arrington</td>
 <td>TX-19</td>
 <td>TX-19</td>
 <td>R+52.1</td>
 <td>R+53.3</td>
 <td>R+1.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Louie Gohmert*</td>
 <td>TX-01</td>
 <td>TX-01</td>
 <td>R+50.3</td>
 <td>R+50.0</td>
 <td>D+0.3</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Michael Cloud</td>
 <td>TX-27</td>
 <td>TX-27</td>
 <td>R+28.8</td>
 <td>R+27.8</td>
 <td>D+1.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Lance Gooden</td>
 <td>TX-05</td>
 <td>TX-05</td>
 <td>R+29.8</td>
 <td>R+26.8</td>
 <td>D+3.0</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Kay Granger</td>
 <td>TX-12</td>
 <td>TX-12</td>
 <td>R+30.2</td>
 <td>R+24.3</td>
 <td>D+5.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Brian Babin</td>
 <td>TX-36</td>
 <td>TX-36</td>
 <td>R+50.7</td>
 <td>R+34.8</td>
 <td>D+15.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Ronny Jackson</td>
 <td>TX-13</td>
 <td>TX-13</td>
 <td>R+65.9</td>
 <td>R+45.1</td>
 <td>D+20.8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>August Pfluger</td>
 <td>TX-11</td>
 <td>TX-11</td>
 <td>R+64.3</td>
 <td>R+40.9</td>
 <td>D+23.4</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Kevin Brady*</td>
 <td>TX-08</td>
 <td>TX-08</td>
 <td>R+49.7</td>
 <td>R+25.7</td>
 <td>D+23.9</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Pat Fallon</td>
 <td>TX-04</td>
 <td>TX-04</td>
 <td>R+56.3</td>
 <td>R+30.6</td>
 <td>D+25.8</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>*Incumbent is retiring or seeking another office.</p>
 <p>Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">What’s interesting, though, is that the favorites for both seats are household names in Texas political circles: In Austin, Rep. Lloyd Doggett, a 27-year incumbent who <a href="https://twitter.com/LloydDoggettTX/status/1456278167132442631" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has the backing</a> of House Speaker Nancy Pelosi, is largely seen as the front-runner for the seat adjacent to Texas’s capital. He <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/10/17/lloyd-doggett-austin-congress-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced the decision in October</a> to run in the newly created 37th District versus his current 35th District which, thanks to new redistricting lines, now runs through San Antonio. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Houston, Republican Wesley Hunt, who <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/texas-7th-district-house-election-lizzie-fletcher-wesley-hunt-2020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">made national headlines</a> during his race against Democratic Rep. Lizzie Fletcher in 2020, <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/01/26/texas-new-congressional-seats-primaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is also favored</a> to win the GOP primary in Texas’s new 38th District. Beyond his <a href="https://rollcall.com/2022/01/27/amid-jim-crow-2-0-rhetoric-some-gop-candidates-of-color-thrive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fundraising edge</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1486821642823208963" target="_blank" rel="noopener">internal polls</a> also give him the upper hand. And beyond that, he has the support of some <a href="https://wesleyfortexas.com/for-release-wesley-hunt-endorsed-by-senator-ted-cruz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">notable members of the GOP establishment</a>, like <a href="https://wesleyfortexas.com/for-release-wesley-hunt-endorsed-by-president-donald-j-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> and Sen. Ted Cruz. If both Hunt and Doggett win their respective primaries, they’re both expected to sail through a general election. </p>



<h2><strong>Will Hispanic voters near the border gravitate toward Republicans? </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Hispanic voters, on average, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/have-latinos-really-moved-toward-the-republican-party/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tend to support the Democratic Party</a>. But in 2020, Trump made decisive gains among Hispanic voters living along Texas’s border, winning 14 of the 28 counties there and flipping eight counties from blue to red. Of course, without Trump on the ballot it’s hard to tell just how much Texas’s Hispanic population will continue its rightward shift. But <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/14/ut-poll-march-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reporting so far</a> suggests that at least Abbott and O’Rourke <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/11/24/beto-orourke-2022-south-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are paying close attention</a> to get-out-the-vote efforts in South Texas, especially now that the state’s new redistricting lines make the area <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democratic-gains-in-texass-big-metro-areas-could-outweigh-republican-success-in-south-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less competitive for the GOP</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Beyond the marquee governor’s race, Republicans are also determined to flip the 15th District, whose Democratic incumbent, Rep. Vicente Gonzalez, <a href="https://www.borderreport.com/news/politics/incumbent-south-texas-congressman-now-running-in-neighboring-border-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decided to seek reelection in a neighboring district</a> (the 34th District) after redistricting made his original seat more competitive. What’s more, the Republican candidate who gave Gonzalez a surprisingly close race in 2020, Monica De La Cruz, <a href="https://myfox8.com/news/republican-challenger-to-run-again-after-narrow-loss-in-texas-border-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is running in the 15th District again</a> and national Republicans, <a href="https://www.monicaforcongress.us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">including Trump</a>, have lined up to support her. The Democratic primary in that district, on the other hand, has been rather quiet. While a handful of Democrats are running for the seat, arguably <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/11/01/texas-rio-grande-valley-congress-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">none have gained quite the amount of traction</a> De La Cruz has.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s at least one other border-area congressional primary that’s drawn national attention in recent months, too: the rematch between Democratic Rep. Henry Cuellar and progressive Jessica Cisneros, a <a href="https://jessicacisnerosforcongress.com/about/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">human rights lawyer</a>, in the 28th District. In 2020, Cuellar narrowly <a href="https://www.tpr.org/news/2020-03-04/henry-cuellar-narrowly-defeats-jessica-cisneros-in-tx-28-democratic-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eked out a win</a>, but his odds this time around are less certain. While Cueller has <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1488264795014844416" target="_blank" rel="noopener">incumbency on his side</a>, his home and campaign office were raided last month, as he is <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/feds-issue-subpoenas-seeking-records-related-rep-cuellar/story?id=82405832" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reportedly under federal investigation</a> for connections he might have to companies or organizations connected to Azerbaijan. (In reviewing subpoenas associated with the investigation, ABC News found that many subjects had ties to the former Soviet Republic.) Cisneros, meanwhile, has the backing of <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/j-street-jessica-cisneros-progressive-primary-texas_n_620af758e4b0ccfb3e59a71d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">notable fundraisers</a> and congressional progressives, like New York Rep. <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/alexdria-ocasio-cortez-aoc-jessica-cisneros-henry-cuellar-1299514/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</a> and Sen. <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/14/politics/bernie-sanders-jessica-cisneros-henry-cuellar-texas-primary/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bernie Sanders</a>. She has also attempted to focus her campaign on <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/02/23/south-texas-star-left-progressive-00010774" target="_blank" rel="noopener">local issues impacting the district</a> versus <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/news-politics/democrats-losing-texas-latinos-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national progressive talking points</a> that pundits (<a href="https://www.axios.com/cuellar-progressive-policy-south-texas-trump-biden-c3c1bab4-cbbf-422f-b4b9-524d98889a8b.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and Cuellar</a>) previously warned might turn off Hispanic voters in the state. Still, beyond the FBI’s reported probe into Cuellar, this race could, once again, serve as a litmus test to how far left Hispanic voters living in the district are willing to go. Cuellar so far has <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/08/05/jessica-cisneros-henry-cuellar-democratic-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">campaigned as a moderate</a> with more experience, but it’s unclear whether that’ll be enough to overcome a potential scandal. </p>



<h2><strong>How will new voting laws affect turnout? </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Texas is one of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/texass-new-law-is-the-climax-of-a-record-shattering-year-for-voting-restrictions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at least 21 states</a> that enacted a new voting law since the 2020 election. But even before these latest restrictions, it was hard to vote in Texas: According to the <a href="https://www.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/elj.2020.0666" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cost of voting index</a>, which evaluates state voting guidelines in their entirety, Texas in 2020 had the most restrictive electoral climate in the country. Taken together, that leaves a big question mark over how things like voting by mail, registering to vote and in-person voting will impact this year’s races. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The law, which among other provisions <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/09/01/texas-voting-bill-greg-abbott/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">requires absentee voters to provide specific information</a> about their Social Security or driver’s license numbers on their absentee-ballot application and gives more power to partisan poll watchers, is already creating some <a href="https://www.austinmonitor.com/stories/2022/02/election-officials-say-texas-new-id-rules-for-voting-by-mail-could-cause-more-ballots-to-get-rejected/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new barriers for voters and election administrators</a>, too. In some of the state’s biggest counties, like Harris and Tarrant, many Texans deemed eligible to vote by mail initially <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/01/24/texas-vote-by-mail-rejections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saw their mail-in ballot applications rejected</a> due to new — and more strict — proof of identity requirements. Moreover, according to recent reports, some mail-in applications <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/08/politics/texas-voting-law-issues/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were submitted to the wrong office</a>, which local officials said derailed the process of getting mail-in ballots to the right people in time. Other issues, like <a href="https://www.khou.com/article/news/politics/texas-voter-registration-card-shortage/285-31662e47-f067-49db-9bce-6739c41ef427" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a shortage of voter registration forms</a> have plagued the state, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, it’s difficult to say with any certainty how many people might not vote as a result of Texas’s law (the state <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/14/texas-primary-voting-turnout/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is already known</a> for its historically low voter turnout). But <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/02/14/texas-primary-voting-turnout/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early voting numbers</a> so far suggest that a number of voters are sitting out this year’s races — likely due to the voting law, a lack of enthusiasm or, probably, a mixture of both.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Whew, that’s a lot to watch. But if you’ve read this far, then I bet you’d be interested in keeping up with our live blog of the election results that’ll kick off tomorrow evening. Starting Tuesday evening at 7:30 p.m. Eastern, join us at FiveThirtyEight as we discuss all things Texas and dissect the results.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1646048700904492</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Will Americans Grade Biden’s Handling Of The Crisis In Ukraine?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-will-americans-grade-bidens-handling-of-the-crisis-in-ukraine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Foreign Policy</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Russia’s invasion of Ukraine will have far more serious repercussions around the world than on U.S. domestic politics. We at FiveThirtyEight are experts on the latter, though, so here’s a look at how the conflict might affect President Biden’s political standing. (With war breaking out only this week, it’s too early to say anything for sure, so consider this a scene-setter of sorts.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First, Biden starts off this crisis with low marks from the American public on foreign policy. In five polls conducted this month,<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/390086/biden-ratings-economy-foreign-affairs-russia-near.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Gallup&lt;/a&gt; (Feb. 1-17), &lt;a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3835" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Quinnipiac University&lt;/a&gt; (Feb. 10-14), &lt;a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/americas-role-in-the-russia-and-ukraine-situation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;The Associated Press/NORC Center for Public Affairs Research&lt;/a&gt; (Feb. 18-21), &lt;a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/23/voters-divided-biden-foreign-policy-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Morning Consult/Politico&lt;/a&gt; (Feb. 19-21) and &lt;a href="https://www.foxnews.com/official-polls/fox-news-poll-president-biden-not-tough-russia" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Fox News&lt;/a&gt; (Feb. 19-22). The first three polls surveyed adults, while the last two surveyed registered voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>10</sup></a> between 52 percent and 58 percent of respondents said they disapproved of Biden’s handling of foreign policy; only 35-44 percent said they approved.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those numbers, however, were likely a hangover from <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/taliban-afghanistan-79496986" target="_blank" rel="noopener">August</a>, when the last American troops started withdrawing from Afghanistan and the Taliban retook control of the nation two weeks before the U.S. evacuation was complete, exacerbating a <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/International/video/afghanistan-faces-humanitarian-crisis-taliban-takes-control-79521011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">humanitarian crisis</a>. Americans were <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-americans-think-about-the-end-of-the-afghanistan-war-and-bidens-handling-of-it-so-far/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unhappy with how Biden handled that situation</a>, and his approval ratings on foreign policy have not moved much since then. For example, Biden’s approval/disapproval rating on foreign policy in an Aug. 28-30 <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/23/voters-divided-biden-foreign-policy-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult/Politico</a> poll was 37/52 — exactly where it was last weekend.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Views of how Biden is handling the Ukraine-Russia crisis weren’t that different. According to a Feb. 18-21 poll from <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/americas-role-in-the-russia-and-ukraine-situation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Associated Press/NORC Center for Public Affairs Research</a>, Americans disapproved of Biden’s handling of “the U.S. relationship with Russia” by 56 percent to 43 percent. Meanwhile, a Feb. 1-17 <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/390086/biden-ratings-economy-foreign-affairs-russia-near.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup</a> poll found that Americans disapproved of his handling of “the situation with Russia” by 55 percent to 36 percent. And in a Feb. 10-14 <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3835" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac University</a> poll, Americans disapproved of his handling of “tensions between Russia and Ukraine” by 54 percent to 34 percent. These figures were all within a few points of his approval numbers on foreign policy more generally in those polls. (In addition, a Feb. 19-22 <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/official-polls/fox-news-poll-president-biden-not-tough-russia" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fox News</a> poll found that 56 percent of registered voters thought Biden had not been tough enough on Russia, virtually identical to the share who disapproved of his foreign-policy performance.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These numbers were also within a few points of <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his <em>overall</em> approval rating</a>, suggesting that Americans may not yet know how to judge Biden on the crisis and have simply retreated to their partisan corners when answering this question. That’s consistent with findings from political science research that Americans <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/01/26/will-foreign-policy-be-a-major-issue-in-the-2016-election-heres-what-we-know/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t have strongly held opinions on foreign policy</a> and <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-2508.2007.00602.x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">look to signals from political elites</a> to tell them how they should feel about it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, a separate <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/24/ukraine-polling-sanctions-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult</a> survey conducted Thursday — the only poll asking about Ukraine conducted entirely since Russia’s invasion so far — told a different tale. In it, registered voters gave Biden a positive net approval rating on his handling of foreign policy in Ukraine and Eastern Europe: 48 percent to 43 percent. This could reflect what will happen to Biden’s approval ratings on Ukraine (and perhaps overall) once the public hears more about the crisis and has new information on which to base their opinions — such as <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/24/1082776912/biden-russia-ukraine-invasion-live" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden’s televised announcement on Thursday</a> that he would impose harsh economic sanctions on Russia and not send U.S. troops to Ukraine. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">As my colleague Geoffrey Skelley wrote at the time</a>, both of those positions are popular among the public.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, the crisis could have potential downsides for Biden too. One of the biggest vulnerabilities for him could be if the conflict disrupts oil exports from Russia, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/2022/02/23/gas-prices-rising-russia-ukraine/6912371001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">leading to higher gasoline prices</a> in the U.S. According to the Morning Consult/Politico poll, 58 percent of registered voters would hold Biden very or somewhat responsible if gasoline prices increased as a result of the conflict; only 28 percent would hold him not too or not at all responsible. (This may be why, in his speech to the nation on Thursday, Biden said he would <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/speeches-remarks/2022/02/24/remarks-by-president-biden-on-russias-unprovoked-and-unjustified-attack-on-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">release more oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve</a> and “do everything in my power to limit the pain the American people are feeling at the gas pump.”)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also unlikely that Biden’s approval rating will increase as a result of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rally_%27round_the_flag_effect" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rally-’round-the-flag effect</a>, or the tendency for presidents’ popularity to surge in times of war or international emergencies. This bump is hardly automatic: Historically, it’s been highly dependent on <a href="https://oxfordre.com/politics/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228637.001.0001/acrefore-9780190228637-e-518" target="_blank" rel="noopener">opposition politicians’ refraining from criticism of the president</a> during times of crisis. But in this era of hyperpartisanship and -polarization, it’s unlikely that Republicans will lay off Biden anytime soon. In fact, Republicans such as <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/meet-the-press/gop-finds-consensus-russia-criticizing-biden-n1289598" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy</a> and <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/ted-cruz-russia-invaded-ukraine-because-of-catastrophic-mistakes-made-by-biden-administration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Ted Cruz</a> have already blamed the Russian invasion on Biden’s “<a href="https://twitter.com/HouseGOP/status/1496206645919105031" target="_blank" rel="noopener">weak</a>” leadership.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For now, though, this is all speculation. A wide range of outcomes are still possible. Ukraine could dominate the headlines for the next several months — or some other major event could take place and overshadow it. U.S. involvement in the conflict could prove to be minimal — or the nation could end up getting dragged into war (a lot of this, of course, depends on what Russian President Vladimir Putin does, which is even less predictable). And Biden could prove a deft negotiator of the situation — or he could bungle it. We say this a lot at FiveThirtyEight, but it is especially true in this circumstance: We’re just going to have to wait to see what happens.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 17:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645814701700484</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The GOP Is Still Largely Skeptical Of Putin — For Now</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-gop-is-still-largely-skeptical-of-putin-for-now/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>Vladimir Putin</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Shortly after news broke that Russia had launched a large-scale attack on Ukraine, a Telegram channel operated by a user known as “<a href="https://www.dallasobserver.com/news/a-qanon-couple-is-behind-the-for-god-and-country-patriot-roundup-at-dallas-hotels-12003194" target="_blank" rel="noopener">QAnon John</a>” posted a photo of former President Trump and Russian President Vladimir Putin, and posed a question to its more than 80,000 followers: Do you trust Putin? In the hundreds of comments below the question, his followers replied with “yes” after “yes.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Throughout the building tensions in Ukraine over the past few weeks, the messaging from Republican leaders has been consistent: <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/trump-putin-russia-ukraine-republican-response/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blame Biden</a>, but don’t praise Putin. And the majority of Republican voters don’t trust the Russian president, according to polls taken prior to the invasion. But there have been notable exceptions to this response in recent days, including former President Trump, Fox News host Tucker Carlson and online conspiracy theories among the far right — all of which may shift Republican rank-and-file views as the conflict continues. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polling over the last few weeks has found Republicans, like most Americans, don’t trust Putin. In an <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/w6rek2s6zg/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economist/YouGov poll</a> conducted Jan. 22-25, 15 percent of Republicans said they had a very or somewhat favorable view of Putin, similar to the 11 percent of Americans overall who said so. A plurality of Republicans (45 percent) said they had a very unfavorable view of the Russian leader. In a <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/02/22150612/2202139_crosstabs_POLITICO_RVs_v1_SH.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult/Politico poll from last week</a>, more Democrats (20 percent) said they strongly or somewhat approved of how Putin was handling the conflict in Ukraine than did Republicans (10 percent). And when asked in <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ukraine-russia-u-s-involvement-opinion-poll-02-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a CBS News/YouGov poll</a> conducted Feb. 8-11 whether the U.S. should support Ukraine, support Russia or neither, only 4 percent of Republicans said “support Russia” (in line with the 5 percent of Democrats who said the same). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that hasn’t stopped influential figures on the right from taking a friendlier position on Putin. On Tuesday, <a href="https://www.clayandbuck.com/president-trump-with-cb-from-mar-a-lago/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump appeared on a conservative radio show</a> and called Putin “smart,” “savvy” and a “peacekeeper.” Even after news broke of the invasion on Wednesday night, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2Rti1j0b7xw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump called the attack</a> “sad” but also defended Putin, saying, “I really don’t believe he wanted to do this initially. I think he wanted to do something and negotiate it. It just got worse and worse.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Fox News host Tucker Carlson struck a similar tone <a href="https://twitter.com/TuckerCarlson/status/1496302694088257539" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on his Tuesday-night broadcast</a>, telling his audience to ask themselves why they hate Putin. “It might be worth asking yourself, since it is getting pretty serious: What is this really about? Why do I hate Putin so much? Has Putin ever called me a racist? Has he threatened to get me fired for disagreeing with him? Has he shipped every middle-class job in my town to Russia? Did he manufacture a worldwide pandemic that wrecked my business and kept me indoors for two years?” The answer to all these questions, Tucker noted, is “no.” However, Carlson changed his tune slightly after Russia invaded, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2022/02/25/tucker-carlson-russia-ukraine-putin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saying on Thursday</a> that “Vladimir Putin started this war,” which he called a “tragedy.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This contrarianism has been noticed by Russian state media, <a href="https://www.grid.news/story/global/2022/02/24/donald-trump-and-tucker-carlson-are-all-over-russian-state-media/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">which has been running clips</a> of Trump, Carlson and former Secretary of State Mike Pompeo in recent days.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In right-wing spaces online, the conversations following Russia’s attack mirrored these two responses. On the pro-Trump message board Patriots.win, posts and memes focused on criticizing and mocking Biden and Democrats but steered clear of actually praising Putin for his actions. Many took an isolationist stance instead.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The more I hear about this, the more I wonder why we should care,” one user wrote in a popular comment on a highly active thread that day.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Fuck the Great Reset. Fuck puppet Xiden.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some on the right use this portmanteau of Biden and Chinese leader Xi Jinping as a reference to what they perceive as the Chinese Community Party’s influence on Biden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> And fuck Russian AND Ukraine. I WANT MY ‘AMERICA FIRST’ AGENDA &amp; PRESIDENT BACK,” wrote another, capturing a sentiment shared by many on the forum. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But among QAnon and other conspiracy-theory communities, like the channel created by QAnon John, praise for Putin was easier to come by. This is because a prevailing theory among QAnon followers is that Putin invaded Ukraine to flush out a supposed “deep-state cabal,” which the followers baselessly allege runs the world and is involved in Satan-worship and child sex trafficking. Many interpreted <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2022/02/24/putin-denazify-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a line from Putin’s speech</a> Thursday where he pledged to “denazify” Ukraine as code for taking out the deep state. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“What does Putin mean by the denazifying of Ukraine?” one user asked in a Telegram chat group Thursday. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Get rid of the Deep State players,” another user replied. “It’s happening all over the world.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Many QAnon followers were also promoting a conspiracy theory about Russia targeting secret U.S. biolabs located in Ukraine that study deadly viruses. The claim that the U.S. has secret biolabs in Ukraine <a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2022/02/24/us-biolabs-ukraine-russia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is false</a> and has been <a href="https://www.kyivpost.com/ukraine-politics/sbu-no-us-biological-laboratories-in-ukraine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pushed by Russian propagandists</a> for years. A tweet thread that was retweeted more than 1,700 times before Twitter suspended the account (though it has since been shared on Telegram and TikTok), expanded on that conspiracy theory, claiming the sites of reported air strikes correlated with the sites of clandestine, U.S.-owned biolabs. QAnon followers later claimed that Twitter’s suspension of the account proved the theory was true.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Must be on to something if they were suspended,” a user posted on the QAnon message board GreatAwakening.win.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Recent polling and the messaging of most Republican leaders show a mostly unified front against Putin, albeit with disagreement over the best way to respond to Russia’s assault on Ukraine. But the mixed messaging from influential sources like Trump, Carlson and the QAnon community threaten to chip away at that resolve. Clearly, some Americans already believe that Putin may not be the bad guy. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Take note of every single ‘elite’ person screeching about Putin and Russia in defense of Ukraine right now,” QAnon influencer IET 17 wrote on Thursday, to his more than 90,000 followers on Telegram. “They’re the enemy.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (Feb. 25, 2022, 1:20 p.m.):</strong> An earlier version of this article incorrectly spelled the first name of Russian President Vladimir Putin.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (Feb. 25, 2022, 3:55 p.m.):</strong> An earlier version of this article said 15 percent of Republicans had an unfavorable view of Putin according to an Economist/YouGov poll. In fact, 15 percent of the Republicans polled said they had a <em>favorable</em> view of him.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645814701700483</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Ketanji Brown Jackson Could Change The Supreme Court</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-ketanji-brown-jackson-could-change-the-supreme-court/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Ketanji Brown Jackson</category>
			<category>SCOTUS</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<category>Supreme Court Nominees</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">After several weeks of mild suspense, President Biden announced that he’s nominating Ketanji Brown Jackson, who currently sits on the D.C. Circuit Court of Appeals, to replace Justice Stephen Breyer on the Supreme Court. Now, the Senate is hurtling toward its fourth Supreme Court confirmation hearing in five years. Jackson, who is the first Black woman ever to be nominated to the court, has support from <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/now/liberals-circle-wagons-around-ketanji-214027021.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several progressive groups</a>. If she’s confirmed, she’ll probably move the court’s Democratic-appointed bloc even further to the left – although it’s not clear from the data we have just how liberal she’ll be. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Jackson’s nomination is historic — she’s poised to become the first Black woman and the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/02/11/ketanji-brown-jackson-supreme-court-defender/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first former public defender</a> to serve on the nation’s highest court. But unlike with <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-amy-coney-barrett-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the previous</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-brett-kavanaugh-would-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two battles</a> over potential justices, the ideological balance of the court isn’t about to change. Jackson, if confirmed, will replace another justice nominated by a Democrat, which means the court will still be dominated by a six-justice conservative majority.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that doesn’t mean Jackson’s worldview won’t matter if she ends up on the Supreme Court – after all, she’s likely to serve for decades. Based on her professional background and her previous rulings, she’s likely to be a more liberal justice than Breyer was, and one who will probably be less willing than Breyer to compromise with the court’s conservatives. That could mean the court – like every other political institution these days – is about to become even more polarized.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Predicting how potential justices will rule when they get their Supreme Court robes is a tricky business. According to one prominent metric of Supreme Court ideology, though, Jackson looks pretty moderate. As the chart below shows, her <a href="https://www.epstein.wustl.edu/jcs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Judicial Common Space</a> (JCS) score would place her toward the middle of the current Supreme Court, slightly to the right of Justice Elena Kagan and well to the right of Justice Sonia Sotomayor. According to those scores, she’s also a middle-of-the-road judge on the court where she’s currently serving.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="896" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">But there are a lot of reasons to think that the JCS scores underrate Jackson’s liberal tendencies quite a bit. For one thing, a different measure from the <a href="https://data.stanford.edu/dime" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Database of Ideology, Money in Politics, and Elections (DIME)</a> puts her to the left of Kagan and even Sotomayor. According to this metric, Jackson is actually one of the most liberal judges on the D.C. Circuit.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1000" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/atd.SCOTUS-NOM.0225-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">These estimates of Jackson’s ideology are so different, in part, because pinning down a lower court judge’s ideological outlook is even more difficult than figuring out how a Supreme Court justice will rule (which is itself no easy task). The JCS scores are <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/60188505fb790b33c3d33a61/t/61f1855081fb31470cda3c37/1643218256396/ReplacingJusticeBreyer.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">based on the idea</a> that the ideology of the politicians who nominate a judge can tell us a lot about how the judge will approach their job, but that means the judge’s own views and rulings aren’t taken into account. And the scores are even less nuanced for judges who serve on courts in Washington, D.C. Usually, JCS scores are based in part on the ideology of a judge’s home-state senators, but since D.C. does not have any senators, those judges’ ideology scores are based entirely on the presidents who nominated them.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The DIME scores, on the other hand, are drawn from the judge’s own political contributions. This has its own limitations, especially for judges. Federal judges <a href="https://www.uscourts.gov/judges-judgeships/code-conduct-united-states-judges#:~:text=Canon%205%3A%20A%20Judge%20Should%20Refrain%20from%20Political%20Activity,-(A)%20General%20Prohibitions&amp;text=(3)%20solicit%20funds%20for%2C,a%20political%20organization%20or%20candidate." target="_blank" rel="noopener">aren’t allowed to donate</a> to campaigns after they join the bench (for Jackson, <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2022/02/profile-of-a-potential-nominee-ketanji-brown-jackson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that happened in 2013</a>), which means this metric can be very dated. For instance, when it comes to the Supreme Court, the DIME scores <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-conservative-supermajority-is-just-beginning-to-flex-its-muscles/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t accurately reflect</a> the ideological leanings of Justices Clarence Thomas and Samuel Alito, two conservatives <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/about/biographies.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who have been federal judges for decades</a>. But in an era where ideological consistency is an increasingly prized feature in judges, even years-old political contributions could be a pretty good signal for how newer justices will rule.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And there are other clues in Jackson’s record that suggest she’d be likely to join Sotomayor on the court’s left flank, rather than staking out a spot in the middle. In her first opinion for the D.C. Circuit, which came out days after Breyer announced his retirement, Jackson <a href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/government/us-supreme-court-contender-jackson-backs-unions-first-ruling-2022-02-01/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struck down a Trump-era policy</a> that had limited the bargaining power of federal unions. Last year, she was also <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/justice-department/appeals-court-rules-against-trump-fight-over-jan-6-committee-n1285700" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of three judges who ruled</a> that former President Donald Trump couldn’t stop presidential documents from being turned over to the House committee investigating the events of Jan. 6. As a district court judge, <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenthelper/6516-jackson-ruling-in-mcgahn-subpo/92d4672db63b5cac498d/optimized/full.pdf#page=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">she ruled</a> that Trump’s former White House counsel, Don McGahn, had to obey a congressional subpoena to testify. “Presidents are not kings,” she wrote. “This means they do not have subjects, bound by loyalty or blood, whose destiny they are entitled to control.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">She’s also <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/30/us/politics/supreme-court-ketanji-brown-jackson.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seen the impact of harsh sentencing policies firsthand</a>. In addition to working as a federal defender, Jackson also spent several years at the U.S. Sentencing Commission, where she was involved in an Obama-era push to make sentencing guidelines for judges less draconian. And one of Jackson’s family members was <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/14/1078086453/ketanji-brown-jackson-supreme-court-biden" target="_blank" rel="noopener">caught up in the war on drugs directly</a>. Her uncle was sentenced to life in prison for a nonviolent drug crime under a “three strikes” law. Years later, President Barack Obama commuted his sentence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those life experiences are unusual for federal judges, who have often <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-biden-is-reshaping-the-courts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spent their careers as prosecutors or corporate lawyers</a>. <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/msen/files/harris-sen-public-defenders.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">There’s evidence</a> that criminal defense experience does have an impact on judges’ decision-making; a study found that defendants assigned to a judge with that kind of experience are, on average, less likely to be incarcerated. And although Jackson has never commented publicly on her uncle’s case, it seems possible that watching a family member go through the criminal justice system may have given her different views about issues like sentencing, which come up not infrequently in Supreme Court cases.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the background that makes Jackson appealing to liberals could make her confirmation process even more contentious. Granted, she hasn’t been especially controversial in the past. When she was nominated to the district court in 2012, former Republican Rep. Paul Ryan — <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/potential-supreme-court-nominee-family-house-speaker-paul/story?id=37187861" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who’s a relative of Jackson’s by marriage</a> — testified in her favor. And when she was appointed to the D.C. Circuit last year, three Republican senators — Lisa Murkowski, Lindsey Graham and Susan Collins — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-joe-manchin-and-kyrsten-sinema-will-probably-vote-for-bidens-supreme-court-pick/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">crossed the aisle to vote for her</a>. Graham, however, <a href="https://twitter.com/LindseyGrahamSC/status/1497218172071645195?s=20&amp;t=x1FsqAM1h7qz2BN-j06c7w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has already indicated</a> that he’ll be taking a very different position on Jackson this time, tweeting that “the radical Left has won President Biden over yet again.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So she’s unlikely to get full-throated support from Republicans this time. The question is how much of a fuss they want to make, considering that no matter how liberal Jackson turns out to be, her confirmation won’t shift the conservative tilt of the court.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional analysis by Laura Bronner.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 16:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645805701532237</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Stop Using The Midterms To Predict Presidential Elections</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/stop-using-the-midterms-to-predict-presidential-elections/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley and Jean Yi</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Presidential Election</category>
			<category>midterm elections</category>
			<category>Midterms</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Presidential Elections</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">The 2022 midterm election hasn’t even happened yet, but speculation about the 2024 presidential race is already underway, with <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ignore-what-potential-2024-presidential-candidates-say-watch-what-they-do/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many potential</a> <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/pence-delivers-campaign-speech-schools-2024-speculation-mounts-n1282654" target="_blank" rel="noopener">candidates positioning</a> themselves <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/02/04/josh-hawley-2024-465756" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for a possible run</a> — and in the case of former President Donald Trump, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2022/01/trump-arizona-rally-2024-election/621244/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doing so quite publicly</a>. Early general election polls are <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">already testing Trump against President Biden</a>, too, with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/12/22/biden-confirm-2024-run/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many questioning</a> whether <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2021/12/why-biden-wants-you-to-think-hes-running-in-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden will even run again</a> in 2024, when he’d be 81 years old. Some Democrats <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/administration/582071-democrats-question-whether-biden-will-actually-run-in-2024?rl=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have even gone as far as to venture</a> that a rough midterm election for their party — which seems quite possible — might discourage Biden from running again, opening the door for Vice President Kamala Harris or another Democrat to win the party’s nomination.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But while a strong Republican performance in 2022 might influence Biden’s thinking on 2024, it’s a mistake to expect the midterm result to predict how the country will vote in the ensuing presidential election. As the chart below shows, there’s little relationship between the margin in the national popular vote for the U.S. House in a midterm election and the national popular vote margin in the next presidential contest.<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.displayr.com/what-is-correlation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;correlation&lt;/a&gt; is a weak -.258 from 1946 to 2020. Of course, there were a handful of presidential cycles with sizable third-party vote shares, such as George Wallace’s &lt;a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/national.php?year=1968&amp;amp;f=0&amp;amp;off=0&amp;amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;14 percent in 1968&lt;/a&gt; and Ross Perot’s &lt;a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/national.php?year=1992&amp;amp;f=0&amp;amp;off=0&amp;amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;19 percent in 1992&lt;/a&gt;, which complicates calculating the presidential vote margin, but even if you exclude those two cases where a third-party candidate won more than 10 percent, there is still little relationship between midterm and presidential results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>12</sup></a> So whatever happens in the House this November, don’t expect it to forecast the results of the next presidential race.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1008" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/skelley.POLLAPALOOZA.0225.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/skelley.POLLAPALOOZA.0225.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/skelley.POLLAPALOOZA.0225.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/skelley.POLLAPALOOZA.0225.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">More often than not, midterm and presidential results have been miles apart. For instance, in 1994, the GOP captured Congress in the midterm “<a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2007/11/congress-runs-into-republican-revolution-nov-8-1994-006757" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican Revolution</a>” amidst then-President Bill Clinton’s <a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/1994/1011/11191.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poor approval ratings</a>, winning the House popular vote by about 7 percentage points. But in 1996, Clinton ended up claiming a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2020/08/23/the-least-important-election-of-our-lives-400075" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sleepy reelection victory</a> by 8.5 points over Bob Dole — a swing of more than 15 points. In fact, on average, there’s been a swing of about 12 points from the midterm to the subsequent presidential contest.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, midterm elections and their following presidential races have sometimes run close together: Democrats swept back into power in the 2006 midterm election with an 8-point edge in the House vote, for instance, and then-President Barack Obama won by a similar 7-point margin nationally in 2008. In fact, midterm and presidential elections have run closer together in recent years — but importantly, there is still not much of a relationship despite this. Rather, this seems to be happening because <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-a-biden-blowout-didnt-happen-and-why-a-2024-blowout-is-unlikely-too/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">landslide presidential wins</a> are increasingly a thing of the past. Instead, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lopsided midterm results</a> for the party not in the White House are increasingly becoming the norm, then followed by highly competitive presidential races.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One big reason midterm and presidential elections have such different outcomes is that they are fundamentally different kinds of contests. Midterm elections, for instance, <a href="http://www.electproject.org/national-1789-present" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tend to have much lower turnout</a> than presidential elections, and what’s more, voters from the party that’s not in the White House are often much <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/07343469.2014.944286" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to turn out</a>. Additionally, <a href="https://digitalcommons.dartmouth.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3365&amp;context=facoa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some voters switch</a> from the president’s party because of dissatisfaction with the status quo. And because the president’s party usually loses ground in a midterm, you still often see <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ominous-signs-for-obama-in-2012/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narratives that suggest</a> a president’s reelection chances <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1982/11/28/republicans-face-indecision-conflict-as-they-assess-1982-election-losses/4f3d86a6-7e8b-497b-8baa-5b7851fca329/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may now be in peril</a> just after a midterm election. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Yet presidents can, of course, <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2647652" target="_blank" rel="noopener">change their approach</a> following a difficult midterm and/or their <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/e234d1aa-d947-11e0-884e-00144feabdc0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">opponents in Congress can overstep</a> after winning power, both of which can help improve the president’s public standing. And perhaps most importantly, two years is a lifetime in politics, leaving plenty of time for important factors like the state of the economy or war and peace to change in meaningful ways that will influence the electorate. For instance, a <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2010/12/poll-most-see-obama-losing-in-2012-046499" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struggling economy</a>, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/116677/presidential-approval-ratings-gallup-historical-statistics-trends.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mediocre approval ratings</a>, and a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1982/11/04/us/reagan-facing-demands-for-compromise-on-economy-after-26-seat-loss-in-house.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bad midterm</a> can become a <a href="https://www.aei.org/economics/again-the-1980s-boom-was-about-more-than-just-the-reagan-tax-cuts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">roaring economy</a>, “<a href="https://youtu.be/pUMqic2IcWA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Again In America</a>,” and a <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/national.php?year=1984&amp;f=0&amp;off=0&amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">landslide victory</a> in that narrow span of time, as was the case for former President Ronald Reagan’s 1984 reelection bid. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Given all this, Biden and Democrats who are uncertain about the party’s standing probably shouldn’t look to the 2022 election result as a sign of whether the president can win in 2024. It’s true that the midterm outcome could alter the public’s perception of Washington if Biden is facing off with a GOP-controlled Congress. But the actual midterm results won’t really tell us whether Biden is doomed or can win reelection. After all, we have no idea where things will stand in a couple years when it comes to the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-isnt-going-anywhere-and-americans-know-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID-19 pandemic</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">inflation and the overall economy</a>, much less sudden developments like the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">U.S.’s potential role</a> in the conflict in Ukraine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, with all this said, it is indeed fun to take a look at the early polling of the 2024 race — trust me, it’s like catnip. Nevertheless, we need to take those early polls with <em>many</em> grains of salt. After all, even polls taken six months out from the general election <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/you-can-pay-attention-to-those-trump-vs-biden-polls-but-be-cautious/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are only moderately predictive of the final result</a> — and at that point, we usually know who the nominees are. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The 2024 election is likely to be pretty competitive considering how divided our politics are, but the candidates do matter at the margins. So regardless of how many polls test Biden against Trump, time will tell whether we will really see the first general election rematch since 1956 — or if one or both parties end up nominating someone else entirely. But one thing is for certain: The result this November will not guarantee any result for November 2024.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Other polling bites</strong></p>



<ul><li>Russia <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/live-updates/russia-ukraine/?id=82467772">attacked Ukraine early Thursday morning</a> in a conflict that has already killed dozens. But while Americans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/">generally support helping Ukraine</a>, they largely oppose military intervention and think the American government should be minimally involved at this point. According to a Feb. 19-20 poll from Morning Consult, 51 percent of <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/22/ukraine-russia-polling-donbas-sanctions-gas-hikes/">registered voters think the U.S. should impose sanctions</a>, while just 19 percent think the U.S. should deploy troops into eastern Ukraine. And with the caveat that this poll doesn’t account for Russia’s recent attacks, support for sanctions has increased 7 percentage points since Morning Consult last asked this question on Feb. 7.</li><li>Amidst ongoing efforts to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/30/books/book-ban-us-schools.html">ban books from school libraries</a>, and statewide efforts to <a href="https://www.edweek.org/policy-politics/map-where-critical-race-theory-is-under-attack/2021/06">restrict how public schools teach race</a>, a Feb. 15-18 poll from CBS News/YouGov found that Americans <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/book-bans-opinion-poll-2022-02-22/">largely oppose efforts to remove books</a> that contain controversial themes from schools. At least 83 percent said books should never be banned for containing political ideas they disagree with, discussions on race, depictions of slavery, or criticisms of historical figures and events from U.S. history. And over three-quarters of respondents, including 63 percent of Republicans and 89 percent of Democrats, said that public schools should be able to teach about ideas and historical events that might make some students uncomfortable.</li><li>Fifty-nine percent of American workers who can do their job from home <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2022/02/16/covid-19-pandemic-continues-to-reshape-work-in-america/">are doing so all or most of the time</a>, according to a Jan. 24-30 survey from the Pew Research Center. That marks a 12-percentage-point decline from those who said the same in October 2020, but the share who say they’re <em>choosing</em> to work from home versus those whose workplaces remain closed or unavailable has almost flipped. Back in October 2020, 64 percent worked at home because the office was closed versus 38 percent now, while 36 percent chose to work from home versus 61 percent now.</li><li><a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2022/02/22/covid-health-care-workers-poll-pandemic-burnout/6844789001/">Healthcare workers still report high job satisfaction</a>, but a majority also say they’ve been struggling with burnout. In a Feb. 9-16 poll from USA Today/Ipsos, 80 percent say they are very or somewhat satisfied with their job. Fifty-nine percent say they feel hopeful or motivated to go to work, while 56 percent say they feel optimistic. But 52 percent report feeling burned out, especially younger workers — 61 percent of healthcare workers under 30 felt this way, versus 45 percent of those 50 and older.</li><li>Americans are paying less attention to national news, with the decline <a href="https://knightfoundation.org/articles/americans-attention-to-national-news-lowest-in-four-years/">mostly coming from Democrats</a>, according to a recent Gallup/Knight Foundation report. A poll of 4,221 U.S. adults from Nov. 23-Dec. 3 found that the share who said they pay a great deal of attention to national news (33 percent) was the smallest since the Knight Foundation started tracking that question in April 2018. The biggest drop in attention came from Democrats: Just 34 percent of Democrats said they pay a great deal of attention to national news, versus 69 percent in November 2020. To be sure, though, attention to national news might be down, but it’s still larger than the overall share who say they pay a great deal of attention to local (21 percent) or international news (12 percent).</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> 42.1 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 52.5 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.4 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-isnt-going-anywhere-and-americans-know-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 41.4 percent approved and 53.0 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -11.6 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 41.3 percent and a disapproval rating of 53.5 percent, for a net approval rating of -12.2 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/generic-ballot-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/generic-ballot-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/generic-ballot-2-3.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> Republicans currently lead by 2.6 percentage points (45 percent to 42.5 percent). A week ago, Republicans led Democrats by 2.1 points (44.8 percent to 42.6 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 1.6 points (43.8 percent to 42.2 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645787701377572</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Americans Currently Support Sanctioning Russia For Invading Ukraine But Are Reluctant To Deploy Troops</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-currently-support-sanctioning-russia-for-invading-ukraine-but-are-reluctant-to-deploy-troops/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>Military</category>
			<category>Russia</category>
			<category>Sanctions</category>
			<category>Ukraine</category>
			<category>Ukraine Crisis</category>
			<category>Vladimir Putin</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">On Thursday, Russia invaded Ukraine, precipitating the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/02/24/politics/us-military-ukraine-russia/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">largest military conflict in Europe</a> since World War II. In response, President Biden has delivered on his promise to impose <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-vows-consequences-russia-stages-full-scale-attack/story?id=83085065" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sweeping economic sanctions</a> against Russia, after weeks of saying he would institute severe sanctions against the country in such an event.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s unclear at this point what these sanctions will do to stop Russian President Vladimir Putin in his invasion of Ukraine, but the sanctions issued by the U.S., in partnership with its allies, intend to hobble Russia’s economy by restricting its major banks’ ability to conduct business as well as the country’s overall ability to remain competitive in the global marketplace, including in particular its ability to bolster its military. In his address earlier this afternoon, Biden also reaffirmed financial and humanitarian support for Ukraine and promised that U.S. military forces in Eastern Europe would <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/24/us/politics/biden-russia-sanctions-ukraine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defend America’s NATO allies</a>, but he was adamant in saying that American troops would not fight against Russia in Ukraine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s still very early in understanding how the U.S. and its allies will respond to Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, but one key factor in how the Biden administration charts its path forward will undoubtedly hinge on <a href="https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/pdf/10.1146/annurev.polisci.11.060406.214132" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the American people’s receptiveness to U.S. involvement</a> in this conflict. And on that point, recent surveys suggest that Americans are leery of U.S. intervention in Ukraine, especially when it comes to sending American troops. This attitude <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-americans-think-about-the-crisis-in-ukraine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hasn’t changed much</a> in the past few weeks, either, even as a Russian invasion became more likely. Americans continue to have strongly negative views of Russia and support imposing strict sanctions that <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/will-wests-russia-sanctions-anything-damage-deter-putin-ukraine-rcna17301" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could damage the Russian economy</a>, but Americans don’t yet seem ready to support direct U.S. military action.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s little doubt that Americans view Russia as a threat, though. Indeed, 71 percent of Americans told <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/4bmkoc0k8o/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Economist/YouGov</a> this week that Russia posed a somewhat or serious threat to the U.S., with 41 percent calling Russia an “immediate and serious” threat — higher than for any other country or group the poll asked about. And in the same survey, 52 percent said it was more important for the U.S. to take a “strong stand” against Russia to prevent it from taking over Ukraine, compared with 24 percent who said it was more important to maintain good relations with Russia. On that question, a majority of both Democrats and Republicans prioritized opposing Russia in the Ukraine situation.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Americans don’t support the U.S. becoming seriously involved in the conflict and, at this point, strongly prefer sanctions and other forms of nonmilitary action to hurt Russia and help Ukraine. For instance, an <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/americas-role-in-the-russia-and-ukraine-situation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AP-NORC poll</a> from last week found that 52 percent of Americans wanted the U.S. to have a minor role in the Russia-Ukraine conflict, compared with only 26 percent who wanted the U.S. to have a major role (although what “major” and “minor” meant here was left open to interpretation). Meanwhile, that Economist/YouGov survey found that 57 percent of Americans felt that imposing economic sanctions on Russia was a good idea, and a sizable plurality of Americans (45 percent) supported giving Ukraine financial aid. But 55 percent thought it was a bad idea to send troops to Ukraine to fight Russians, and a slight plurality (37 percent) said the same of sending U.S. forces to Ukraine for support but not to fight the Russians.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that Americans <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/02/22/ukraine-russia-polling-donbas-sanctions-gas-hikes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have become even more skeptical</a> of putting troops on the ground now than they were earlier this month. Morning Consult conducted polls on <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/02/08174124/2202035_crosstabs_GEOPOLITICAL_RISK_UKRAINE_RVs_v2_LM.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 7</a> and <a href="https://assets.morningconsult.com/wp-uploads/2022/02/22150208/2202127_crosstabs_GEOPOLITICAL_RISK_RVs_v2_CC.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Feb. 19-20</a> in which they asked registered voters if they preferred imposing sanctions on Russia or sending more U.S. troops to Eastern Europe under a variety of scenarios, ranging from a Russian-backed coup establishing a pro-Russian government in Ukraine to a complete Russian occupation. And across four of the five scenarios Morning Consult asked about, American voters prefered imposing sanctions to military action in both polls, except in the event that Russia invades and occupies all of Ukraine. In early February, respondents were more likely to support sending troops than just imposing sanctions, but by last week, Americans were evenly split. This speaks to a broader trend between Morning Consult’s two polls: The share of registered voters who preferred sanctions rose slightly in its second poll while the share who backed sending more U.S troops to the region shrank.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This doesn’t mean that Americans would necessarily oppose a deployment of American military forces to the region, however. Americans were split, after all, on that worst-case scenario in Morning Consult’s latest polling, and more broadly, The Economist/YouGov found that a plurality (44 percent) of Americans thought it was a good idea to send troops to NATO allied countries in Eastern Europe, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Understanding where American views go from here is difficult, but as images from Ukraine take over the news, and as Biden and other U.S. leaders direct the country’s response to Russia’s invasion, it’s possible American views on Ukraine will change. By its very nature, a military action of this scope creates an incredibly volatile situation, which means it’s hard to understand Americans’ attitudes at this point. But as things change, we will be keeping a close watch on what Americans think about the Russia-Ukraine conflict.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 20:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645738201178672</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We’re Hiring A Senior Editor For Interactives</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/were-hiring-a-senior-editor-for-interactives/</link>
						<dc:creator>Christopher Groskopf</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Christopher Groskopf</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Jobs</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight is seeking a thoughtful, energetic and ambitious <strong>Senior Editor for Interactives </strong>to help lead our interactive and visual journalism. Under the direction of the Deputy Editor, who heads the Interactives and Graphics team, the Senior Editor for Interactives will manage a subset of the Interactives team and its projects. This is a high-impact, interdisciplinary role that may combine elements of people management, project management and editorial leadership. Given the expansive nature of this position, we anticipate tailoring this job to the skills and interests of whomever we hire. The ideal candidate will be someone who derives deep satisfaction from leading others to do their best work.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Senior Editor for Interactives will report to the Deputy Editor and work closely with other senior editors to manage the flow of our work. This full-time role with benefits is a U.S.-based position. Our offices are in New York, but full-time remote work may be considered. If you have questions, please email Deputy Editor <a href="mailto:chris.groskopf@abc.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chris Groskopf</a>. To apply, please submit a cover letter and résumé through the <a href="https://jobs.disneycareers.com/job/new-york/senior-editor-interactives-fivethirtyeight/391/24150372912" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Disney Careers portal</a>. </p>



<h2><strong>Responsibilities:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Managing 2-4 members of the Interactives team by providing regular feedback and mentoring and creating structured opportunities for growth.</li><li>Managing 1-3 concurrent projects, including coordinating kickoffs, check-ins, and retrospectives; tracking tasks; and communicating with other editors and the copy desk.</li><li>Maintaining a “no surprises” standard for managing both people and projects, ensuring that all stakeholders, including the Deputy Editor, always know where things stand.</li><li>Managing a nimble design and development process that adapts to changing circumstances, particularly with deadlines.</li><li>Partnering with the Deputy Editor on all aspects of managing the Interactives team, including developing team policies, making assignments and setting strategy.</li><li>Representing the Interactives team in key conversations, such as with stakeholders at ABC News and Disney.</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Basic Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Experience in <em>at least two </em>of the following areas:<ul><li>Managing people</li><li>Managing software projects</li><li>Editing interactive and visual journalism</li></ul></li></ul>



<ul><li>A functional understanding of web-development technologies, including HTML, CSS and JavaScript.</li><li>The ability to prioritize among many kinds of tasks and the self-awareness to know when it’s better to say no rather than take on too much.</li><li>The ability to diplomatically negotiate and reach compromises among many stakeholders who may sometimes have conflicting interests.</li><li>Kindness.</li></ul>



<h2><strong>Preferred Qualifications:</strong></h2>



<ul><li>A solid understanding of U.S. politics, particularly electoral politics, and/or major U.S. sports.</li><li>Fluency in basic statistics.</li><li>Fluency in at least one programming language, ideally JavaScript.</li><li>Prior experience applying product-design techniques relevant to large journalism projects, such as user research, rapid prototyping or user testing.</li><li>Prior experience as a Technical Project Manager or Product Manager.</li></ul>



<p data-paragraph="main">ABC News and FiveThirtyEight are equal opportunity employers. Applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, color, religion, sex, national origin, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability or protected veteran status.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 15:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1645720201341852</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
