<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 02:29:07 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 01:29:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>What the Supreme Court’s Gun Ruling Means For Gun Control</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-the-supreme-courts-gun-ruling-means-for-gun-control/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Gun Control</category>
			<category>Guns</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/supreme-court/" name="">Supreme Court</a></p>
						
													<h1>What the Supreme Court’s Gun Ruling Means For Gun Control</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 23, 2022, at 1:20 PM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="A person wears an NRA hat in front of the US Supreme Court" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241437230-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241437230-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241437230-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241437230-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>STEFANI REYNOLDS / AFP via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The Supreme Court just dramatically expanded Americans’ right to bear arms. In a 6-3 opinion, with the court’s Republican-appointed justices in the majority, the court ruled that a New York law that heavily restricts the ability to carry a concealed handgun in public violates the Constitution. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This decision is a big deal. Previously, the court had only said that the Constitution protected the ability to have a gun <em>inside</em> the home for self-defense. In that decision, which came down in 2008, the justices didn’t rule on how guns carried <em>outside</em> the home could be regulated. It took almost 15 years for the justices to come back to that question, but now they have. The Second Amendment “protect[s] an individual’s right to carry a handgun for self-defense outside the home,” wrote Justice Clarence Thomas in the majority opinion for <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/20-843_7j80.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thursday’s ruling</a>. Laws like New York’s, which required people who wanted a license to carry a concealed handgun in public to show they have a good reason, are no longer allowed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That doesn’t mean there is no way to regulate the carrying of guns in public — Justice Brett Kavanaugh said that explicitly in his concurring opinion. But Thursday’s ruling does change the way regulations are evaluated. Thomas’s opinion states regulations need to be historically consistent with the Second Amendment. That means when they look at a modern gun regulation, judges will have to figure out if another, reasonably similar law was passed earlier in the country’s history. Previously, courts had also considered whether a regulation could be justified for other reasons, but that second layer of consideration is no longer allowed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What all of this means in practice, though, will have to be worked out by the lower courts, which means there will likely be a flood of new litigation over gun restrictions that could come right back to the Supreme Court.</p>



<h2><strong>The decision is a big expansion of gun rights</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gun rights advocates have been waiting for over a decade for this ruling – and it did not disappoint. Thomas, who has been <a href="https://www.law.com/nationallawjournal/2018/03/27/thomas-calls-the-second-amendment-a-constitutional-orphan-stevens-now-says-get-rid-of-it/?slreturn=20220523125429" target="_blank" rel="noopener">complaining for years</a> about the court’s reticence to clarify the meaning and scope of the Second Amendment, wrote a sweeping opinion that expands gun rights significantly, and could have a big impact on Americans’ lives.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s because the 2008 opinion, while it transformed the way that the Second Amendment is interpreted to include an individual right to bear arms, didn’t actually change the status quo very much. There were relatively few laws that restricted the ability to have a gun at home, and the justices were clear that the opinion didn’t extend further. <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3165011" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A study that looked</a> at lower court rulings on Second Amendment challenges from 2008 to 2016 found that the Supreme Court’s opinion didn’t really change the way other judges were ruling on gun regulations (though, the study acknowledged, that could also be due in part to the types of cases under consideration).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Before Thursday’s ruling, judges had two factors to consider when evaluating the constitutionality of a gun regulation: Does it fit with the history of the Second Amendment? And does the state have another reasonable justification — like social science data suggesting that the law could reduce gun violence? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Under the new ruling, state governments can no longer argue that a gun restriction should be upheld because it serves an important interest. Instead, judges will only consider whether “the regulation is consistent with this Nation’s historical tradition of firearm regulation.” In his opinion, Thomas noted that modern regulations don’t have to be a “dead ringer for historical precursors.” But <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/supreme-court-verge-expanding-second-amendment-gun-rights" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as gun law experts have pointed out</a>, figuring out whether modern gun regulations are similar enough to laws that were passed 200 years ago won’t be a simple matter. The ruling opens the door for every gun regulation that was upheld under the 2008 ruling to be challenged again — in a judiciary that is much more conservative than it was even a few years ago.</p>



<h2><strong>New battle lines in the war over gun laws</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">As with many Supreme Court rulings, we won’t understand the full implications of today’s ruling for a long time. Five other states and the District of Columbia have laws like New York’s, and they will have to pass new regulations for people who want to carry handguns in public. That in itself is not a small thing, since the states include California, New Jersey and Massachusetts, which are populous states with big cities. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the conservative justices could have gone further and cut down a huge swath of gun regulations at once, which they did not. “Our holding decides nothing about who may lawfully possess a firearm or the requirements that must be met to buy a gun,” Justice Samuel Alito wrote in his concurring opinion. “Nor does it decide anything about the kinds of weapons that people may possess.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The ruling does, however, create a bunch of new opportunities for advocates who want to limit states’ ability to determine who can carry a gun and where. In his opinion, Thomas said that guns can still be banned in “sensitive places,” but didn’t expand much further on what a “sensitive place” actually is. In his dissent, Justice Stephen Breyer pointed out that with a historical approach, this category could turn out to be pretty limited. “Where does that leave the many locations in a modern city with no obvious 18th- or 19th-century analogue?” he wrote. “What about subways, nightclubs, movie theaters, and sports stadiums?”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So the future will depend, at least in part, on what state lawmakers try to do. Lawmakers in a state like New York or California <a href="https://twitter.com/TweetBenMax/status/1540009090415529985?s=20&amp;t=ao4Ef7ichRZfS8UQ9-VEug" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could test the limits</a> of the Supreme Court’s ruling by designating the subway, Broadway theaters or grocery stores as “sensitive places” where heightened restrictions can be applied. The risk for them, of course, is that the next Supreme Court ruling could expand gun rights even further.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 18:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1656009001394343</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Republicans Are Defining The Jan. 6 Hearings</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-are-defining-the-jan-6-hearings/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Jan. 6 Investigation</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/january-6th-investigation/" name="">Jan. 6 Investigation</a></p>
						
													<h1>Republicans Are Defining The Jan. 6 Hearings</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 23, 2022, at 8:06 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="January 6th Hearing Day 4" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241442644-e1655985095913.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241442644-e1655985095913.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241442644-e1655985095913.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241442644-e1655985095913.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Republicans like (from left) Arizona state House Speaker Rusty Bowers, Georgia Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger and his deputy Gabriel Sterling testified at the Jan. 6 hearings.													<p>Tom Williams / CQ-Roll Call, Inc via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Before the House select committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the U.S. Capitol started its hearings, it was easy to wonder who the hearings were for exactly. Americans’ <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/january-6-capitol-attack-cbs-news-poll-analysis/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">views on the violence</a> have become entrenched, congressional hearings <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-host-a-congressional-hearing-that-actually-like-does-something/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aren’t what they used to be</a>, and the GOP <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/jun/14/trump-big-lie-support-republican-primary-winners-gop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has seemingly not paid a price</a> for rallying behind false election claims that incited anti-democratic violence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But after the first few sessions of the hearings, the committee’s audience is clear, as is its strategy to change minds. These are hearings for Republicans, by Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Despite the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/22/us/politics/jan-6-committee-republicans.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GOP leadership’s boycott of the committee</a>, it has relied almost exclusively on testimony from Republicans, conservatives and members of then-President Donald Trump’s inner circle to detail the attack and the events leading up to it. For Republicans who are following these hearings, the call is coming from inside the house.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The testimony has come from a far wider network than the Republican figures who have long since been written off by Trump and his loyalists as “RINOs,” or “Republicans in name only.” The hearings have featured several segments from interviews with Bill Barr, Trump’s former attorney general. Barr testified that he repeatedly told Trump the election-fraud claims were baseless and that the Department of Justice had investigated the claims and found no evidence of widespread fraud. “I made it clear I did not agree with the idea of saying the election was stolen and putting out this stuff, which I told the president was bullshit,” Barr was heard saying in a tape of his deposition played during the first hearing. “And, you know, I didn’t want to be a part of it, and that’s one of the reasons that went into me deciding to leave when I did.” While the two parted on bad terms over Trump’s incessant yet disproven claims of election fraud, Barr is a lifelong conservative who not only served under President George H.W. Bush but was also a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/14/us/politics/william-barr-attorney-general.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">loyal ally</a> to Trump as his attorney general. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We’ve also heard from many legal experts in Trump’s orbit who tried to convince the former president that the “Big Lie” was baseless, such as former White House attorney Eric Herschmann. In a recorded deposition played during one hearing, Herschmann recalled conversations with Trump lawyer John Eastman — a major architect behind Trump’s attempts to overturn the election — disputing that there was a legal path forward. After the Jan. 6 attack, Herschmann said Eastman continued to push for a way for Trump to hold onto power, to which Herschmann says he replied, “Are you out of your effing mind?”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">During the hearing on Tuesday, the committee underscored that the individuals who were pressured most by Trump’s claims were in fact former allies. The first question asked of Brad Raffensperger, the secretary of state of Georgia, and Rusty Bowers, the speaker of the Arizona House, was whether it was fair to say that they, as fellow Republicans, wanted Trump to win. They both answered yes. Bowers himself campaigned with Trump in 2020. It would be hard to dispute the conservative bona fides of most of the witnesses we’ve heard from, and even Trump seems to recognize this, instead <a href="https://www.msnbc.com/rachel-maddow-show/maddowblog/problems-trumps-case-jan-6-committee-rcna34563" target="_blank" rel="noopener">claiming that much of the damning testimony</a> is the result of misleading video editing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The testimony of conservative witnesses has also underscored how much pressure Republicans faced to fall in line with Trump’s claims. In many cases, Republicans were faced with putting their political career on the line to stand up for the truth or else go along with a lie.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The committee faces a difficult challenge in reaching Republicans. Even after days of hearings, recent polling shows Republicans have a very different view of what happened on Jan. 6. Sixty-one percent of Republicans believe Trump acted appropriately on Jan. 6, according to a <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/578506037/Yahoo-News-Survey-January-6th" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Yahoo News/YouGov survey</a> conducted June 10-13, and 59 percent said they don’t believe the attack was part of a conspiracy to overturn the election. In fact, 74 percent of Republicans in that survey said they believe Jan. 6 was caused by “left-wing protesters trying to make Trump look bad,” a claim that is not supported by any evidence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Just as it was more compelling to have Republican lawyer (and later senator) Fred Thompson ask the question that broke open the Watergate hearings, Jan. 6 and the Big Lie that led to it are stories for Republicans to tell. These are not adversaries dramatizing the events for political gain. These are dyed-in-the-wool conservatives from all levels of government sounding the alarm against their own party and its leader because what they witnessed was too disturbing to let happen. If the committee has any hope of breaking through to Republican voters, this is it.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 13:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655986501182346</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What We Lose When We Lose Competitive Congressional Districts</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-lose-when-we-lose-competitive-congressional-districts/</link>
						<dc:creator>Lee Drutman</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Lee Drutman</dc:creator>
			<category>Negative Partisanship</category>
			<category>Polarization</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/polarization/" name="">Polarization</a></p>
						
													<h1>What We Lose When We Lose Competitive Congressional Districts</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/lee-drutman/" title="" rel="author">Lee Drutman</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 23, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt='"I Voted" stickers are seen on a table' src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1401532468-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1401532468-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1401532468-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1401532468-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Michael M. Santiago / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Competitive congressional districts have been <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/as-swing-districts-dwindle-can-a-divided-house-stand/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">steadily disappearing for decades</a>. In the current redistricting cycle, six highly competitive districts in the House of Representatives were <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">drawn out of existence</a>. The Cook Political Report estimates that <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/house-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less than 8 percent</a> of congressional districts will be competitive come November. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is a problem. It’s not because competitive districts are a powerfully moderating force on our democracy — instead, the decline of competitive districts is a problem that reflects deeper causes of partisan polarization and leaves the overwhelming majority of Americans in places where their votes don’t matter, and where parties and candidates don’t need to work for anybody’s votes.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Governing in America requires compromise. But when over 90 percent of congressional districts lean toward one of the two major parties, that means most representatives have little incentive to compromise. In fact, representatives increasingly <a href="https://washingtonmonthly.com/2016/01/10/the-freedom-caucus-is-sort-of-right/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">face strong pressures to be very partisan</a>, which has made governing very difficult.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But perhaps more importantly, when there isn’t competition, citizens and parties have little reason to show up and vote. Instead it becomes the highly organized donors and activists who are engaged, while the rest of the district is ignored. It’s true that competitive districts might not produce especially moderate candidates, but they are important when it comes to engaging and informing citizens. And this participation has valuable spillover effects for communities, well beyond our elections. </p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Four decades ago, <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/vitalstats_ch2_tbl16.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than a third of congressional districts</a> split their tickets, and as recently as 30 years ago, more than a third were <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/changing-how-primaries-work-probably-wont-make-politics-less-divisive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">potentially competitive</a>. It was smart politics, in other words, to be “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-bipartisanship-in-the-senate-is-dying/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bipartisan</a>.” Fuzzy partisan boundaries and candidate-centered elections meant broad coalitions operated across what was <a href="https://oxford.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.1093/oso/9780190913854.001.0001/oso-9780190913854-chapter-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more like a four-party system</a>, with many liberal Republicans and conservative Democrats voting together while many conservative Republicans and liberal Democrats also voted together.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Party leaders also didn’t have as much leverage to enforce a party line, and genuine cross-partisan policy agreements developed in part because the parties overlapped so much ideologically. In such an environment, compromise could thrive without threatening fundraising or reelection processes.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But driven by the geographic sorting of parties, the nationalization of politics around divisive culture-war issues and continued close national elections, that overlap vanished; instead, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-hatred-negative-partisanship-came-to-dominate-american-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hyper-partisan hatred has come to dominate American politics</a>,  pulling the major parties apart and pushing voters onto two competing teams. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the process, competitive and split-ticket districts have almost entirely vanished. In the 2020 election, only <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-only-16-districts-voted-for-a-republican-and-a-democrat-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">16 congressional districts</a> backed a presidential nominee from one party and a House candidate from the other party, the fewest in 100 years. Meanwhile, the share of competitive districts — here, defined by the Cook Political Report as having a <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/cook-pvi/introducing-2021-cook-political-report-partisan-voter-index" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Partisan Voting Index</a> between D+5 and R+5<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meaning that, in the two previous presidential elections, the average difference between how a district votes and how the country votes overall was within 5 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> — has fallen from about a third of districts to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less than one in 10</a> by 2018.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1068" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="796" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS.0623-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Perhaps the best way to understand what’s happening is if we think of partisanship and district competitiveness as two opposing forces, with one force strong and one much weaker. Partisanship is the strong force pulling the parties further apart; it demands parties take conflicting stances on issues and draw sharp contrasts. And it is galvanized by the same forces responsible for the decline of competitive districts, especially geographic partisan sorting and the nationalization of culture-war issues.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The presence of competitive districts, meanwhile, is the weak force pulling the parties closer together. These districts encourage incumbents to demonstrate at least some modicum of bipartisanship. But the trends that strengthen partisanship also make competitive districts even rarer, further undermining their potential ability to encourage problem-solving cross-partisanship.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Today, with few competitive and even fewer split-ticket districts, this weak compromise-seeking force is no match for the much stronger compromise-<em>repelling </em>force of partisanship. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The representatives holding competitive districts often still pursue cross-party compromise. More moderate members — as defined by <a href="https://voteview.com/data" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DW-Nominate</a>, which quantifies the ideology of every member of Congress based on roll call votes cast in a legislative session — do often hail from more competitive districts, as you can see in the chart below:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1114" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="826" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-2.0622-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Notably, however, the gap between the voting records of Democrats in competitive districts versus Republicans in competitive districts is actually quite large — much bigger than the difference between, say, a Republican hailing from a competitive district and a Republican hailing from a safe district. Additionally, even though district partisanship and voting records are moderately correlated for both parties, there is considerable variation in how different members elected in 2020 in similarly partisan districts voted, evident above.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In short, competitive districts are somewhat of a moderating force. But Democrats in slightly Republican districts are still miles away from Republicans in slightly Democratic districts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One reason is that most swing districts are only swing districts because they have about the same number of Republican and Democratic voters — not because they are home to many undecided centrists. As <a href="https://ctausanovitch.com/SSRN-id2477157.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a 2015 paper argued</a>: “Reformers often idealize such moderate districts because it is believed that they are most conducive to the political competition that is supposed to produce moderate representation. … [However], the fact that such districts are more likely to be heterogeneous ironically mitigates their ability to elect moderate legislators.” Put another way, swing districts are not inherently moderate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://web.mit.edu/cstewart/www/papers/cand_position_3.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Another study of House members who served between 1874 and 1996</a> found very little in common between incumbents and challengers of different parties running at the district level. <a href="https://stanforddpl.org/papers/hall_fowler_longterm/hall_fowler_longterm.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Another study</a> examining elections from 1946 to 2010 for Congress and 1972 to 2010 for state legislatures found that even once elected, officials did not adjust their voting behavior to more closely match district-level ideology. In other words, candidates have <em>always </em>positioned themselves closer to their party than a candidate from another party, and even in closely-contested districts, they moderate very little. Moreover, provided they keep winning elections, there really isn’t any need for them to moderate. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20031208115700id_/http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu:80/~burden/bjpsfinal.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some candidates hew closer</a> to the middle than others in competitive districts, and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20031208115700id_/http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu:80/~burden/bjpsfinal.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">primary challenges</a> have tugged candidates away from the center, even in competitive districts. Between the 1940s and the 1970s, when polarization was generally low, and both parties were incoherent ideologically at the national level, <a href="https://web.mit.edu/cstewart/www/papers/cand_position_3.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">candidates converged modestly in the middle of their district</a>. But today, in a divided and polarized two-party system, the middle is a hard and lonely place to be, and an even harder place to get to as a candidate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This disappearance of cross-partisan compromise has made governing in America challenging. Without the possibility of building broad legislative coalitions, little gets done in Congress on the most urgent issues , and that’s because all the most urgent issues inevitably become high-stakes issues for the next election, where <a href="https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/2018/03/22/insecure-majorities-will-ensure-that-the-senate-remains-gridlocked-for-the-foreseeable-future/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">compromise would only muddy the message.</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But arguably, the more damaging consequence is how many Americans don’t matter in our elections – and how that drives broader disengagement. In competitive districts, parties and candidates must work to mobilize all kinds of<em> </em>voters for the general election, but in districts where one party dominates — which is the overwhelming majority of districts in the U.S. — this isn’t the case, as whomever wins the primary almost always wins the general election. General elections are a fait accompli, and parties and candidates campaign accordingly. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The most solid and consistent finding in <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0261379416300956" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voter turnout</a> <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0261379405000910" target="_blank" rel="noopener">literature</a> is that competition boosts turnout. And as you can see in the chart below, turnout in 2018 was, indeed, higher in competitive districts:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1030" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="792" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623-mob.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/drutman.COMPETITIVE-ELEXS-3.0623-mob.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The effects go beyond turnout. Citizens who live in competitive electoral areas tend to be <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43653079" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more interested in public affairs</a>. They are <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/24710877" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more politically informed.</a> They are even <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt3fhnxn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to volunteer and be involved in community activity.</a> These markers of healthy civic life decline in uncompetitive districts.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The decline of competitive districts is a real problem for American democracy.  With an overwhelming majority of voters living in districts where their general election votes don’t matter, and where parties and candidates don’t have to mobilize any support to win, it’s all too easy for many voters to check out. Competitive districts may not guarantee moderate representation, but they do engage voters in a meaningful election, with powerful knock-on civic engagement benefits. How to <a href="https://www.vox.com/the-big-idea/2017/4/26/15425492/proportional-voting-polarization-urban-rural-third-parties" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reverse this decline</a> is a more complicated matter of debate. But the problem is real, and our democracy has substantial work to do to fix it. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655982001214233</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why It’s Possible For Some Americans To Support Abortion Yet Oppose Roe</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-its-possible-for-some-americans-to-support-abortion-yet-oppose-roe/</link>
						<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why It's Possible For Some Americans To Support Abortion Yet Oppose Roe</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/natalie-jackson/" title="" rel="author">Natalie Jackson</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 22, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt='A demonstrator holds a sign that reads "Goodbye Roe" outside the US Supreme Court' src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241283594-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241283594-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241283594-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241283594-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Bill Clark / CQ-Roll Call, Inc via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">A common assumption of the debate around overturning Roe v. Wade, which established the constitutional right to abortion in 1973, is that there are just two sides to it. On one side, the thinking goes, are those who think abortion should be legal and that Roe should be upheld, while on the other side are those who think abortion should be illegal and that Roe should be overturned.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, the Public Religion Research Institute, where I’m the research director, <a href="https://www.prri.org/spotlight/most-oppose-overturning-roe-v-wade-widespread-confusion-over-a-post-roe-world/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">surveyed more than 5,000 Americans back in March on their views on abortion</a>, and we found that 64 percent of Americans said abortion should be legal in most or all cases, while 35 percent said abortion should be illegal in most or all cases.<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The poll was conducted March 11-30, 2022, prior to the leaked Supreme Court draft opinion that overturned Roe, and has a margin of error of +/- 1.6 percentage points. If respondents skipped a given question, they were excluded from its analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These results are <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/06/13/about-six-in-ten-americans-say-abortion-should-be-legal-in-all-or-most-cases-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">consistent with other polls</a> on the topic — a majority of Americans generally support abortion being legal, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1576/abortion.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">although the exact share varies</a> depending on how questions are phrased and which answer options are provided. However, perhaps somewhat counterintuitively, 43 percent of those who thought abortion should be illegal in most or all cases <em>opposed </em>overturning Roe, while 26 percent of those who thought abortion should be legal in most or all cases <em>supported</em> overturning Roe.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A common reaction to this type of misalignment in opinions is that survey respondents are wrong. Indeed, when discussing this finding with some of my highly informed friends, their first instinct was that people are not intelligent or not paying attention. As an opinion researcher, I have seen that reaction to my work more times than I can count.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible that a respondent could see “Roe v. Wade” and hastily click “oppose,” thinking that was the correct answer for opposing abortion, and vice-versa for those who support abortion. And even though the survey question wording defines Roe v. Wade as “the 1973 Supreme Court decision that affirmed a constitutional right to abortion,” there could be some misunderstanding of what it means to “overturn” a case. But assuming this misalignment all stems from a lack of intelligence or understanding fails to acknowledge that many people do hold truly nuanced opinions on complex issues like abortion and Roe. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/11/28/politics/abortion-roe-vs-wade-john-roberts-supreme-court/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">based on an analysis of his writings, statements and prior decisions</a>, Supreme Court Chief Justice John Roberts is likely one of those people — he appears to think abortion should be illegal but opposes overturning Roe. No one would call Roberts uninformed. Granted, most Americans are not as well-informed as Roberts, nor do they place the importance on Supreme Court precedent that Roberts does. But investigating what we do know about people who hold seemingly inconsistent views on abortion and overturning Roe reveals where cross pressures could result in conflicting views.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">As is true of most abortion-related public opinion, there are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-real-dividing-line-on-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not large gender differences</a>; women and men are equally likely to hold cross-pressured opinions. There are, however, clear patterns by race, age and education. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Black (39 percent) and Hispanic (36 percent) Americans, for instance, were more likely to fall into this cross-pressured category than white (28 percent), Asian or Pacific Islander (28 percent) or multiracial Americans (21 percent). By age, younger Americans — particularly those between ages 30 and 49 — were more likely to report cross-pressured views (37 percent) than other age groups, as were parents of children under 18 (38 percent) compared to non-parents (28 percent). Finally, 4 in 10 Americans with a high school level education or less were in this category, which was much smaller than the share with more formal education (31 percent some college education; 19 percent college degree or higher).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">More Republicans (36 percent) than Democrats (26 percent) fell into this conflicted category. And given that most Republicans think that abortion should be illegal, more fell into the illegal-but-don’t-overturn category (24 percent); given that most Democrats think abortion should be legal, meanwhile, more fell into the legal-but-overturn category (18 percent).</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Abortion is an issue with distinct religious implications, so unsurprisingly quite a few Christian groups have particularly high shares that fall into this cross-pressured category. When we break down the two cross-pressured categories, more white evangelical Protestants, Hispanic Protestants and Hispanic Catholics fell into the illegal-but-don’t-overturn category than the legal-but-overturn category, while more Black Protestants and non-Christian religious Americans fell into the legal-but-overturn category. At least 35 percent of each of these groups fell into the cross-pressured category.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All of this taken together strongly suggests that the people most likely to be cross-pressured on abortion were Black, Hispanic, parents, those between the ages of 30 and 49, those with a high school education, Republican or religious.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Lower education levels could also explain some of what we see — consider that in the same survey, 61 percent of those with a high school education or less said they did not know what will happen in their state if Roe is overturned. Those with some college (47 percent) and a college degree or higher (37 percent) were much less likely to say they’re not sure.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the same time, even though Republicans and Christians are generally associated with anti-abortion opinions, substantial shares of these groups said that they personally think abortion should be illegal but don’t want Roe overturned. That could be for  reasons similar to Roberts, or maybe they don’t want to leave everything up to the states. Then again, it could be evidence of simply accepting the status quo — <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2022/05/06/americas-abortion-quandary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a Pew Research Center poll</a> conducted in the same time frame as PRRI’s found that only 36 percent of Americans had given much thought to the issue.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, some of these dynamics could shift in the coming weeks and months if Roe is, in fact, overturned in the Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization case. What will not change, however, is that opinion about abortion and Roe v. Wade is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-americans-really-think-about-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">complex and nuanced</a>. Using only one survey question to look at the issue is a mistake; views on abortion cannot be reduced to a simple legal/illegal framework, even when it comes to Roe. The answers simply might not mean what you think they mean.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655896501705506</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Went Down In The June 21 Elections In Alabama, Virginia And Georgia</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/alabama-virginia-georgia-election/</link>
						<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 House Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Alabama Senate</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Results</category>
			<category>Georgia Politics</category>
			<category>Live Blog</category>
			<category>Primary Results</category>
			<category>Runoff Election</category>
			<category>The Big Lie</category>
			<category>Virginia Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 23:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655856001431847</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Are 1 Percent Of Americans Evil?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-are-1-percent-of-americans-evil/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Ipsos</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Polling</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-are-1-percent-of-americans-evil/">
	<div data-podcast-id="337704" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Are 1 Percent Of Americans Evil?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6498383092.mp3?updated=1655845061">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">The latest redistricting cycle is almost over, and we have a somewhat finalized national map of new districts to assess. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew breaks down how the new map falls along partisan lines and why there are a record-low number of competitive districts. They also discuss a new poll from YouGov that asked Americans where they fall on the Dungeons &amp; Dragons alignment chart, ranging from good to evil as well as lawful to chaotic. Unsurprisingly, not many Americans identify as evil.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the team looks at the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/3-in-10-americans-named-political-polarization-as-a-top-issue-facing-the-country/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">newest polling</a> from FiveThirtyEight’s collaboration with Ipsos, in which Americans were asked about the most important political issues leading up to the midterms. This edition focused on political polarization, crime and gun violence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 21:57:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655851501662132</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>8 Primaries and Runoffs To Watch In Alabama, Georgia And Virginia</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/8-primaries-and-runoffs-to-watch-in-alabama-georgia-and-virginia/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Alabama</category>
			<category>Georgia Primary</category>
			<category>Virginia Primary</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>8 Primaries and Runoffs To Watch In Alabama, Georgia And Virginia</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 20, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Voters Cast Ballots In Alabama Primary" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240882336-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240882336-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240882336-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240882336-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Tuesday’s elections repeat a common theme in the primaries so far: How far to the right will Republicans go?													<p>Andi Rice / Bloomberg / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Wait, haven’t we seen this episode? On Tuesday, voters in Alabama and Georgia head <em>back</em> to the polls for reruns of several races that weren’t decided <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/georgia-texas-primary-election-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on May 24</a>. (In those states, if no candidate receives a majority of the vote in the primary, the top two vote-getters go to a runoff.) In addition, Virginia is holding its regularly scheduled primary. In total, this makes for eight competitive primaries we’re watching.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As has been the case for most primary days so far this year, this week’s drama is focused on the Republican side of the aisle. The GOP has the chance to nominate several candidates of color as part of a larger effort this year to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/04/us/politics/gop-diversity-texas-arizona.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">appeal to a more diverse electorate</a>. Former President Donald Trump has also endorsed candidates in three competitive primaries, and he’s surely watching to see whether that’s enough to push them over the finish line. However, the war may already have been won: Regardless of whether they have Trump’s personal support, almost all of the Republicans on the ballot this week share his populist, illiberal vision for the GOP.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AP22157640675880-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AP22157640675880-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AP22157640675880-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/AP22157640675880-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>The runoff for Georgia’s 10th Congressional District has gotten nasty, with Mike Collins (left) sending out inflammatory mailers against his opponent, Vernon Jones (right), a onetime Democrat endorsed by former President Donald Trump. <p>Brynn Anderson / AP Photo</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Georgia</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> 2nd, 6th and 10th congressional districts</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>7 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Republican primary in Georgia’s <strong>10th District</strong> left off on a cliffhanger: Trucking company owner Mike Collins received 26 percent of the vote, while former state Rep. Vernon Jones was close behind, with 22 percent. The runoff has <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/trumps-waning-influence-key-factor-in-georgia-gop-runoffs/H7KGEQWXUZEEXEPFS3RZPU6WH4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gotten especially nasty</a>, too. Collins’s campaign, for instance, has handed out rape whistles with Jones’s name on them to remind voters that Jones has been <a href="https://www.11alive.com/article/news/politics/rape-allegation-shadows-vernon-jones/85-4efb1016-2350-48bf-9a9c-69a87003e465" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accused of rape</a>. They’ve also sent out mailers claiming that Jones, who is Black and whose election would likely result in the highest number of Black Republicans in the House since Reconstruction, is a “<a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/trumps-waning-influence-key-factor-in-georgia-gop-runoffs/H7KGEQWXUZEEXEPFS3RZPU6WH4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">radically anti-white racist</a>.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Collins campaign has also attacked Jones for being “a corrupt career politician who is actually a Democrat from DeKalb County” (a.k.a. Atlanta). It’s true that Jones did indeed represent DeKalb County, which is miles away from the 10th District, as a Democrat for 20 years in various capacities, but Jones was also a <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/politics-blog/republicans-kick-off-rnc-with-help-from-georgias-vernon-jones/EQHZJBHF2RGSJEQ5QAJOGZB7IM/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">staunch Trump supporter</a> in the 2020 election and has since <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/georgia-vernon-jones-joining-republican-party" target="_blank" rel="noopener">switched parties</a>. (The reason Jones is running in the 10th is that Trump agreed to endorse him for this open seat in exchange for Jones’s <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/after-meeting-with-trump-georgias-vernon-jones-likely-to-exit-gop-gubernatorial-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropping his long-shot campaign for governor</a>, where he was siphoning votes away from Trump’s endorsed candidate, former Sen. David Perdue.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, this runoff has also become a proxy war between Trump and arguably his greatest Peach State nemesis, Gov. Brian Kemp, who <a href="https://www.gwinnettdailypost.com/local/politics/brian-kemp-endorses-mike-collins-over-vernon-jones-in-10th-congressional-district/article_b3233716-eda0-11ec-a596-ef130b3d2b1b.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed Collins</a> last week. (As you might remember, Trump endorsed Perdue’s failed campaign to oust Kemp because Kemp would not acquiesce to Trump’s wishes to overturn the 2020 election.) However, Collins is <a href="https://www.gpb.org/news/2021/09/17/mike-collins-launches-10th-congressional-district-bid-in-trumps-image" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far from an anti-Trumper</a>: <a href="https://archive.ph/8HjsI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Like Jones</a>, he believes that voter fraud is the <a href="https://player.fm/series/mission-timpossible-2465276/oconee-co-candidates-forum-pt-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only reason</a> Trump lost the 2020 election. So no matter who wins the runoff, the district’s dark-red hue all but guarantees the former president a new ally in Congress.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">While the 10th District runoff is unpredictable as we don’t have any polling of the race, Trump’s pick in the Republican runoff for Georgia’s <strong>6th District </strong>looks like the underdog. In early May, Trump <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/trump-picks-a-side-in-georgias-6th-district-race/EKFJVQQ2NJEOHKARE2NV7UR2HQ/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed</a> attorney Jake Evans, who also happens to be the son of Trump’s former ambassador to Luxembourg. However, physician Rich McCormick outpaced Evans in the May 24 primary, 43 percent to 23 percent.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">This may be a case of voters seeing through Trump’s endorsement and preferring the candidate who is Trumpier on the merits. While Evans <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/politics-blog/the-jolt-does-stacey-abrams-have-plans-for-2022-and-2024/6566XFPHNNB33JDWE6Q532QBD4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has said</a> that “[w]e will never know whether [there] were sufficient legal votes to overturn” the 2020 election, McCormick <a href="https://www.pbs.org/video/congressional-district-6-r-mbsyqs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still has not conceded</a> his 2020 campaign for Congress, believing himself to be the victim of voter fraud.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Or it could just be a testament to the power of money in politics: McCormick has raised almost <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/GA/06/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">twice as much money</a> as Evans, and School Freedom Fund, a super PAC allied with the Club for Growth, has <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/races/outside-spending?cycle=2022&amp;id=GA06&amp;spec=N" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spent $1.3 million</a> to help McCormick win. Trump’s endorsed candidate beat the Club for Growth’s endorsed candidate the two previous times the two GOP juggernauts went head to head this cycle, but it looks like the third time might be the charm for the Club. Regardless, the winner here on Tuesday will almost certainly flip this seat red in November, as it was redrawn in redistricting to have a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> of R+24.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Redistricting also gave southwest Georgia’s <strong>2nd District</strong> a more competitive (D+4) partisan lean, giving Republicans hope that the right GOP nominee can beat Democratic Rep. Sanford Bishop. Jeremy Hunt seems perfectly cast for the role: A Black Army veteran who would not only make the House GOP caucus more racially diverse but also potentially appeal to the district’s sizable Black population. However, Hunt mustered only 37 percent in the primary, setting up a runoff with attorney Chris West, who received 30 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">West has attacked Hunt for <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/runoff-2022-georgia-2nd-candidates-hunt-west-debate-district-ties/NTSDHW2AKRAKZEI73YJ5SEJLQM/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">being a recent transplant to the district</a>, but in this era of nationalized politics, what might matter more is Hunt’s national profile: He has appeared on Fox programs <a href="https://www.wrbl.com/news/georgia-news/2nd-congressional-district-candidates-claim-fox-news-tipping-the-scale-in-favor-of-jeremy-hunt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">15 times since January</a>, and major party figures like former U.N. Ambassador Nikki Haley have <a href="https://www.axios.com/local/atlanta/2022/06/09/national-gop-leaders-target-southwest-georgia-race" target="_blank" rel="noopener">campaigned for him</a>. There haven’t been any public polls of the race, but Hunt has also raised way more money than West, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2GA02189/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$770,493</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2GA02155/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$286,691</a>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241232973-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241232973-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241232973-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1241232973-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Republicans are divided on who to support in the race for Virginia’s 7th Congressional District, which is currently represented by Abigail Spanberger, a Democrat. <p>Meagan Flynn / The Washington Post / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Virginia</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> 2nd and 7th congressional districts</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>7 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Virginia is the sole state holding its regular primary this week — but only for some offices. The commonwealth allows parties to nominate candidates at conventions or via party-run (as opposed to state-run) primaries if they want, and the GOP took this option in both noncompetitive seats, like the <a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-and-regional/govt-and-politics/rep-bob-good-easily-wins-5th-district-gop-nomination/article_9ae4b5d2-de13-5497-bea1-b21e0c530c13.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">5th</a>, <a href="https://www.insidenova.com/news/arlington/gop-has-its-nominee-to-take-on-beyer-in-8th-district/article_3386346e-db48-11ec-b7f4-a379ed8f209f.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">8th</a> and <a href="https://www.wmal.com/2022/05/09/jim-myles-wins-republican-nomination-in-virginias-11th-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">11th</a> districts, as well as in competitive seats, like the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/05/22/hung-cao-jennifer-wexton-virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">10th District</a>, where they nominated Navy veteran Hung Cao last month.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Republicans are still holding primaries for two seats they have high hopes of flipping in November. One of those is the <strong>2nd District</strong>, a R+6 seat currently represented by Democratic Rep. Elaine Luria. Luria was a strong Democratic recruit when she first won the seat in 2018 — a Navy veteran in a seat anchored by the Navy towns of Norfolk and Virginia Beach. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, national Republicans are trying the same strategy, as they’ve consolidated around state Sen. Jen Kiggans, a former Navy helicopter pilot: House Minority Leader <a href="https://twitter.com/JenKiggans/status/1488516011888463874" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kevin McCarthy</a> and the <a href="https://congressionalleadershipfund.org/clf-announces-first-trailblazers-endorsements-of-the-2022-cycle/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congressional Leadership Fund</a> have both endorsed her. However, fellow Navy veteran Jarome Bell has gotten a smattering of support from the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/03/07/bob-good-jarome-bell-endorsement/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trumpier wing of the party</a>, including Arizona Rep. Paul Gosar and former National Security Advisor Michael Flynn. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Bell believes not only that the 2020 election was stolen but also that the people responsible should be <a href="https://www.pilotonline.com/government/virginia/vp-nw-statehouse-republicans-politics-20220509-pcyifg2g4vfxlodvbxaejvnowe-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">executed for treason</a>. His nomination would likely make it harder for Republicans to flip this light-red seat, but luckily for them, Kiggans looks like the favorite: She has outraised Bell <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2VA02064/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.3 million</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0VA02175/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$492,051</a>, and a <a href="https://www.politico.com/minutes/congress/06-1-2022/poll-in-virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll from a pro-Kiggans group</a> gave her a 35-percentage-point lead over Bell last month.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans are also targeting Democratic Rep. Abigail Spanberger in Virginia’s <strong>7th District</strong>, which has a partisan lean of D+2. Unlike in the 2nd District, the GOP nomination here is wide open: Four candidates have raised at least $500,000, and we don’t have any public polling to suggest who might be leading. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">State Sen. Bryce Reeves is the top fundraiser with <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2VA10216/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$680,511</a>, and he has the support of prominent figures in what was once the tea party movement, such as Sen. <a href="https://starexponent.com/news/local/u-s-sen-mike-lee-endorses-reeves-for-congress/article_9146d440-19ab-5e19-a9de-d34ccbe467f8.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mike Lee</a> and <a href="https://freedomworksforamerica.org/press-releases/freedomworks-for-america-endorses-bryce-reeves-in-virginias-seventh-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FreedomWorks</a>. However, the right is apparently divided on this race, as Sen. <a href="https://twitter.com/tedcruz/status/1501211143691325440" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ted Cruz</a>, former state Attorney General <a href="https://twitter.com/yestoyesli/status/1490861342361886724" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ken Cuccinelli</a> and Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas’s wife and conservative activist <a href="https://twitter.com/yestoyesli/status/1513631116506370059" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Virginia “Ginni” Thomas</a> are backing Prince William County Supervisor Yesli Vega. If elected, Vega would be the first Hispanic member of Congress from Virginia.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Sen. Tom Cotton, a potential 2024 presidential candidate who has spent the cycle trying to elect more military veterans, has also <a href="https://starexponent.com/news/senator-cotton-endorses-anderson-for-congress-in-vas-7th-district/article_54f652ac-94aa-59ce-b758-0a604742dee5.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed</a> former Green Beret Derrick Anderson. The fourth serious contender is Stafford County Board of Supervisors Chair Crystal Vanuch, although she had spent significantly less money (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2VA07287/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$99,856</a>) than the other three as of June 1.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240887464-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240887464-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240887464-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240887464-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Originally, former President Donald Trump endorsed Mo Brooks for a Senate seat in Alabama, but then he rescinded his endorsement and, in the runoff, shifted his support to Brooks’s rival, Katie Britt. <p>Andi Rice / Bloomberg / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Alabama</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> U.S. Senate, 5th Congressional District, secretary of state</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>8 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/11-primaries-to-watch-in-alabama-arkansas-minnesota-and-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Previously on</a> “the Republican primary for <strong>U.S. Senate</strong> in Alabama,” Trump had endorsed loyalist Rep. Mo Brooks, then unendorsed him after he lost an early polling lead to former Business Council of Alabama President Katie Britt. However, Brooks’s campaign recovered enough to make a runoff with Britt: He received 29 percent of the vote on May 24 to Britt’s 45 percent, beating out Army veteran Mike Durant (23 percent) for second place.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That result puts Britt well within striking range of a majority, and she has one advantage in the runoff that she didn’t in the first round: <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/news/news-hgbj9bay6y2129" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s endorsement</a>. This has given her a solid lead in polls of the runoff. For example, an <a href="https://emersonpolling.reportablenews.com/pr/alabama-2022-britt-holds-double-digit-advantage-over-brooks-in-senate-runoff-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emerson College poll</a> from June 12-15 gave Britt 50 percent and Brooks 34 percent; when undecided voters were pushed to pick a candidate, Britt’s lead widened, with her getting 59 percent to Brooks’s 41 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Additionally, whoever wins on Tuesday should waltz into office in November in this deep-red state, replacing retiring Sen. Richard Shelby. Based on their reputations entering the race, you’d expect Britt to be a more pragmatic senator like Shelby (in whose office she used to work), while Brooks would be more of a pro-Trump bombthrower, but the way the primary has evolved has inverted these images somewhat. Britt has fully sided with Trump on <a href="https://twitter.com/VaughnHillyard/status/1528918324192608257" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not wanting to certify</a> the 2020 election (Shelby voted to certify), while Brooks responded to Trump’s snub of him by claiming that he stood up to the former president’s illegal demands that Brooks <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/23/us/politics/trump-mo-brooks-senate.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">help him rescind the election result</a> (though, to be clear, Brooks still believes the <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mo-brooks-fox-news-2020-election-fraud-exchange-2022-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">election was stolen</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There is also a Republican runoff on Tuesday for Brooks’s old <strong>5th District</strong>, a safely Republican seat in northern Alabama. Madison County Commission Chairman Dale Strong had been criticized for <a href="https://www.al.com/news/huntsville/2022/02/two-counties-gop-leaders-challenge-dale-strongs-right-to-run-for-congress-on-gop-ballot.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relocating a local Confederate memorial</a>, but it apparently didn’t hurt him too badly in the May 24 primary, when he took a strong first place, with 45 percent of the vote. Former Assistant Secretary of the Army for Manpower and Reserve Affairs Casey Wardynski, who is aligned with the die-hard conservative <a href="https://yellowhammernews.com/house-freedom-caucus-political-arm-endorses-casey-wardynski-in-al-5-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Freedom Caucus</a>, came in second, with 23 percent. A <a href="https://yellowhammernews.com/cygnal-poll-dale-strong-in-dominant-position-to-win-al-5-gop-runoff/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">post-primary poll</a> of the runoff gave them similar numbers (Strong with 46 percent, Wardynski with 31 percent), so Strong’s path to victory on Tuesday looks a lot shorter.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the winner of the GOP runoff for <strong>secretary of state</strong> will almost certainly become Alabama’s new top election official. And though the specific winner is still up in the air, we already know it will be someone who <a href="https://www.al.com/news/2022/02/spotlight-shines-on-alabama-secretary-of-state-race-as-views-over-2020-election-and-trump-loom-large.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gives credence</a> to baseless claims of voter fraud. State Rep. Wes Allen has <a href="https://www.alreporter.com/2022/06/07/qa-with-republican-candidates-for-alabama-secretary-of-state/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pledged</a> to withdraw Alabama from the Electronic Registration Information Center, a tool that shares voter-registration data among states and has become the subject of <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/09/1076529761/right-wing-conspiracies-have-a-new-target-a-tool-that-fights-actual-voter-fraud" target="_blank" rel="noopener">right-wing conspiracy theories</a>, while state Auditor Jim Zeigler has said that “extremely concerning questions remain” about the 2020 results in key swing states.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The May primary was very close — Zeigler received 43 percent of the vote and Allen received 40 percent — and the runoff looks like a toss-up too. A <a href="https://www.alreporter.com/2022/06/13/new-alabama-secretary-of-state-run-off-poll-shows-zeigler-above-allen/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 6-9 poll</a> of the runoff from McLaughlin &amp; Associates put Zeigler at 34 percent and Allen at 28 percent, with a plurality of voters undecided. </p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">As always, we’ll be live-blogging the results of these primaries on Tuesday night as the votes are tallied. We hope you’ll <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tune in</a>!</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655721001663554</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Jan. 6 Hearings Are Really An Inquest Into The ‘Big Lie’</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-jan-6-hearings-are-really-an-inquest-into-the-big-lie/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Jan. 6 Investigation</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/january-6th-investigation/" name="">Jan. 6 Investigation</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Jan. 6 Hearings Are Really An Inquest Into The 'Big Lie'</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 17, 2022, at 10:46 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="A screen displays video from the January 6 insurrection during a hearing" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1402697868-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1402697868-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1402697868-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1402697868-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Chip Somodevilla / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/108487673512460517" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Former President Donald Trump</a> thinks the House select committee investigating the deadly Jan. 6 riot at the U.S. Capitol shouldn’t be investigating the attack, but instead investigating the claims of voter fraud that spurred the attack. But Trump must not be watching the hearings, because they <em>are</em> about those claims. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, the hearings are less about the specific acts committed on that day, and more about the disinformation campaign Trump waged before and after the 2020 election. This campaign told millions of Americans a lie, convinced them it was true and <a href="https://www.insider.com/all-the-us-capitol-pro-trump-riot-arrests-charges-names-2021-1" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.insider.com/all-the-us-capitol-pro-trump-riot-arrests-charges-names-2021-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">inspired hundreds to attempt to violently disrupt</a> the country’s democratic process. The hearings have shown how Trump continued to promote the “Big Lie” even as his advisers told him it was nonsense, dozens of court cases attempting to prove fraud were dismissed, and investigators failed to find any evidence of fraud. The hearings have centered on the systemic rot of Trump’s denialism, and how that culminated in the Jan. 6 attack. The focus of the hearings is twofold: the disease of misinformation, not just the symptoms of its malignancy, and how that disease, when left unchecked, can devolve into a violently destructive force. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Monday, the committee used recorded and live testimony from people in Trump’s inner circle to demonstrate that the claims of election fraud being raised by Trump and his supporters were investigated and that they repeatedly turned out to be bunk. Taped testimony from Bill Stepien, Trump’s campaign manager for 2020 and former Trump Attorney General Bill Barr, as well as live testimony from Benjamin Ginsberg, a Republican election lawyer and BJay Pak, a former Trump-appointed U.S. attorney in Georgia, told stories of various claims being chased down to no avail. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Stepien recalled a claim, for example, that noncitizens had cast illegal ballots in Arizona. “And with the margins being as close as they were, as previously described, that could potentially matter,” Stepien said. So he asked Trump campaign attorney Alex Cannon to look into it. “I recall that the response to that, the reality of that, was not illegal citizens voting in the election, I think it was like overseas voters voting in the election. So obviously, people who were eligible to vote.”</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Another example was covered in Barr’s testimony — a claim that more mail-in ballots were returned in Pennsylvania than were sent out. This claim was promoted by Pennsylvania state Sen. Doug Mastriano, who is now the Republican nominee for governor in the state. Mastriano <a href="https://twitter.com/SenMastriano/status/1332398733401591808?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tweeted in November 2020</a> that the state mailed out 1.8 million ballots yet received 2.6 million mail-in votes back. But that’s not true: Mastriano was comparing the number of mail-in ballots sent out for the <em>primary</em> election to the number returned in the general election. In fact, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/fact-checking-afs:Content:9787630390" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than 3 million Pennsylvania voters</a> requested mail-in ballots for the general.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These allegations were investigated by the Justice Department as well as by Trump’s campaign team, according to testimony, and were repeatedly proven false. But those bringing this information to the then-president encountered the same problem that fact-checkers have since the election: With so many false claims of fraud, every time one was disproved, a stack of hundreds of other false claims remained.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">“There was an avalanche of all these allegations of fraud that built up over a number of days,” Barr said in recorded testimony. “And it was like playing Whac-A-Mole, because something would come out one day and then the next day it would be another issue.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">During Thursday’s hearing, the focus was on another inaccurate claim of Trump’s, that former Vice President Mike Pence could and should act to prevent the certification of the election results. Though the hearing at times turned into a dissection of constitutional language, the committee revealed that many of Trump’s legal advisers — excluding John Eastman, who concocted the Pence plan originally — had determined long before Jan. 6 that Pence could not actually stop the certification, and they made that clear to the president. Yet Trump continued to publicly suggest that Pence ought to act and that, if he didn’t, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/02/10/966396848/read-trumps-jan-6-speech-a-key-part-of-impeachment-trial" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump was “going to be very disappointed” in Pence.</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The committee tried to make the case that the continued insistence from Trump and his team that Pence had the power and responsibility to stop the vote made Pence a target: It shared video from the attack of rioters calling Pence a “traitor” who had “betrayed the United States,” and saying he “deserves to burn.” They punctuated this with never-before-seen images of Pence in the secure underground location where the secret service had escorted him after the mob breached the Capitol building. </p>





<p data-paragraph="main">As the hearings move forward through the rest of the information the committee has found, lies will almost certainly continue to be a focus. The attack was the manifestation of the underlying disease of misinformation, and the hearings help demonstrate how sick the nation has become.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 15:46:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655478001574694</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Happens When American Children Learn About Racism?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-american-children-learn-about-racism/</link>
						<dc:creator>Neil Lewis Jr.</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Neil Lewis Jr.</dc:creator>
			<category>Critical Race Theory</category>
			<category>Racism</category>
			<category>Schools</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/racism/" name="">Racism</a></p>
						
													<h1>What Happens When American Children Learn About Racism?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/neil-lewis-jr/" title="" rel="author">Neil Lewis Jr.</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 17, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt='A boy holds a "stop the hate" sign' src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1231790779-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1231790779-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1231790779-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1231790779-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Erin Clark / The Boston Globe via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Americans have spent over 150 years arguing about what kind of history we should teach to our children. In “<a href="https://www.press.umich.edu/99348/schoolbook_nation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Schoolbook Nation</a>,” a book that examines the history of conflicts over American curricula, historian Joseph Moreau noted that a variety of Americans have worried about the sky falling if the “wrong” versions of history were taught in our schools. Americans, as Moreau documented, were concerned about this in the 1870s, again in the 1920s and, <a href="https://time.com/6075193/critical-race-theory-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as we’ve seen recently</a>, they are <a href="https://www.economist.com/united-states/2021/07/10/americas-history-wars" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still concerned today</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One present source of tension is the question of whether and how we should teach children about racism, as well as other less rosy aspects of the nation’s history. Politicians, parents and other influential actors have strong and divided views about this. One side assumes that teaching a more critical version of history would be beneficial to our children and thus argue for <a href="https://envs.ucsc.edu/internships/internship-readings/freire-pedagogy-of-the-oppressed.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">adding more lessons</a> critical of American history to curricula; the other side assumes that such lessons would be harmful and therefore argue that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/10/us/texas-critical-race-theory-ban-books.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">critical content should be banned</a> from the classroom.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This, though, raises an important empirical question: What actually happens when we teach students critical lessons about American history? Or, put another way, what happens when American children learn about racism?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Social scientists have studied this question for years and found that, overall, there is a lot to be gained from schools teaching students about more challenging aspects of American history. For instance, in one <a href="https://methods.sagepub.com/reference/the-sage-encyclopedia-of-communication-research-methods/i5632.xml#:~:text=Field%20experiments%20are%20studies%20using,context%20of%20the%20natural%20environment." target="_blank" rel="noopener">field experiment</a> conducted in high schools across the Chicago metropolitan area, University of Chicago political scientist Matthew Nelsen <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11109-019-09573-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">randomly assigned nearly 700 high schoolers to read different versions of history textbook segments</a> and then measured what effect they had on students from different racial backgrounds. </p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Some students were assigned to read excerpts adapted from a widely-circulated history book that presents a relatively typical retelling of American history. Other students were assigned to read excerpts from a more critical history book that foregrounded “marginalized groups, systemic injustice and grassroots political action.” What happened to the students that read these different versions of history?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First and foremost, Nelsen found that, compared to students who read the more traditional history text, students of all racial backgrounds benefitted from reading the more critical text. Latino and Black youth, for instance, reported a greater willingness to participate in acts of political engagement and were also more willing to express their views on a variety of issues. In another work, Nelsen also found that white students <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1047840X.2021.1971457?tab=permissions&amp;scroll=top" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported a greater appreciation</a> for the contributions that Black, Latino and Asian Americans have made to American society.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Political scientists are not the only ones finding results like this. Nelsen’s findings are consistent with a larger body of research conducted by a team of psychologists from Northwestern University, the University of Georgia and the University of Vermont. In their <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1047840X.2021.1971453" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent review of the literature on this topic</a>, psychologist Sylvia Perry and her colleagues noted that teaching children about racism can actually increase the empathy they have for members of other groups, as well as their concerns about systemic racism. They point to studies showing, for example, that <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17988315/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when white children learn about racism</a> they are more likely to value racial fairness and show more positive attitudes and empathy toward Black people.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard not to look at these results and think — great! — if only our schools taught more critical histories of the U.S., it could improve how different racial groups interact with each other. But that’s not what’s happened in the last few years. In fact, there is currently an active push to restrict how race and racism are taught in schools: Between January 2021 and April 2022, almost 200 bills were introduced across the U.S. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-anti-critical-race-theory-bills-are-taking-aim-at-teachers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to ban the teaching of critical perspectives</a> on the history of the United States.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Given the benefits of teaching a more critical version of American history, one might wonder why there is such active resistance to it. But perhaps, unsurprisingly, the answer to that lies within the very same findings I already presented. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One way to <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/23727322211033000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">summarize the research</a> I’ve cited is that when American children are taught more challenging lessons about history, young people of color are inspired to become civically and politically engaged, and young white people gain greater appreciation for their fellow citizens of color. According to Columbia University psychologists Ariel Mosley and Larisa Heiphetz, <a href="https://academiccommons.columbia.edu/doi/10.7916/d8-7v4r-3059" target="_blank" rel="noopener">there may be an expansion of “moral circles” across different racial groups</a> — that is, young people from different walks of life could end up feeling greater moral obligations to work together and help one another and, as such, become less tolerant of the social systems that maintain and reinforce inequality.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If you believe in the virtues of a multiracial democracy, then the thought of a diverse coalition of young people coming together to help one another and push for the expansion of rights and greater equity and justice in society might be heartwarming. But if you have a different set of beliefs, ones that are more oriented toward <a href="https://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/3207711/Sidanius_SocialDominanceOrientation.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">social dominance</a> or a preference for hierarchy and inequality, then findings like the ones I’ve described might be the very kind of evidence that terrifies you.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Consider that in a recent <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/13684302211030009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">longitudinal study that followed over 2,600 white Americans</a> over three years, New York University and University of Massachusetts Amherst psychologists Eric Knowles, Linda Tropp and Mao Mogami found that compared to white Democrats, white Republicans believed more strongly that minority groups would collude against white people, which could threaten their standing in society if white people did not band together to defend their ingroup interests.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, these concerns about which racial groups might hold power in society are not new. Nelsen, the political scientist I mentioned earlier, <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1047840X.2021.1971457?tab=permissions&amp;scroll=top" target="_blank" rel="noopener">noted in a recent paper</a> that they have long been at the heart of debates about what history schools should teach. White Americans, for instance, have worried for some time now that teaching more critical history in our schools — lessons about racism and other forms of oppression — might cause the nation to lose some of its traditions, and could even lead to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-white-victimhood-fuels-republican-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“reverse discrimination” against white Americans</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, one reason why so many white Americans, especially white Republicans, might be concerned about the effects of teaching children about racism — and are actively trying to ban such lessons from schools — is a fear about what this type of education might mean for their own power in society. Teaching about racism could lead to greater cross-race coalition building and the expansion of rights and opportunities for racial minorities to participate in key decision-making systems, but that idea is interpreted by some Americans as an existential threat.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is the fear that’s lurking beneath the surface of debates about how to teach our nation’s history. Both sides of the debate seem to have beliefs that are aligned with the evidence: They believe, for instance, that teaching critical lessons about our nation’s history might change power dynamics in the U.S. For some, this is a good thing and something they want children to be taught. But for others, such lessons evoke a sense that they are, to use the language of University of Pennsylvania political communication scientist Diana Mutz, <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.1718155115" target="_blank" rel="noopener">under siege by engines of change</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional research from </em><em>Nicholas Norton at the Cornell Law Library</em>.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655464501049593</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What It’s Like To Open An Abortion Clinic Right Now</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-its-like-to-open-an-abortion-clinic-right-now/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>Partners In Abortion Care Clinic</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>What It’s Like To Open An Abortion Clinic Right Now</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 16, 2022, at 11:43 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="ABORTION-CLINIC-0619-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-0619-4x3-1.png?w=1024" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-0619-4x3-1.png?w=1024" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-0619-4x3-1.png?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-0619-4x3-1.png?w=2048 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY FIVETHIRTYEIGHT / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"><em>This is the first entry in a series tracking what it’s like to open an all-trimester abortion clinic in the U.S. as abortion rights are being curtailed.</em></p>



<hr><p data-paragraph="main">Late last year, Dr. Diane Horvath and Morgan Nuzzo decided they wanted to take the plunge and start their own business. They looked for funding from traditional and not-so-traditional sources, figured out creative ways to cut costs and hired lawyers to help them navigate the world of business leases, bank loans and incorporation documents.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s a journey familiar to entrepreneurs all over the country — but unlike Horvath and Nuzzo, those entrepreneurs aren’t opening an <a href="https://www.partnersinabortioncare.com/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all-trimester abortion clinic</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s an unsettling time to be an abortion provider in America. At some point in the next few weeks, the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/02/supreme-court-abortion-draft-opinion-00029473" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could overturn Roe v. Wade</a>, the 1973 opinion that established a constitutional right to abortion, sending the issue back to the states. <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/article/2022/06/13-states-have-abortion-trigger-bans-heres-what-happens-when-roe-overturned" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thirteen states</a> would promptly ban the procedure, and <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/state-policy/explore/abortion-policy-absence-roe" target="_blank" rel="noopener">another dozen</a> could heavily restrict it. If that happens, abortion providers in the states where abortion remains legal would suddenly face a <a href="https://sites.utexas.edu/txpep/files/2022/03/TxPEP-out-of-state-SB8.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">surge of out-of-state patients</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One state that’s likely to see an influx is Maryland, which is where Horvath and Nuzzo are opening their clinic, Partners in Abortion Care. In a country where abortion providers are increasingly on the defensive, both Horvath and Nuzzo are curiously upbeat. “The one thing that’s moving us along and making it so we’re not despairing is that we’re working toward getting this clinic open,” Horvath said. “We all want to burn shit down and light it on fire but we’re going to build something instead.” </p>





<p data-paragraph="main">But can they build it fast enough given the Supreme Court’s impending decision? By the time I met Horvath and Nuzzo, in April, they had been trying to get their clinic off the ground for five months. They had qualified for a business loan that they estimated would cover about a fifth of their costs, but they were still waiting to hear back from foundations that said they were committed to helping expand abortion access. In desperation, they set up a <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/expand-abortion-access-in-maryland" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GoFundMe page</a>, which ended up being a major source of funding: In just over two months, they raised more than $260,000. “I never thought I’d have to crowdfund an abortion clinic,” Horvath said. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-NuzzoHorvath.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-NuzzoHorvath.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-NuzzoHorvath.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-CLINIC-NuzzoHorvath.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>With money raised on GoFundMe and a grant from a foundation, Morgan Nuzzo (left), a certified nurse-midwife, and Dr. Diane Horvath, an OB/GYN, plan to open an all-trimester abortion clinic in Maryland this fall. <p>David F. Choy / PARTNERS IN ABORTION CARE</p></figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">When we spoke a few weeks later, Nuzzo told me she had a lead on a procedure chair she had found on Facebook Marketplace. “I’ll put it in our storage facility next to the ultrasound machine we bought on Craigslist,” she said. This sounds a little weird, Nuzzo was quick to add, but she said the equipment worked fine and they needed to make progress. “Why not just wait for our money to roll in and buy everything new? Well, we can’t if we want to open in the fall.”</p>



<hr><p data-paragraph="main">Opening a small business is never easy, but getting an abortion clinic off the ground comes with a special set of hurdles — particularly a clinic that offers abortions later in pregnancy. Even when timing and funding aren’t an issue, something as simple as <a href="https://news.syr.edu/blog/2022/05/10/architecture-expert-and-researcher-of-abortion-clinics-on-the-future-of-access/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">finding a location</a> can be incredibly difficult. Many landlords don’t want to rent to abortion providers, and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-06-03/how-zoning-law-is-used-against-abortion-providers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">local zoning laws</a> sometimes restrict where abortion clinics can operate. Other businesses might also object to being located in the same shopping plaza as a facility that’s a magnet for protesters. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Because of these challenges, it’s relatively rare for a new provider not affiliated with Planned Parenthood or another existing clinic to find its footing. According to Caitlin Myers, an economist at Middlebury College who maintains a database of abortion providers who publicly advertise their services, 356 providers opened or reopened between January 1, 2013, and June 1, 2022, while 405 clinics closed, reclosed or stopped providing abortions.<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some clinics have opened and closed multiple times since 2013, which means they may be counted more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> About 58 percent of the newly opened or reopened clinics are connected to Planned Parenthood, and many others are part of established clinic chains. The impending fall of Roe has not changed this trend. Per Myers, as of June 1, only 10 clinics had opened since January, and just three more (including Partners in Abortion Care) were planning to open in the fall. Meanwhile, 20 clinics had closed or reclosed in the first five months of the year.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1772" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic-desktop.0615.png" alt="Bar chart of dots representing the number of abortion clinics, including Planned Parenthood clinics, that have opened or closed in the U.S. each year from January 1, 2013, to June 1, 2022, showing that more abortion clinics are closing than opening. During this time the U.S. has a net loss of 49 clinics." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic-desktop.0615.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic-desktop.0615.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic-desktop.0615.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="750" height="1368" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic.0615-mobile.png" alt="Bar chart of dots representing the number of abortion clinics, including Planned Parenthood clinics, that have opened or closed in the U.S. each year from January 1, 2013, to June 1, 2022, showing that more abortion clinics are closing than opening. During this time the U.S. has a net loss of 49 clinics." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic.0615-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic.0615-mobile.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ATD.all-term-abortion-clinic.0615-mobile.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Horvath and Nuzzo are used to doing difficult things. A certified nurse-midwife, Nuzzo is something of an anomaly in her field. Maryland recently became one of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/17/states-expand-abortions-flood-of-patients-00032815" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a handful of states</a> allowing certain health-care workers who aren’t medical doctors, like registered nurses and nurse-midwives, to provide both medication and procedural abortions, but it’s still uncommon for midwives to specialize in abortion. “The only reason I’ve been trained [to do abortions] is because I just kept hanging around and being like, ‘Can I try? Can I try? Do you think I could do this?’” Nuzzo said. Horvath, for her part, comes from a more traditional background and has been an outspoken advocate for abortion rights. In 2016, after the hospital she worked for tried to stop her from talking publicly about the abortions she had performed, she filed a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/03/us/doctor-warned-to-be-silent-on-abortion-files-civil-rights-complaint.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">federal civil rights complaint</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those kinds of barriers won’t exist at Partners in Abortion Care. Despite considerable pressure from potential funders, Horvath and Nuzzo decided not to incorporate as a nonprofit, so they are free to engage in political advocacy, something they plan to continue doing. “I remember when Trump said, ‘Oh, they’re ripping babies out of the womb at 39 weeks for abortion,’ blah, blah, blah, I got asked about it in a bunch of interviews,” Horvath said. “I was working for a nonprofit advocacy organization at the time, and the wording we landed on was something like, ‘Statements like that don’t represent medical reality.’ And I was like, ‘What we should be saying is, this is a fucking lie.’” (What Trump described <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/04/28/fact-checking-trumps-comments-democrats-late-term-abortion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">does not happen</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To find a space for their clinic, Horvath and Nuzzo worked with an investor who agreed to purchase a facility for them to rent in College Park, Maryland. That gave them the security of knowing they didn’t have to raise money to buy their own space, as their landlord was supportive of the clinic. But the clock was ticking. They had signed a lease, but by early June, when Roe seemed likely to be overturned any day, they still didn’t have the keys to the facility — which meant they couldn’t buy equipment or hire staff.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Getting into the space to start renovations was another barrier. After months of fruitless meetings with potential funders, they got a $300,000 grant from a small foundation, so between that and the GoFundMe money, Horvath and Nuzzo could finally afford to start paying themselves a salary three months before the clinic was slated to open. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even that timeline — which is speedy by the standards of starting any other business — wasn’t as swift as Horvath and Nuzzo had hoped. Ideally, it would have been better to open in June, before the Supreme Court’s ruling. Now, by the time Partners in Abortion Care does open, the landscape of abortion access could be completely different. And the number of people needing the services of an all-trimester abortion clinic will probably be higher.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Horvath told me about a third-trimester abortion she had performed with Nuzzo’s help. “I remember taking care of a very young girl who was like, stunned, the whole time,” Horvath said. The patient was confused because at that stage of pregnancy, an abortion involves a labor induction, which can hurt a lot. “She kept saying, ‘Why am I in all this pain?’” Later, when the girl was in recovery, Horvath turned to her and asked what she was most looking forward to when she got home. “And she goes, ‘I kind of just want to go back to being a kid again,’” Horvath said. “I had to go into my office and I just started sobbing. And I was like, ‘I will never be able to do anything else. Because this is where I need to be.’”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In some sense, that’s why Horvath and Nuzzo are so optimistic: At a moment of crisis, they have a job to do. I talked to Nuzzo one Friday afternoon in early June, when the Supreme Court’s decision could come out any day. “I feel very happy right now,” she said. “Roe might fall on Monday, but OK: We finally have money. Enough to open, I think. This is the moment, and we’re here. So I feel good about that.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 16:43:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655397001624356</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Has Your State Made It Harder To Vote?</title>
			<link>https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/voting-restrictions-by-state/</link>
						<dc:creator>Elena Mejía</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Elena Mejía and Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Administration</category>
			<category>Politics</category>
			<category>The Big Lie</category>
			<category>Voting</category>
			<category>Voting Laws</category>
			<category>Voting Restrictions</category>
			<category>Voting Rights</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>In some, nearly every step of the voting process has changed since 2020.</p>
<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/elena-mejia-lutz/">Elena Mejía</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/">Alex Samuels</a></p>
<p>One consequence of former President Donald Trump’s “Big Lie,” or the false claim that the 2020 election was stolen, is that many states have changed voting laws in their states, making it harder to cast a ballot. In total, we found in our analysis of data from The Brennan Center for Justice, the Voting Rights Lab, the National Conference of State Legislatures and FiveThirtyEight’s own database that since the 2020 election, 24 states have passed 56 new laws that restrict voting, in some cases affecting nearly every step of the process.</p>
<p>Trump’s “Big Lie” fueled a vast amount of voting restrictionsThe number of steps in the voting process targeted by restrictive voting laws passed since 2020, sized by the number of restrictions affecting each stepINININNYNYNYNHNHNHIAIAIANDNDNDVAVAVANCNCNCGAGAGAALALALKYKYKYMSMSMSFLFLFLARARARLALALAOKOKOKKSKSKSTXTXTXAZAZAZNENENENVNVNVUTUTUTWYWYWYIDIDIDMTMTMTMEMEMEMAMAMARIRIRICTCTCTVTVTVTNJNJNJDEDEDEMDMDMDPAPAPAMIMIMIOHOHOHWVWVWVSCSCSCWIWIWIILILILMOMOMOMNMNMNSDSDSDCOCOCONMNMNMCACACAORORORWAWAWATNTNTNHIHIHIAKAKAK</p>
<p>The number of restrictions signed into law in 2021 was unprecedented. In fact, according to the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/voting-laws-roundup-may-2021">Brennan Center for Justice</a>, the total number of restrictions shatters the previous record-high year, which was 2011, when 14 states enacted 19 laws by October of that year. In other words, depending on where you live, how you cast your ballot this year could be very different. That’s why here at FiveThirtyEight, we’re going to walk you through the new voting restrictions in each state and how they might affect you at each step of the voting process.</p>
<p>REGISTER TO VOTE</p>
<p>The first step in the voting process is registering to vote. Since the 2020 election, 17 states have taken steps to increase the frequency of voter roll purges, which could remove eligible voters from the registration list, often with little notice, and require voters to reregister or cast a provisional ballot when they arrive at their polling place. This is the case in Iowa, where voters are marked as inactive if they didn’t vote in the last general election and if they haven’t registered again or reported a change to voter registration. Other states, like Montana, also took steps to make registration harder by <a href="https://montanafreepress.org/2022/05/17/montana-court-overturns-voting-rights-injunction/">ending Election Day registration</a>. In total, there are 29 new laws in place that target voter registration.</p>
<p>ELECTIONDAYELECTIONDAY35 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAY35 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAYMost states with new restrictionsdo not offer same-day voter registrationMost states with new restrictionsdo not offer same-day voter registrationMSTXAKAROHRISCTNAZFLGAINKYHINMMOIDOKNCNYDEVAKSMDMEMNNJORWVLAMAILALIACACOMIPASDWYNEUTCTNHNVWIMTVTWAMSTXAKAROHRISCTNAZFLGAINKYHINMMOIDOKNCNYDEVAKSMDMEMNNJORWVLAMAILALIACACOMIPASDWYNEUTCTNHNVWIMTVTWANorth Dakota has no voter registration.APPLY FOR MAIL-IN BALLOT</p>
<p>While <a href="https://www.ncsl.org/research/elections-and-campaigns/vopp-table-18-states-with-all-mail-elections.aspx">some states</a> conduct elections mostly or entirely by mail, other states rely on more of a mix of in-person and absentee voting. In 2020, though, given the pandemic, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-absentee-voting-looked-like-in-all-50-states/">absentee voting</a>, especially with mail-in ballots, was really popular. In fact, it helped <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-absentee-voting-looked-like-in-all-50-states/">clinch President Biden’s victory in 2020</a>. But as a result, a number of states have passed laws that restrict people’s ability to vote by mail. For instance, GOP-led states like Georgia, Texas and Iowa now prohibit mailing absentee ballot applications to voters who haven’t requested one. In total, there are 14 new laws in place that make it harder to apply for an mail-in ballot.</p>
<p>ELECTIONDAYELECTIONDAY25 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAY25 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAYEXCUSE REQUIREDNO EXCUSE REQUIREDFour states with some of themost restrictive deadlines toreturn a mail ballot alsoimplemented new restrictionsFour states with some of themost restrictive deadlines toreturn a mail ballot alsoimplemented new restrictionsKYINTXTNMAWVALARLASCNYDEMONHCTRIIAOKAZGANEFLKSNCPAMENMWIIDOHVAAKILMIMNMTNJSDWYMDNDKYINTXTNMAWVALARLASCNYDEMONHCTRIIAOKAZGANEFLKSNCPAMENMWIIDOHVAAKILMIMNMTNJSDWYMDNDDeadlines to request a mail ballot are not specified by law in North Dakota and Mississippi.RETURN MAIL-IN BALLOT</p>
<p>Some states have also tweaked existing deadlines for when absentee ballots need to be returned, giving voters less time to fill out their forms and return them to the appropriate election officials. In Arkansas, for instance, absentee ballots must now be received the Friday before Election Day (the deadline was previously the day before the election). Other states, like Kentucky and Texas, have restricted or criminalized the practice of returning absentee ballots on behalf of someone else, a practice sometimes referred to as “ballot harvesting.” In total, there are 14 new laws in place that have made returning an absentee ballot more difficult.</p>
<p>ELECTIONDAYELECTIONDAY5 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAY5 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAY15 DAYS AFTERELECTION DAY15 DAYS AFTERELECTION DAY— Iowa limited the number of drop boxesand ballot harvesting, posingextra hurdles for disabled voters— Iowa limited the number of drop boxesand ballot harvesting, posingextra hurdles for disabled votersLAARFLGAIAINKYMTALAZCOCTDEHIIDMAMEMIMNMONENHNMOKPARISCSDTNVTWIWYTXKSNCVANVMSWVNJCANYORNDAKMDOHUTILLAARFLGAIAINKYMTALAZCOCTDEHIIDMAMEMIMNMONENHNMOKPARISCSDTNVTWIWYTXKSNCVANVMSWVNJCANYORNDAKMDOHUTILThere isn’t a receipt deadline by which ballots have to be received in Washington; any ballot received after the election postmarked before Election Day counts.EARLY VOTING</p>
<p>One of the biggest changes to early voting is new restrictions on when voters can actually cast their ballots. Some states passed laws limiting the number of days people could vote early in person. In Kentucky, for instance, county clerks could offer early in-person voting in 2020 as many as 12 days out from the election, but now it’s limited to just the Thursday, Friday and Saturday before an election. Additionally, a handful of states now have new or more stringent identification requirements for those who want to vote early. In total, there are 14 new laws in place that make early voting more challenging.</p>
<p>ELECTIONDAYELECTIONDAY50 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAY50 DAYS BEFOREELECTION DAYIn-person early voting not available to all voters.In-person early voting not available to all voters.Montana now allows somepolling places to delay openings —Montana now allows somepolling places to delay openings —Texas outlawed 24-hour voting and setstricter limits on early voting hours —Texas outlawed 24-hour voting and setstricter limits on early voting hours —KYOKKSLAMDMAFLDENYUTIDWVWITXNVSCARNDHITNNMAKCONCGAORWAIARIAZINOHMTCANEWYILMIVAMEPANJSDVTMNALCTMOMSNHKYOKKSLAMDMAFLDENYUTIDWVWITXNVSCARNDHITNNMAKCONCGAORWAIARIAZINOHMTCANEWYILMIVAMEPANJSDVTMNALCTMOMSNHKansas, Florida, Utah, Colorado and Maine allow local officials some flexibility in determining early voting periods.ELECTION DAY VOTING</p>
<p>But not every voter can cast his or her ballot early. Instead, many vote in-person on Election Day. And there are three major ways states targeted Election Day voting post-2020: by introducing stricter voter ID laws, placing additional restrictions on polling places and limiting the accessibility of voting. In Texas, for instance, voting from cars or curbside voting is now banned for people without a disability, which eliminates a pandemic-era change that allowed <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/11/02/harris-county-drive-thru-locations-closed/">thousands of voters</a> to cast their ballots in one of the state’s most populous counties. Additionally, any person assisting a Texan voting in person must fill out new paperwork disclosing their relationship to the voter. In total, there are 14 new laws in place that introduce hurdles to voting in-person on Election Day.</p>
<p>BALLOT VERIFICATION</p>
<p>Casting a ballot doesn’t necessarily mark the end of the voting process. In some states, there are extra steps that take place after voting in order to verify that the person who cast a ballot is the intended voter, and that, too, has gotten more difficult after 2020. Officials, for instance, may reject ballots that do not meet certain verification requirements as is the case in Indiana, where a new law mandates that county election boards, or the absentee board members in the office of the circuit court clerk, compare the signature of the voter on the absentee ballot with the signature on the absentee-ballot application, the electronic poll book or on file. In total, there are 16 new laws in place that change the ballot verification process. Some states — though not all — do allow voters to fix mistakes on their ballot via a process known as “ballot curing.” Even the states that allow voters to fix errors have passed laws that make it more difficult to do so, like Nevada, which shortened the length of time in which voters can fix errors on ballots.</p>
<p>LimitsBALLOT CURINGStrengthens SIGNATURE MATCHINGMandatesAUDITSEstablishesFRAUD UNITSAllowsPARTISAN INTERFERENCE</p>
<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-high-turnout-in-georgia-doesnt-mean-voting-restrictions-havent-had-an-effect/">As we’ve written before</a>, though, it’s challenging at this point to see whether even the most stringent election laws will have a large-scale effect on turnout or which party wins and where. Rather, it’ll be the effect on everyday citizens that matters most when assessing how voting has gotten harder. We don’t know, for instance, whether a handful of voters or thousands of voters will be deterred — or unable to — cast a ballot in states with these new anti-democratic voting measures in place. On the whole, though, voting in this year’s elections will look different from previous cycles. It’s possible, too, that there are more restrictions on the horizon: As long as belief in the “Big Lie” remains <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/06/14/more-than-100-gop-primary-winners-back-trumps-false-fraud-claims/">a central component</a> of Republican fealty to Trump, lawmakers will continue to push measures that add additional hurdles for voters as a tool to win elections.</p>
<p>METHODOLOGY</p>
<p>The list of restrictive voting laws was collated using data from <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/state-voting-bills-tracker-2021">The Brennan Center for Justice</a>, the <a href="https://tracker.votingrightslab.org/pending/search">Voting Rights Lab</a> and <a href="https://legiscan.com/datasets">Legiscan</a>. It’s limited to any laws enacted in the 50 states since Jan. 1, 2021, that place new limitations or restrictions on the voting process. We did not include any laws that are simply rolling back voting rights expansions enacted in 2020 in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. All categorizations are based on our readings of the legislative text, and are discretionary.</p>
<p>CREDITS</p>
<p>Additional research by Jean Yi and Maya Sweedler. Additional development by Jay Boice. Illustrations by Emily Scherer. Copy editing by Maya Sweedler. Story editing by Sarah Frostenson. Visual editing by Christopher Groskopf.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655374501695631</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: More Trouble For Democrats In The Rio Grande Valley</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-more-trouble-for-democrats-in-the-rio-grande-valley/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Nevada</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>South Carolina</category>
			<category>Texas</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-more-trouble-for-democrats-in-the-rio-grande-valley/">
	<div data-podcast-id="337441" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: More Trouble For Democrats In The Rio Grande Valley">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP1940904857.mp3?updated=1655328033">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Republican Mayra Flores won the special election in Texas’s 34th Congressional District on Tuesday, avoiding a runoff and flipping the longtime Democratic seat in Texas’s Rio Grande Valley. In this installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast, the crew recaps that race and other notable results from the June 14 primaries. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Nevada, which Republicans will face off against incumbent Democrats in the highly competitive state this fall came into focus. Four statewide Republican nominees have at least dabbled in “Big Lie” conspiracy theories, including the nominee for secretary of state, Jim Marchant, who said he wouldn’t have certified the 2020 election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And in South Carolina, Trump’s endorsees against Republican incumbent representatives delivered a split decision. Rep. Tom Rice, one of ten Republicans who voted to impeach Trump, was defeated by Russell Fry. Rep. Nancy Mace, who has been critical of Trump, defeated her challenger Katie Arrington.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 22:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655329501349726</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The New National Congressional Map Is Biased Toward Republicans</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-new-national-congressional-map-is-biased-toward-republicans/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/redistricting/" name="">Redistricting</a></p>
						
													<h1>The New National Congressional Map Is Biased Toward Republicans</h1>
																			<h2>Neither party was a clear winner in redistricting, but competition and people of color definitely lost.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 15, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Back in March, I <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-house-maps-republican-bias-will-plummet-in-2022-because-of-gerrymandering/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">started off an article</a> with the sentence, “Congressional redistricting — the process of redrawing the nation’s 435 congressional districts to reflect the results of the 2020 census — is not quite finished, but it’s getting darn close.” Clearly, I jinxed it: Since then, the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national redistricting landscape</a> has changed substantially, thanks to a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extreme-bias-of-floridas-new-congressional-map/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new Republican-drawn plan</a> in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/florida/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida</a> and a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-york-just-cost-democrats-their-big-redistricting-advantage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">court-ordered</a> remap of <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-york/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, it’s taken the 2021-22 redistricting cycle from a clear win for Democrats to something <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-countless-confusing-sometimes-contradictory-takeaways-of-the-2021-22-redistricting-cycle/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far more ambiguous</a> — perhaps best described as the preservation of a Republican-leaning status quo. And a ruling earlier this month striking down <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/louisiana/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Louisiana’s congressional map</a> is yet another reminder that the 2021-22 redistricting cycle <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-34324865" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ain’t over till it’s over</a> — and, in fact, very likely won’t be over until well after 2022. That said, the map below is <em>probably</em> the one that will get used in this year’s congressional elections (with Louisiana pending, of course).<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Granted, that’s also what &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/baseballot/status/1532462996399718402?s=20&amp;amp;t=PLAj9dL_UNbziQfTkmdzsQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;I said&lt;/a&gt; before Louisiana’s map was struck down. However, there’s something special about Louisiana: It &lt;a href="https://ballotpedia.org/Primary_elections_in_Louisiana" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;doesn’t hold a traditional primary&lt;/a&gt;, so unlike every other state, it doesn’t need to use a new congressional map before the November election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>5</sup></a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1230" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615-mobile.png" alt="" width="750" height="990" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615-mobile.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/rakich.REDISTRICTING-OVERVIEW.0615-mobile.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And as has been true <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/advantage-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for decades</a>, this national congressional map is biased toward Republicans. Assuming Louisiana’s congressional map is reinstated upon appeal,<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A likely outcome given the conservative nature of the &lt;a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2018/08/30/under-trump-5th-circuit-becoming-even-more-conservative/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;5th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-conservative-supermajority-is-just-beginning-to-flex-its-muscles/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;U.S. Supreme Court&lt;/a&gt;, the two courts above the one that struck down Louisiana’s map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>6</sup></a> the 2022 House map will feature 208 congressional districts with a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> of R+5 or redder, compared with 187 districts that have a FiveThirtyEight partisan lean of D+5 or bluer. Throw in the highly competitive seats, and 225 districts would be more Republican than the country as a whole, while 210 would be more Democratic. In other words, if the national House popular vote were perfectly tied, Republicans would theoretically win 225 seats and Democrats would win 210 (ignoring, for now, other factors like candidate quality).<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If Louisiana’s old map is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reinstated and the legislature draws a new map that has two predominantly Black seats — as ordered by the lower court — you can add one seat to Democrats’ totals in this paragraph and subtract one seat from Republicans’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By this measure, however, Democrats are actually in a slightly better position than they were before, having added a handful of Democratic-leaning seats. Under the <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/blob/master/partisan-lean/fivethirtyeight_partisan_lean_DISTRICTS.csv" target="_blank" rel="noopener">old congressional lines</a> (those used in the 2020 election), there were 208 congressional districts with partisan leans of R+5 or redder and 181 with partisan leans of D+5 or bluer. Counting swing seats, 230 seats were redder than the nation as a whole, while 205 seats were bluer.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, by other measures, the new map is better for Republicans. First, the “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-tipping-point-states-favor-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tipping-point</a>” congressional seat — i.e., the majority-making 218th bluest and 218th reddest seat in the House — is slightly more Republican-leaning. Under the old lines, the tipping-point seat had a FiveThirtyEight partisan lean of R+2.3; under the new ones, the tipping-point seat will have a FiveThirtyEight partisan lean of R+2.5 (again, assuming Louisiana’s map is reinstated on appeal).<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, if Louisiana’s map is not reinstated and the legislature draws a new one with two predominantly Black seats, the tipping-point seat would go back to having a partisan lean of R+2.3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the short term (i.e., in this year’s midterms), Republicans are also more likely to pick up seats from redistricting. Remember that all the numbers above merely reflect each seat’s underlying partisanship; they don’t account for which party currently holds each seat. And when we do that, we see that more Democratic-held seats have been turned red this redistricting cycle than Republican-held seats have been turned blue. By my calculations, Republicans can expect a net gain of roughly three or four seats this November due to the effects of redistricting alone — not accounting for shifts in voter preference.<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the gory math behind that calculation. Between nine and 12 Democratic-held districts have been redrawn to favor Republicans (two in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Arizona&lt;/a&gt;, three in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/florida/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Florida&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Georgia&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/michigan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Michigan&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/ohio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Ohio&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/tennessee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Tennessee&lt;/a&gt; and potentially one each in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/kansas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Kansas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/maryland/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Maryland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-jersey/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;New Jersey&lt;/a&gt;), while between four and seven Republican-held districts have been redrawn to favor Democrats (two in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/california/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;California&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/illinois/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Illinois&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/michigan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Michigan&lt;/a&gt; and potentially one each in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/louisiana/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Louisiana&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-mexico/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;New Mexico&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/ohio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Ohio&lt;/a&gt;). That’s a net gain of five seats for Republicans, give or take. However, Republicans also lost one or two seats on net from &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;reapportionment&lt;/a&gt;: Population trends added one red seat in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/florida/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Florida&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/montana/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Montana&lt;/a&gt;, one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Texas&lt;/a&gt; and potentially one in &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Colorado&lt;/a&gt;, but they also subtracted one from &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/illinois/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Illinois&lt;/a&gt;, one from &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/michigan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Michigan&lt;/a&gt;, one from &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-york/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;New York&lt;/a&gt;, one from &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/a&gt; and one from &lt;a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/west-virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;West Virginia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>10</sup></a> </p>





<p data-paragraph="main">Some of the House map’s GOP bias is due to geography (i.e., the Democratic tendency to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/07/upshot/why-democrats-cant-win.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cluster in cities</a>, plus rural areas’ tendency to vote Republican). But a lot is also due to deliberate decisions by partisan mapmakers — namely, Republican lawmakers drawing congressional maps that advantage their own party. In 2014, a <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2457468" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pair of academics</a> created a metric called the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/sites/default/files/legal-work/How_the_Efficiency_Gap_Standard_Works.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">efficiency gap</a>, which attempts to quantify this phenomenon by measuring how efficient a map is at converting votes into seats for a given party. And using this measure, we find that seven of the 11 most biased congressional maps in the country were drawn by Republicans, while only one Democratic-drawn map (<a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/illinois/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Illinois</a>’s) provides Democrats with more than 1.2 undeserved seats. </p>


<div>

<section><header><h5>Many states’ congressional maps have strong partisan biases</h5>
 <p>How many extra congressional seats Republicans or Democrats theoretically gained from biased map-drawing in each state that has completed redistricting as of June 14, 2022, according to the efficiency-gap metric</p>
 </header><div>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.redistricting-overview.10"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="0"><span>State<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="1">Map Enacted <span>By<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="2" data-sort-method="number"><span>Districts<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="3" data-sort-method="number">Efficiency <span>Gap<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col" data-sort-index="4" data-sort-method="number" aria-sort="ascending" data-sort-default="true">Extra <span>Seats<span><span>▲</span><span>▼</span></span>
 </span>
 </th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Texas</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="38">38</td>
 <td data-sort="15.3">R+15</td>
 <td data-sort="5.814">R+5.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Florida</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="28">28</td>
 <td data-sort="20.2">R+20</td>
 <td data-sort="5.656">R+5.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>California</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="52">52</td>
 <td data-sort="5.3">D+5</td>
 <td data-sort="2.756">D+2.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Ohio</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="15">15</td>
 <td data-sort="15.5">R+16</td>
 <td data-sort="2.325">R+2.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Illinois</td>
 <td><span></span>Democrats</td>
 <td data-sort="17">17</td>
 <td data-sort="13.2">D+13</td>
 <td data-sort="2.244">D+2.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="14">14</td>
 <td data-sort="15.9">R+16</td>
 <td data-sort="2.226">R+2.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="8">8</td>
 <td data-sort="26.7">R+27</td>
 <td data-sort="2.136">R+2.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Jersey</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="12">12</td>
 <td data-sort="15.5">D+16</td>
 <td data-sort="1.86">D+1.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>South Carolina</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="7">7</td>
 <td data-sort="24.8">R+25</td>
 <td data-sort="1.736">R+1.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Iowa</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="41.6">R+42</td>
 <td data-sort="1.664">R+1.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Tennessee</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="9">9</td>
 <td data-sort="16.9">R+17</td>
 <td data-sort="1.521">R+1.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New York</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="26">26</td>
 <td data-sort="5.8">D+6</td>
 <td data-sort="1.508">D+1.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Connecticut</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="5">5</td>
 <td data-sort="29.7">D+30</td>
 <td data-sort="1.485">D+1.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Massachusetts</td>
 <td><span></span>Both parties</td>
 <td data-sort="9">9</td>
 <td data-sort="15.8">D+16</td>
 <td data-sort="1.422">D+1.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Mexico</td>
 <td><span></span>Democrats</td>
 <td data-sort="3">3</td>
 <td data-sort="39.3">D+39</td>
 <td data-sort="1.179">D+1.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Utah</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="28.7">R+29</td>
 <td data-sort="1.148">R+1.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Indiana</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="9">9</td>
 <td data-sort="12.3">R+12</td>
 <td data-sort="1.107">R+1.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oregon</td>
 <td><span></span>Democrats</td>
 <td data-sort="6">6</td>
 <td data-sort="17.2">D+17</td>
 <td data-sort="1.032">D+1.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Missouri</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="8">8</td>
 <td data-sort="11">R+11</td>
 <td data-sort="0.88">R+0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arkansas</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="21.4">R+21</td>
 <td data-sort="0.856">R+0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="42.5">D+43</td>
 <td data-sort="0.85">D+0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oklahoma</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="5">5</td>
 <td data-sort="15.6">R+16</td>
 <td data-sort="0.78">R+0.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td><span></span>Democrats</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="19.2">D+19</td>
 <td data-sort="0.768">D+0.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Alabama</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="7">7</td>
 <td data-sort="9.8">R+10</td>
 <td data-sort="0.686">R+0.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Montana</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="33.2">R+33</td>
 <td data-sort="0.664">R+0.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Rhode Island</td>
 <td><span></span>Democrats</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="28.8">D+29</td>
 <td data-sort="0.576">D+0.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Minnesota</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="8">8</td>
 <td data-sort="6.8">R+7</td>
 <td data-sort="0.544">R+0.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="17">17</td>
 <td data-sort="3">D+3</td>
 <td data-sort="0.51">D+0.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kentucky</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="6">6</td>
 <td data-sort="6.7">R+7</td>
 <td data-sort="0.402">R+0.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hawaii</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="19.9">D+20</td>
 <td data-sort="0.398">D+0.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Idaho</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="19.7">R+20</td>
 <td data-sort="0.394">R+0.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Mississippi</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="7.8">R+8</td>
 <td data-sort="0.312">R+0.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kansas</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="4">4</td>
 <td data-sort="5.7">D+6</td>
 <td data-sort="0.228">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>West Virginia</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="10.4">R+10</td>
 <td data-sort="0.208">R+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="9">9</td>
 <td data-sort="2.3">D+2</td>
 <td data-sort="0.207">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maryland</td>
 <td><span></span>Both parties</td>
 <td data-sort="8">8</td>
 <td data-sort="2.4">D+2</td>
 <td data-sort="0.192">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Virginia</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="11">11</td>
 <td data-sort="1.7">D+2</td>
 <td data-sort="0.187">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td><span></span>Court</td>
 <td data-sort="14">14</td>
 <td data-sort="1.3">D+1</td>
 <td data-sort="0.182">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Washington</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="10">10</td>
 <td data-sort="1.6">D+2</td>
 <td data-sort="0.16">D+0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maine</td>
 <td><span></span>Both parties</td>
 <td data-sort="2">2</td>
 <td data-sort="6.4">R+6</td>
 <td data-sort="0.128">R+0.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="8">8</td>
 <td data-sort="1.5">R+2</td>
 <td data-sort="0.12">R+0.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nebraska</td>
 <td><span></span>Republicans</td>
 <td data-sort="3">3</td>
 <td data-sort="2.5">D+3</td>
 <td data-sort="0.075">D+0.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Michigan</td>
 <td><span></span>Commission</td>
 <td data-sort="13">13</td>
 <td data-sort="0.3">0</td>
 <td data-sort="0.039">D+0.0</td>
 </tr></tbody></table></div>
 <footer><p>Sources: U.S. Census Bureau, The Upshot, Voting Election and Science Team, Ryne Rohla/Decision Desk HQ</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">In fairness, this wasn’t because Democrats didn’t <em>want</em> to gerrymander. If given the opportunity, they may have tried to draw Democratic-friendly maps in states like <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colorado</a> or <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/washington/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Washington</a> where they have full control of state government. However, they didn’t have the chance; those states have vested the power of redistricting in independent or bipartisan commissions. (Though commissions are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/did-redistricting-commissions-live-up-to-their-promise/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not a cure-all for gerrymandering</a> — maps like <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/california/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">California</a>’s and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-jersey/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Jersey</a>’s still have notable Democratic biases despite being drawn by commissions.) As it was, though, only five maps this cycle (worth 32 districts) ended up getting enacted unilaterally by Democratic politicians or institutions,<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although it’s worth noting that Democrats could have enacted Maryland’s and Massachusetts’s unilaterally had they wanted to, since they have veto-proof majorities in the legislature in those two states. As it happened, though, Republican Govs. Larry Hogan and Charlie Baker, respectively, agreed to sign their Democratic-drawn maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> while 18 (worth 171 districts) were enacted unilaterally by Republican ones. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s an even bigger disparity than <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we expected at the beginning of the cycle</a>, when we observed that Democrats controlled the redistricting process in eight states worth 75 districts but Republicans controlled the process in 20 states worth 187 districts. That’s because liberal courts cracked down on gerrymandering this cycle and generally enforced fairer congressional maps — even when it hurt the Democratic Party. Most notably, Democrats initially drew maps with galling efficiency gaps in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/maryland/final_plan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maryland</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-york/amended_democratic_proposal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York</a>, only to see them get struck down in court. However, courts in Republican-controlled states largely did not return the favor. For example, despite appearing to be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extreme-bias-of-floridas-new-congressional-map/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">slam-dunk</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-court-ruling-in-alabama-could-boost-black-political-power-throughout-the-south/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">illegal gerrymanders</a> under <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ohios-overturned-congressional-map-shows-how-lawsuits-might-scramble-redistricting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">established judicial precedent</a>, Republican-drawn maps in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alabama</a>, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/florida/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/ohio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ohio</a> look like they will stand for at least the 2022 election. </p>





<p data-paragraph="main">The resulting national congressional rat’s nest doesn’t just hurt Democrats; it also hurts the average voter who just wants their vote to matter. As Republicans drew maps to help protect their vulnerable incumbents, they decreased the number of competitive House seats around the country. The number of swing seats has been <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/as-swing-districts-dwindle-can-a-divided-house-stand/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">declining for years</a> due to both gerrymandering and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ending-gerrymandering-wont-fix-what-ails-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">simple polarization</a>, but this year, we’re on pace for the smallest number of non-safe seats (defined as having partisan leans between D+15 and R+15) in decades. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By our reckoning, the new maps<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other than Louisiana’s, for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> have six fewer highly competitive seats (partisan leans between D+5 and R+5) than the old ones. The number of competitive Republican districts (partisan leans between R+5 and R+15) has decreased by even more — 13 seats! However, the number of competitive Democratic districts (partisan leans between D+5 and D+15) has increased by 12.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Republicans cut competitive seats from the House</h5>
 <p>The change in the number of “solid” and “competitive” seats from the old to the new House maps in states where Democrats enacted the new map, Republicans enacted the new map and both or neither party enacted the new map as of June 14, 2022</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.redistricting-overview.11"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Category</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Dem-Enacted Maps</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">GOP-Enacted Maps</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Neither/Both Parties’ Maps</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Total</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><span></span>Solid D</td>
 <td>-3</td>
 <td>+4</td>
 <td>-7</td>
 <td>-6</td>
 </tr><tr><td><span></span>Competitive D</td>
 <td>+6</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 <td>+7</td>
 <td>+12</td>
 </tr><tr><td><span></span>Highly Competitive</td>
 <td>0</td>
 <td>-9</td>
 <td>+3</td>
 <td>-6</td>
 </tr><tr><td><span></span>Competitive R</td>
 <td>-1</td>
 <td>-9</td>
 <td>-3</td>
 <td>-13</td>
 </tr><tr><td><span></span>Solid R</td>
 <td>-2</td>
 <td>+16</td>
 <td>-5</td>
 <td>+9</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>“Solid Democratic” seats have FiveThirtyEight partisan leans of D+15 or bluer; “competitive Democratic” seats have partisan leans between D+5 and D+15; “highly competitive” seats have partisan leans between D+5 and R+5; “competitive Republican” seats have partisan leans between R+5 and R+15; “solid Republican” seats have partisan leans of R+15 or redder.</p>
 <p>Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.</p>
 <p>SOURCES: U.S. CENSUS BUREAU, THE UPSHOT, VOTING ELECTION AND SCIENCE TEAM, RYNE ROHLA/DECISION DESK HQ</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">This reflects the different goals the two parties had in redistricting this year, as can be seen plainly when we break down the seat change by which party enacted the new maps. Having <a href="https://www.wbur.org/hereandnow/2016/07/19/gerrymandering-republicans-redmap" target="_blank" rel="noopener">won the 2011-12 redistricting cycle</a>, Republicans had little left on their redistricting to-do list other than to reinforce Republican-held seats that weren’t as red as they could be. As a result, they drew a whopping 18 fewer swing and light-red seats in exchange for 16 more dark-red ones.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the other hand, the number of solidly blue seats decreased by three in states where Democrats unilaterally redistricted. But the number of light-blue seats grew by six. That’s because Democrats’ goal in redistricting wasn’t to draw safer seats for themselves; it was to draw more seats that leaned Democratic, whether by a lot or a little. The way they did this in states like <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-mexico/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Mexico</a> was to dismantle solidly blue districts and spread their wealth of Democratic voters out among more districts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, it’s a risky strategy. Democrats could hold several seats they might otherwise have lost — but, in a particularly good election year for Republicans, they could also lose seats that wouldn’t have been in danger under the old maps. But for a party trying to dig its way out from under a Republican-biased House map, it may be worth risking more losses in a worst-case scenario in order to make it possible for the party to win a majority in (more common) neutral scenarios.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Up to this point, I’ve been focusing on the partisan impact of the 2021-22 redistricting cycle. But I’d be remiss not to mention the racial impact too. As part of their efforts to draw the best possible maps for their side, both parties — but mostly Republicans — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-house-maps-republican-bias-will-plummet-in-2022-because-of-gerrymandering/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">neglected to provide full representation to people of color</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Sometimes, this took the form of denying seats to racial minorities even when their numbers could support them. For example, Texas’s nonwhite population <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/08/12/texas-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">increased by almost 4 million people</a> between the 2010 and 2020 censuses, almost single-handedly earning the state two new congressional districts. But the state did not add any new districts where people of color were the largest racial or ethnic group. Similarly, it is readily possible to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-court-ruling-in-alabama-could-boost-black-political-power-throughout-the-south/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">draw two predominantly Black districts in Alabama and Louisiana</a>, but the maps passed by those states’ Republican legislatures contained just one predominantly Black district each. (This is why Louisiana’s map has been found illegal, for now.) The new maps in <a href="https://arktimes.com/arkansas-blog/2022/03/07/federal-suit-challenges-arkansas-congressional-districts-over-racial-gerrymandering-of-2nd-district" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arkansas</a>, <a href="https://www.gpb.org/news/2021/12/31/lawsuits-claim-georgias-redistricting-maps-ignore-black-population-growth" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia</a> and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/congress-naacp-south-carolina-lawsuits-house-elections-eb3c5825d5c9582b708a3c7ddffd541d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">South Carolina</a> are also currently subject to lawsuits over racial gerrymandering.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Other times, this took the form of actively decreasing the clout of nonwhite voters. This is difficult, if not impossible, to quantify since a racial group does not have to constitute a majority of a district in order for that district to elect that racial group’s preferred candidate. But districts in Florida, Georgia, Maryland, Michigan, Nevada and North Carolina all got whiter to the extent that their ability to consistently elect Black or Hispanic voters’ candidate of choice is now in question. Most egregiously, the predominantly Black congressional district between Tallahassee and Jacksonville — which was <a href="https://mcimaps.com/lets-talk-about-the-florida-5th-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">created explicitly to elect</a> Black voters’ candidates of choice and <a href="https://jaxtrib.org/2022/02/22/florida-legislature-unite-against-gov-desantis-redistricting-expert-to-protect-black-jacksonville-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">both Democrats and Republicans alike</a> agreed was constitutionally protected — no longer exists under Florida’s new map.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Voting-rights advocates are suing over that maneuver, too, and the case is <a href="https://floridapolitics.com/archives/529274-florida-supreme-court-declines-to-hear-challenge-to-congressional-map-ahead-of-midterms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">currently pending</a> before a mid-level Florida appeals court. A final decision isn’t expected before the midterms (especially since the losing side would almost certainly appeal to the Florida Supreme Court anyway), but that doesn’t mean the lawsuit will disappear. In fact, it is just one of many lawsuits that could continue to change the face of the national congressional map for years after the “2021-22” redistricting cycle is supposed to be complete.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On that note, we already know that at least one state will have to go through the redistricting process <em>again</em> during 2023-24: <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/north-carolina/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">North Carolina</a>. The North Carolina Supreme Court struck down the legislature’s first two attempts at drawing a congressional map and eventually imposed its own, but the map is only valid for one election cycle. Several other states could join North Carolina. There’s Florida, of course, where past rulings by the Florida Supreme Court (albeit a less conservative one) suggest that the new map should be struck down as both a racial and partisan gerrymander. This would necessitate a complete redraw ahead of the elections in 2024 — or, if the case really drags on, 2026.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Ohio Supreme Court is also <a href="https://www.cleveland.com/news/2022/03/ohio-supreme-court-sets-arguments-for-challenges-to-republican-congressional-map-past-start-of-voting-for-may-primary-election.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">currently considering</a> the legality of Ohio Republicans’ second attempt at a congressional map, which is not all that different from the one that was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ohios-overturned-congressional-map-shows-how-lawsuits-might-scramble-redistricting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struck down as a partisan gerrymander</a> in January. If they strike it down again, Ohio will have to adopt a new map for the 2024 elections. And regardless, Ohio will have to adopt a new map for 2026 anyway, since this one was not passed with bipartisan support, which is required in Ohio for a map to last the entire decade.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are also Alabama and Louisiana, whose maps seem destined to be decided by a single U.S. Supreme Court decision next year, as they both hinge on the question of whether the Voting Rights Act requires them each to draw a second Black district. Because this is a federal case, the decision here could also inspire — or force — other states to redraw their maps to include fewer or more minority-opportunity seats, depending on which way the ruling goes.</p>





<p data-paragraph="main">But the case with the biggest potential repercussions is a federal lawsuit brought by Republicans in North Carolina that <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-ask-us-supreme-court-curb-state-courts-election-oversight-role-2022-03-02/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">makes a radical argument</a>: that only state legislatures, not state courts, have the power to draw new congressional districts. The Supreme Court will <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/moore-v-harper-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decide on Thursday</a> whether to take the case, and if they decide to embrace its argument to the fullest, every congressional map not enacted by a legislature could be invalidated. This would mean not only throwing out court-ordered maps in Connecticut, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Wisconsin, but potentially also commission-drawn maps in Arizona, California, Colorado, Hawaii, Idaho, Michigan, Montana, New Jersey and Washington. In other words, the 2020s could see a historic amount of mid-decade redistricting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And this underscores the folly of ever declaring redistricting complete; maps are never set in stone. The national congressional map might be “darn close” to final for 2022, but it will continue to evolve in the years after. While it’s tempting to wrap up <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our redistricting coverage</a> with a neat little bow, I’m not going to do that. Redistricting doesn’t work like that. Maps could still change; partisan and racial biases could still get better or worse. This isn’t goodbye; it’s see you later.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655289001095219</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Went Down During The June 14 Primary Elections</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/nevada-south-carolina-primary-election/</link>
						<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>2022 House Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Results</category>
			<category>Elections</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Live Blog</category>
			<category>Maine</category>
			<category>Nevada Politics</category>
			<category>North Dakota election results</category>
			<category>Primary Results</category>
			<category>South Carolina Primary</category>
			<category>Special Elections</category>
			<category>Texas Politics</category>
			<category>The Big Lie</category>
			<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 23:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655248501743676</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We Want To Hear About Your Experiences With Abortion Restrictions In U.S. Hospitals</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-want-to-hear-about-your-experiences-with-abortion-restrictions-in-u-s-hospitals/</link>
						<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>Catholic Hospitals</category>
			<category>Roe V. Wade</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>We Want To Hear About Your Experiences With Abortion Restrictions In U.S. Hospitals</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/maggie-koerth/" title="" rel="author">Maggie Koerth and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Maggie Koerth and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 14, 2022, at 2:59 PM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Midsection of female patient waiting in hospital exam room" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1309074515-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1309074515-4X3.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1309074515-4X3.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1309074515-4X3.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">If the U.S. Supreme Court really does overturn Roe v. Wade, abortion would effectively become illegal in 13 states — and heavily restricted in many others — because of trigger laws designed to go into effect either immediately or within weeks. Each of these laws is a little different, but all of them make some kind of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/04/us/abortion-trigger-laws.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exception for the health or life of the mother.</a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But determining when someone’s health or life is at risk is not always straightforward. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Medical science doesn’t come with tidy boundaries between life and death, emergency and non-emergency. Sometimes it’s not clear if an emergency is life-threatening until it’s too late. Other times, a medical problem could mean losing years of one’s life or struggling with long-term health problems but not necessarily dying today or tomorrow. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We’re looking for patients, clinicians and hospital administrators who have had to navigate these kinds of situations. We’re especially interested in talking to people who have had to ask a hospital board to approve an abortion in this kind of case, or who have been on the boards considering such cases. We want to understand how biology and medicine leave patients and the people who care for them in gray areas that can’t be easily legislated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If this describes you, we’d like to hear from you. Please fill out <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe-l422cY70CKMe_GjN8-GmubJjH5ZChEZgEeSLdNoMpqK0YA/viewform?usp=sf_link" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this form</a> and we may get back to you about an upcoming story. </p>


<div>
<iframe loading="lazy" src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe-l422cY70CKMe_GjN8-GmubJjH5ZChEZgEeSLdNoMpqK0YA/viewform?embedded=true" width="640" height="1389" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin">Loading…</iframe>
</div>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 19:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655235002361976</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>3 In 10 Americans Named Political Polarization As A Top Issue Facing The Country</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/3-in-10-americans-named-political-polarization-as-a-top-issue-facing-the-country/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>American Issues</category>
			<category>Polarization</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>3 In 10 Americans Named Political Polarization As A Top Issue Facing The Country</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/holly-fuong/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley and Holly Fuong</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 14, 2022, at 12:09 PM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="IPSOS-ISSUES-0614-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/IPSOS-ISSUES-0614-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/IPSOS-ISSUES-0614-4x3-1.png?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/IPSOS-ISSUES-0614-4x3-1.png?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/IPSOS-ISSUES-0614-4x3-1.png?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY FIVETHIRTYEIGHT / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>




				<div>
											<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/IPSOS-ISSUES_Section-Block.png" alt="" width="153" height="115" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/IPSOS-ISSUES_Section-Block.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/IPSOS-ISSUES_Section-Block.png?w=153 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/IPSOS-ISSUES_Section-Block.png?w=306 2x"></a>
										<div>
						<p>This article is part of our <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/">America's Issues</a> series.</p>
					</div>
				</div>
			


<p data-paragraph="main">Political division <a href="https://legacy.voteview.com/political_polarization_2015.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been on the rise</a> for years in the U.S. The gap between the two parties <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/solutions-to-political-polarization-in-america/confronting-asymmetric-polarization/3966003B2517E22BF288796AC4985F34" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has only grown more sharply</a> in Congress, while the share of Americans who interact with people from the other party <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-and-republicans-should-argue-more-not-less/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has plummeted</a>. Furthermore, many Americans <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/journalism/2020/03/04/about-one-fifth-of-democrats-and-republicans-get-political-news-in-a-kind-of-media-bubble/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only read news or get information</a> from sources that align with their political beliefs, which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-partisans-look-at-the-same-evidence-on-ukraine-and-see-wildly-different-things/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exacerbates fundamental disagreements</a> about the basic facts of many political problems.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, hatred — specifically, hatred of the other party — increasingly <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-hatred-negative-partisanship-came-to-dominate-american-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defines our politics</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard to overstate <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/our-radicalized-republic/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how dire the situation is</a> because it’s been this way for a while. It’s something, too, that everyday Americans are feeling — and are worried about. “American citizens are growing more extreme and isolated in their political views,” said a white woman in her mid-30s from Wisconsin who identified as a Democrat. “No one can respect each other’s opinions and try to work together in a peaceful way,” said a Republican Hispanic man from California in his mid-20s. “Individuals and the media hard-sell their own views with no understanding or attempted understanding of other viewpoints,” said an independent Black woman from Texas in her mid-60s.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polarization and extremism ranked third across a list of 20 issues that we asked about in the <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/FiveThirtyEight-2022-midterm-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">latest FiveThirtyEight/Ipsos poll</a>, which was conducted from May 26 to June 6. Using Ipsos’s <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/solutions/public-affairs/knowledgepanel" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KnowledgePanel</a>, we interviewed the same 2,000 or so Americans from our previous survey, and of the 1,691 adults who responded, 28 percent named “political extremism or polarization” as one of the most important issues facing the country,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As was the case in the first wave of our survey, we asked respondents about the most important issues in three different ways: an open-ended question where they could write what issue or issues were most important to them, and then two multiple choice questions where respondents could choose up to three issues from a list of 20, including “other” or “none of these,” that they were either personally worried about or that they thought were most important to the country. Sample is weighted to match the general population. This poll’s margin of error is +/- 2.9 percentage points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> trailing only “inflation or increasing costs” and “crime or gun violence,” the latter of which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/over-40-percent-of-americans-now-rate-gun-violence-as-a-top-issue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">surged in the aftermath</a> of mass shootings in Buffalo, New York, and Uvalde, Texas.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Americans are pretty concerned with political polarization" aria-label="Dot Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/cnADC/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="607" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Americans typically have not ranked polarization or extremism as a top concern. Historically, concerns around the economy or fear of military conflict have loomed the largest in American minds. But over the past decade, Gallup has seen a larger share of people cite <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/165302/dysfunctional-gov-surpasses-economy-top-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dissatisfaction with the government or poor leadership</a> as the nation’s top issue, reaching <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/246800/record-high-name-government-important-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">record highs</a> in recent years. This is similar to what we found in our survey, too. Almost 3 in 10 Americans said they were worried about extremism and polarization, which is essentially unchanged from our poll last month.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats were the most likely to name polarization or extremism as a top worry, at 33 percent, but independents and Republicans weren’t too far behind at 28 percent and 23 percent, respectively. This does seem, though, to be an issue that Americans who are more politically engaged care about. For instance, 38 percent of likely voters named it as a top concern, compared with 28 percent overall, which marked the largest gap between likely voters and Americans as a whole on any issue we measured.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How Americans define “polarization” varies. Some spoke of the inability of the two major parties to compromise, while others blamed political leaders or the other party. But overall, regardless of how they identified politically, most Americans blamed elites for America’s divides. Sixty-four percent said they felt political polarization is mostly driven by political and social elites, compared with only 11 percent who thought it had more to do with how ordinary Americans think and behave.<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;About 25 percent said they didn’t know or skipped the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> “Both political parties have moved way to the outside, and there's no center pole for people to meet at,” said Sandra O’Kay, an elderly woman from Virginia who identified as an independent. “Congress is not making the rules. They're just fighting one another.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And when we asked about what specific groups or ideas might be driving polarization, there was also a fair amount of consensus on the four leading contributors: politicians, wealthy donors, social media companies and mainstream media outlets. After that, though, agreement broke down, and there were some stark differences across party lines. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Americans blame politicians and the media for stoking divisions" aria-label="Dot Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/2pDYG/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="481" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The biggest splits by party came over the role of conservative media outlets, religion and religious leaders. Nearly two-thirds of Americans thought conservative media had a “major” or “significant” impact on political division. However, as you can see in the chart above, this was strongly split along party lines. Eighty-one percent of Democrats said this, compared with only 48 percent of Republicans, while independents echoed where Americans fell overall. Democrats were also more likely to say that religion or religious leaders were major drivers of polarization, which probably reflects the fact that <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2020/06/02/the-changing-composition-of-the-electorate-and-partisan-coalitions/pp_2020-06-02_party-id_2-05/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats are much more likely to be religiously unaffiliated</a> than Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There were also smaller but still noticeable splits over the role racism, capitalism and wealth inequality play in stoking division. For instance, solid majorities of both Democrats and Republicans said that they felt that racism had had a major or significant impact on polarization, with 82 percent of Democrats and 62 percent of Republicans answering that way. However, given that Republicans and Democrats <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/theres-still-a-huge-partisan-gap-in-how-americans-see-discrimination/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">view discrimination very differently</a>, they likely answered this way for very different reasons. Meanwhile, Democrats were likelier to blame wealth inequality and capitalism than were Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some of this disagreement on what’s driving polarization likely reflects just how far apart the two parties are on a variety of issues; however, even where there are stark disagreements, those differences are often still overstated. We asked respondents in our survey whether they agreed with five statements that we thought were polarizing, and to guess how members of the other party would respond. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the topic of whether abortion should be legal in cases of rape, incest or to save the life of the mother, a majority of Democrats and Republicans were on the same side — about 89 percent of Democrats and 64 percent of Republicans agreed with this statement. However, their <em>perceptions</em> of each other were starkly different: Democrats thought that a minority (only 30 percent) of Republicans agreed, whereas Republicans correctly thought that a solid majority (68 percent, which is still an underestimate) of Democrats agreed with the statement.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Americans hold some misperceptions about one another" aria-label="Dot Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/qQR4v/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="679" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That said, there were other instances where Democrats and Republicans knew just how divided they were on an issue. For instance, on the topic of what should be taught in middle and high schools, 64 percent of Democrats and 16 percent of Republicans said that schools should teach about sexual orientation and gender identity. And respondents from both parties guessed within 2 percentage points of the actual share of the other party that agreed with the statement. We saw a somewhat similar picture regarding whether middle and high schools should teach race and racism in the U.S. Eighty-three percent of Democrats said they should, while Republicans perceived Democratic support at 65 percent; meanwhile, just 29 percent of Republicans agreed, while Democrats thought 19 percent of Republicans were in support.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The disconnect between Democrats and Republicans over race and racism is further exemplified by their vastly different responses to Republican South Carolina Sen. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/04/29/992063405/president-biden-gops-tim-scott-offer-diverging-views-of-race-in-america" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tim Scott’s</a> statement, “America is not a racist country. It's wrong to try to use our painful past to dishonestly shut down debates in the present.” In our survey, we asked respondents to score eight public statements on whether they represented an extreme or non-extreme viewpoint,<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We defined “extreme” as responses that said the statement was “very” or “somewhat” extreme, and “not extreme” as responses that rated the statement as “not very” or “not at all” extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> and when they were asked to rate Scott’s anonymized quote as “extreme” or “not extreme,” almost three in four Democrats said that it was extreme, as opposed to just 34 percent of Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These partisan differences are in part related to the ethnic diversity of Democrats, as Black and Hispanic Americans account for a <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2020/06/02/the-changing-composition-of-the-electorate-and-partisan-coalitions/pp_2020-06-02_party-id_2-02/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">larger portion of the Democratic Party</a> than the Republican Party. Tellingly, respondents’ answers also varied by race or ethnicity, with nearly three-quarters of Black Americans and 57 percent of Hispanic Americans finding the statement extreme, compared to 48 percent of white Americans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Suffice it to say, there are <em>real</em> differences between the two parties, but most Americans (62 percent) still want the U.S. to actively reduce political polarization. Only 9 percent think that the U.S. should let things be.<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;About 30 percent said that they didn’t know or skipped the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> But as our poll shows time and time again, many Americans don’t think political leaders and elites represent their interests. “I feel like I have to just kind of read up on what people are saying and what people are doing and try to figure out who's the least extreme, who I side with. [To make the U.S. less polarized,] I think [we need] cooperation and collaboration between everybody, politicians and people in general,” said Sara from Alabama. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s evident, too, that polarization is weighing heavily on many Americans, as it’s hard to see a way out of our current partisan gridlock. “I think things have to hit such a dark, grizzly, rock-bottom state,” said Randal Strauss, a 55-year old independent man from Nebraska. “Where people think, hey, something's got to change.”</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional reporting by Maya Sweedler and Santul Nerkar. Art direction by Emily Scherer. Copy editing by Santul Nerkar. Graphics by Ryan Best. Story editing by Sarah Frostenson.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 17:09:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655226001678857</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>10 Elections To Watch In Nevada, South Carolina And Texas</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/10-elections-to-watch-in-nevada-south-carolina-and-texas-2/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Nevada Politics</category>
			<category>South Carolina Primary</category>
			<category>Texas Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>10 Elections To Watch In Nevada, South Carolina And Texas</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 14, 2022, at 11:37 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Nevada Primary Early Voting" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Nevada will be one of the most important states to watch on Tuesday as it hosts seven competitive primaries.													<p>Bill Clark / CQ-Roll Call, Inc. / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">This week’s primaries are a gamble — and not just because many of them are in Nevada. Former President Donald Trump is backing challengers to not one but two incumbent members of Congress, which will once again put the power of his endorsement to the test. Meanwhile, both parties face decisions about how far right or left of center a nominee can be in a swing seat and still stand a chance of winning in November.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All told, four states are holding primaries on Tuesday: Maine, Nevada, North Dakota and South Carolina. We aren’t expecting any races in Maine or North Dakota to be competitive, but to make up for it, there’s a special election in Texas that either party could plausibly win. So grab your lucky dice and let’s roll through the important elections this week.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Former state Rep. Katie Arrington is one of two primary challengers in South Carolina who has former President Donald Trump’s endorsement. <p>Sean Rayford / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>South Carolina</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> 1st and 7th congressional districts</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close:</strong> 7 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Plenty of Republicans — like South Carolina’s own senators, Lindsey Graham and Tim Scott — have walked the line between criticizing and praising Trump and have managed to stay on his good side, but Rep. Nancy Mace, of South Carolina’s <strong>1st Congressional District</strong>, has not. Despite working for his 2016 presidential campaign early in the primary season, Mace <a href="https://www.postandcourier.com/news/newsmaker-scs-nancy-mace-speaks-out-about-jan-6-and-her-former-boss-donald-trump/article_0134c7f8-61ce-11ec-8f9a-c317e9d5151b.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ripped Trump a new one</a> after the Jan. 6 attack on the Capitol, saying that the insurrection had “wiped out” “[e]very accomplishment that Republicans have made over the last four years.” However, she quickly tried to mend those fences with votes against a bipartisan Jan. 6 commission and for ousting anti-Trump Rep. Liz Cheney from House Republican leadership.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump didn’t buy it. In February, he <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/news/news-49ynqegxvm1542" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed</a> former state Rep. Katie Arrington — a loyalist who shares his false belief that the <a href="https://www.wltx.com/article/news/local/vote/mace-arrington-meet-in-south-carolina-1st-district-unitedstates-house-representative-debate-politics/101-29a0132a-8f28-4804-a2e5-86456ea8d9e6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election was stolen</a> — in the Republican primary against Mace. Notably, too, Arrington has experience taking down incumbents in this coastal, Charleston-area seat: She <a href="https://www.goupstate.com/story/news/politics/elections/state/2018/06/13/trump-backer-arrington-defeats-sanford-in-primary/11985379007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defeated former Rep. Mark Sanford</a> in the 2018 Republican primary.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Mace looks like a tougher foe, however. First, she outraised Arrington by a whopping <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0SC01394/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$4.1 million</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2SC01150/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$909,447</a>, as of May 25. Second, Mace isn’t as anti-Trump as Sanford, who briefly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2019/11/12/mark-sanford-presidential-bid-trump-069872" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ran against Trump</a> for the 2020 Republican presidential nomination; she didn’t vote to impeach Trump, for instance. She’s also <a href="https://m.facebook.com/nancyrmace/videos/im-standing-in-front-of-trump-tower-with-a-message-this-morningsc01-lowcountryfi/1054561101770084/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">argued</a> that Arrington (who lost the general election in 2018) would lose the seat to Democrats in the fall, though redistricting made the 1st District safely Republican (it has a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> of R+17), so that isn’t an honest argument. The primary could go either way: The only non-internal poll of the race, conducted May 26-29 by the <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/SC01-GOP-Primary-Poll-Report-0601.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trafalgar Group</a>, gave Mace 46 percent and Arrington 41 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Next door in the <strong>7th District</strong>, though, another anti-Trump Republican looks like he’s in more trouble. Rep. Tom Rice was one of the more anonymous members of the House GOP caucus before Jan. 13, 2021, when he shockingly <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-us-news-elections-impeachments-south-carolina-7278bdc701aaa2d74d1f46c97a6233e0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voted to impeach Trump</a> for his role in the Jan. 6 riot. (The vote came so far out of left field that some observers initially thought it was an error.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Six other Republicans, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/454411952597146/permalink/697460194958986/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all</a> <a href="https://www.spencermorrisforcongress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of</a> <a href="https://barbaraarthurforcongress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">them</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/GarrettBartonSC/status/1473815874561667075?s=20&amp;t=BrkMwQl3bZd9Mabp7BE0jg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ardent</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/MarkMcBrideUS/status/1409976933601927170?s=20&amp;t=BrkMwQl3bZd9Mabp7BE0jg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> <a href="https://www.newsobserver.com/news/state/south-carolina/article259273459.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defenders</a>, filed to run against Rice, and initially the field was <a href="https://twitter.com/IAmNickReynolds/status/1504097178700165123?s=20&amp;t=GA4y7JlS1eh2Ch6Jjg-Wxg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quite muddled</a> — Rice wasn’t polling great, but neither was anyone else. But in February, Trump tapped state Rep. Russell Fry as <a href="https://www.postandcourier.com/myrtle-beach/politics/donald-trump-endorses-russell-fry-in-primary-challenge-to-sc-congressman-tom-rice/article_863bba62-8387-11ec-ab26-63ae4d94c45d.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his preferred candidate</a>, and Fry shot up in the polls. According to another <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/SC07-GOP-Primary-Poll-Report-0601.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trafalgar Group poll</a>, also conducted May 26-29, Fry entered the home stretch with 42 percent support to Rice’s 25 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With other candidates like self-funder Ken Richardson still earning a decent share of the vote, however, it looks very possible that no one will win a majority on Tuesday. If that happens, the top two finishers — likely to be Fry and Rice — will head to a runoff on June 28. But given the size of the anti-incumbent vote, Rice is probably cooked either way.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Could Republican congressional candidate Mayra Flores flip Texas’s 34th District red?</figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Texas </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch: </strong>34th Congressional District </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>8 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Texas’s primaries <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/texas-election-biden-state-of-the-union/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were on March 1</a> with its <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/11-primaries-to-watch-in-alabama-arkansas-minnesota-and-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">runoff elections</a> on May 24, but there’s one more election on our radar in the Lone Star State before this November’s general election: the special election in the <strong>34th District</strong> <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/03/24/filemon-vela-resign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">following the resignation</a> of Democratic Rep. Filemon Vela. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The winner of Tuesday’s special election will finish Vela’s truncated term, which ends in January. But Republicans in the state are eager to go ahead and flip the 34th District as they attempt to make inroads in South Texas — along with <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democratic-gains-in-texass-big-metro-areas-could-outweigh-republican-success-in-south-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several other border-area seats</a> in the fall. Republican gains in the 34th might be short-lived, though, because while Tuesday’s election will happen under the previous, more competitive boundaries of the 34th District — which has a partisan lean of D+5 — the November election, which will decide who succeeds Vela for a full term in Congress, will be held under new district boundaries that are much more favorable to Democrats — its boundaries have a partisan lean of D+17. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the Republican side, the biggest name in the four-person field is Mayra Flores, the current GOP nominee for the seat in the November general election. Not only does Flores have the backing of Texas Gov. <a href="https://www.gregabbott.com/governor-greg-abbott-endorses-mayra-flores-for-congressional-district-34/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Greg Abbott</a>, but she also has the support of the <a href="https://congressionalleadershipfund.org/trailblazers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congressional Leadership Fund</a>, a super PAC close to House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy. There haven’t been many public polls of the race, but a new <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/5u8kf9ryfiwrb7i/RRH%20Elections%20TX-34%20Poll%20Release.pdf?dl=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RRH Elections/Poll Project USA</a> poll gave Flores a 9-point edge over her nearest opponent, former Cameron County Commissioner Dan Sanchez, a Democrat. According to the survey, Flores led among likely or completed voters with 43 percent support, while Sanchez netted 34 percent. Another internal party poll conducted in late April by <a href="https://www.nrcc.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/TX-CD-34_Memo.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ragnar Research Partners for Flores</a> and the National Republican Congressional Committee similarly gave Flores an edge over Sanchez, 24 percent support to 19 percent. In that survey, Democrat Rene Coronado, a civil service director, came in third, at 9 percent, while Republican Juana Cantu-Cabrera, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/03/01/us/elections/results-texas-us-house-district-34.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of Flores’s opponents</a> in the March primary, earned 7 percent. Forty-one percent of voters, however, were still undecided. And as far as outside spending goes, Flores has an edge here, too. She and <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1534518699805261825" target="_blank" rel="noopener">her allies</a> have <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1529849232521322503" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poured hundreds of thousands</a> of dollars and resources into TV ads, and as of May 25, Flores significantly outraised Sanchez. Sanchez does, though, have a little bit more cash on hand (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/committee/C00811901/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$104,017</a>) than Flores (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/committee/C00768994/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$100,387</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is a historically Democratic seat. Vela <a href="https://bioguide.congress.gov/search/bio/V000132" target="_blank" rel="noopener">represented the district since 2013</a>, and Democratic presidential candidates handily beat Republicans in the district in <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2021/3/23/1220127/-Daily-Kos-Elections-statewide-election-results-by-congressional-and-legislative-districts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2012 and 2016</a>. And in 2020, President Biden still won the district by <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2012/11/19/1163009/-Daily-Kos-Elections-presidential-results-by-congressional-district-for-the-2012-2008-elections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">4 percentage points</a>. But the Republican offensive has caught Democrats off guard in an area of the state <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/11/04/joe-biden-texas-border-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they have long dominated</a>. Part of the struggle for Democrats here is that the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee didn’t get involved in the race <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1533090469504245761?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">until recently</a>, when it launched a $100,000 ad buy in partnership with Sanchez’s campaign. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It seems as if Democrats’ strategy has been to avoid investing heavily in this race and instead wait until the fall. It’s also worth noting that Sanchez <em>isn’t</em> running to fill Vela’s full term; instead, it’s Democratic Rep. Vicente Gonzalez — who opted to not run in Tuesday’s special election — who <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/03/01/us/elections/results-texas-us-house-district-34.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sailed through the March 1 primary</a> and will be the party’s nominee against Flores this fall. So, even if Sanchez were to<em> </em>win, he’d hold the seat only until January. National Democrats, meanwhile, have maintained that Gonzalez will easily triumph in November, especially since that race will take place under district lines that are more favorable to Democrats. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, though, another possible wrinkle in Tuesday’s race is that the special election could<em> </em>go to a runoff given the presence of Coronado and Cantu-Cabrera, two lesser-known candidates, on the ballot; if no candidate receives a majority of the vote, the top two vote-getters go head-to-head later this year. Still, Sanchez <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/06/06/republicans-south-texas-special-election-tx-34/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has expressed confidence</a> that his party can win the seat outright.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Former state Attorney General Adam Laxalt is the front-runner in Nevada’s Republican primary for U.S. Senate. <p>Bill Clark / CQ-Roll Call, Inc / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Nevada</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> U.S. Senate; 1st, 3rd and 4th congressional districts; governor; attorney general; secretary of state</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close:</strong> 10 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democratic Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto is one of the most vulnerable politicians in the country this year, and eight Republicans are running for <strong>U.S. Senate</strong> in hopes of replacing her. The front-runner is former state Attorney General Adam Laxalt, who boasts endorsements from both <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/donald-trump-endorses-ex-nevada-ag-adam-laxalt-for-senate-2424479/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> and the <a href="https://www.clubforgrowth.org/elections/pac-endorsed-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Club for Growth</a>, an anti-government-spending outside group that has a lot of influence in Republican primaries. Laxalt was a co-chair of Trump’s 2020 campaign in Nevada and <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2021/11/08/adam-laxalt-trumpism-and-the-big-lie-a-chronology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced a lawsuit</a> two days after the election, falsely alleging that thousands of improper votes had been cast in Nevada. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Army veteran Sam Brown has run a <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/2022/05/10/republican-candidate-sam-brown-nevada-senate-race-primary-election-2022/7374118001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stunningly effective grassroots campaign</a> that has contrasted his <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/outsider-nevadas-gop-senate-primary-surges-rattling-trumps-pick-rcna31225" target="_blank" rel="noopener">outsider status</a> with Laxalt’s establishment roots. (Laxalt is the grandson of former Nevada Gov. and Sen. Paul Laxalt.) Brown has also somehow tried to position himself as even Trumpier than Laxalt, too, arguing that Laxalt was <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/09/in-an-odd-early-morning-debate-brown-says-laxalts-efforts-to-save-trump-were-too-late/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not aggressive <em>enough</em></a> in trying to stop alleged voter fraud. As of May 25, Brown has raised more than $2 million from small donors and <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/S2NV00308/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost $4 million</a> in total, which he has used to outspend Laxalt on TV and radio ads through June 1. A <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-laxalt-has-a-14-point-lead-over-brown-in-week-before-election-day" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 6-7 poll</a> from OH Predictive Insights/the Nevada Independent still gave Laxalt a 48 percent to 34 percent lead among likely voters, but that represented a tightening of the race since <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-cortez-masto-leads-laxalt-in-senate-race-but-biden-disapproval-foreboding" target="_blank" rel="noopener">January</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even more Republicans — 15! — are vying for the right to take on Democratic incumbent Steve Sisolak in the race for <strong>governor</strong>. When former Sen. Dean Heller <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/dean-heller-launches-bid-for-governor-attempts-political-comeback-three-years-after-senate-loss" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jumped into the race</a> last year, he <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/independent-poll-sisolak-cortez-masto-hold-slim-leads-over-likely-gop-opponents" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looked like the favorite</a> based on his political experience (he didn’t lose a single election from 1990 until 2018) and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/dean-heller-running-governor-nevada-refuses-say-joe-biden-won-n1279869" target="_blank" rel="noopener">born-again Trumpism</a>. But Heller <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/sisolak-raises-record-4-5-million-in-2021-has-more-cash-than-all-gop-foes-combined" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struggled with fundraising</a> and <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/politics/2022/05/05/gop-ex-u-s-senator-dean-heller-lags-race-nevada-governor/7403033001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">failed to make voters forget his moderate past</a>. By January 2022, a new front-runner <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-sisolak-leads-governor-candidates-lombardo-tops-gop-field" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had emerged</a>: Clark County Sheriff Joe Lombardo. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ironically, Lombardo is not as Trumpist as Heller on issues like <a href="https://www.8newsnow.com/news/local-news/immigration-proves-to-be-flashpoint-between-lombardo-other-gop-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">immigration</a> and the <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/politics/2021/07/01/southern-nevada-sheriff-looks-north-first-bid-governors-office/7818738002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election</a> (when asked if it was fair, he said he didn’t have enough information to say), but Trump <a href="https://www.fox5vegas.com/2022/04/28/trump-endorses-joe-lombardo-governor-nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed him anyway</a> in late April, after it became clear he was leading. Despite that vote of confidence, however, Lombardo doesn’t seem to be running away with the nomination. The aforementioned <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-lombardo-maintains-gop-governor-primary-lead-lg-and-sos-races-remain-close" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OH Predictive Insights/Nevada Independent poll</a> gave him just 34 percent, little changed from January. But instead of Heller (who took just 10 percent), his closest competitor was Trump true believer Joey Gilbert, an attorney and former professional boxer who <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/01/06/gubernatorial-hopeful-joey-gilbert-no-regrets-about-jan-6/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attended the Jan. 6 riot</a>. Gilbert received 21 percent support in the poll.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans also face a choice of whom to nominate in Nevada’s three competitive, Democratic-held U.S. House seats. Thanks to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">redistricting</a>, that list now includes the <strong>1st District</strong>, which went from a FiveThirtyEight partisan lean of D+22 to just D+4 in an attempt to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/democrats-gamble-with-their-nevada-gerrymander/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shore up the other Democratic seats</a>. Eight Republicans are <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2022/jun/10/scrum-of-challengers-jockey-to-face-titus-in-nevad/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fighting for the nomination</a>, and without any public polls of the primary, it’s hard to say who’s favored. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One strong contender could be Carolina Serrano, who led the Trump campaign’s Hispanic outreach efforts in Las Vegas in 2020. In addition to her campaign experience, Serrano has raised the most money as of May 25 (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV04094/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$568,123</a>) and has Laxalt’s endorsement. But Army veteran Mark Robertson has raised nearly as much (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV03153/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$542,621</a>) and has the backing of diehard Arizona conservative Rep. Andy Biggs. Pro-Israel activist David Brog has also raised a respectable <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV01298/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$381,728</a>, and former Rep. Cresent Hardy could draw support from those looking for an experienced hand (though he has somehow raised just <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H8NV04059/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$9,000</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Whoever wins will face Democratic Rep. Dina Titus in November … probably. Titus <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/titus-facing-hardest-race-in-recent-years-to-retain-seat-in-newly-competitive-district" target="_blank" rel="noopener">faces a challenge in the Democratic primary</a> from progressive activist Amy Vilela, who has been endorsed by <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/bernie-sanders-endorses-vilela-in-house-primary-against-incumbent-titus" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Bernie Sanders</a> and <a href="https://ourrevolution.com/endorsements/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our Revolution</a>. It’s rare, of course, for an incumbent to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ed-markey-won-but-its-still-been-a-rough-year-for-incumbents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lose in a primary</a>, but there are a couple reasons to think this could be a sleeper race. First, because of how drastically Nevada’s congressional map was redrawn, only 52 percent of people in the new 1st District are Titus’s current constituents, meaning she may not get the full benefits of incumbency. Also, despite getting outraised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H8NV03036/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.3 million</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV01264/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$490,568</a>, Vilela has actually spent more money than Titus ($437,195 to $329,210) as of May 25, suggesting Titus may not be taking the challenge seriously. (That said, it’s possible that Titus has spent a lot more since then.) If Vilela does pull off an upset, though, it could make it more challenging for Democrats to hold this newly competitive seat in the current, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican-leaning</a> political environment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans also have their eye on defeating Democratic Rep. Susie Lee in the <strong>3rd District</strong>, with its partisan lean of only D+2. Attorney April Becker looks like the <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/09/attorney-leads-in-fundraising-endorsements-in-cd3-republican-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cream of a five-candidate crop</a>: She has raised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV03161/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.2 million</a> and has a ton of institutional support from the <a href="https://nrcc.org/candidates/april-becker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Republican Congressional Committee</a>, House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy and the Nevada Republican Party. Groups that aim to elect more Republican women to Congress, such as <a href="http://maggieslist.org/candidates/2022-candidates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maggie’s List</a> and Rep. Elise Stefanik’s <a href="https://elevate-pac.com/our-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">E-PAC</a>, are also <a href="https://viewpac.org/who-we-support/#NEVADA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">backing her</a> to <a href="https://winningforwomen.com/2022-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the hilt</a>. However, two men — engineer John Kovacs and Army veteran Noah Malgeri — have also raised a <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/NV/03/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">respectable sum of money</a> for their campaigns and can’t be counted out.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, three candidates are <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/trio-of-republicans-target-horsford-in-4th-district-2577111/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seeking the Republican nomination</a> to take on Democratic Rep. Steven Horsford in the <strong>4th District</strong>, which is now Nevada’s bluest House seat, at D+5. Assemblywoman Annie Black is probably Democrats’ dream opponent; she has <a href="https://anniefornevada.com/anniegrams/the-real-big-lie-is-that-biden-won-fair-and-square/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vociferously argued</a> that the 2020 election was stolen, and she <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2021/jan/09/democratic-group-wants-nevada-lawmaker-who-cheered/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attended the Jan. 6 riot</a> outside the Capitol (but also condemned those who actually broke into the building). However, she has raised only about half as much money as Air Force veteran Sam Peters, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV04128/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$360,755</a> versus <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0NV04023/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$716,382</a>, respectively. Peters, though, is no moderate; he has said he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/07/us/politics/republican-election-fraud-claims.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would not have voted to certify</a> the results of the 2020 election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With Republican <strong>Secretary of State</strong> Barbara Cegavske term-limited, Nevadans will also elect a new top election official this year — an extremely important post given Nevada’s status as a key swing state. And most of the candidates in the Republican primary are at least sympathetic to — if not fully convinced by — Trump’s false belief that the <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2022/jun/09/gop-secretary-of-state-candidates-largely-cling-to/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election was stolen</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That includes the two front-runners, former Assemblyman Jim Marchant and former state Sen. Jesse Haw, who were tied for first place in the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1CTiQCmW_nxI108fJ9qg6VzVm_pGvctHi/edit#gid=1338850840" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most recent poll</a> of the race. However, Marchant has been much more assertive about his antidemocratic convictions. After losing a congressional race in 2020, Marchant <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/judge-rejects-marchant-request-for-new-election-in-congressional-race-over-voter-fraud-allegations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sued for a rerun of the election</a>, claiming he was a victim of fraud. “Your vote hasn’t counted for decades,” he <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/in-debates-secretary-of-state-candidates-cast-wildly-different-visions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told voters at a February debate</a>. “You haven’t elected anybody. The people that are in office have been selected. You haven’t had a choice.” Marchant says he <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/candidates-say-trump-won-2020now-running-oversee-future-elections-rcna26241" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would not have certified the 2020 election</a> in Nevada if he had been secretary of state at the time, and he wants to ban the use of electronic voting machines, mail voting and early voting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By contrast, Haw, who has been blanketing the state with <a href="https://twitter.com/haw_jesse/status/1519346263031894016?s=20&amp;t=rGq0l2QaQq7Cm2tfa-sbYQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TV ads</a> thanks to his significant financial advantage over his opponents, has been more evasive. He <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/elections-and-big-lie-come-to-the-fore-in-secretary-of-state-primaries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told the Nevada Independent</a> that the 2020 election “had a lot of shenanigans and potential fraud” but has focused mostly on besmirching Nevada’s liberal election laws, such as a new regulation allowing non-family members to return other people’s absentee ballots.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The <a href="https://dc.medill.northwestern.edu/blog/2022/05/24/nevada-sos-race/#sthash.92Cx5p68.cSjmsZ6M.dpbs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only Republican</a> who has publicly acknowledged that President Biden legitimately won the election is Sparks City Councilman Kristopher Dahir, but he took only 3 percent in the poll. The winner of the GOP primary will face attorney Cisco Aguilar, the only Democrat in the running, in November.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/meet-nevada-gop-candidates-support-trumps-big-lie-85370871</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, two Republicans are also running in hopes of unseating Democratic <strong>Attorney General</strong> Aaron Ford, the state’s chief law-enforcement officer. Former Nevada Cannabis Association President Tisha Black’s campaign is being run by consultants with <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/gop-primary-for-nevadas-top-cop-pits-establishment-backed-lawyer-against-conservative-firebrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ties to the Republican establishment</a>, but she faces a spirited challenge from conservative activist Sigal Chattah. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Chattah says she decided to run for attorney general because of her belief that Nevada’s COVID-19 restrictions were unconstitutional, and her <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SwwGGjk2XUs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">provocative rhetoric</a> on and off the campaign trail has sometimes gotten her in trouble. (Most notably, a <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/ag-candidate-in-feud-with-former-ally-says-text-not-racist-leaked-to-damage-her-2528181/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">text message was leaked</a> in which she said Ford, who is Black, “should be hanging from a [expletive] crane.”) She also says she wants to <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/20/chattah-black-spar-in-republican-ag-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prosecute women who have abortions</a>, though she has acknowledged that abortion is legally protected in Nevada and that she is obligated to uphold the law.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Both Black and Chattah have also pledged to use the power of their office to prosecute voter fraud, which they believe is <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/state-ag-races-litmus-test-gop-election-claims-82706738" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more common than it really is</a>. (“Our democracy, I believe, is in question,” Black told the <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/gop-primary-for-nevadas-top-cop-pits-establishment-backed-lawyer-against-conservative-firebrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada Independent</a>.) The <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1i1i21SmRkaavn80r1vqV89tVJcUY5JdO/edit#gid=1473190800" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only poll of the primary</a>, conducted back in early May by OH Predictive Insights/the Nevada Independent, found a toss-up race, with the two candidates virtually tied and a plurality of voters undecided.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/nevada-democrats-vulnerable-fall-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-85371231</p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">That’s all she wrote for now, but our primary coverage will continue when the results start to roll in on Tuesday night. Join us at 7 p.m. Eastern for our <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">live blog</a>!</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 16:37:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655221501686637</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>10 Elections To Watch Today</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/10-elections-to-watch-in-nevada-south-carolina-and-texas/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Nevada Politics</category>
			<category>South Carolina Primary</category>
			<category>Texas Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>10 Elections To Watch Today</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Alex Samuels</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 14, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Nevada Primary Early Voting" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240963853-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Nevada will be one of the most important states to watch on Tuesday as it hosts seven competitive primaries.													<p>Bill Clark / CQ-Roll Call, Inc. / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">This week’s primaries are a gamble — and not just because many of them are in Nevada. Former President Donald Trump is backing challengers to not one but two incumbent members of Congress, which will once again put the power of his endorsement to the test. Meanwhile, both parties face decisions about how far right or left of center a nominee can be in a swing seat and still stand a chance of winning in November.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All told, four states are holding primaries on Tuesday: Maine, Nevada, North Dakota and South Carolina. We aren’t expecting any races in Maine or North Dakota to be competitive, but to make up for it, there’s a special election in Texas that either party could plausibly win. So grab your lucky dice and let’s roll through the important elections this week.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1239146693-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Former state Rep. Katie Arrington is one of two primary challengers in South Carolina who has former President Donald Trump’s endorsement. <p>Sean Rayford / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>South Carolina</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> 1st and 7th congressional districts</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close:</strong> 7 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Plenty of Republicans — like South Carolina’s own senators, Lindsey Graham and Tim Scott — have walked the line between criticizing and praising Trump and have managed to stay on his good side, but Rep. Nancy Mace, of South Carolina’s <strong>1st Congressional District</strong>, has not. Despite working for his 2016 presidential campaign early in the primary season, Mace <a href="https://www.postandcourier.com/news/newsmaker-scs-nancy-mace-speaks-out-about-jan-6-and-her-former-boss-donald-trump/article_0134c7f8-61ce-11ec-8f9a-c317e9d5151b.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ripped Trump a new one</a> after the Jan. 6 attack on the Capitol, saying that the insurrection had “wiped out” “[e]very accomplishment that Republicans have made over the last four years.” However, she quickly tried to mend those fences with votes against a bipartisan Jan. 6 commission and for ousting anti-Trump Rep. Liz Cheney from House Republican leadership.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump didn’t buy it. In February, he <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/news/news-49ynqegxvm1542" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed</a> former state Rep. Katie Arrington — a loyalist who shares his false belief that the <a href="https://www.wltx.com/article/news/local/vote/mace-arrington-meet-in-south-carolina-1st-district-unitedstates-house-representative-debate-politics/101-29a0132a-8f28-4804-a2e5-86456ea8d9e6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election was stolen</a> — in the Republican primary against Mace. Notably, too, Arrington has experience taking down incumbents in this coastal, Charleston-area seat: She <a href="https://www.goupstate.com/story/news/politics/elections/state/2018/06/13/trump-backer-arrington-defeats-sanford-in-primary/11985379007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defeated former Rep. Mark Sanford</a> in the 2018 Republican primary.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Mace looks like a tougher foe, however. First, she outraised Arrington by a whopping <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0SC01394/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$4.1 million</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2SC01150/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$909,447</a>, as of May 25. Second, Mace isn’t as anti-Trump as Sanford, who briefly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2019/11/12/mark-sanford-presidential-bid-trump-069872" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ran against Trump</a> for the 2020 Republican presidential nomination; she didn’t vote to impeach Trump, for instance. She’s also <a href="https://m.facebook.com/nancyrmace/videos/im-standing-in-front-of-trump-tower-with-a-message-this-morningsc01-lowcountryfi/1054561101770084/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">argued</a> that Arrington (who lost the general election in 2018) would lose the seat to Democrats in the fall, though redistricting made the 1st District safely Republican (it has a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> of R+17), so that isn’t an honest argument. The primary could go either way: The only non-internal poll of the race, conducted May 26-29 by the <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/SC01-GOP-Primary-Poll-Report-0601.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trafalgar Group</a>, gave Mace 46 percent and Arrington 41 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Next door in the <strong>7th District</strong>, though, another anti-Trump Republican looks like he’s in more trouble. Rep. Tom Rice was one of the more anonymous members of the House GOP caucus before Jan. 13, 2021, when he shockingly <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-us-news-elections-impeachments-south-carolina-7278bdc701aaa2d74d1f46c97a6233e0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voted to impeach Trump</a> for his role in the Jan. 6 riot. (The vote came so far out of left field that some observers initially thought it was an error.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Six other Republicans, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/454411952597146/permalink/697460194958986/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all</a> <a href="https://www.spencermorrisforcongress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of</a> <a href="https://barbaraarthurforcongress.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">them</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/GarrettBartonSC/status/1473815874561667075?s=20&amp;t=BrkMwQl3bZd9Mabp7BE0jg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ardent</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/MarkMcBrideUS/status/1409976933601927170?s=20&amp;t=BrkMwQl3bZd9Mabp7BE0jg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> <a href="https://www.newsobserver.com/news/state/south-carolina/article259273459.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defenders</a>, filed to run against Rice, and initially the field was <a href="https://twitter.com/IAmNickReynolds/status/1504097178700165123?s=20&amp;t=GA4y7JlS1eh2Ch6Jjg-Wxg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quite muddled</a> — Rice wasn’t polling great, but neither was anyone else. But in February, Trump tapped state Rep. Russell Fry as <a href="https://www.postandcourier.com/myrtle-beach/politics/donald-trump-endorses-russell-fry-in-primary-challenge-to-sc-congressman-tom-rice/article_863bba62-8387-11ec-ab26-63ae4d94c45d.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his preferred candidate</a>, and Fry shot up in the polls. According to another <a href="https://www.thetrafalgargroup.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/SC07-GOP-Primary-Poll-Report-0601.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trafalgar Group poll</a>, also conducted May 26-29, Fry entered the home stretch with 42 percent support to Rice’s 25 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With other candidates like self-funder Ken Richardson still earning a decent share of the vote, however, it looks very possible that no one will win a majority on Tuesday. If that happens, the top two finishers — likely to be Fry and Rice — will head to a runoff on June 28. But given the size of the anti-incumbent vote, Rice is probably cooked either way.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240727010-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Could Republican congressional candidate Mayra Flores flip Texas’s 34th District red?</figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Texas </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch: </strong>34th Congressional District </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>8 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Texas’s primaries <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/texas-election-biden-state-of-the-union/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were on March 1</a> with its <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/11-primaries-to-watch-in-alabama-arkansas-minnesota-and-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">runoff elections</a> on May 24, but there’s one more election on our radar in the Lone Star State before this November’s general election: the special election in the <strong>34th District</strong> <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/03/24/filemon-vela-resign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">following the resignation</a> of Democratic Rep. Filemon Vela. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The winner of Tuesday’s special election will finish Vela’s truncated term, which ends in January. But Republicans in the state are eager to go ahead and flip the 34th District as they attempt to make inroads in South Texas — along with <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democratic-gains-in-texass-big-metro-areas-could-outweigh-republican-success-in-south-texas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several other border-area seats</a> in the fall. Republican gains in the 34th might be short-lived, though, because while Tuesday’s election will happen under the previous, more competitive boundaries of the 34th District — which has a partisan lean of D+5 — the November election, which will decide who succeeds Vela for a full term in Congress, will be held under new district boundaries that are much more favorable to Democrats — its boundaries have a partisan lean of D+17. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the Republican side, the biggest name in the four-person field is Mayra Flores, the current GOP nominee for the seat in the November general election. Not only does Flores have the backing of Texas Gov. <a href="https://www.gregabbott.com/governor-greg-abbott-endorses-mayra-flores-for-congressional-district-34/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Greg Abbott</a>, but she also has the support of the <a href="https://congressionalleadershipfund.org/trailblazers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congressional Leadership Fund</a>, a super PAC close to House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy. There haven’t been many public polls of the race, but a new <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/5u8kf9ryfiwrb7i/RRH%20Elections%20TX-34%20Poll%20Release.pdf?dl=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RRH Elections/Poll Project USA</a> poll gave Flores a 9-point edge over her nearest opponent, former Cameron County Commissioner Dan Sanchez, a Democrat. According to the survey, Flores led among likely or completed voters with 43 percent support, while Sanchez netted 34 percent. Another internal party poll conducted in late April by <a href="https://www.nrcc.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/TX-CD-34_Memo.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ragnar Research Partners for Flores</a> and the National Republican Congressional Committee similarly gave Flores an edge over Sanchez, 24 percent support to 19 percent. In that survey, Democrat Rene Coronado, a civil service director, came in third, at 9 percent, while Republican Juana Cantu-Cabrera, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/03/01/us/elections/results-texas-us-house-district-34.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of Flores’s opponents</a> in the March primary, earned 7 percent. Forty-one percent of voters, however, were still undecided. And as far as outside spending goes, Flores has an edge here, too. She and <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1534518699805261825" target="_blank" rel="noopener">her allies</a> have <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1529849232521322503" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poured hundreds of thousands</a> of dollars and resources into TV ads, and as of May 25, Flores significantly outraised Sanchez. Sanchez does, though, have a little bit more cash on hand (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/committee/C00811901/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$104,017</a>) than Flores (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/committee/C00768994/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$100,387</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is a historically Democratic seat. Vela <a href="https://bioguide.congress.gov/search/bio/V000132" target="_blank" rel="noopener">represented the district since 2013</a>, and Democratic presidential candidates handily beat Republicans in the district in <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2021/3/23/1220127/-Daily-Kos-Elections-statewide-election-results-by-congressional-and-legislative-districts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2012 and 2016</a>. And in 2020, President Biden still won the district by <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2012/11/19/1163009/-Daily-Kos-Elections-presidential-results-by-congressional-district-for-the-2012-2008-elections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">4 percentage points</a>. But the Republican offensive has caught Democrats off guard in an area of the state <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/11/04/joe-biden-texas-border-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they have long dominated</a>. Part of the struggle for Democrats here is that the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee didn’t get involved in the race <a href="https://twitter.com/PatrickSvitek/status/1533090469504245761?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">until recently</a>, when it launched a $100,000 ad buy in partnership with Sanchez’s campaign. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It seems as if Democrats’ strategy has been to avoid investing heavily in this race and instead wait until the fall. It’s also worth noting that Sanchez <em>isn’t</em> running to fill Vela’s full term; instead, it’s Democratic Rep. Vicente Gonzalez — who opted to not run in Tuesday’s special election — who <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/03/01/us/elections/results-texas-us-house-district-34.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sailed through the March 1 primary</a> and will be the party’s nominee against Flores this fall. So, even if Sanchez were to<em> </em>win, he’d hold the seat only until January. National Democrats, meanwhile, have maintained that Gonzalez will easily triumph in November, especially since that race will take place under district lines that are more favorable to Democrats. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, though, another possible wrinkle in Tuesday’s race is that the special election could<em> </em>go to a runoff given the presence of Coronado and Cantu-Cabrera, two lesser-known candidates, on the ballot; if no candidate receives a majority of the vote, the top two vote-getters go head-to-head later this year. Still, Sanchez <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2022/06/06/republicans-south-texas-special-election-tx-34/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has expressed confidence</a> that his party can win the seat outright.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1240964086-711.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Former state Attorney General Adam Laxalt is the front-runner in Nevada’s Republican primary for U.S. Senate. <p>Bill Clark / CQ-Roll Call, Inc / Getty Images</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Nevada</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> U.S. Senate; 1st, 3rd and 4th congressional districts; governor; attorney general; secretary of state</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close:</strong> 10 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democratic Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto is one of the most vulnerable politicians in the country this year, and eight Republicans are running for <strong>U.S. Senate</strong> in hopes of replacing her. The front-runner is former state Attorney General Adam Laxalt, who boasts endorsements from both <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/donald-trump-endorses-ex-nevada-ag-adam-laxalt-for-senate-2424479/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> and the <a href="https://www.clubforgrowth.org/elections/pac-endorsed-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Club for Growth</a>, an anti-government-spending outside group that has a lot of influence in Republican primaries. Laxalt was a co-chair of Trump’s 2020 campaign in Nevada and <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2021/11/08/adam-laxalt-trumpism-and-the-big-lie-a-chronology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced a lawsuit</a> two days after the election, falsely alleging that thousands of improper votes had been cast in Nevada. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Army veteran Sam Brown has run a <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/2022/05/10/republican-candidate-sam-brown-nevada-senate-race-primary-election-2022/7374118001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stunningly effective grassroots campaign</a> that has contrasted his <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/outsider-nevadas-gop-senate-primary-surges-rattling-trumps-pick-rcna31225" target="_blank" rel="noopener">outsider status</a> with Laxalt’s establishment roots. (Laxalt is the grandson of former Nevada Gov. and Sen. Paul Laxalt.) Brown has also somehow tried to position himself as even Trumpier than Laxalt, too, arguing that Laxalt was <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/09/in-an-odd-early-morning-debate-brown-says-laxalts-efforts-to-save-trump-were-too-late/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not aggressive <em>enough</em></a> in trying to stop alleged voter fraud. As of May 25, Brown has raised more than $2 million from small donors and <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/S2NV00308/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost $4 million</a> in total, which he has used to outspend Laxalt on TV and radio ads through June 1. A <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-laxalt-has-a-14-point-lead-over-brown-in-week-before-election-day" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 6-7 poll</a> from OH Predictive Insights/the Nevada Independent still gave Laxalt a 48 percent to 34 percent lead among likely voters, but that represented a tightening of the race since <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-cortez-masto-leads-laxalt-in-senate-race-but-biden-disapproval-foreboding" target="_blank" rel="noopener">January</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even more Republicans — 15! — are vying for the right to take on Democratic incumbent Steve Sisolak in the race for <strong>governor</strong>. When former Sen. Dean Heller <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/dean-heller-launches-bid-for-governor-attempts-political-comeback-three-years-after-senate-loss" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jumped into the race</a> last year, he <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/independent-poll-sisolak-cortez-masto-hold-slim-leads-over-likely-gop-opponents" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looked like the favorite</a> based on his political experience (he didn’t lose a single election from 1990 until 2018) and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/elections/dean-heller-running-governor-nevada-refuses-say-joe-biden-won-n1279869" target="_blank" rel="noopener">born-again Trumpism</a>. But Heller <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/sisolak-raises-record-4-5-million-in-2021-has-more-cash-than-all-gop-foes-combined" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struggled with fundraising</a> and <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/politics/2022/05/05/gop-ex-u-s-senator-dean-heller-lags-race-nevada-governor/7403033001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">failed to make voters forget his moderate past</a>. By January 2022, a new front-runner <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-sisolak-leads-governor-candidates-lombardo-tops-gop-field" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had emerged</a>: Clark County Sheriff Joe Lombardo. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ironically, Lombardo is not as Trumpist as Heller on issues like <a href="https://www.8newsnow.com/news/local-news/immigration-proves-to-be-flashpoint-between-lombardo-other-gop-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">immigration</a> and the <a href="https://www.rgj.com/story/news/politics/2021/07/01/southern-nevada-sheriff-looks-north-first-bid-governors-office/7818738002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election</a> (when asked if it was fair, he said he didn’t have enough information to say), but Trump <a href="https://www.fox5vegas.com/2022/04/28/trump-endorses-joe-lombardo-governor-nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed him anyway</a> in late April, after it became clear he was leading. Despite that vote of confidence, however, Lombardo doesn’t seem to be running away with the nomination. The aforementioned <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-lombardo-maintains-gop-governor-primary-lead-lg-and-sos-races-remain-close" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OH Predictive Insights/Nevada Independent poll</a> gave him just 34 percent, little changed from January. But instead of Heller (who took just 10 percent), his closest competitor was Trump true believer Joey Gilbert, an attorney and former professional boxer who <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/01/06/gubernatorial-hopeful-joey-gilbert-no-regrets-about-jan-6/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attended the Jan. 6 riot</a>. Gilbert received 21 percent support in the poll.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans also face a choice of whom to nominate in Nevada’s three competitive, Democratic-held U.S. House seats. Thanks to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">redistricting</a>, that list now includes the <strong>1st District</strong>, which went from a FiveThirtyEight partisan lean of D+22 to just D+4 in an attempt to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/democrats-gamble-with-their-nevada-gerrymander/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shore up the other Democratic seats</a>. Eight Republicans are <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2022/jun/10/scrum-of-challengers-jockey-to-face-titus-in-nevad/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fighting for the nomination</a>, and without any public polls of the primary, it’s hard to say who’s favored. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One strong contender could be Carolina Serrano, who led the Trump campaign’s Hispanic outreach efforts in Las Vegas in 2020. In addition to her campaign experience, Serrano has raised the most money as of May 25 (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV04094/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$568,123</a>) and has Laxalt’s endorsement. But Army veteran Mark Robertson has raised nearly as much (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV03153/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$542,621</a>) and has the backing of diehard Arizona conservative Rep. Andy Biggs. Pro-Israel activist David Brog has also raised a respectable <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV01298/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$381,728</a>, and former Rep. Cresent Hardy could draw support from those looking for an experienced hand (though he has somehow raised just <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H8NV04059/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$9,000</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Whoever wins will face Democratic Rep. Dina Titus in November … probably. Titus <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/titus-facing-hardest-race-in-recent-years-to-retain-seat-in-newly-competitive-district" target="_blank" rel="noopener">faces a challenge in the Democratic primary</a> from progressive activist Amy Vilela, who has been endorsed by <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/bernie-sanders-endorses-vilela-in-house-primary-against-incumbent-titus" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Bernie Sanders</a> and <a href="https://ourrevolution.com/endorsements/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our Revolution</a>. It’s rare, of course, for an incumbent to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ed-markey-won-but-its-still-been-a-rough-year-for-incumbents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lose in a primary</a>, but there are a couple reasons to think this could be a sleeper race. First, because of how drastically Nevada’s congressional map was redrawn, only 52 percent of people in the new 1st District are Titus’s current constituents, meaning she may not get the full benefits of incumbency. Also, despite getting outraised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H8NV03036/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.3 million</a> to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV01264/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$490,568</a>, Vilela has actually spent more money than Titus ($437,195 to $329,210) as of May 25, suggesting Titus may not be taking the challenge seriously. (That said, it’s possible that Titus has spent a lot more since then.) If Vilela does pull off an upset, though, it could make it more challenging for Democrats to hold this newly competitive seat in the current, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican-leaning</a> political environment.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans also have their eye on defeating Democratic Rep. Susie Lee in the <strong>3rd District</strong>, with its partisan lean of only D+2. Attorney April Becker looks like the <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/09/attorney-leads-in-fundraising-endorsements-in-cd3-republican-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cream of a five-candidate crop</a>: She has raised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV03161/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.2 million</a> and has a ton of institutional support from the <a href="https://nrcc.org/candidates/april-becker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Republican Congressional Committee</a>, House Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy and the Nevada Republican Party. Groups that aim to elect more Republican women to Congress, such as <a href="http://maggieslist.org/candidates/2022-candidates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maggie’s List</a> and Rep. Elise Stefanik’s <a href="https://elevate-pac.com/our-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">E-PAC</a>, are also <a href="https://viewpac.org/who-we-support/#NEVADA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">backing her</a> to <a href="https://winningforwomen.com/2022-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the hilt</a>. However, two men — engineer John Kovacs and Army veteran Noah Malgeri — have also raised a <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/NV/03/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">respectable sum of money</a> for their campaigns and can’t be counted out.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, three candidates are <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/trio-of-republicans-target-horsford-in-4th-district-2577111/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seeking the Republican nomination</a> to take on Democratic Rep. Steven Horsford in the <strong>4th District</strong>, which is now Nevada’s bluest House seat, at D+5. Assemblywoman Annie Black is probably Democrats’ dream opponent; she has <a href="https://anniefornevada.com/anniegrams/the-real-big-lie-is-that-biden-won-fair-and-square/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vociferously argued</a> that the 2020 election was stolen, and she <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2021/jan/09/democratic-group-wants-nevada-lawmaker-who-cheered/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attended the Jan. 6 riot</a> outside the Capitol (but also condemned those who actually broke into the building). However, she has raised only about half as much money as Air Force veteran Sam Peters, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NV04128/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$360,755</a> versus <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0NV04023/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$716,382</a>, respectively. Peters, though, is no moderate; he has said he <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/07/us/politics/republican-election-fraud-claims.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would not have voted to certify</a> the results of the 2020 election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With Republican <strong>Secretary of State</strong> Barbara Cegavske term-limited, Nevadans will also elect a new top election official this year — an extremely important post given Nevada’s status as a key swing state. And most of the candidates in the Republican primary are at least sympathetic to — if not fully convinced by — Trump’s false belief that the <a href="https://lasvegassun.com/news/2022/jun/09/gop-secretary-of-state-candidates-largely-cling-to/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election was stolen</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That includes the two front-runners, former Assemblyman Jim Marchant and former state Sen. Jesse Haw, who were tied for first place in the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1CTiQCmW_nxI108fJ9qg6VzVm_pGvctHi/edit#gid=1338850840" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most recent poll</a> of the race. However, Marchant has been much more assertive about his antidemocratic convictions. After losing a congressional race in 2020, Marchant <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/judge-rejects-marchant-request-for-new-election-in-congressional-race-over-voter-fraud-allegations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sued for a rerun of the election</a>, claiming he was a victim of fraud. “Your vote hasn’t counted for decades,” he <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/in-debates-secretary-of-state-candidates-cast-wildly-different-visions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told voters at a February debate</a>. “You haven’t elected anybody. The people that are in office have been selected. You haven’t had a choice.” Marchant says he <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/candidates-say-trump-won-2020now-running-oversee-future-elections-rcna26241" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would not have certified the 2020 election</a> in Nevada if he had been secretary of state at the time, and he wants to ban the use of electronic voting machines, mail voting and early voting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By contrast, Haw, who has been blanketing the state with <a href="https://twitter.com/haw_jesse/status/1519346263031894016?s=20&amp;t=rGq0l2QaQq7Cm2tfa-sbYQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TV ads</a> thanks to his significant financial advantage over his opponents, has been more evasive. He <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/elections-and-big-lie-come-to-the-fore-in-secretary-of-state-primaries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told the Nevada Independent</a> that the 2020 election “had a lot of shenanigans and potential fraud” but has focused mostly on besmirching Nevada’s liberal election laws, such as a new regulation allowing non-family members to return other people’s absentee ballots.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The <a href="https://dc.medill.northwestern.edu/blog/2022/05/24/nevada-sos-race/#sthash.92Cx5p68.cSjmsZ6M.dpbs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only Republican</a> who has publicly acknowledged that President Biden legitimately won the election is Sparks City Councilman Kristopher Dahir, but he took only 3 percent in the poll. The winner of the GOP primary will face attorney Cisco Aguilar, the only Democrat in the running, in November.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/meet-nevada-gop-candidates-support-trumps-big-lie-85370871</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, two Republicans are also running in hopes of unseating Democratic <strong>Attorney General</strong> Aaron Ford, the state’s chief law-enforcement officer. Former Nevada Cannabis Association President Tisha Black’s campaign is being run by consultants with <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/gop-primary-for-nevadas-top-cop-pits-establishment-backed-lawyer-against-conservative-firebrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ties to the Republican establishment</a>, but she faces a spirited challenge from conservative activist Sigal Chattah. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Chattah says she decided to run for attorney general because of her belief that Nevada’s COVID-19 restrictions were unconstitutional, and her <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SwwGGjk2XUs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">provocative rhetoric</a> on and off the campaign trail has sometimes gotten her in trouble. (Most notably, a <a href="https://www.reviewjournal.com/news/politics-and-government/nevada/ag-candidate-in-feud-with-former-ally-says-text-not-racist-leaked-to-damage-her-2528181/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">text message was leaked</a> in which she said Ford, who is Black, “should be hanging from a [expletive] crane.”) She also says she wants to <a href="https://www.nevadacurrent.com/2022/05/20/chattah-black-spar-in-republican-ag-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prosecute women who have abortions</a>, though she has acknowledged that abortion is legally protected in Nevada and that she is obligated to uphold the law.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Both Black and Chattah have also pledged to use the power of their office to prosecute voter fraud, which they believe is <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/state-ag-races-litmus-test-gop-election-claims-82706738" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more common than it really is</a>. (“Our democracy, I believe, is in question,” Black told the <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/gop-primary-for-nevadas-top-cop-pits-establishment-backed-lawyer-against-conservative-firebrand" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada Independent</a>.) The <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1i1i21SmRkaavn80r1vqV89tVJcUY5JdO/edit#gid=1473190800" target="_blank" rel="noopener">only poll of the primary</a>, conducted back in early May by OH Predictive Insights/the Nevada Independent, found a toss-up race, with the two candidates virtually tied and a plurality of voters undecided.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/nevada-democrats-vulnerable-fall-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-85371231</p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">That’s all she wrote for now, but our primary coverage will continue when the results start to roll in on Tuesday night. Join us at 7 p.m. Eastern for our <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">live blog</a>!</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655203501654513</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Are Centrists The Most Powerful Politicians?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-are-centrists-the-most-powerful-politicians/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Gun Control</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<category>Nevada</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-are-centrists-the-most-powerful-politicians/">
	<div data-podcast-id="336810" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Are Centrists The Most Powerful Politicians?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP3862188828.mp3?updated=1655157380">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">On Sunday, 10 Democrats and 10 Republicans in the Senate announced that they had reached an agreement on new gun-safety measures and funding for mental-health services and school security. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew explains how senators made this bipartisan deal and considers whether this unwritten gun-control legislation could be passed by the end of the year. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The team also discusses Alaska’s special primary election to replace its longtime U.S. representative, Don Young, who died in March. Former Gov. Sarah Palin is leading so far, but results won’t be certified for about two more weeks, until all the mail-in ballots have been processed and counted. And on Tuesday, four states — Maine, Nevada, North Dakota and South Carolina — are holding their primary elections, but only Nevada and South Carolina have competitive races; the most interesting race to watch on Tuesday, though, is another special election in Texas, where candidates are vying to succeed Rep. Filemon Vela for the rest of his term in the 34th Congressional District, after he resigned in April. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, FiveThirtyEight’s Kaleigh Rogers and Galen Druke talk about the ongoing <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-january-6-committee-hosted-a-hearing-for-the-21st-century/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House select committee hearings</a> investigating the Jan. 6 attack on the U.S. Capitol and how the messaging is developing through both emotional testimony and raw footage from the day of the insurrection.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 22:54:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655158501328451</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Overturning Roe Could Change The Way Americans Think About Abortion</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-overturning-roe-could-change-the-way-americans-think-about-abortion/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Roe V. Wade</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Overturning Roe Could Change The Way Americans Think About Abortion</h1>
																			<h2>And the Supreme Court.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 13, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="ABORTION-SCOTUS-POLLING_4x3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-SCOTUS-POLLING_4x3.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-SCOTUS-POLLING_4x3.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-SCOTUS-POLLING_4x3.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/ABORTION-SCOTUS-POLLING_4x3.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">If the conservative Supreme Court justices were hoping that eliminating abortion protections would make Americans think the country was on their side, they might not be as persuasive as they hope. <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/3574x" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A new preprint</a> from Chelsey Clark and Elizabeth Levy Paluck, researchers at Princeton University, shows that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/02/supreme-court-abortion-draft-opinion-00029473" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the recent leak</a> of a draft Supreme Court decision to overturn Roe v. Wade made some Americans more likely to think others <em>wanted</em> abortion protections. Perhaps as a result, these Americans also saw the justices as more out of step with mainstream public opinion. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Clark and Paluck conducted a panel survey of U.S. residents (one that returns to the same group of participants over time) between June 2020 and May 2022, and their study found that the share of panel participants who think that <em>other</em> Americans support legal abortion spiked after the draft opinion became public.<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In one question in this study, participants were asked, “To what extent do you believe that people in America disagree or agree that a woman should continue to be able to have an abortion legally?” and were allowed to respond “strongly agree,” “agree,” “somewhat agree,” “neutral,” “somewhat disagree,” “disagree” or “strongly disagree.” For the purpose of our analysis, we combined “strongly agree” and “agree” and omitted the share of participants who answered “neutral.” The study’s original sample comprised 3,013 participants, and by the final survey, the study had retained 1,149 of the participants. Though the sample was unweighted, its demographic makeup remained similar between the first survey and the final survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> Notably, the sample for this survey is not representative of the general U.S. population: Participants tended to be more liberal, younger, whiter and less religious than the American public as a whole. So, while the findings can’t be extrapolated to everyone in the country, several political scientists who did not conduct the research but reviewed the findings told us that the survey’s results are nevertheless an intriguing signal of how some Americans — particularly people on the left — might be responding to the leak.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Panelists likelier to say others support abortion rights after leak" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/mxvD5/21/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="634" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">After the leak, self-identified conservatives were also more likely to say that other people supported legal abortion, although the effect was smaller than among self-identified liberals. In other words, the news that the Supreme Court appears poised to overturn Roe may have made a higher share of panel participants think that Americans want to <em>keep</em> those protections, regardless of what they personally think about abortion. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the survey, personal attitudes toward the legality and morality of abortion shifted little in response to the leak. But Clark and Paluck believe that media coverage of the leak may have jolted some Americans — particularly liberals — into realizing that support for abortion rights is more widespread than they’d thought. “The leak comes out, and then there are all these headlines about outrage, about how this is going against the majority opinion of Americans,” Clark, a doctoral student in social psychology who is leading the study, told me. “That actually appears to be changing how some people are thinking about the social environment around them — what other people find to be acceptable.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s worth reiterating: Paluck and Clark’s sample is unweighted, and therefore, it isn’t representative of the country as a whole. That being said, the findings do point to how liberals in particular might be thinking about the issue. “It’s likely that [the study’s participants] do reflect a large proportion of Americans — we just can’t say with certainty that they do,” said <a href="https://govt.dartmouth.edu/people/sean-jeremy-westwood" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sean Westwood</a>, a professor of government at Dartmouth College who reviewed the study’s findings.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The strength of the study is its ability to return to the same participants again and again and to see what does — and doesn’t — change their minds. And the leak did have an impact on some of those participants. “I think what we’re seeing here is an epiphany of sorts,” said <a href="https://polisci.columbia.edu/content/donald-p-green" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Donald P. Green</a>, a professor of political science at Columbia University who also reviewed the study’s findings. “You see the liberal public, especially, being increasingly alarmed at the prospect of an activist, conservative court. It’s like they’re poker players who have just seen someone lay down their hand.” This lines up, too, with other recent polling suggesting that <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/393104/pro-choice-identification-rises-near-record-high.aspx?utm_source=alert&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=morelink&amp;utm_campaign=syndication" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats are more likely</a> to identify as “pro-choice” than they were before the leak.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The study also picked up a shift in panel participants’ view of the Supreme Court more broadly. The share of participants who believe the Supreme Court is conservative also rose after the leak. Unlike the shift in perceptions of the extent to which other Americans support legal abortion, though, this change had been building for a while. The shift seems to have accelerated between a survey from August 2020 and one from November 2021.<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These two months represent the sixth and seventh surveys in the study. The researchers did not conduct a survey for this study in the interim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a> And it was likely affected by Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, a liberal, being <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-amy-coney-barrett-could-change-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">replaced by Justice Amy Coney Barrett, a conservative</a>, giving the court’s right wing an even stronger, six-justice majority.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Panelists say the Supreme Court is growing more conservative" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/XDnVe/15/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="640" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Those results are especially noteworthy given the findings of <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/epdf/10.1073/pnas.2120284119" target="_blank" rel="noopener">another recent study</a> from a group of scholars who have tracked public opinion of the court’s decisions over more than a decade. The court’s opinions have taken a sharp right turn in recent years, but not everyone realized that was happening. “​​Democrats are kind of bad at understanding how conservative the court is,” said <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/msen/home" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maya Sen</a>, a professor at Harvard University and one of the co-authors of the paper. But it makes sense, she added, that the leak would have changed that, at least for some people. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to Sen, people tend to widely recognize only two Supreme Court cases — Brown v. Board of Education and Roe v. Wade. “So boom, we have the news that the court is going to overturn this quite popular, very widely known precedent,” she said. Clark and Paluck’s findings make a lot of sense in that context. “There’s a huge spotlight that’s all of a sudden being shined on a court that’s been operating under the radar, and showing this is actually a really conservative court,” she said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The leaked opinion, of course, was just a draft. At some point in the next few weeks, the actual ruling will come out, and it could look different. But Clark said that if the court does overturn Roe, outrage would could easily continue to grow. After all, such a ruling would lead to more media coverage as well as more discussion of how the court’s decision <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-americans-stand-on-abortion-in-5-charts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">doesn’t reflect where most Americans stand</a> on abortion. Even if people’s individual views don’t change much, the perception that the court's action is out of step with public opinion could embolden people on the left to protest and talk to their neighbors about the issue — which could, in turn, reinforce the perception that the court’s action is far more conservative than many Americans want.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And ultimately, that could be dangerous for the Supreme Court. In the past, the justices <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/who-can-stop-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have generally hewed to public opinion</a>, in part because there’s always the possibility that they could be reined in by the other branches of government. Right now, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/is-it-time-to-expand-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the risk to the court looks pretty low</a> since few congressional Democrats seem interested in adding more justices to the court — which is their main option for responding. But the findings from Clark and Paluck’s study, as well as from the study co-authored by Sen, suggest that court reform could get more popular. Clark and Paluck found that, after the leak of the Dobbs draft, the liberal participants in their panel survey were more in favor of reducing the court’s power to decide certain types of controversial issues, and Sen and her co-authors similarly found that Democrats who were more aware of how conservative the court really is were more in favor of measures to curb its power. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Whether that will translate into action by politicians is, of course, much harder to predict. But these findings suggest that overturning Roe isn’t a risk-free proposition for the justices — in fact, a backlash could already be brewing.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1655118001233502</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
