<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 21:29:06 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 20:29:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Unvaccinated America, In 5 Charts</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/unvaccinated-america-in-5-charts/</link>
						<dc:creator>Elena Mejía</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Elena Mejía</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>COVID-19 Vaccine</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">The COVID-19 pandemic is now, more than ever, a story about the unvaccinated. They’re the most vulnerable — in states reporting breakthrough infections, over 90 percent of cases, hospitalizations and deaths have occurred among people who are unvaccinated or not yet fully vaccinated, according to a <a href="https://www.kff.org/policy-watch/covid-19-vaccine-breakthrough-cases-data-from-the-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">study from the Kaiser Family Foundation</a> (KFF). And this significant pool of Americans <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/jul/17/unvaccinated-coronavirus-covid-variants-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may open the door</a> for even more dangerous mutations than the delta variant — nearly <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/delta-variant.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">twice as contagious</a> than previous strains — that could challenge the effectiveness of existing vaccines.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So who, exactly, are we talking about? Three in 10 American adults remain unvaccinated, according to the <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-july-2021/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">latest survey</a> from the KFF. But they’re not a monolith — their reasons, backgrounds, politics and willingness to eventually get vaccinated all vary. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First, among vaccine holdouts, the biggest group are those who say they definitely don’t want the vaccine — about 14 percent of the overall population — and there’s no evidence they’re changing their minds. That number has remained pretty constant for months. (The most recent poll we have was conducted in July, so we’ll have to wait to see if the increased risk posed by the delta variant changes anything.)</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1082" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1.-DESKTOPpng.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1.-DESKTOPpng.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1.-DESKTOPpng.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1.-DESKTOPpng.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1792" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1-MOBILE.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1-MOBILE.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1-MOBILE.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-1-MOBILE.png?w=1240 2x"></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ten percent of vaccine-eligible Americans want to “wait and see” how the vaccine is working for others before deciding whether to get the jab. This group has shrunk significantly over time, suggesting they can be swayed. They’re more diverse than the hard noes; 4 in 10 adults in the wait-and-see group are people of color, compared with 26 percent in the “definitely not” group. There are also larger proportions of Democrats, younger adults and people reporting lower levels of education and income among the wait-and-see-ers. They have concerns about the vaccine, but some of them are also facing access barriers, said Liz Hamel, director of public opinion and survey research at the Kaiser Family Foundation.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">“They may not have paid time off of work in getting the vaccine and recovering from side effects, they may not have a trusted health care provider that they can go to to ask them questions about the vaccine, and they’re also more likely than the ‘definitely not’ group to say that they’re worried about getting infected,” Hamel said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Most adults who have yet to get the vaccine, whether because of worries about safety or access barriers, say it’s unlikely they’ll get the jab this year — and nearly half say they “definitely” won’t. </p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="532" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Compared to the “wait-and-see” group, those in the “definitely not” group have larger proportions of non-Hispanic white adults, Republicans, adults living in rural areas and white evangelical Christians.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The 14 percent of Americans who are firmly opposed to getting the vaccine are overwhelmingly non-Hispanic white adults, they are much more likely to be insured, and they are more likely to identify as Republican.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1122" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-DESKTOP.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-DESKTOP.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-DESKTOP.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-DESKTOP.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="2862" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-MOBILE.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-MOBILE.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-MOBILE.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-3-MOBILE.png?w=1240 2x"></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">You can see partisanship geographically too: The vaccination <a href="https://www.kff.org/policy-watch/the-red-blue-divide-in-covid-19-vaccination-rates-is-growing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gap has been growing</a> between counties that voted for former President Donald Trump and those that voted for President Biden. In two months, the gap went from 6.5 percent to 11.7 percent.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-DESKTOP.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-DESKTOP.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-DESKTOP.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-DESKTOP.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1694" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-MOBILE.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-MOBILE.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-MOBILE.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-4-MOBILE.png?w=1240 2x"></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those firmly opposed to the jab are also much more likely to believe misinformation about the COVID-19 vaccines. A Kaiser Family Foundation <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-april-2021/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey</a> from April found that 81 percent of the “definitely not” group was more likely to believe or was unsure about at least one vaccine myth, including the false ideas that vaccines contain fetal cells, cause infertility or change our DNA. This may explain why they still overwhelmingly think the vaccine is a bigger risk to their health than COVID-19.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="886" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-DESKTOP.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-DESKTOP.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-DESKTOP.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-DESKTOP.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1668" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-MOBILE.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-MOBILE.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-MOBILE.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mejia.VACCINE-POLLS.0813-5-MOBILE.png?w=1240 2x"></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">So as the ‘wait and see’ group has shrunk over the last few months, and the share of vaccinated Americans has climbed to about 70 percent, the bloc of still unvaccinated Americans has become more heavily made up of those who remain staunchly unpersuaded to get a vaccine. And that could become a problem for everyone. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/06/science/johnson-delta-vaccine-booster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vaccines</a> <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-delta-variant-and-covid-19-vaccines-what-to-know-11627079604" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have proven</a> to be effective against the delta variant, but unvaccinated Americans can open the door for more dangerous mutations. If that time comes, vaccinated Americans may be in trouble too, Dr. Anthony Fauci of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases said in an <a href="https://www.mcclatchydc.com/news/coronavirus/article253248688.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">interview</a> with McClatchy last week.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“People who are not getting vaccinated mistakenly think it’s only about them. But it isn’t. It’s about everybody else, also,” Fauci said.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/year-karaoke-fivethirtyeight-77653577</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-lotteries-smart-nudge-improve-vaccination-rates-nate-77989609</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628851502737416</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How The Infrastructure Deal Might Test The Limits Of Popular Bills</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-infrastructure-deal-might-test-the-limits-of-popular-bills/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>House Democrats</category>
			<category>Infrastructure</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Mitch McConnell</category>
			<category>Nancy Pelosi</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Something rare just happened in Congress. During an era defined by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-much-longer-can-this-era-of-political-gridlock-last/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">extreme partisan animosity</a>, Republican and Democratic senators came together on Tuesday<strong> </strong>to <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/senate-passes-11-trillion-bipartisan-infrastructure-bill-big/story?id=79378221" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pass a $1.1 trillion infrastructure package</a> that invests billions of dollars in roads, bridges and infrastructure projects; provides federal funding to <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/inside-senates-bipartisan-infrastructure-bill-79387452" target="_blank" rel="noopener">modernize public transportation</a> and the electrical grid, allowing for more <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/02/us/climate-electricity-infrastructure.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">renewable energy</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At first blush, this looks like a huge win for President Biden, who campaigned on <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/22/biden-bipartisan-infrastructure-deal-500526" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the importance of bipartisanship</a>. And as my colleague Geoffrey Skelley <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-much-do-americans-really-care-about-bipartisanship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previously reported</a>, Americans like it (or at least they say they like it) when Republicans and Democrats work together. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But this bill is not without political risk for Biden and Democrats. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For starters, it faces a long path to becoming law. That’s because House Speaker Nancy Pelosi <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/08/11/senate-passes-infrastructure-bill-and-budget-resolution.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has held firm</a> in her decision to not bring up the infrastructure bill in the House until the Senate passes a second, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/08/11/senate-passes-3point5-trillion-budget-resolution-after-infrastructure-bill.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">far more ambitious spending package</a> through the budget reconciliation process. Progressive House members have also threatened to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/08/10/the-senate-passes-infrastructure-bill-whats-next.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">withhold support for the bipartisan infrastructure bill</a> unless the Senate acts on this bigger package that includes funding for climate change and health care, among other priorities. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This could set up a big political fight for Democrats this fall. Sen. Joe Manchin of West Virginia, one of the chamber’s most vocal moderate Democrats, says <a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-business-825739838a790668b2d2855a72821d56" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he has not decided</a> if he’ll support the legislation with its current price tag of $3.5 trillion, issuing a statement in which he warned of the bill’s “<a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/us-senate-debate-35-trillion-spending-plan-enters-second-day-2021-08-11/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">grave consequences</a>” for the nation’s debt. Sen. Krysten Sinema of Arizona, another vocal moderate, said in late July that <a href="https://www.azcentral.com/story/news/politics/arizona/2021/07/28/arizona-sen-kyrsten-sinema-wont-back-democrats-3-5-trillion-reconciliation-bill/5402193001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">she will not support</a> a bill of that price. Plus, touting ambitious bill packages hasn’t worked well for Democrats in the past. Back in 2010, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/WN/HealthCare/obama-signs-health-care-bill-law/story?id=10178597" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Affordable Care Act</a> faced a similarly divided Democratic Party, and in fact, subsequent research suggests that the law hurt Democrats in that year’s midterms. <a href="https://sites.dartmouth.edu/nyhan/files/2021/03/health-care-vote-effects.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">One 2012 study found</a> that Democrats who voted in favor of the ACA saw their vote share <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1532673X11433768" target="_blank" rel="noopener">drop by 8.5 percentage points</a>, on average. Moreover, Republicans didn’t just do well that midterm cycle — they won their largest share of seats in the House <a href="https://history.house.gov/Institution/Party-Divisions/74-Present/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">since the 1940s</a>.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/bidens-approval-rating-fallen-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79388894</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that voters will be turned off if the fight over passing the infrastructure and reconciliation bills drags on too long and is perceived as too complicated. Research has found that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/voters-like-a-political-party-until-it-passes-laws/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voters often punish</a> — rather than reward — parties that move to achieve their policy goals. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s working in Democrats’ favor right now, though, is that the infrastructure bill is popular. An <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2021/08/04/americans-support-infrastructure-bill-poll" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economist/YouGov</a> poll from last week found that 51 percent of U.S. adults supported the infrastructure measure, while just 19 percent opposed it. A Quinnipiac survey <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3814" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released the same day</a> put support for the bill even higher, with 65 percent of Americans approving of the package. That said, both polls suggest that more Democrats than Republicans are in favor: 61 percent of Democrats versus 47 percent of Republicans in the Economist/YouGov poll, and a whopping 93 percent of Democrats versus 41 percent of Republicans in the Quinnipiac poll.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One reason something like infrastructure appeals to Americans is because many think that improving infrastructure should be a priority in Washington. According to an <a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-business-government-and-politics-only-on-ap-a5454467619247e89b9c87697ac0d6f5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AP-NORC survey in July</a>, both Republicans and Democrats were overwhelmingly in favor of various proposals for the infrastructure bill, including funding for roads, bridges and ports as well as funding for pipes that supply public drinking water.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/presidents-used-to-be-the-faces-of-their-political-parties-is-that-no-longer-the-case/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="Biden standing at a podium in mid-sentence." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1233836459-4x3-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1233836459-4x3-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1233836459-4x3-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1233836459-4x3-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Presidents Used To Be The Faces Of Their Political Parties. Is That No Longer The Case? <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/presidents-used-to-be-the-faces-of-their-political-parties-is-that-no-longer-the-case/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">And this fits in <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2021/06/bidens-plan-for-getting-big-things-done.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden’s governing strategy</a> of trying to pass measures that are popular with the overall electorate in the hope that voters will later reward him and Democrats. But it’s not clear whether that strategy will pay off. It’s certainly better than Biden trying to push through unpopular bills, but as the Washington Post’s Perry Bacon Jr. wrote for FiveThirtyEight earlier this year, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-dont-fear-an-electoral-backlash-for-opposing-really-popular-parts-of-bidens-agenda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">popularity around the COVID-19 stimulus package</a> that Democrats passed in Biden’s first 100 days may not result in electoral benefits. For instance, polling from the Pew Research Center found that support for the bill was especially high among <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/can-bidens-covid-19-relief-bill-help-democrats-avoid-a-midterm-defeat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lower-income Republicans</a>, but at least as it pertains to Biden’s approval rating, Republican voters not only largely disapprove of Biden, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-really-really-dislike-biden-but-its-not-just-about-him/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they <em>strongly</em> disapprove of him</a> as well. At the end of the day, it could be that most Americans are not going to break from their political views regardless of what the other side passes in terms of policy.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also likely Republicans will <a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-business-climate-164e59e31e42a646bc520042ac5e13af" target="_blank" rel="noopener">try and use the high cost</a> of the infrastructure and reconciliation bills as leverage against Democrats next year. A <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/most-gop-senators-sign-pledge-to-not-help-democrats-on-debt-ceiling-11628638081" target="_blank" rel="noopener">number of Republicans</a>, including Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell, have already vowed that Democrats “<a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-business-9fa48bfe5daeb95179cf539b59c4b7e2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">won’t get our help</a>” to raise the debt limit. Moreover, the bipartisan infrastructure bill now in front of the House is expensive. According to an estimate from the nonpartisan Congressional Budget Office, the bill is expected to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/05/us/politics/infrastructure-cost-senate-cbo.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">add $256 billion to the federal debt</a> over the next decade, and as we hinted at, debate over the debt limit this fall is already expected to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/08/09/democrats-debt-limit-mcconnell-502885" target="_blank" rel="noopener">further divide the two parties</a>. Plus, polls suggest that even now voters are concerned about inflation and the federal government’s ability to handle it. According to a <a href="https://thehill.com/hilltv/what-americas-thinking/566297-poll-inflation-named-as-top-economic-concern-among-voters" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hill-HarrisX poll</a> in August, 31 percent of registered voters named inflation as their top concern when thinking about the future of the economy. Among Republicans, that number jumped to 37 percent, but 23 percent of Democrats also put inflation as their top concern. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With Congress in recess until mid-September, it’ll be awhile before we have a clear sense for where this political fight is headed, and which party has the upperhand, but for now, it’s possible that we’ve seen the limit to what popular bills can do.</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>A <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/climate-change-impact-warning-report-united-nations-intergovernmental-panel-ipcc-code-red-humanity/">major climate report</a> released Monday by the U.N.’s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change found that global temperatures are likely to lead to even worse heat waves and other types of extreme weather. Despite that alarming finding, though, U.S. adults don’t seem to be taking climate change more seriously, according to new polling from <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/08/09/climate-change-natural-disasters-ipcc-report-data/">Morning Consult</a>. In fact, since May, concern over climate change and its impact has remained steady: The share of U.S. adults who say they’re “very concerned” has hovered between 38 percent and 42 percent, while roughly one-third of adults say they’re “somewhat concerned.”</li><li>On Tuesday, New York Gov. Andrew Cuomo <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/andrew-cuomo-had-nowhere-to-go-but-out/">announced plans to resign</a> after the state’s attorney general, Letitia James, released a report last week detailing <a href="https://ag.ny.gov/sites/default/files/2021.08.03_nyag_-_investigative_report.pdf">allegations of sexual harassment by 11 different women</a>. Now Lt. Gov. Kathy Hochul will become governor, making her the state’s first female governor. But polls show she’s unknown to most New Yorkers. When Marist <a href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/polls/new-york-state-marist-poll-results-analysis-august-11-2021/">asked residents about Hochul’s favorability</a>, 64 percent of New Yorkers said either they’ve never heard of her or they don’t know how to rank her.. That said, just 13 percent had an unfavorable view of her and 23 percent had a favorable view, so there is a lot of upside here for Hochul to make a positive impression as she has <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/amp/Politics/wireStory/hochul-run-governor-finishing-cuomos-term-79420623">now said she plans to run for governor in 2022</a>. </li><li>The COVID-19 pandemic has significantly changed how Americans get groceries. According to new Gallup polling, the percentage of U.S. adults who now <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/353090/grocery-shopping-online-fewer-dining.aspx">say that they order groceries online at least monthly</a> has more than doubled, going from 11 percent in 2019, to 23 percent now. And at this point, this phenomenon is mostly concentrated among married people with young children (37 percent) and those with an annual household income over $100,000 (29 percent). However, a majority of American adults (64 percent) say they never order groceries for pickup or delivery. </li><li>There’s been a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/first-it-was-sex-ed-now-its-critical-race-theory/">big discussion as of late</a> into whether schools should be allowed to teach critical race theory and have frank discussions about racism in the U.S. And new polling from the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/08/12/deep-divisions-in-americans-views-of-nations-racial-history--and-how-to-address-it/">Pew Research Center</a> shows that most Americans believe increased attention to  the history of racism is a good thing for society. Per the poll, 53 percent of U.S. adults think it’s “very” or “somewhat” good for society to be aware of the history of slavery and racism in America, while 26 percent of respondents think it’s bad for society. The survey found wide partisan and racial divides, too. Black (75 percent), Asian American (64 percent) and Hispanic adults (59 percent) were more likely to view heightened attention to this topic as a good thing, while just a little under half of white adults (46 percent) felt the same way. The partisan divide was even more stark, Pew found. Among Republicans and Republican-leaning independents, only 25 percent said greater attention to racism and slavery was good for society, compared to 78 percent of Democrats and Democratic-leaning independents. </li><li>Democrats and Democratic leaners voters are more likely than Republicans and Republican leaners to support making college tuition free, according to new polling from the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/08/11/democrats-overwhelmingly-favor-free-college-tuition-while-republicans-are-divided-by-age-education/">Pew Research Center</a>. Per their survey, 85 percent of Democrats said they favor making college tuition free, compared to just 36 percent of Republicans. Those most strongly supportive of tuition-free college were adults who fall between the ages of 18-29 (73 percent), who have only a high school diploma (69 percent) and who were women (68 percent). There was a racial divide, too: overwhelming majorities of Black (86 percent), Hispanic (82 percent) and Asian American (69 percent) adults supported free college tuition, but only 53 percent of white adults did.</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><img src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/biden-approval-rating-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/biden-approval-rating-1.png"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>, 50.2 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 43.4 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of +6.8 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-in-favor-of-vaccine-mandates-but-support-is-driven-mainly-by-those-who-have-already-gotten-the-jab/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 50.4 percent approved and 43.3 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of +7.0 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 51.6 percent and a disapproval rating of 42.2 percent (a net approval rating of +9.4 points).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/cuomo-resigning-now-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79389991</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/anti-establishment-sentiment-ballot-parties-week-79248883</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628851502737415</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What If The House Of Representatives Had More Than 435 Seats?</title>
			<link>https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/435-representatives/</link>
						<dc:creator>Ryan Best</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Ryan Best</dc:creator>
			<category>2020 Census</category>
			<category>Census</category>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Gerrymandering</category>
			<category>Politics</category>
			<category>Reapportionment</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>PUBLISHED AUG. 6, 2021, AT 10:25 AM</p>
<p>What If The House Of Representatives Had More Than 435 Seats?See how adding more seats makes Congress more representative</p>
<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/ryan-best/">Ryan Best</a></p>
<p>The number of voting members in the U.S. House of Representatives has been stuck at 435 for more than 100 years1 even though the country’s population has more than tripled in that time. This has created the perfect recipe for unequal representation: Every decade, these 435 seats in the House <a href="https://www.census.gov/topics/public-sector/congressional-apportionment/about.html">must be reapportioned</a> to adjust for population changes, even though more seats aren’t added. This means representatives in some states like Delaware end up representing way more people than in other states like Montana.</p>
<p><em>Here’s how apportionment works and which states are over- and underrepresented as a result</em></p>
<p>We’ve now apportioned all 435 seats in the House! Notice how smaller states are much more likely to be further from the national average.</p>
<p>Start over ↻</p>
<p>SEATS ALLOCATED:</p>
<p>435/435</p>
<p>10m203040-200k-100kEVEN+100k+200kState populationAverage state district size vs. national average</p>
<p><em>UNDER</em>REPRESENTED</p>
<p><em>OVER</em>REPRESENTED</p>
<p>The closer states get to the national average (EVEN), the more equal their representation is</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>PRIORITY</th>
<th>STATE</th>
<th>POP.</th>
<th>SEATS</th>
<th>POP. PER SEAT</th>
</tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td data-val="6">6</td>
<td>California</td>
<td data-val="39576757">39.6m</td>
<td data-val="52">52</td>
<td data-val="761091.4807692308">761k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="3">3</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td data-val="29183290">29.2m</td>
<td data-val="38">38</td>
<td data-val="767981.3157894737">768k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="4">4</td>
<td>Florida</td>
<td data-val="21570527">21.6m</td>
<td data-val="28">28</td>
<td data-val="770375.9642857143">770k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="1">1</td>
<td>New York</td>
<td data-val="20215751">20.2m</td>
<td data-val="26">26</td>
<td data-val="777528.8846153846">778k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="11">11</td>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td data-val="13011844">13.0m</td>
<td data-val="17">17</td>
<td data-val="765402.5882352941">765k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="15">15</td>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td data-val="12822739">12.8m</td>
<td data-val="17">17</td>
<td data-val="754278.7647058824">754k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="2">2</td>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td data-val="11808848">11.8m</td>
<td data-val="15">15</td>
<td data-val="787256.5333333333">787k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="13">13</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td data-val="10725274">10.7m</td>
<td data-val="14">14</td>
<td data-val="766091">766k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="22">22</td>
<td>North Carolina</td>
<td data-val="10453948">10.5m</td>
<td data-val="14">14</td>
<td data-val="746710.5714285715">747k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="9">9</td>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td data-val="10084442">10.1m</td>
<td data-val="13">13</td>
<td data-val="775726.3076923077">776k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="10">10</td>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td data-val="9294493">9.3m</td>
<td data-val="12">12</td>
<td data-val="774541.0833333334">775k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="7">7</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td data-val="8654542">8.7m</td>
<td data-val="11">11</td>
<td data-val="786776.5454545454">787k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="14">14</td>
<td>Washington</td>
<td data-val="7715946">7.7m</td>
<td data-val="10">10</td>
<td data-val="771594.6">772k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="5">5</td>
<td>Arizona</td>
<td data-val="7158923">7.2m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="795435.8888888889">795k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="12">12</td>
<td>Massachusetts</td>
<td data-val="7033469">7.0m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="781496.5555555555">781k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="18">18</td>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td data-val="6916897">6.9m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="768544.1111111111">769k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="24">24</td>
<td>Indiana</td>
<td data-val="6790280">6.8m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="754475.5555555555">754k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="19">19</td>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td data-val="6185278">6.2m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="773159.75">773k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="20">20</td>
<td>Missouri</td>
<td data-val="6160281">6.2m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="770035.125">770k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="29">29</td>
<td>Wisconsin</td>
<td data-val="5897473">5.9m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="737184.125">737k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="31">31</td>
<td>Colorado</td>
<td data-val="5782171">5.8m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="722771.375">723k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="33">33</td>
<td>Minnesota</td>
<td data-val="5709752">5.7m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="713719">714k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="30">30</td>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td data-val="5124712">5.1m</td>
<td data-val="7">7</td>
<td data-val="732101.7142857143">732k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="34">34</td>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td data-val="5030053">5.0m</td>
<td data-val="7">7</td>
<td data-val="718579">719k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="23">23</td>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td data-val="4661468">4.7m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="776911.3333333334">777k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="27">27</td>
<td>Kentucky</td>
<td data-val="4509342">4.5m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="751557">752k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="38">38</td>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td data-val="4241500">4.2m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="706916.6666666666">707k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="21">21</td>
<td>Oklahoma</td>
<td data-val="3963516">4.0m</td>
<td data-val="5">5</td>
<td data-val="792703.2">793k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="36">36</td>
<td>Connecticut</td>
<td data-val="3608298">3.6m</td>
<td data-val="5">5</td>
<td data-val="721659.6">722k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="17">17</td>
<td>Utah</td>
<td data-val="3275252">3.3m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="818813">819k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="25">25</td>
<td>Iowa</td>
<td data-val="3192406">3.2m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="798101.5">798k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="28">28</td>
<td>Nevada</td>
<td data-val="3108462">3.1m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="777115.5">777k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="32">32</td>
<td>Arkansas</td>
<td data-val="3013756">3.0m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="753439">753k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="35">35</td>
<td>Mississippi</td>
<td data-val="2963914">3.0m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="740978.5">741k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="37">37</td>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td data-val="2940865">2.9m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="735216.25">735k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="40">40</td>
<td>New Mexico</td>
<td data-val="2120220">2.1m</td>
<td data-val="3">3</td>
<td data-val="706740">707k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="42">42</td>
<td>Nebraska</td>
<td data-val="1963333">2.0m</td>
<td data-val="3">3</td>
<td data-val="654444.3333333334">654k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="8">8</td>
<td>Idaho</td>
<td data-val="1841377">1.8m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="920688.5">921k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="16">16</td>
<td>West Virginia</td>
<td data-val="1795045">1.8m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="897522.5">898k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="41">41</td>
<td>Hawaii</td>
<td data-val="1460137">1.5m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="730068.5">730k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="43">43</td>
<td>New Hampshire</td>
<td data-val="1379089">1.4m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="689544.5">690k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="44">44</td>
<td>Maine</td>
<td data-val="1363582">1.4m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="681791">682k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="48">48</td>
<td>Rhode Island</td>
<td data-val="1098163">1.1m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="549081.5">549k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="49">49</td>
<td>Montana</td>
<td data-val="1085407">1.1m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="542703.5">543k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="26">26</td>
<td>Delaware</td>
<td data-val="990837">991k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="990837">991k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="39">39</td>
<td>South Dakota</td>
<td data-val="887770">888k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="887770">888k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="45">45</td>
<td>North Dakota</td>
<td data-val="779702">780k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="779702">780k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="46">46</td>
<td>Alaska</td>
<td data-val="736081">736k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="736081">736k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="47">47</td>
<td>Vermont</td>
<td data-val="643503">644k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="643503">644k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="50">50</td>
<td>Wyoming</td>
<td data-val="577719">578k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="577719">578k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="0"></td>
<td>Total</td>
<td data-val="331108434">331.1m</td>
<td data-val="435">435</td>
<td data-val="761168.8137931034">761k</td>
</tr></tbody></table><p>A scatterplot of states by state population and average district size versus the national average, where dots are sized by state population. With 435 seats in the House, the average state’s population per congressional seat is 50.2k people away from the national average.</p>
<p>With all 435 House seats apportioned, we see significant discrepancies in district sizes across states. Montana and Rhode Island, for instance, will each have about 215,000 fewer people per district than the national average. Delaware, by contrast, will be the most underrepresented state in the union: Its 990,837 residents will have just one representative. But it’s not just the smaller — that is, less populous — states that get a raw deal. Bigger states also suffer from underrepresentation compared with some smaller states. Take California: Its population is 68.5 times as large as Wyoming’s, but based on the 2020 census, California was apportioned only 52 seats compared with Wyoming’s one. This means the average California House member will represent more than 761,000 constituents, while Wyoming’s will represent just shy of 578,000.</p>
<p>To be sure, perfectly equal representation in the House isn’t actually attainable — the fact that each state is guaranteed at least one seat and that districts can’t cross state lines limits what’s possible. But we could get <i>much</i> closer to equal representation if we expanded the size of the House beyond our current (and rather arbitrary) cap of 435.</p>
<p>One method we could use to add more seats to the House is the <em>small state rule</em>, where we’d divide the total U.S. population by that of the smallest state (Wyoming). Another is the <em>cube root law</em>, or the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20446639">trend observed in political science</a> that the number of seats in many countries’ lower chambers is quite close to the <a href="https://www.calculatorsoup.com/calculators/algebra/cuberoots.php">cube root</a> of that nation’s population. And in some countries that have even more representatives <a href="https://fruitsandvotes.wordpress.com/2014/01/07/economix-expand-the-us-house/">like the U.K., France and Germany</a>, political scientists have found that number is closer to the cube root of twice the country’s population (<em>2x cube root law</em>).</p>
<p><em>Try implementing these strategies — or any House size up to 1,000 seats</em></p>
<p>With 435 seats in the House, the average state’s population per congressional seat is 50.2k people away from the national average.</p>
<p>seats</p>
<p>SMALL STATE RULEDivide the total U.S. population by that of the smallest stateCUBE ROOT LAWTake the cube root of the total U.S. population2X CUBE ROOT LAWTake the cube root of <i>two times</i> the total U.S. population 10m203040-200k-100kEVEN+100k+200kState populationAverage state district size vs. national average</p>
<p><em>UNDER</em>REPRESENTED</p>
<p><em>OVER</em>REPRESENTED</p>
<p>The closer states get to the national average (EVEN), the more equal their representation is</p>
<table><tbody><tr><th>PRIORITY</th>
<th>STATE</th>
<th>POP.</th>
<th>SEATS</th>
<th>POP. PER SEAT</th>
</tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td data-val="6">6</td>
<td>California</td>
<td data-val="39576757">39.6m</td>
<td data-val="52">52</td>
<td data-val="761091.4807692308">761k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="3">3</td>
<td>Texas</td>
<td data-val="29183290">29.2m</td>
<td data-val="38">38</td>
<td data-val="767981.3157894737">768k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="4">4</td>
<td>Florida</td>
<td data-val="21570527">21.6m</td>
<td data-val="28">28</td>
<td data-val="770375.9642857143">770k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="1">1</td>
<td>New York</td>
<td data-val="20215751">20.2m</td>
<td data-val="26">26</td>
<td data-val="777528.8846153846">778k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="11">11</td>
<td>Pennsylvania</td>
<td data-val="13011844">13.0m</td>
<td data-val="17">17</td>
<td data-val="765402.5882352941">765k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="15">15</td>
<td>Illinois</td>
<td data-val="12822739">12.8m</td>
<td data-val="17">17</td>
<td data-val="754278.7647058824">754k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="2">2</td>
<td>Ohio</td>
<td data-val="11808848">11.8m</td>
<td data-val="15">15</td>
<td data-val="787256.5333333333">787k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="13">13</td>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td data-val="10725274">10.7m</td>
<td data-val="14">14</td>
<td data-val="766091">766k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="22">22</td>
<td>North Carolina</td>
<td data-val="10453948">10.5m</td>
<td data-val="14">14</td>
<td data-val="746710.5714285715">747k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="9">9</td>
<td>Michigan</td>
<td data-val="10084442">10.1m</td>
<td data-val="13">13</td>
<td data-val="775726.3076923077">776k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="10">10</td>
<td>New Jersey</td>
<td data-val="9294493">9.3m</td>
<td data-val="12">12</td>
<td data-val="774541.0833333334">775k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="7">7</td>
<td>Virginia</td>
<td data-val="8654542">8.7m</td>
<td data-val="11">11</td>
<td data-val="786776.5454545454">787k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="14">14</td>
<td>Washington</td>
<td data-val="7715946">7.7m</td>
<td data-val="10">10</td>
<td data-val="771594.6">772k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="5">5</td>
<td>Arizona</td>
<td data-val="7158923">7.2m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="795435.8888888889">795k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="12">12</td>
<td>Massachusetts</td>
<td data-val="7033469">7.0m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="781496.5555555555">781k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="18">18</td>
<td>Tennessee</td>
<td data-val="6916897">6.9m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="768544.1111111111">769k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="24">24</td>
<td>Indiana</td>
<td data-val="6790280">6.8m</td>
<td data-val="9">9</td>
<td data-val="754475.5555555555">754k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="19">19</td>
<td>Maryland</td>
<td data-val="6185278">6.2m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="773159.75">773k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="20">20</td>
<td>Missouri</td>
<td data-val="6160281">6.2m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="770035.125">770k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="29">29</td>
<td>Wisconsin</td>
<td data-val="5897473">5.9m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="737184.125">737k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="31">31</td>
<td>Colorado</td>
<td data-val="5782171">5.8m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="722771.375">723k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="33">33</td>
<td>Minnesota</td>
<td data-val="5709752">5.7m</td>
<td data-val="8">8</td>
<td data-val="713719">714k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="30">30</td>
<td>South Carolina</td>
<td data-val="5124712">5.1m</td>
<td data-val="7">7</td>
<td data-val="732101.7142857143">732k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="34">34</td>
<td>Alabama</td>
<td data-val="5030053">5.0m</td>
<td data-val="7">7</td>
<td data-val="718579">719k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="23">23</td>
<td>Louisiana</td>
<td data-val="4661468">4.7m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="776911.3333333334">777k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="27">27</td>
<td>Kentucky</td>
<td data-val="4509342">4.5m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="751557">752k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="38">38</td>
<td>Oregon</td>
<td data-val="4241500">4.2m</td>
<td data-val="6">6</td>
<td data-val="706916.6666666666">707k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="21">21</td>
<td>Oklahoma</td>
<td data-val="3963516">4.0m</td>
<td data-val="5">5</td>
<td data-val="792703.2">793k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="36">36</td>
<td>Connecticut</td>
<td data-val="3608298">3.6m</td>
<td data-val="5">5</td>
<td data-val="721659.6">722k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="17">17</td>
<td>Utah</td>
<td data-val="3275252">3.3m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="818813">819k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="25">25</td>
<td>Iowa</td>
<td data-val="3192406">3.2m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="798101.5">798k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="28">28</td>
<td>Nevada</td>
<td data-val="3108462">3.1m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="777115.5">777k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="32">32</td>
<td>Arkansas</td>
<td data-val="3013756">3.0m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="753439">753k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="35">35</td>
<td>Mississippi</td>
<td data-val="2963914">3.0m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="740978.5">741k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="37">37</td>
<td>Kansas</td>
<td data-val="2940865">2.9m</td>
<td data-val="4">4</td>
<td data-val="735216.25">735k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="40">40</td>
<td>New Mexico</td>
<td data-val="2120220">2.1m</td>
<td data-val="3">3</td>
<td data-val="706740">707k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="42">42</td>
<td>Nebraska</td>
<td data-val="1963333">2.0m</td>
<td data-val="3">3</td>
<td data-val="654444.3333333334">654k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="8">8</td>
<td>Idaho</td>
<td data-val="1841377">1.8m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="920688.5">921k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="16">16</td>
<td>West Virginia</td>
<td data-val="1795045">1.8m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="897522.5">898k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="41">41</td>
<td>Hawaii</td>
<td data-val="1460137">1.5m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="730068.5">730k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="43">43</td>
<td>New Hampshire</td>
<td data-val="1379089">1.4m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="689544.5">690k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="44">44</td>
<td>Maine</td>
<td data-val="1363582">1.4m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="681791">682k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="48">48</td>
<td>Rhode Island</td>
<td data-val="1098163">1.1m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="549081.5">549k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="49">49</td>
<td>Montana</td>
<td data-val="1085407">1.1m</td>
<td data-val="2">2</td>
<td data-val="542703.5">543k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="26">26</td>
<td>Delaware</td>
<td data-val="990837">991k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="990837">991k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="39">39</td>
<td>South Dakota</td>
<td data-val="887770">888k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="887770">888k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="45">45</td>
<td>North Dakota</td>
<td data-val="779702">780k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="779702">780k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="46">46</td>
<td>Alaska</td>
<td data-val="736081">736k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="736081">736k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="47">47</td>
<td>Vermont</td>
<td data-val="643503">644k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="643503">644k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="50">50</td>
<td>Wyoming</td>
<td data-val="577719">578k</td>
<td data-val="1">1</td>
<td data-val="577719">578k</td>
</tr><tr><td data-val="0"></td>
<td>Total</td>
<td data-val="331108434">331.1m</td>
<td data-val="435">435</td>
<td data-val="761168.8137931034">761k</td>
</tr></tbody></table><p>As you’ve probably discovered, the more seats we add to the House, the more equal representation generally gets across all 50 states. That said, there are some pretty big limitations to how many seats we could realistically add to the chamber. (Can you imagine the electoral and logistical chaos that would ensue from doubling the size of the House in one fell swoop?) Bottom line: Each seat we do add to our current cap of 435 does get us just that much closer to the one-person, one-vote ethos that the House was ultimately created to fulfill.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628766001622789</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How The House Got Stuck At 435 Seats</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-house-got-stuck-at-435-seats/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>435</category>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Democracy</category>
			<category>House of Representatives</category>
			<category>Population</category>
			<category>Reapportionment</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<category>Representation</category>
			<category>U.S. House</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Apportionment, or the process of determining <a href="https://www.census.gov/data/tables/2020/dec/2020-apportionment-data.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the number of seats</a> each state has in the U.S. House of Representatives, happens like clockwork at this point. Every 10 years, the Census Bureau counts how many people each state has and then uses that number to calculate how many representatives each state gets out of the 435 seats.<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strictly speaking, the House has &lt;a href="https://history.house.gov/Institution/Apportionment/Determining-Apportionment/#:~:text=The%20total%20membership%20of%20the,Representatives%20from%20the%2050%20states." target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;441 members&lt;/a&gt;: 435 are voting members from each of the 50 states, and six are nonvoting members. The District of Columbia, Guam, the U.S. Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands and American Samoa each have a delegate, while Puerto Rico has a resident commissioner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>1</sup></a> In April, for instance, we learned from the reapportionment process that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">California would lose a seat for the very first time</a> while Texas would gain two.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But despite some states losing seats while others pick them up, the reapportionment process is itself now fairly mundane. That wasn’t always the case, though.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/435-representatives/"><img alt="Photo illustration of the U.S. Capitol building" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/435-16x9-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/435-16x9-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/435-16x9-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/435-16x9-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				See Also: <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/435-representatives/">What If The House Of Representatives Had More Than 435 Seats? »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2016/04/washington-casts-first-presidential-veto-april-5-1792-221503" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first presidential veto</a> was used on the apportionment law, so it’s been a hot issue from the very, very beginning,” said <a href="https://uwm.edu/history/people/anderson-margo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Margo Anderson</a>, a professor emerita at University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee who studies <a href="http://yalebooks.com/book/9780300195422/american-census" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the social and political history of the census</a>. In fact, until the House was capped at 435 seats<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This number increased to 437 in 1959 to accommodate the statehood of Alaska and Hawaii but returned to 435 in 1963, after the reapportionment process in 1960.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> by the <a href="https://history.house.gov/Historical-Highlights/1901-1950/The-Permanent-Apportionment-Act-of-1929/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1929 Permanent Apportionment Act</a>, each apportionment period was regularly accompanied by clashes over how to best divvy up political power in Congress — including the size of the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the one hand, it’s probably a good thing that Congress is no longer debating the size of the House every 10 years. After all, the reason we have the 1929 Permanent Apportionment Act in the first place is that Congress <a href="https://datasociety.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/House-Arrest-Dan-Bouk.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was unable to reach an agreement</a> on how to reapportion the House for nearly a decade.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/bidens-approval-rating-fallen-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79388894</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">On the other hand, the fact that the size of the House hasn’t increased in more than a century is a real problem for our democracy. For starters, there is an ever wider gulf between Americans and their representatives, as the average number of people represented in a district has more than tripled, from about 210,000 in 1910 to about 760,000 in 2020.<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout this piece, we’ll often refer to census years as the time when the House was reapportioned for simplicity’s sake. But historically, Congress has &lt;a href="https://www.census.gov/history/www/reference/apportionment/apportionment_legislation_1790_-_1830.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;usually passed apportionment acts&lt;/a&gt; in the year or two &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the census was released, but still in time for elections ahead of the next Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>3</sup></a> Moreover, some states are severely <a href="https://apportionment.us/Ladewig&amp;Jasinski.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over- and underrepresented</a> as a result.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Increasing the size of the House would not resolve all the challenges facing the U.S., as any expansion would involve trade-offs. For instance, adding representatives could decrease day-to-day legislative efficiency, and it would undoubtedly increase the size of the federal government. Yet expanding the House is one of the more straightforward reforms that leaders in Washington could pursue in our era of polarized politics. The size of the House is <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/app/details/USCODE-2006-title2/USCODE-2006-title2-chap1-sec2a" target="_blank" rel="noopener">determined by statute</a>, not the Constitution, meaning Congress could pass (and the president could sign) a law to change it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s worth exploring, then, whether 435 is still an appropriate number of House members to represent our sprawling, diverse nation. Whether Congress will take up this issue anytime soon is another question entirely, but here’s how we got stuck at 435 in the first place — and what it would mean if we increased that number.</p>



<hr><h2><strong>Why 435?</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">There have been 435 seats in the House for so long now that it might seem as if the Founding Fathers had foreseen it as a natural ceiling for the chamber’s size. But that isn’t the case: 435 is entirely arbitrary. The House arrived at that number because of political expediency — and it has stayed there because of it, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Up until 1910, when the chamber <a href="https://www.census.gov/history/pdf/1910_Apportionment.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expanded from 391 to 435 seats,</a><a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon statehood, Congress added two seats for New Mexico and one for Arizona in 1912 during the &lt;a href="https://history.house.gov/Congressional-Overview/Profiles/62nd/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;62nd Congress&lt;/a&gt;, which had already passed the &lt;a href="https://www.census.gov/history/pdf/1910_Apportionment.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Apportionment Act of 1911&lt;/a&gt;. This brought the total number of House seats to 394 before the House expanded to 435 seats in the 63rd Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>4</sup></a> the size of the House had experienced a mostly unchecked pattern of growth. Only once, after the 1840 census, did the number of seats in the House not increase; 1910, however, marked the last time the House grew, even though the U.S. population has more than tripled since then, from over 90 million in 1910 to over 330 million today.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1062" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-desktop-annotweak.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-desktop-annotweak.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-desktop-annotweak.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-desktop-annotweak.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="2130" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-mobile-annotweak.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-mobile-annotweak.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-mobile-annotweak.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.1-mobile-annotweak.png?w=1240 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The 1920 census is when things broke down. For the first time, <a href="https://www.census.gov/history/www/programs/geography/urban_and_rural_areas.html#:~:text=The%201920%20census%20marked%20the,population%20was%20defined%20as%20urban." target="_blank" rel="noopener">a majority of the population lived</a> in “urban” areas. And although the Census Bureau’s definition was broad — it included any place with at least 2,500 people — the finding reflected America’s power center was moving away from rural areas toward urban ones <a href="https://oxfordre.com/americanhistory/view/10.1093/acrefore/9780199329175.001.0001/acrefore-9780199329175-e-327" target="_blank" rel="noopener">due to industrialization</a> and high levels of <a href="https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/european-immigrants-united-states-2016" target="_blank" rel="noopener">immigration from Southern and Eastern Europe</a>. This made the apportionment process particularly challenging, as Congress had to navigate two competing concerns: first, the worry that greater urban power would lead to rural seat loss if the House didn’t expand, and second, a <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2018/08/08/taft-signs-bill-increasing-house-size-to-433-aug-8-1911-761943" target="_blank" rel="noopener">growing belief</a> among many members that the House was already too crowded and that an increase in seats would make it truly unwieldy.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Nevertheless, the Republican chair of the House Census Committee <a href="https://datasociety.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/House-Arrest-Dan-Bouk.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">put forward legislation</a> in 1921 to increase the size of the House by 48 seats — 483 in total. Once again, this would have prevented any state from losing a seat, a politically attractive option.<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minimizing seat loss had long been a major consideration in the apportionment process, to the point that only a handful of states lost any seats in the five apportionments from 1870 to 1910.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> But this time both parties were deeply divided over expanding the House, with arguments that adding seats would be too expensive or hinder legislative functions. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Congress tried a number of alternatives. First, the House passed <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1921/01/20/archives/house-kills-plan-for-increase-to-483-votes-overwhelmingly-for.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an amended bill</a> to keep the House at 435 members. Eleven states stood to lose seats as a result, and unsurprisingly many senators from those states worked behind the scenes to keep that bill from ever getting a vote in the Senate. Next, the House tried to expand to just 460 seats instead of 483, which would have caused only two states to lose a seat, but that narrowly failed by four votes on the House floor. This left Congress at an impasse, and over the next few years, reapportionment stalled. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some rural legislators charged that the timing of the 1920 census presented an inaccurate picture of the country’s population, claiming for instance that many people had migrated to cities only temporarily during World War I but would soon return to rural areas. Others argued that non-citizens ought to be excluded from the counts, which would have primarily affected Northern states with large immigrant populations. Meanwhile, some Northern Republicans, upset by Democrats’ disenfranchisement of Black Americans in the South, countered that representation ought to be reduced in Southern states that suppressed voting rights. There were also arguments over which method was best for <a href="https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/R41382.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">apportioning seats,</a> as one method tended to put <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1991/05/27/in-battle-over-reapportionment-even-math-is-a-target/f540a781-7fda-414c-9e10-d955372556d4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">slightly more seats in less populous states</a> and the other put more seats in more populous states.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The lack of consensus on how to reapportion the House meant that by the late 1920s, reapportionment had dragged on for nearly a decade and had <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/25110586" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all the makings of a constitutional crisis</a>. “The issue began to come to a head as the 1928 election loomed,” said Anderson of the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. “Because the realization was, we’ve got the Electoral College apportioned on the basis of the 1910 census, and if the popular vote and the electoral vote diverge, it’s because we didn’t reapportion.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/cuomo-resigning-now-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79389991</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Fortunately for electoral legitimacy, Republican Herbert Hoover won both the popular and electoral vote <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/national.php?year=1928&amp;f=0&amp;off=0&amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the 1928</a> presidential election. Having served from 1921 to 1928 as secretary of commerce, which oversees the Census Bureau, he was especially cognizant of Congress’s apportionment failure. In April 1929, Hoover called a special session of Congress, where one of the main focuses was apportionment, and by June, legislation had passed both the House and Senate and was signed by Hoover. The law, the Apportionment Act of 1929, created what we know as the “automatic” reapportionment process today. It capped the number of House seats at 435 and moved the responsibility of determining the seat count from Congress to the president — an early example of <a href="https://today.law.harvard.edu/feature/presidential-power-surges/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congress giving away power</a> to the executive branch.<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is why even now the secretary of commerce &lt;a href="https://uscode.house.gov/view.xhtml?req=(title:13%20section:141%20edition:prelim)%20OR%20(granuleid:USC-prelim-title13-section141)&amp;amp;f=treesort&amp;amp;edition=prelim&amp;amp;num=0&amp;amp;jumpTo=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;reports apportionment figures&lt;/a&gt; to the president, who then transmits that information to Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>6</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But given the rancor surrounding reapportionment, the law didn’t come without serious consequences for representation. Specifically, it <a href="https://www.americanbar.org/groups/public_education/publications/insights-on-law-and-society/volume-20/issue-2/an-enumeration-of-the-population--a-history-of-the-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cut requirements</a> that members be elected in single districts and that those districts be contiguous and compact, serving relatively equal-sized populations. This meant a state that lost seats could now draw wildly disproportionate districts to keep power in more rural parts of the state. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It essentially created massive malapportionment for the next 40 years,” said Anderson. But, she stressed, this was done because it made the law “politically palatable.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, the law’s lack of a population requirement helps explain why more than half of all members from rural districts backed it, even though most of the states that lost seats were based in the rural South and Midwest.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In total, 21 states lost seats as part of the reapportionment process, and most of them were in the South or Midwest. Meanwhile, the 11 states that gained seats were industrial states like New York and Michigan and fast-growing states mostly in the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> These representatives knew their states might lose seats, but they hedged that their slower-growing or shrinking districts might not end up on the chopping block now that the apportionment process didn’t require districts to have equal populations.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Later, to uphold the tenet of “one person, one vote,” the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/1963/22" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would rule</a> that congressional districts must be approximately equal in population, but that wouldn’t happen until 1964. And even then, unequal representation in the House has persisted, largely because the size of the chamber hasn’t budged despite massive growth in the U.S. population.</p>



<hr><h2><strong>The problem with being stuck at 435</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">In 1910, the largest state, New York, had about 9 million more people than the smallest — that is, least populous — state, Nevada. But today, the largest state, California, has nearly <em>39 million more people</em> than the smallest, Wyoming. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This staggering gap makes it far more likely for states to end up with wildly unequal district populations thanks to the Constitution’s requirement that each state have at least one congressional district. The Supreme Court requires districts to have equal populations, but this applies only to the districts within a state — not between states. So even though the average House district will have just over 760,000 people after this round of reapportionment, each state’s average district will vary quite a bit, especially as states get smaller in size.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/advantage-gop/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An illustration of an elephant and a donkey playing tennis on top of a leaning stack of books. The books’ spines are labeled “Supreme Court,” “State Legislature,” “Electoral College,” “Senate,” and “House of Representatives.”" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/MINORITY-RULE-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/MINORITY-RULE-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/MINORITY-RULE-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/MINORITY-RULE-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Advantage, GOP <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/advantage-gop/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Take the smallest and largest states with only one representative: Wyoming and Delaware, respectively. Wyoming, with just under 578,000 people, winds up overrepresented because it’s guaranteed a seat despite falling well short of that 760,000 national average. Conversely, Delaware has nearly 991,000 people, which leaves it underrepresented because it isn’t quite large enough to earn a second seat. Meanwhile, Montana has only about 95,000 more people than Delaware, but that’s enough for the apportionment formula to eke out a second seat, meaning Montana will have two districts to Delaware’s one and an average district size of just over 542,000, making its constituents the most represented in the country.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">State lines make perfectly equal districts across the country impossible, but there’s no question that increasing the size of the House would help reduce how unequal district sizes among states have become. Expanding the House could also make districts smaller, which in turn could help with representation, as the average number of people living in a congressional district has grown by about 520,000 people from 1920 to 2020 — three times more than the total shift from 1790 to 1910.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1002" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1096" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2-mob.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.2-mob.png?w=1240 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In fact, the problem of representation in the U.S. is so bad that each member of the House represents far more people on average than legislators in most other large, developed — or developing — democracies. On the one hand, this is somewhat understandable given the U.S. has the third-largest population in the world after China and India, the latter of which also happens to be the only democracy with more people per representative than the U.S. But beyond India, other large democracies with more than 100 million people, like Brazil and Japan, offer their constituents far more representation than the U.S. Moreover, their lower legislative chambers are only somewhat bigger than the U.S. House.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>The U.S. has a representation problem</h5>
 <p>Average population per seat in the lower legislative chamber or unicameral legislature in the U.S. and 30 other democracies</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.stuck-at-435.3"><thead><tr><th colspan="1">Country</th>
 <th colspan="1">Population (millions)</th>
 <th colspan="1">Seats</th>
 <th colspan="1">Avg. population per seat</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>India</td>
 <td>1,326.1</td>
 <td>543</td>
 <td>2,442,161</td>
 </tr><tr><td>United States*</td>
 <td>331.1</td>
 <td>435</td>
 <td>761,169</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Brazil</td>
 <td>211.7</td>
 <td>513</td>
 <td>412,702</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colombia</td>
 <td>49.1</td>
 <td>172</td>
 <td>285,377</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Japan</td>
 <td>125.5</td>
 <td>465</td>
 <td>269,909</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Mexico</td>
 <td>128.6</td>
 <td>500</td>
 <td>257,299</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Argentina</td>
 <td>45.5</td>
 <td>257</td>
 <td>176,962</td>
 </tr><tr><td>South Korea</td>
 <td>51.8</td>
 <td>300</td>
 <td>172,784</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Australia</td>
 <td>25.5</td>
 <td>151</td>
 <td>168,652</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Spain</td>
 <td>50.0</td>
 <td>350</td>
 <td>142,902</td>
 </tr><tr><td>South Africa</td>
 <td>56.5</td>
 <td>400</td>
 <td>141,159</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Germany†</td>
 <td>80.2</td>
 <td>598</td>
 <td>134,046</td>
 </tr><tr><td>France</td>
 <td>67.8</td>
 <td>577</td>
 <td>117,588</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Chile</td>
 <td>18.2</td>
 <td>155</td>
 <td>117,334</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Netherlands</td>
 <td>17.3</td>
 <td>150</td>
 <td>115,203</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Canada</td>
 <td>37.7</td>
 <td>338</td>
 <td>111,521</td>
 </tr><tr><td>United Kingdom</td>
 <td>65.8</td>
 <td>650</td>
 <td>101,171</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Italy</td>
 <td>62.4</td>
 <td>630</td>
 <td>99,052</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Poland</td>
 <td>38.3</td>
 <td>460</td>
 <td>83,222</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Belgium</td>
 <td>11.7</td>
 <td>150</td>
 <td>78,138</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Israel</td>
 <td>8.7</td>
 <td>120</td>
 <td>72,296</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Czech Republic</td>
 <td>10.7</td>
 <td>200</td>
 <td>53,512</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hungary</td>
 <td>9.8</td>
 <td>199</td>
 <td>49,105</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Austria</td>
 <td>8.9</td>
 <td>183</td>
 <td>48,412</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Portugal</td>
 <td>10.3</td>
 <td>230</td>
 <td>44,794</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Switzerland</td>
 <td>8.4</td>
 <td>200</td>
 <td>42,020</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Zealand</td>
 <td>4.9</td>
 <td>120</td>
 <td>41,046</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Greece</td>
 <td>10.6</td>
 <td>300</td>
 <td>35,357</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Denmark</td>
 <td>5.9</td>
 <td>179</td>
 <td>32,790</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Sweden</td>
 <td>10.2</td>
 <td>349</td>
 <td>29,233</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Finland</td>
 <td>5.6</td>
 <td>200</td>
 <td>27,858</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Population estimates for countries other than the U.S. are all from July 2020.</p>
 <p>*The population of the 50 U.S. states. <br>†The Bundestag, Germany’s lower legislative chamber, must have a minimum of 598 seats. Due to Germany’s electoral system, which can assign additional seats, the size of the Bundestag often fluctuates. It has 709 seats now.</p>
 <p>Sources: CIA World Factbook; U.S. Census Bureau; “A Different Democracy,” by Steven L. Taylor et al.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">“Our congressional districts are just massive, there’s really nothing else like it,” said Jonathan Rodden, a <a href="https://politicalscience.stanford.edu/people/jonathan-rodden" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political scientist at Stanford University</a> who studies political geography. “The scale of districts in Canada, the U.K. and Australia is so much smaller … the U.S. is really an outlier in this.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Brian Frederick, a <a href="https://www.bridgew.edu/department/political-science/dr-brian-frederick" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political scientist at Bridgewater State University</a>, studies apportionment issues and <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Congressional-Representation--Constituents-The-Case-for-Increasing-the/Frederick/p/book/9780415873468" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has argued</a> that the House should be expanded. He notes how the size of America’s districts hurts the quality of representation that voters receive. In fact, his research has found a <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249692020_Constituency_Population_and_Representation_in_the_US_House" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lot of upsides for smaller districts</a>. For instance, representatives who serve fewer people are more popular, more likely to have contact with their constituents and more likely to get higher marks for their constituent service. Moreover, they often better reflect the views and makeup of the people in their districts. “The reality is that it’s easier to represent fewer people than it is a larger number of citizens on a per-district basis,” said Frederick. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Both he and Rodden noted that an expansion of the House could also increase the relative demographic diversity in the House. For instance, having districts with smaller populations could produce a plurality-Native American congressional district in Arizona or New Mexico, which is currently not possible given the size of the group’s population. However, Rodden warned that opportunities to expand representation for minority groups could vary, especially in the South, where Black voters are often <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/06/09/how-a-widespread-practice-to-politically-empower-african-americans-might-actually-harm-them/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over-concentrated in districts</a> to <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26600481" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ensure representation</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Adding seats to the House could have <a href="https://contentdm.washburnlaw.edu/digital/collection/wlj/id/5912/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">electoral benefits</a>, too. First, a growing House would make it less likely that states lose representation in the reapportionment process. Under current conditions, states with a shrinking population often lose seats, but this is true even of states where the population is growing.<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Michigan, Ohio and Pennsylvania all grew about 2 percent between 2010 and 2020, for instance, but all three states still lost seats in the 2020 apportionment process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> An expansion of the House would also help reduce the Electoral College’s bias toward small states, as more populous states would pick up more representatives, and therefore electoral votes in the Electoral College.<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A state’s electoral vote count is the total number of representatives plus a state’s two senators. (The current number of electors is also what FiveThirtyEight is named after, so if this happened, we might have to consider a name change. Perhaps SixThirtyEight?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> And finally, a larger House could theoretically <a href="https://www.fordham.edu/download/downloads/id/14402/Why_the_House_Must_Be_Expanded___Democracy_Clinic.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">help reduce partisan gerrymandering</a>. As Rodden told me, when you add more and more seats, you converge on proportional representation at some point because the districts just become so small. Still, he cautioned that line drawers could get pretty creative, so more districts might not always result in more proportional representation.<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Unintentional-Gerrymandering%3A-Political-Geography-Chen-Rodden/05b1766bb58a5419d28dae07e4cbc7e27f2109ec" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;a 2013 paper&lt;/a&gt; that Rodden co-authored, he found that the more districts were added to Florida’s map, the more proportional the partisan split became across those districts, although Republicans still retained an advantage given Democrats’ overconcentration in urban areas. But he didn’t find this pattern everywhere. For instance, his forthcoming study of Pennsylvania’s map didn’t find that adding more districts led to more proportional outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>10</sup></a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Clearly, expanding the House has many potential upsides — many of them beneficial to democracy, too — but, of course, a lot hinges on just how many seats would be added. And on that point there is no easy answer.</p>



<hr><h2><strong>How to expand the House</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">A number of ideas have emerged for how best to expand the House. Some reformers have suggested a one-time, arbitrary fix, like <a href="https://www.amacad.org/ourcommonpurpose/recommendation-1-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">adding 50 seats</a>. Others have argued for a more substantive overhaul, like resizing the House <a href="https://www.outsidethebeltway.com/representation-in-the-house-the-wyoming-rule/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">based on the population of the smallest state</a> — often called the Wyoming rule, as Wyoming has occupied this position since 1990. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But there’s actually a fairly straightforward solution that isn’t too far off from what America used to do before — albeit unintentionally. It’s known as the <a href="https://oxford.universitypressscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199287741.001.0001/acprof-9780199287741-chapter-12" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cube root law</a> in political science, or the fact that the size of a country’s parliament often hews to the <a href="https://www.mathsisfun.com/numbers/cube-root.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cube root</a> of the nation’s population.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://ps.ucdavis.edu/people/mshugart" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew Shugart</a>, a professor emeritus at University of California, Davis, has <a href="https://books.google.com/books/about/Seats_and_Votes.html?id=DzVsQgAACAAJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tried to unpack why this is often the case</a>. After all, there is no law that says countries’ parliaments must be the cube root of their population, yet they often are, as the chart below shows. Of the 30 major democracies <a href="https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300198089/different-democracy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shugart and his co-authors looked at</a> alongside the U.S., a majority of them have legislatures very close to — or fairly near — the cube root of their populations.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1246" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1690" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3-mob.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.3-mob.png?w=1240 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Take Canada. Its lower legislative chamber, the House of Commons, has 338 seats, almost exactly in line with the cube root law’s expectation of 335 seats. This is in large part because Canada has <a href="https://redecoupage-federal-redistribution.ca/content.asp?section=info&amp;dir=his/rep&amp;document=p1&amp;lang=e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frequently adjusted the chamber’s seat count</a> to account for population growth. But other bigger democracies like Brazil and Japan also have seat counts that fall fairly close to the cube root of their respective populations. Of course, this isn’t true of every democracy Shugart and his co-authors studied. Some countries like the U.S. fall well below the cube root of its population. And countries like Australia, India and Israel are even more underrepresented than the U.S. in their legislatures.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lower chambers in the case of Australia and India. Israel has a unicameral legislature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> It’s also the case that some countries like Germany, Italy and the U.K. may actually be <em>overrepresented</em> in their lower chambers — for instance, the U.K.’s House of Commons has 650 seats, well more than the expected 404 seats.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An illustration of a wrecking ball breaking down a brick wall that looks like the American flag." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Why The Two-Party System Is Effing Up U.S. Democracy <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to Shugart, the reason why representation in countries’ lower chambers is often so close to the cube root of their populations is that the legislators must strike a balance between communicating with one another and their constituents. “It is about finding what is the optimal size,” he said. And in many countries, that seems to be roughly the cube root of a country’s population.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, it’s a pattern the U.S. used to mostly follow until the size of the House was capped at 435 seats in 1929. But as the chart below shows, the House would have to grow to 692 seats to reflect where the cube root law expects representation in the U.S. to be now.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1158" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="620" height="1502" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4-mob.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4-mob.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4-mob.png?w=620 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/skelley.STUCK-AT-435.4-mob.png?w=1240 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That would make the House almost 60 percent larger than it is now, so it’s hard to imagine a one-time increase of that scope. Shugart suggested a phased expansion over the next few decades, although he also didn’t think the House necessarily had to get all the way to 692 seats — he just stressed that, according to the cube root law, where the U.S. currently falls suggests that it is dramatically underrepresented. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Regardless of the potential benefits of a bigger House, though, there would likely be steep opposition to expanding it because of some of the tradeoffs — and potential downsides — involved. For instance, a larger House would by necessity mean a bigger government and more spending. House members <a href="https://pressgallery.house.gov/member-data/salaries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">make $174,000 per year</a>, and after five years of service <a href="https://www.senate.gov/CRSpubs/ac0d1dd5-7316-4390-87e6-353589586a89.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they are also eligible for a pension</a>. Combine that with new staff, new construction for office space, perhaps even a roomier House chamber and you’re talking about <a href="https://www.mattglassman.com/?p=4325" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many millions or even billions of dollars</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There could also be consequences for governing, too, such as more gridlock and partisanship. “By increasing the number of players who have to be satisfied in the legislative game, you make arriving at the kind of majorities — or, in most cases, supermajorities — that you need to pass legislation more difficult,” said <a href="https://harrisburg.psu.edu/faculty-and-staff/l-marvin-overby-phd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">L. Marvin Overby</a>, a political scientist at Pennsylvania State University-Harrisburg who studies Congress and <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.2307/3235166?journalCode=pol" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has expressed skepticism</a> toward the promised benefits of House expansion. He also warned that a bigger House might produce fewer competitive seats <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ending-gerrymandering-wont-fix-what-ails-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">thanks to partisan sorting</a> and fewer representatives open to compromise. “You would have even less of an incentive as an individual member of Congress to try to do things on a bipartisan basis,” said Overby, “because your district would be increasingly homogeneous — increasingly Democratic or increasingly Republican.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As such, even more elections may be effectively decided by primaries instead of general elections than they are today, which is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/changing-how-primaries-work-probably-wont-make-politics-less-divisive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">already the case</a> in the vast majority of House districts. And with more safe seats, incumbents would likely have an even easier time getting reelected than <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/articles/house-primaries-a-little-more-action-this-year-than-usual/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they currently do</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In addition, there simply isn’t public support for expansion at this point. In 2018, 51 percent of Americans told the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2018/04/26/5-the-electoral-college-congress-and-representation/#should-the-allocation-of-senate-seats-or-the-size-of-the-house-be-changed" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a> that the size of the House should stay the same, while only 28 percent wanted to expand it (another 18 percent actually wanted to shrink it). Moreover, members of Congress aren’t wild about the idea, either. Legislation <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-bill/996/text?r=7&amp;s=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">introduced in February</a> by Rep. Alcee Hastings of Florida, a Democrat <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/us-rep-alcee-hastings-dies-84-impeached-judge-76899297" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who died in April</a>, aims to establish a bipartisan commission to examine the size of the House, among other things. But the bill has only four co-sponsors and <a href="https://www.sun-sentinel.com/news/politics/elections/fl-ne-alcee-hastings-house-size-electoral-college-20210209-ezlhpnqfq5ag3er6kzz7iwjuzq-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looks unlikely to go anywhere</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Clearly, there are pros and cons to increasing the size of the House, but at the very least, the idea should be more openly debated because, in terms of changes that could be made to our institutions, expanding the House is actually doable. For instance, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-senate-has-always-favored-smaller-states-it-just-didnt-help-republicans-until-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Senate’s small-state bias often gets a lot more attention</a>, but any change to the Senate would require a constitutional amendment whereas the size of the House could be altered with a simple bill.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It’s going to be difficult to increase the size of the House of Representatives; I’m under no illusions,” said Frederick of Bridgewater State University. Nevertheless, it may be time for a change given how unequal districts have become between states and how underrepresented Americans are after more than 100 years of being stuck at 435 House members. Said Frederick, “There’s no doubt that a larger House with smaller constituency population size per district would improve the representational quality that citizens receive from members of Congress.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/anti-establishment-sentiment-ballot-parties-week-79248883</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628766001622788</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Still Unsure About Getting The COVID-19 Vaccine? Start Here.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/still-unsure-about-getting-the-covid-19-vaccine-start-here/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19 Vaccine</category>
			<category>FAQ</category>
			<category>Vaccination</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">In the early days of the pandemic, there was a real sense of camaraderie. We were all in this together. We stood on our balconies and stoops and leaned out windows to clap for front-line workers. We stayed home to keep each other safe. Now, that altruistic mentality has reverted to the all-too-familiar mean of tribalism. It can feel like the <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/anthony-fauci-covid-19-unvaccinated-americans-delta-variant-face-the-nation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">battle lines have been drawn</a>: on one side, those who have been vaccinated, and on the other, those who haven’t. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But things are never that black and white. Even among those who have been vaccinated, many people <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2021/07/unvaccinated-different-anti-vax/619523/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">still have concerns and questions about the vaccine</a>. And among those who haven’t, their reasons for not getting the jab vary from <a href="https://morningconsult.com/covid19-vaccine-dashboard/#section-26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">concerns over potential side effects</a>, to a <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/newsbeat-58086377" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fear of needles</a>, to simply <a href="https://twitter.com/DeNovo_Fatima/status/1424693278469984256" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not being able</a> to take time off work. The <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations_vacc-total-admin-rate-total" target="_blank" rel="noopener">roughly 30 percent</a> of eligible Americans who have yet to be vaccinated are not all anti-vaccine conspiracy theorists, and treating them as such could make them <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2021/07/24/how-talk-vaccine-hesitant-friends-family-about-getting-shot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even less likely</a> to get the shot.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We’ve collected some of the most common concerns with vaccination mentioned by people who are vaccine hesitant, and we’ve provided evidence-based responses to each one. If you or someone you know share any of these concerns, click through to see what information is out there to help you make this important decision. </p>



<ul><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#around-long-enough">The vaccine hasn’t been around long enough for me to know it’s safe.</a>” </li><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#breakthrough">I can still get COVID-19 after getting vaccinated, so there’s no point in getting the shot</a>.” </li><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#asymptomatic-spread">Vaccinated people can still spread the virus, so it doesn’t make a difference to public health if I’m unvaccinated</a>.” </li><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#FDA-approval">The vaccines haven’t been fully approved by the FDA</a>.”</li><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#already-had-covid">I already had COVID-19, so I’m immune and don’t need the vaccine</a>.” </li><li>“<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#vaccine-infertility">I heard the vaccine can cause infertility</a>.” </li></ul><p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/Health/video/covid-19-vaccines-work-74654465</p>


<hr><h2><strong>“The vaccine hasn’t been around long enough for me to know it’s safe.” </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s true that compared to something like a tetanus shot, which has been in use for <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/pubs/pinkbook/tetanus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly a century</a>, COVID-19 vaccines have a much shorter record of safety. But there are a few things to consider. One is that, due to the pandemic, <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations?country=OWID_WRL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">billions of people</a> have received these vaccines. Collecting data on how a medical intervention impacts <em>billions</em> of people would take decades in any other scenario, but we’ve been able to get it in just a few months. And because these vaccines are new, they are being carefully monitored. It’s how experts were able to identify that the AstraZeneca vaccine carries a small risk of a rare blood clot condition called thrombocytopenia syndrome. The <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/healthcare-pharmaceuticals/rare-blood-clot-cases-not-higher-after-astrazeneca-second-dose-study-2021-07-28/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">risk is less than 10 in 1 million</a>, yet researchers were able to identify it quickly due to intensive monitoring and the sheer number of people getting their shots. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">While the Pfizer and Moderna vaccines are the first vaccines using mRNA that have been approved, research on this kind of vaccine delivery method has been <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/11/10/the-story-of-mrna-how-a-once-dismissed-idea-became-a-leading-technology-in-the-covid-vaccine-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">happening for decades</a>. <a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=Dendritic%20cell%20immunotherapy%20for%20HIV-1%20infection%20using%20autologous%20HIV-1%20RNA%3A%20a%20randomized%2C%20double-blind%2C%20placebo-controlled%20clinical%20trial&amp;journal=J.%20Acquir.%20Immune%20Def.%20Syndr.&amp;volume=72&amp;pages=31-38&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;author=Jacobson%2CJM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Previous clinical</a> <a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?title=Immunization%20of%20HIV-1-infected%20persons%20with%20autologous%20dendritic%20cells%20transfected%20with%20mRNA%20encoding%20HIV-1%20Gag%20and%20Nef%3A%20results%20of%20a%20randomized%2C%20placebo-controlled%20clinical%20trial&amp;journal=J.%20Acquir.%20Immune%20Def.%20Syndr.&amp;volume=71&amp;pages=246-253&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;author=Gandhi%2CRT" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trials</a> for mRNA vaccines showed the vaccines were safe, with mild side effects like headache or soreness at the injection site. It also might be helpful to know that mRNA (or messenger ribonucleic acid) is not some new, lab-created substance, it’s a <a href="https://theconversation.com/what-is-mrna-the-messenger-molecule-thats-been-in-every-living-cell-for-billions-of-years-is-the-key-ingredient-in-some-covid-19-vaccines-158511" target="_blank" rel="noopener">naturally-occurring molecule</a> that our body produces and uses as part of its daily cellular functions. </p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-pharmas-lucrative-patent-system-is-complicating-the-pandemic/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A hand holding vials of the vaccine. Below the hand is more vials of the COVID-19 vaccine." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/GettyImages-1314111214-16x9-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/GettyImages-1314111214-16x9-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/GettyImages-1314111214-16x9-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/GettyImages-1314111214-16x9-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				How Pharma’s Lucrative Patent System Is Complicating The Pandemic <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-pharmas-lucrative-patent-system-is-complicating-the-pandemic/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We’re also building on decades of understanding of how vaccines work,” said Namandjé Bumpus, director of the Johns Hopkins University Department of Pharmacology and Molecular Sciences. Part of that understanding includes the fact that adverse side effects from vaccines almost always show up very soon after they’ve been administered — from a few minutes, as in the rare cases of anaphylaxis after the Pfizer and Modern vaccines, to a few weeks, as <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-021-01419-1#:~:text=There%20is%20now%20compelling%20evidence,vector%20vaccine%20or%20the%20Ad26." target="_blank" rel="noopener">we saw with</a> the rare blood clot condition. The <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/vaccines-are-highly-unlikely-to-cause-side-effects-long-after-getting-the-shot-" target="_blank" rel="noopener">longest time</a> before a side effect appeared for any type of vaccine has been six weeks. And because vaccines are designed to prompt our body to mount its own immune response, the actual vaccine doesn’t stay in our system — our bodies <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/vaccines-are-highly-unlikely-to-cause-side-effects-long-after-getting-the-shot-" target="_blank" rel="noopener">process the ingredients</a> in the shot within a day or two. Since the vaccines have been in use for months at this point, any side effects should have emerged. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Could there be unforeseen effects of the vaccines that haven’t yet appeared? Possibly. But as Genevieve Kanter, an economist at the University of Pennsylvania who studies the regulation of biomedical technologies, pointed out, the novel coronavirus — and its variants — also haven’t been around very long. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We don’t know the long-term effects of COVID-19, either,” Kanter said. But what we know so far isn’t ideal: <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/coronavirus/covid-long-haulers-long-term-effects-of-covid19" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Some people who recover from COVID-19</a> have side effects that have lasted for months, including fatigue, breathing difficulties and cognitive impairments. </p>



<hr><h2><strong>“I can still get COVID-19 after getting vaccinated, so there’s no point in getting the shot.” </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since before the vaccines were even available, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/covid-19-vaccine-dont-expect-cure-scientists/story?id=71333281" target="_blank" rel="noopener">experts have warned</a> that they wouldn’t be 100 percent effective at preventing infection. Luckily, the vaccines that we ended up with were actually much more effective than what <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/covid-19-vaccine-dont-expect-cure-scientists/story?id=71333281" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early predictions suggested</a> — Moderna and Pfizer are both <a href="https://www.yalemedicine.org/news/covid-19-vaccine-comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener">better than 90 percent</a>, and Johnson &amp; Johnson is around <a href="https://www.yalemedicine.org/news/covid-19-vaccine-comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener">72 percent effective</a> against the original strain of COVID-19 in the U.S. — but since they aren’t 100 percent, that means some vaccinated people can still get COVID-19. Early studies show the vaccines are less effective against the delta variant, with both <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2108891" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pfizer</a> and <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.06.28.21259420v1.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Moderna</a> around 90 percent effective against infection, and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/06/science/johnson-delta-vaccine-booster.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">J&amp;J</a> up to 71 percent effective against hospitalization. And we’re seeing <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/delta-variant-most-prevalent/2021/08/08/d1017f0e-f558-11eb-9068-bf463c8c74de_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more breakthrough infections</a> as the delta variant spreads.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Nevertheless, study after study shows that your risk of getting COVID-19 is much lower if you’re vaccinated than if you’re unvaccinated. In <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/react-study-shows-fully-vaccinated-are-three-times-less-likely-to-be-infected" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a study published last week</a> that followed over 98,000 people in England from late-June to mid-July, vaccinated individuals were three times less likely to contract COVID-19 than unvaccinated individuals, even as the delta variant dominated cases. In fact, even if you do get infected after vaccination, your risks of getting seriously ill, needing to go in the hospital, needing to go in the intensive care unit or dying are reduced even further. Vaccinated Americans have accounted for less than 0.06 percent of hospitalizations, according to <a href="https://www.kff.org/policy-watch/covid-19-vaccine-breakthrough-cases-data-from-the-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a review from the Kaiser Family Foundation</a>, which looked at states that report breakthrough cases. Of the more than <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">166 million Americans</a> who have been vaccinated, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/covid-19/health-departments/breakthrough-cases.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1,507 have died after contracting COVID-19</a> — a rate of 0.0009 percent. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/year-karaoke-fivethirtyeight-77653577</p>


<hr><h2><strong>“Vaccinated people can still spread the virus, so it doesn’t make a difference to public health if I’m unvaccinated.”</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Our understanding about whether vaccinated individuals can spread the virus to others is still evolving, and though <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/coronavirus-live-updates/2021/07/30/1022867219/cdc-study-provincetown-delta-vaccinated-breakthrough-mask-guidance" target="_blank" rel="noopener">there’s evidence to suggest that they can</a>, there are still important public health reasons to get a jab. For one, your chances of getting COVID-19 in the first place <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/specials/data-shows-how-rare-severe-breakthrough-covid-infections-are/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are reduced when you’re fully vaccinated</a>, which will in turn limit your likelihood of spreading the virus to someone else — you can’t spread what you don’t have. The more people who are vaccinated, the less easily the virus is able to circulate in the population. This helps protect people who can’t yet be vaccinated, such as children under age 12, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/09/health/coronavirus-children-delta.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who are being hospitalized at much higher rates</a> than earlier in the pandemic. You may have read about herd immunity and the fact that, for this virus, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-08-03/delta-s-spread-seen-pushing-herd-immunity-threshold-above-80" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we would need very high levels of immunity</a> to reach that point. But Namandjé Bumpus, director of the department of pharmacology and molecular sciences at Johns Hopkins University, pointed out that regardless of whether we reach herd immunity, a more vaccinated population will lessen the spread of COVID-19 — a 70 percent vaccination rate is still better than 60 percent, which is better than 50 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Herd immunity is not this magic number where suddenly a bell will be rung across the country,” Bumpus said. “Every person counts.”</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-in-favor-of-vaccine-mandates-but-support-is-driven-mainly-by-those-who-have-already-gotten-the-jab/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="Someone’s hands holding open a box of COVID-19 Astrozenica vaccine vials." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/0806_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/0806_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/0806_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/0806_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Americans Are In Favor Of Vaccine Mandates. But Support Is Driven Mainly By Those Who Have Already Gotten The Jab. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-in-favor-of-vaccine-mandates-but-support-is-driven-mainly-by-those-who-have-already-gotten-the-jab/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">But perhaps even more important for public health is the fact that fewer infections provide less opportunity for the virus to mutate into new, potentially more deadly, strains. Each time the novel coronavirus infects a person, <a href="https://theconversation.com/how-the-coronavirus-mutates-and-what-this-means-for-the-future-of-covid-19-154499" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it replicates inside the body</a>. When the virus duplicates, it sometimes makes an exact copy of itself, and other times its copies have a slight mutation. Sometimes these mutations make the virus weaker, and other times, they make it stronger — such as being better able to <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02039-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attach to our cells</a> — according to Dr. Jonathan Li, director of the Harvard/Brigham Virology Specialty Laboratory at Harvard University.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Every time the virus infects a new person, there’s a chance it can find a mutation that benefits itself,” Li said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those beneficial mutations are what allow the novel coronavirus to evolve into new variants, including the delta variant, which is <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2021/07/07/delta-variant-covid/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly 50 percent more contagious</a> than the original strain of the virus. New variants may be <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00121-z%E2%80%9D" target="_blank" rel="noopener">able to evade our immune responses</a>, rendering our existing vaccines less effective (<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/delta-variant.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as with</a> delta) or making it easier for unvaccinated people to <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/unvaccinated-more-than-twice-as-likely-to-get-covid-19-again-cdc-says-11628276064" target="_blank" rel="noopener">get COVID-19 a second time</a>. By getting vaccinated, you’ll reduce the likelihood that you’ll get an infection, denying the virus a new opportunity to mutate and get stronger. And even if you do get a rare breakthrough infection, the <a href="https://news.arizona.edu/story/covid-19-vaccine-reduces-severity-length-viral-load-those-who-still-get-infected" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccines help reduce</a> the length and severity of infection, meaning you’re still reducing the time the virus has to mutate. </p>



<hr><h2><strong>“The vaccines haven’t been fully approved by the FDA.”</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s true, none of the vaccines currently in use have been fully approved by the Food and Drug Administration. However, they have all been granted emergency use authorization, which is <a href="https://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines/emergency-use-authorization-vaccines-explained" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not an easy hurdle to clear</a>, and is constantly monitored — the FDA could <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccinesafety/concerns/recalls.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">revoke this authorization</a> at any time if safety concerns arose. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/03/us/politics/pfizer-vaccine-approval.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">All signs suggest the FDA will fully approve</a> these vaccines within the coming months. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Part of the reason the process has taken so long is because <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/139638/download" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the FDA required six months</a> of safety data to consider full approval, so we needed to wait until enough time had passed to collect the data. That means the process for granting full approval requires a “longer follow-up, [but] not necessarily more rigorous review,” said Susan S. Ellenberg, a former FDA official and a professor emeritus of biostatistics, medical ethics and health policy at the University of Pennsylvania who was on the Operation Warp Speed Data and Safety Monitoring Board. Given the urgency of a deadly pandemic, the emergency use authorization was granted to make sure we could get access to these vaccines sooner rather than later. Plus, if the FDA had rushed the full approval process, it may have eroded trust in the vaccines, rather than increased it, according to Ravina Kullar, an infectious disease expert and fellow at the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</p>



<hr><h2><strong>“I already had COVID-19, so I’m immune and don’t need the vaccine.” </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Having a bout of COVID-19 does provoke an immune response, but <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/people-who-already-had-covid-19-should-still-get-vaccinated-scientists-urge" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we still don’t know</a> how robust that response is or how long it lasts. It’s an unknown, whereas the vaccines are well studied and understood, so you can be assured your shot will give you a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/science-health-coronavirus-pandemic-ad52011f4ca1853fad6eee41a7310c2e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strong immune response</a>. It also isn’t as easy to confirm that you’ve had COVID-19 as it is to confirm that you’ve been vaccinated, which could pose problems for travel or work, depending on requirements. </p>



<hr><h2><strong>“I heard the vaccine can cause infertility.” </strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are a lot of rumors about potential scary side effects from the vaccine, and the ones around fertility are particularly frightening. However, there is no evidence that the vaccines cause any fertility risks — in fact, <a href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/media-resources/science-in-5/episode-24---vaccine-myths-vs-science" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no vaccine in history</a> has ever caused infertility. <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/need-extra-precautions/pregnant-people.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pregnant people are also at a higher risk</a> of more severe COVID-19 infections, so getting vaccinated is especially prudent if you might become pregnant.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One version of this rumor <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/uk-factcheck-syncytin-idUSKBN2A42S7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">appears to be based on a confusion</a> between two types of proteins. The novel coronavirus attaches to the cells in our body using spike proteins. The mRNA vaccines (Pfizer and Moderna) are designed to prompt our body to produce these spike proteins so that our immune system can learn how to identify them and attack them in case we come in contact with the virus. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2021/06/28/coronavirus-vaccines-dont-cause-infertility/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Some people have confused these spike proteins</a> with a completely different kind of protein called syncytin-1, which is part of placenta formation during pregnancy. They claimed the vaccine will cause our immune system to attack syncytin-1, causing infertility or miscarriages. This is not true. Syncytin-1 and the spike protein are immunologically very different, and our body can easily distinguish between the two, according to Ravina Kullar, an infectious disease expert and member of the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“There is one small similarity, but the overall construction of the protein is completely different,” Kullar said. “Our immune system is way too smart to be confused by that.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (Aug. 14, 2021, 1 p.m.): </strong>A previous version of this article compared COVID-19 deaths in all vaccinated Americans, regardless of infection, to the death rate for all infected Americans. That comparison has been removed.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/dr-fauci-life-post-vaccine-bidens-approach-pandemic-74864671</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628676002261179</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Andrew Cuomo Had Nowhere To Go But Out</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/andrew-cuomo-had-nowhere-to-go-but-out/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>Andrew Cuomo</category>
			<category>Kathy Hochul</category>
			<category>New York Politics</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<category>Sexual Harassment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">After New York Attorney General <a href="https://ag.ny.gov/sites/default/files/2021.08.03_nyag_-_investigative_report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Letitia James’s report</a> found that Gov. Andrew Cuomo had violated state and federal law by <a href="https://www.timesunion.com/state/article/Attorney-general-concludes-Cuomo-sexually-16359949.php?IPID=Times-Union-HP-CP-Spotlight" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sexually harassing 11 women</a>, Cuomo <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-andrew-cuomo-resign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seemed intent</a> on riding it out. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Just last week <a href="https://apnews.com/article/andrew-cuomo-investigation-sexual-harassment-04b0e7ba80db368124a5e9c9bcf4dc0d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he denied the report’s charges</a> and said that he wouldn’t resign. But with <a href="https://abc7ny.com/andrew-cuomo-biden-resign-attorney-general-letitia-james/10927344/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most Democrats, including President Biden</a>, calling for his resignation, an impending impeachment investigation in the state legislature and public opinion now solidly against him, it all became too much for Cuomo. On Tuesday, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/andrew-cuomo-resign-york-governor-sexual-harassment-allegations/story?id=76171581" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he announced his resignation</a>, effective Aug. 24.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">When the allegations of sexual harassment first broke earlier this year, one of Cuomo’s political saving graces was that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/4-ways-andrew-cuomos-political-future-could-play-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public opinion hadn’t turned against him</a>. But in the aftermath of the report’s release, that quickly changed. Polls found that <a href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Marist-Poll_NYS-NOS-and-Tables_202108040647-2.pdf#page=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">anywhere from 60</a> to <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3816" target="_blank" rel="noopener">70 percent</a> of New Yorkers thought Cuomo should resign or that the state legislature should start impeachment proceedings if he didn’t resign, including a majority of Democrats. With such strong opposition within his own party, Cuomo had few options available to him. He had reportedly tried <a href="https://www.thecity.nyc/2021/8/9/22616581/cuomo-impeachment-seeking-deal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to reach a backroom deal</a> whereby he wouldn’t seek reelection in exchange for avoiding impeachment, but that clearly doesn’t seem to have been an option. The state legislature had been in the process of moving ahead with impeachment proceedings.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-much-scandals-hurt-candidates-running-for-re-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Some politicians have survived scandals</a>, but as my colleague Nathaniel Rakich has previously noted, politicians faced with charges of sexual harassment <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/4-ways-andrew-cuomos-political-future-could-play-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been forced out at a higher rate</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-people-are-resigning-from-congress-than-at-any-time-in-recent-history/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after the #MeToo movement in 2017</a>, when claims of sexual harassment and misconduct in the work place have been taken more seriously.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Cuomo posed a serious liability to his own party. Sexual harassment is something that Americans, especially Democrats, view as a significant problem. In 2019, 80 percent of Democrats <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/247901/americans-views-sexual-harassment-workplace-victimization-trends.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told Gallup that they thought sexual harassment was a major problem</a>, while 62 percent of Americans overall thought the same. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it was also easier for Democrats to push for Cuomo’s resignation because his successor, Lt. Gov. Kathy Hochul, wasn’t herself mired in scandal, and as a Democrat, she would also keep the party in charge of the state. By comparison, one big reason the Democratic governor of Virginia, Ralph Northam, didn’t resign following his <a href="https://richmond.com/news/local/government-politics/resisting-calls-to-resign-northam-denies-hes-in-racist-yearbook-photo-admits-he-appeared-in/article_f75d342d-e028-586e-8631-70d52424d604.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blackface scandal in 2019 was that his immediate successors, both Democrats, all</a> had their own problems: the lieutenant governor <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2019/2/4/18210638/justin-fairfax-ralph-northam-virginia-sex-assault-allegation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">faced multiple sexual assault allegations</a> and the attorney general had <a href="https://wamu.org/story/19/02/06/virginia-ag-mark-herring-admits-to-blackface-photo-from-college/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his own blackface scandal</a>. Had Democrats pushed for all three to step down, the governorship might have ended up in Republican hands. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Hochul makes history now as the first woman governor of New York, but given she only has 15 months left to serve in Cuomo’s term, this also puts the 2022 New York gubernatorial election under a cloud of uncertainty as Cuomo — especially prior to the allegations — <a href="https://apnews.com/article/health-government-and-politics-campaigns-coronavirus-pandemic-0eca65bc9468ec773628c4045a8470ea" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was expected to mount a bid for a fourth term</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If Hochul runs, the fact that she is an unelected incumbent could make for an interesting electoral dynamic. Right now, she’s not terribly well known — about half of New York’s registered voters in <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3816" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent Quinnipiac University poll</a> said they didn’t have an opinion of her job performance. That gives Hochul an opening to make an impression with voters, but she doesn’t have much time. The 2022 campaign is already underway, and even though unelected gubernatorial incumbents who run for a full term have <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/articles/stepping-up-how-governors-who-have-succeeded-to-the-top-job-have-performed-over-the-years/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tended to win their party’s nomination</a>, they also are more vulnerable to a primary challenge than elected incumbents. And in a blue state like New York, there are a number of high-profile Democrats who might throw their hat in the ring. That said, it’s early yet, and we still don’t even know if Hochul will run. But for now, we’re keeping an eye on what New Yorkers think of Hochul and what that means for the race for the governor’s mansion in 2022.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 22:51:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628635502024804</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Emergency Politics Podcast: Why Cuomo Chose To Resign</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/emergency-politics-podcast-why-cuomo-chose-to-resign/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Andrew Cuomo</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Infrastructure</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Resignation</category>
			<category>Sexual Harassment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/emergency-politics-podcast-why-cuomo-chose-to-resign/">
	<div data-podcast-id="314200" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Emergency Politics Podcast: Why Cuomo Chose To Resign">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP5666915401.mp3?updated=1628629613"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">New York Gov. Andrew Cuomo announced his resignation a week after the state attorney general issued a report confirming allegations of sexual harassment. He will be replaced by Lieutenant Gov. Kathy Hochul, who will become the first female governor of New York. In this emergency installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics Podcast, the crew talks about what led to Cuomo’s resignation, how New Yorkers feel about his replacement and what this means for New York’s 2022 Democratic primary race for governor.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 22:03:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628631002209621</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How The Rise Of White Identity Politics Explains The Fight Over Critical Race Theory</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-rise-of-white-identity-politics-explains-the-fight-over-critical-race-theory/</link>
						<dc:creator>Michael Tesler</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Michael Tesler</dc:creator>
			<category>Critical Race Theory</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Republican Party</category>
			<category>White Identity</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Critical race theory is quickly becoming <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2021/06/24/critical-race-theory-fox-news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Republican Party’s favorite culture-war cudgel.</a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">From April to mid-July, <a href="https://www.mediamatters.org/fox-news/fox-news-obsession-critical-race-theory-numbers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fox News mentioned it nearly 2,000 times</a>, per Media Matters, a left-leaning media watchdog that tracks right-leaning media outlets. In fact, since February, mentions of the theory have more than doubled month-over-month on Fox News with prominent Republicans, including former <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jackbrewster/2021/06/18/trump-says-critical-race-theory-borders-on-psychological-abuse/?sh=3086eaba450e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">President Donald Trump</a>, former <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/mike-pence-gop-critical-race-theory-state-sanctioned-racism-1604033" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vice President Mike Pence</a>, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/florida-race-and-ethnicity-government-and-politics-education-74d0af6c52c0009ec3fa3ee9955b0a8d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis</a> and <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/news/559208-ted-cruz-says-critical-race-theory-is-as-racist-as-klansmen-in-white-sheets" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Ted Cruz</a>, all railing against it.        </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The attacks aren’t merely rhetorical, either. According to a July report from the Brookings Institute, <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2021/07/02/why-are-states-banning-critical-race-theory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eight states</a> (Idaho, Oklahoma, Tennessee, Texas, Iowa, New Hampshire, Arizona and South Carolina) have passed laws banning critical race theory-related content from being taught in schools. Similar legislation has been <a href="https://www.edweek.org/policy-politics/map-where-critical-race-theory-is-under-attack/2021/06" target="_blank" rel="noopener">introduced in over a dozen other state capitols</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Few Americans can define what <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/many-americans-embrace-falsehoods-about-critical-race-theory-2021-07-15/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">critical race theory</a> actually is — an academic framework that <a href="https://www.edweek.org/leadership/what-is-critical-race-theory-and-why-is-it-under-attack/2021/05" target="_blank" rel="noopener">originated among legal scholars in the 1970s</a> to help explain how racism permeates American institutions — but it’s not surprising that it has emerged as a bogeyman on the political right. Increasingly, the Republican base is politically animated by white racial grievances, which is a major reason why misrepresentations of critical race theory — “<a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/news/559208-ted-cruz-says-critical-race-theory-is-as-racist-as-klansmen-in-white-sheets" target="_blank" rel="noopener">every white person is racist</a>” or “<a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/06/15/scholar-strategy-how-critical-race-theory-alarms-could-convert-racial-anxiety-into-political-energy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">certain children are inherently bad people because of their skin color</a>” — have found such a receptive audience. After all, many of the same grievances helped fuel Trump’s rise. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">From the earliest days of his 2016 presidential campaign, Trump’s <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/03/03/how-political-science-helps-explain-the-rise-of-trump-the-role-of-white-identity-and-grievances/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">support has been most heavily concentrated</a> among white Americans who think they face significant racial discrimination. In fact, perceived anti-white discrimination powerfully predicted voter preferences in the 2016 general election. One <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/discrimination-race-religion_n_5833761ee4b099512f845bba" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey</a> conducted shortly after the election found Trump voters were over four times more likely than Clinton voters <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/discrimination-race-religion_n_5833761ee4b099512f845bba" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to say white Americans face “a lot” of discrimination</a> (45 percent versus 10 percent, respectively); other polls also consistently showed that Republicans and Trump’s 2016 supporters <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/racial-justice-2020-george-floyd/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saw racial discrimination</a> against white people as <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-fix/wp/2017/08/02/discrimination-against-whites-was-a-core-concern-of-trumps-base/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a bigger problem than unfair treatment of racial and ethnic minorities</a> in American society. Those views have only grown more pronounced in Republican politics. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For example, the chart below, which draws on data from the American National Election Studies, shows that support for the Republican presidential candidate has steadily grown by 12-to-15 percentage points since 2012 among white Americans who think there’s at least a moderate amount of anti-white discrimination in the U.S.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="White racial grievance increasingly drives GOP politics" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/hSzFS/4/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="475" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, the reverse is true among white Americans who don’t think there’s much anti-white discrimination: Support for the Republican presidential candidate has steadily dropped. The same pattern holds even after accounting for several factors that are also strongly correlated with presidential vote choice, such as partisanship, ideology and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racial_resentment_scale" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racial resentment</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is still a relatively new phenomenon in our politics, however. For instance, I found in my research with fellow political scientists John Sides and Lynn Vavreck that perceptions of anti-white discrimination <a href="https://unherd.com/2019/01/trumps-white-identity-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were not as predictive of voters’ preferences</a> in elections immediately preceding 2016, after controlling for other relevant factors. With Trump’s rise in 2016, perceived anti-white discrimination became a significantly more powerful predictor of voting behavior with the same controls in place.   </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, white grievance politics now explains more than just vote choice. Sides, Vavreck and I <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/gwsslcf9zzcudz9/white%20identity21.pdf?dl=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found in a 2021 working paper</a> that perceived anti-white discrimination increasingly predicts public opinion of people and policies connected to the former president, like Pence or repealing the Affordable Care Act. We also find that perceived anti-white discrimination is increasingly associated with Americans’ partisan attachments, much the way public opinion of Barack Obama often spilled over into <a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1017/s0022381612000904" target="_blank" rel="noopener">anti-Black</a> and <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/10659129211007211" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Islamophobic attitudes</a> that would shape party identification during his presidency.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These findings dovetail with the important research of Duke University political scientist Ashley Jardina. Her book, <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/white-identity-politics/5C330931FF4CF246FCA043AB14F5C626" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“White Identity Politics</a>,” argues that white racial grievances more strongly influence political beliefs when white people perceive themselves as under threat, which is one reason why Trump was so effective in his <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-trumps-use-of-white-identity-politics-strategic/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">many appeals</a> to the <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/think/opinion/trump-stephen-miller-capitalize-white-america-s-fear-its-racial-ncna1102081" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cultural</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/14/us/politics/donald-trump-white-identity.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">economic</a> and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2018/06/21/donald-trump-is-a-symbol-of-white-identity-politics-in-europe-too/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">physical threats</a> that they were supposedly facing. And Republican attacks on critical race theory follow the same playbook, framing its teachings as an anti-white “<a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/annals-of-inquiry/how-a-conservative-activist-invented-the-conflict-over-critical-race-theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">existential threat to the United States</a>.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republican politics have become so animated by white victimhood in the Trump era that any honest accounting of racial injustice in U.S. history is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-politics-of-white-liberals-and-white-conservatives-are-shaped-by-whiteness/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost certain to draw conservative ire</a>. Indeed, I found that the share of Republicans who think there’s too much Black history taught in schools <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2018/02/28/democrats-and-republicans-are-increasingly-divided-on-the-value-of-teaching-black-history/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">increased by 30 percentage points</a> from 2000 to 2018. But when you combine the rise of white identity politics in the GOP with its mischaracterization of critical race theory as tantamount to anti-white indoctrination, it’s even easier to see how a relatively obscure framework emerged as a leading issue in Republican Party politics. Moreover, the war on critical race theory suggests that the white grievance politics Trump helped activate isn’t going anywhere; rather, it’s a key part of the GOP strategy moving forward.  </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628590501613275</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What To Watch For As States Draw New Congressional Maps</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-watch-for-as-states-draw-new-congressional-maps/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Gerrymandering</category>
			<category>Ohio</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Primaries</category>
			<category>Redistricting Tracker</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-watch-for-as-states-draw-new-congressional-maps/">
	<div data-podcast-id="314164" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What To Watch For As States Draw New Congressional Maps">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9709685202.mp3?updated=1628547909"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">In his first six months in office, President Biden had the most stable <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-bidens-approval-rating-has-barely-budged-in-his-first-6-months/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval rating</a> in history. His approval rating is still <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">incredibly steady</a>, but in recent weeks it has begun to decline. In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses why Biden’s approval rating is falling and how much Democrats should worry. They also check in on the results from the two recent primary elections in Ohio. Lastly, they announce the launch of <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/">FiveThirtyEight’s Redistricting Tracker</a> and talk about the most important factors going into the congressional redistricting process.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 23:26:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628550001661212</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Redistricting Looks Like In Every State</title>
			<link>https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/</link>
						<dc:creator>Ryan Best</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Ryan Best， Aaron Bycoffe and Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2020 Census</category>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Gerrymandering</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>An updating tracker of proposed congressional maps — and whether they might benefit Democrats or Republicans in the 2022 midterms and beyond.</p>
<p> </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628505002701143</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How To Make Sense Of Our Redistricting Tracker</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-redistricting-tracker-works/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Electoral Map</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<category>Redistricting Tracker</category>
			<category>U.S. House</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1200" height="745" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-guide-topper.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-guide-topper.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-guide-topper.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-guide-topper.png?w=1400 2x"><figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p></figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Circle Thursday, Aug. 12 on your calendar: That’s the date on which the U.S. Census Bureau now <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/08/05/1024878625/2020-census-data-redistricting-voting-districts-when-release" target="_blank" rel="noopener">says</a> it will release block-level results from the 2020 census — the data that state and local governments use for redistricting. And given that this data dump was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-delayed-census-has-affected-redistricting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">delayed several months due to the pandemic</a>, the announcement will touch off a frantic, nationwide scramble to redraw voting districts in time for the 2022 midterm elections. <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/news/politics/2021/07/09/michigan-supreme-court-redistricting-timeline/5296643001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Many states</a> are already <a href="https://www.desmoinesregister.com/story/news/politics/2021/05/20/iowa-districts-legislature-special-session-likely-census-delay-redistricting-unfinished/5146158001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">down to the wire</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s hard to overstate the impact that redistricting will have over American politics for the next 10 years. Republicans enter this redistricting cycle with the power to redraw <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-states-won-and-lost-seats-in-the-2020-census/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">187 congressional districts to Democrats’ 75</a>,<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also 167 districts where neither party enjoys full control of redistricting — either because of independent commissions or split partisan control. Plus, there are six at-large seats (Alaska, Delaware, North Dakota, South Dakota, Vermont and Wyoming) that won’t be redrawn at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> which means redistricting could hand control of the House of Representatives <a href="https://cookpolitical.com/redistrictnopaywall" target="_blank" rel="noopener">back to Republicans in 2022</a> all by itself given Democrats’ mere <a href="https://pressgallery.house.gov/member-data/party-breakdown" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eight-seat majority</a>. In fact, to understand the possible fallout of a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/the-gerrymandering-project/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gerrymandered</a> congressional map, look no further than what happened after the 2011 redistricting cycle, when Republicans drew more than five times as many congressional districts as Democrats, resulting in a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/advantage-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">record-setting Republican bias</a> in U.S. House elections <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/partisan-gerrymandering-north-carolina/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">throughout the 2010s</a>. This means what happens in the 2021-22 redistricting process could have repercussions for not only 2022, but also 2024, 2026 and throughout the rest of the decade.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, it is very important to track how the partisan makeup and competitiveness of districts in the congressional maps that get drawn this fall, winter and spring change — which is exactly what we’re doing at FiveThirtyEight. Today, we launched our <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2021-22 redistricting tracker</a>, your one-stop shop for following the congressional redistricting process.<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every state will also redraw its state-legislative boundaries before 2022, but we won’t be tracking legislative redistricting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> You can look up which party controls redistricting in each state, where the process currently stands and when to expect a new map to take effect; for states with proposed or final maps, you can also view the demographic and partisan breakdown of the new districts, see which party gained or lost ground and check if the map exhibits any signs of gerrymandering. Allow us to walk you through all the bells and whistles:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="1296" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/01.National-Map.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/01.National-Map.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/01.National-Map.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/01.National-Map.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The first thing you’ll see on the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national page of the tracker</a> is a map of all congressional districts nationwide, with each district shaded according to its <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a>.<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> We’re considering districts with a partisan lean of D+15 or bluer as solidly Democratic; districts with a partisan lean between D+15 and D+5 as competitive but Democratic-leaning; districts with a partisan lean between D+5 and R+5 as highly competitive; districts with a partisan lean between R+5 and R+15 as competitive but Republican-leaning; and districts with a partisan lean of R+15 or redder as solidly Republican.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These categories are based on the historical competitiveness of districts with a given partisan lean. But we were also deliberately generous with our definition of “competitive”; for instance, we think it would be wrong to consider an R+14 district as “safe” for Republicans, even though the party has historically won such districts nine times out of 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a></p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/anti-establishment-sentiment-ballot-parties-week-79248883</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, though, the new congressional map is mostly empty, since, other than the six <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/At-large" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at-large</a> states, no state has final maps yet. But once the map fills in more, you’ll be able to compare it to the old (pre-2021) congressional map in a few different ways. First, you can compare the maps themselves by toggling between “New Maps” and “Old Maps” in the upper-right corner. Second, you can compare the partisan tilt of the old maps and the new maps at a glance via the two waffle charts below the map. For instance, you can see the old map brought Republicans to the cusp of a House majority on the strength of Republican-leaning seats alone; how will the new map compare when it’s fully filled in?</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="600" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/02.BoP-robotext.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/02.BoP-robotext.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/02.BoP-robotext.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/02.BoP-robotext.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">We’ll also keep you up to date with the latest redistricting news, including a continually updated blurb summarizing the national big picture on redistricting; a regularly updating feed of state-specific redistricting news from our friends at <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">All About Redistricting</a>;<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All About Redistricting is a nonpartisan website founded by law professor Justin Levitt and now run by law professor Doug Spencer. We highly recommend checking it out if you’re looking for redistricting coverage that’s even wonkier than ours: Each state page features detailed explanations of redistricting law, has summaries of how redistricting played out in 2001 and 2011 and even covers state-legislative redistricting, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> a list of maps we’ve recently added or updated on our own tracker; and a feed that features FiveThirtyEight’s and ABC News’s latest standalone articles on redistricting.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A map of the U.S. puzzle pieces that are blue, red, and gray" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/REDISTRICTING-TRACKER-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				What Redistricting Looks Like In Every State <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the bottom of the national page, you’ll find a table where you can quickly look up the date by which each state is expected to finalize a new map, whether new maps have been proposed and the partisan breakdown of the old map (and, eventually, the new one). Once states begin to finalize their maps, we’ll move those states to a separate table without the deadline and status columns — but with a column indicating whether the map got better for Democrats or for Republicans.<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on whether the party’s chance of winning a majority of the state’s congressional districts significantly increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a> </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="1423" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/03.state-list.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/03.state-list.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/03.state-list.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/03.state-list.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Every state also has its own page on our tracker, which you can access using the menu on the left or by selecting the state in the map or table on the national page. At the top of each state page, you can see how redistricting works in that state, including which party (if any) currently has control over it, as well as a timeline of important dates in the redistricting process. For instance, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/ohio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here’s Ohio</a>:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="810" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/04.Ohio_.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/04.Ohio_.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/04.Ohio_.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/04.Ohio_.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And in states where new maps have been proposed (currently just Colorado), you’ll also see a table of all the maps we’re tracking — including their status, who proposed them and how many red, blue and competitive seats they each have. We make no promises to track <em>every</em> proposed map in <em>every</em> state — we’re not going to be able to analyze every map submitted to the California Citizens Redistricting Commission, for instance — but we will track those maps that have a realistic chance of becoming law.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="340" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/05.Colorado-proposed-list.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/05.Colorado-proposed-list.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/05.Colorado-proposed-list.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/05.Colorado-proposed-list.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Select a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/colorado/preliminary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">proposed map</a> for the really good stuff: a data-heavy analysis of the partisanship and demographic breakdown of the map. (Once a state approves a final map, all this stuff will fill in on its <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/colorado/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">main state page</a>, too.) Like the national home page, this page has partisan-lean-shaded maps of both the old and new district lines; two horizontal charts representing the old and new balances of power in the state’s congressional delegation; and a text description of how many Democratic-leaning, Republican-leaning and highly competitive seats are in the new map (plus how that differs from the old map).</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="2060" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/06.Colorado-proposed-breakdown.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/06.Colorado-proposed-breakdown.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/06.Colorado-proposed-breakdown.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/06.Colorado-proposed-breakdown.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Next is a section that we suspect a lot of you will care about: an attempt to quantify how fair the new map is. Gerrymandering is an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-cant-we-just-burn-gerrymandering-to-the-ground/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">incredibly complex topic</a>, and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/hating-gerrymandering-is-easy-fixing-it-is-harder/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">there is no one objectively fair way to draw a map</a>, but we’ve settled on three metrics that attempt to get at the question of whether a map is drawn in an anti-competitive fashion. (If you’re interested in checking out additional measures of a map’s fairness, we recommend those from the <a href="https://gerrymander.princeton.edu/tests" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Princeton Gerrymandering Project</a>, <a href="https://planscore.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PlanScore</a> and <a href="https://davesredistricting.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dave’s Redistricting App</a>.) You can also see how a given proposed map compares with the old map or other proposed maps on each metric; the shaded row is the map you’re currently viewing.<a data-footnote-id="18" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-18" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maps appear in order from most biased toward Democrats to most biased toward Republicans; for the “competitiveness” measure, they appear from most to least competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>18</sup></a> </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="480" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/07.Colorado-proposed-fairness.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/07.Colorado-proposed-fairness.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/07.Colorado-proposed-fairness.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/07.Colorado-proposed-fairness.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Here’s how our three fairness metrics are calculated:</p>



<ul><li>The <strong>median seat</strong> metric compares the partisan lean of the median, or tipping-point, district in the state to the partisan lean of the state as a whole. The idea here is that the median seat should have roughly the same partisanship as the state, or else it’s possible that the party that wins the statewide vote will not win a majority of its congressional districts. For example, the <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/blob/master/partisan-lean/fivethirtyeight_partisan_lean_STATES.csv">partisan lean of Colorado</a> is D+6.4, and the partisan lean of the median district in its old congressional map (the <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/blob/master/partisan-lean/fivethirtyeight_partisan_lean_DISTRICTS.csv">6th District</a>) is D+11.5, so the map has a 5.2-point<a data-footnote-id="19" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-19" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s not 5.1 points because of rounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>19</sup></a> bias toward Democrats. In other words, if the two parties exactly tied in the Colorado popular vote, Democrats would be expected to win the 6th District by 5.2 percentage points — and Republicans would theoretically need to win the Colorado popular vote by more than 5.2 percentage points in order to capture a majority of its congressional districts.</li><li>The <strong>efficiency gap</strong> metric is based on a formula <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2457468">developed by a pair of academic researchers in 2014</a> whose goal was to set a quantifiable, legal standard for what constitutes gerrymandering.<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their efforts failed when the Supreme Court rejected the standard in its 2018 decision in &lt;a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/gill-v-whitford/"&gt;Gill v. Whitford&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>20</sup></a> The efficiency gap is the difference between the two parties’ “wasted votes” divided by the total number of voters, where “wasted votes” are defined as all votes cast for the losing party in a district as well as votes for the <em>winning</em> party in excess of a majority. To take a simple example, imagine a state with three districts — two of which Republicans win 60 votes to 40 votes, and one of which Democrats win 90 votes to 10 votes. Democrats have 40 wasted votes in each of the first two districts and 39 in the third (because they won 39 more votes than 51, the district’s majority threshold), for a total of 119. Meanwhile, Republicans have nine wasted votes in each of the first two districts and 10 in the third district, for a total of 28. The map’s efficiency gap is therefore 91 (119 minus 28) divided by 300 (the total number of votes in all three districts), or 30.3 percentage points in favor of Republicans.<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since there are no House elections under the new maps yet, we calculate the efficiency gap for all maps based on the results of the 2020 presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>21</sup></a></li><li>Finally, the <strong>competitiveness</strong> metric is much more straightforward: It is simply the number of districts in a map that have a partisan lean between D+5 and R+5 — i.e., districts easily winnable by either party. This isn’t a measure of partisan bias, but rather of how competitive a map is and how responsive it is to changes in the political environment.</li></ul><p data-paragraph="main">If a map scores poorly on these three metrics, it might be gerrymandered. Then again, it might also just be that the state’s political geography has a <a href="https://www.nccourts.gov/assets/inline-files/LDTX154.pdf?YcdXhXVmKchq3lc8BQXQ5YK3IjOED1ZX" target="_blank" rel="noopener">built-in bias against one party</a> (for instance, if the vast majority of the state’s Democrats are packed into just one city). And if a map scores well on these metrics, it also doesn’t necessarily mean it <em>isn’t</em> gerrymandered in some other way. For instance, states can be racially gerrymandered to dilute the influence of nonwhite voters,<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although in practice, this usually results in a partisan bias as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> or a map might break up <a href="https://aceproject.org/main/english/bd/bdb05c.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">communities of interest</a>, although these are often notoriously difficult to define (and, thus, quantify).</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-governor-and-house-primary-races-were-watching-so-far/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An orange background with a cartoon head and a word bubble that reads: “Florida does have a knack for being close no matter which way the political winds are blowing.”" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/SlackChat_0721-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/SlackChat_0721-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/SlackChat_0721-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/SlackChat_0721-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				The Governor And House Primary Races We’re Watching So Far <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-governor-and-house-primary-races-were-watching-so-far/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, the last table on each map page sums up the politics and demographics of the new map, including each district’s exact partisan lean and its incumbent representative. Here, you can see at a glance whether any incumbents have been drawn into an opposite-party district — or thrown into a district with a fellow incumbent. (By default, each representative is assigned to the new district that contains the greatest share of his or her current district. But if the representative has announced his or her intention to run for reelection in a different district — which will often happen to avoid scenarios like those we described above — we’ll switch him or her over to that district instead.) </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1780" height="1000" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/08.Colorado-proposed-district-breakdown.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/08.Colorado-proposed-district-breakdown.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/08.Colorado-proposed-district-breakdown.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/08.Colorado-proposed-district-breakdown.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">You can also see the racial makeup of the voting-age population (i.e., residents age 18 or older) in each new district. Because voting these days is so racially polarized, this is an important indicator of whether nonwhite communities will have adequate representation in Congress. The Voting Rights Act <a href="http://www.publicmapping.org/what-is-redistricting/redistricting-criteria-the-voting-rights-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">requires</a> that, where possible, districts must be drawn to give minority communities the ability to elect the candidate of their choice — which is usually, but not necessarily, interpreted as a district where a racial minority makes up at least 50 percent of the voting-age population. But there is no hard-and-fast rule. In fact, districts with a minority population significantly higher than 50 percent may be trying to “pack” nonwhite voters into too few districts — the mark of a racial gerrymander. And, of course, districts with a minority population below 50 percent may still elect a minority candidate. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Each map and state page finishes up with a state-specific version of some of the modules you were first introduced to on the national page, such as the latest changes and additions to our tracker, the latest news from All About Redistricting and — in particularly interesting states — a blurb summarizing the current status and debates surrounding redistricting. In other words, if you’re interested in redistricting in a specific state, you should be able to follow the whole process from soup to nuts simply by bookmarking its state page.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, we hope you bookmark the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">entire redistricting tracker</a> and refer back to it often over the next several months. We’ll be keeping everything updated in real time, so there will always be new maps to evaluate and new progress to track. And since the tracker is a living document, if you see anything that needs to be updated — or have any other suggestions for it — please don’t hesitate to <a href="mailto:nathaniel.rakich@fivethirtyeight.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">drop us a line</a>. With the long-delayed census data finally becoming available this week, we expect things will start changing quickly!</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/voters-react-scandals-cuomos-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79271602</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628505002701142</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Americans Are In Favor Of Vaccine Mandates. But Support Is Driven Mainly By Those Who Have Already Gotten The Jab.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-are-in-favor-of-vaccine-mandates-but-support-is-driven-mainly-by-those-who-have-already-gotten-the-jab/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>COVID-19 Vaccine</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">As cases rise nationwide due to the high number of unvaccinated Americans and the highly transmissible delta variant of the novel coronavirus, many governments and businesses have turned to vaccine mandates as a potential solution. Major corporations such as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/03/business/vaccine-mandate-employees-microsoft.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google, Microsoft and The Walt Disney Company</a><a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FiveThirtyEight is owned by Disney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a> have recently announced that they will require in-person employees to be vaccinated, and President Biden (along with <a href="https://www.usnews.com/news/best-states/articles/2021-07-29/these-governors-are-mandating-the-covid-19-vaccine-for-government-employees" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several state governors</a>) will require their workers to <a href="https://apnews.com/article/lifestyle-joe-biden-business-health-travel-a1670ffa08f1f2eab42c675d99f1d9ad" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attest that they are vaccinated</a> or else face stringent masking, testing and social-distancing requirements.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Despite prominent voices on the right giving vaccine mandates labels such as “<a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/mcenany-biden-vaccine-mandates-nyc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Orwellian</a>,” they are actually pretty popular among the American public. And where they are controversial, it’s based less on partisanship than on whether the individuals have been vaccinated themselves.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First, the overall numbers. According to a late July <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/07/28/return-to-normal-vaccine-mandates-polling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult</a> poll, 56 percent of adults said employers should probably or definitely require COVID-19 vaccinations for their employees and customers; only 32 percent said they probably or definitely should not. That confidence extends to schools, too. Last month, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/353042/parents-support-mask-mandate-divided-vaccines.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup</a> found that 60 percent of Americans supported mandatory vaccines for high school students and 56 percent supported them for middle school students — although among K-12 parents, those numbers were notably lower (47 percent and 43 percent, respectively).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, the numbers don’t meaningfully change when Americans are asked about the government mandating vaccines for the general population. The <a href="https://osf.io/6wcn9/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID States Project</a>, a polling consortium out of Northeastern, Harvard, Rutgers and Northwestern universities, found in a June/July poll that 64 percent of Americans approved of the government requiring <em>everyone</em> to get a COVID-19 vaccine. All but three states (North Dakota, South Dakota and Wyoming) had a majority in favor of mandatory vaccines.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s because, while there <em>is</em> a partisan divide over mandatory vaccines, a healthy share of Republicans actually do support them too. Morning Consult found that 38 percent of Republicans supported company-mandated vaccines, albeit with 49 percent opposed. And the COVID States Project found that 45 percent of Republicans supported even government-mandated vaccines for all. Of course, these numbers paled in comparison to support among Democrats: 76 percent in the Morning Consult poll (with 15 percent opposed), 84 percent in the COVID States Project poll.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-republicans-have-changed-their-messaging-on-the-covid-19-vaccine-is-it-too-little-too-late/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="House Minority Whip speaks at a podium, with other GOP representatives and the congressional building behind him." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GettyImages-1234110870-4x3-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GettyImages-1234110870-4x3-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GettyImages-1234110870-4x3-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GettyImages-1234110870-4x3-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Some Republicans Have Changed Their Messaging On The COVID-19 Vaccine. Is It Too Little, Too Late? <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-republicans-have-changed-their-messaging-on-the-covid-19-vaccine-is-it-too-little-too-late/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">But these partisan divides are just proxies for the real schism over mandatory shots: individual vaccination status. For example, Morning Consult found that 74 percent of already-vaccinated people supported company-mandated vaccines, while 54 percent of unvaccinated people opposed them. Interestingly, 28 percent of unvaccinated people actually <em>supported</em> mandatory vaccines — if you are one of these people, we’d love to hear from you! </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All of this is a reminder that, even as vaccine hesitancy remains a very real problem, a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/08/03/politics/most-americans-vaccinated-polls/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“landslide majority” of Americans of every persuasion</a> have happily gotten inoculated. And so while there are significant divides in <em>who</em> approves of vaccine mandates, overall support is consistently high — despite what you might hear on cable news. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>Marquette University Law School is out with its <a href="https://law.marquette.edu/poll/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/MLSPSC03Toplines.html">annual poll on the U.S. Supreme Court</a>, and Americans somewhat or strongly approve of the nation’s highest court 60 percent to 39 percent, making it, per the same poll, the most popular of the three branches of government. However, that approval rating was down 6 percentage points from last year, largely because of a decrease in popularity among Republicans. The public generally perceives the court as a center-right institution: A plurality of respondents (42 percent) rated the court as moderate, while 37 percent rated it as somewhat conservative.</li><li>In 10 of the countries polled by the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/07/30/those-on-ideological-right-favor-fewer-covid-19-restrictions-in-most-advanced-economies/">Pew Research Center</a>, that country’s political right was more likely than its left or center to think there should have been fewer coronavirus restrictions. In Greece, however, 55 percent of the political left thought there should have been fewer restrictions, but only 34 percent of the right. Unsurprisingly, though, it was the U.S. that had the largest gap between left and right: 52 percent of stateside conservatives wanted fewer restrictions, while only 7 percent of liberals did. (Turns out we win the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/olympics-medal-count/">gold medal</a> for polarization too.)</li><li>Between <a href="https://www.sacbee.com/news/california/fires/article253286498.html">massive wildfires</a> and <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/data/2021/07/oregons-heat-wave-death-toll-grows-to-116.html">heat waves</a>, it has been a grueling summer in the American West. Nearly half (47 percent) of Westerners told <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2021/08/02/many-americans-feel-recent-effects-climate-change?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_medium=website_article&amp;utm_campaign=climate_change">YouGov</a> that the wildfires had affected them personally or that they had experienced reduced air quality from them. In addition, 53 percent said they had felt temperatures over 100 degrees Fahrenheit in the past week.</li><li>In July, female gymnasts from Germany wore <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/07/26/sport/tokyo-germany-unitard-intl-scli-spt/index.html">full-body unitards</a> in protest of the “sexualization” of their typical uniform, and the Norwegian women’s beach handball team was <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/07/21/1018768633/a-womens-beach-handball-team-is-fined-for-not-wanting-to-wear-bikini-bottoms">fined</a> for wearing shorts instead of bikini bottoms. In North America at least, the public overwhelmingly sides with the athletes in this controversy. According to <a href="https://2g2ckk18vixp3neolz4b6605-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Legers-North-American-Tracker-August-4th-2021_v2.pdf">Léger</a>, 82 percent of Canadians and 77 percent of Americans think female athletes should have the right to decide what uniform they want to wear at competitions.</li><li>A <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/entertainment/survey-results/daily/2021/08/02/7cb9b/1">YouGov poll</a> has found that 62 percent of American adults don’t know what “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rickrolling">rickrolling</a>” is, while 31 percent do — mostly those under age 35. For the full results, <a href="https://tinyurl.com/8zcc757u">click here</a>. </li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/biden-approval-rating-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/biden-approval-rating-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="24" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-24" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>24</sup></a> 50.4 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 43.3 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of +7.0 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/partisanship-isnt-the-only-reason-why-so-many-americans-remain-unvaccinated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 51.4 percent approved and 43.3 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of +8.1 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 51.9 percent and a disapproval rating of 42.3 percent, for a net approval rating of +9.5 points.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CLARIFICATION (Aug. 9, 2021, 10:40 a.m.): </strong>This story has been updated to make clear that beach handball is not an Olympic sport.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/voters-react-scandals-cuomos-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79271602</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/anti-establishment-sentiment-ballot-parties-week-79248883</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628247601659987</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Some Republicans Have Changed Their Messaging On The COVID-19 Vaccine. Is It Too Little, Too Late?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-republicans-have-changed-their-messaging-on-the-covid-19-vaccine-is-it-too-little-too-late/</link>
						<dc:creator>Mary Radcliffe</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Mary Radcliffe and Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>COVID-19 Vaccine</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">According to local media, when reporters asked House Minority Whip Steve Scalise in the beginning of April when he planned to get a COVID-19 vaccine, he replied, “Soon.” A month later, when asked again, his sense of urgency — or lack thereof — <a href="https://www.nola.com/news/coronavirus/article_f569bf58-e970-11eb-8456-7ba1aef698cd.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remained the same</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then in July, something changed. Sitting inside a clinic in his home state of Louisiana, the No. 2 Republican in the House posed for a photo as he got vaccinated at last. Four days later, <a href="https://www.wtvr.com/news/national/coronavirus/republicans-amp-up-calls-for-americans-to-get-covid-19-vaccine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at a press conference</a> outside the U.S. Capitol, he encouraged others to do so too. “I have high confidence in it,” Scalise said of the vaccine. “I got it myself.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Scalise isn’t the only Republican who has suddenly changed his tone. That same week, Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, whose 2022 reelection campaign merchandise <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/jul/14/florida-ron-desantis-digs-fauci-merchandise-covid" target="_blank" rel="noopener">features drink koozies</a> that say “Don’t Fauci My Florida,” noted that nearly everyone hospitalized now for COVID-19 was unvaccinated. “These vaccines are saving lives,” he said at a <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/wireStory/florida-covid-19-hospitalizations-jump-significantly-79024355" target="_blank" rel="noopener">press conference</a>. Even hosts on Fox News, where COVID-19 was initially denied as a “<a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2020/09/fox-news-covid-denial-hasnt-aged-well" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hoax</a>,” are <a href="https://twitter.com/Acyn/status/1417300107960094720?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1417300107960094720%7Ctwgr%5E%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.businessinsider.com%2Fsean-hannity-fox-hosts-recant-disinformation-campaign-covid-19-vaccine-2021-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">encouraging viewers to get vaccinated</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But their statements of support — prompted by the spread of the highly transmissible delta variant — are unlikely to change the minds of those who are certain they don’t want the shot. Some <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/11/trumps-lies-about-coronavirus/608647/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prominent members of the party</a> and <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/legalentertainment/2020/04/10/covid-19-lawsuit-against-fox-news/?sh=610644855739" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conservative media networks</a> spent months downplaying the severity of the pandemic and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/20/us/politics/republicans-coronavirus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spreading misinformation</a> about the vaccines, and their sudden about-face is unlikely to be enough to change that dynamic. But for those who were hesitant — but not necessarily opposed — there may be some chance for Republicans to change minds.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Not all Republicans have rejected the vaccine, but <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-profile-of-the-unvaccinated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most vaccine refusers</a> <a href="https://echeloninsights.com/in-the-news/july-omnibus-covid/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are Republican</a>. That doesn’t mean their resistance is partisan alone — but it may mean it’s difficult for partisan leaders to persuade people to get the vaccine. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For one thing, <a href="https://morningconsult.com/covid19-vaccine-dashboard/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccine resistance is well-entrenched</a> at this point, and <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/04/22/covid-vaccine-holdouts-access-data/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">concerns about</a> how fast the vaccine moved through clinical trials — not to mention social media <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/20/us/politics/republicans-coronavirus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">disinformation about the efficacy of the inoculation</a> — are still prevalent. On top of that, some well-known members of the GOP, like Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and Sen. Ron Johnson of Wisconsin, are still embracing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/23/coronavirus-vaccine-republicans-500668" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccine skepticism</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republican leaders’ pleas to get the vaccine also aren’t new. Just ask former President Donald Trump. Having gotten the vaccine himself <a href="https://www.axios.com/trump-vaccinated-coronavirus-bd88b0fa-6a19-483d-8fd4-d949f23f25f9.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in January</a> — but <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-03-01/trump-wife-quietly-got-white-house-shots-as-others-went-public" target="_blank" rel="noopener">out of the public eye</a> — he <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/03/16/978008056/trump-encourages-his-supporters-to-get-covid-19-vaccine-within-limits-of-freedom" target="_blank" rel="noopener">encouraged his supporters</a> to follow suit. “I would recommend it to a lot of people that don’t want to get it,” he said in a phone interview on <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/trump-urges-all-americans-to-get-covid-vaccine-its-a-safe-vaccine" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fox News</a> in March. “It’s a great vaccine, it’s a safe vaccine, and it’s something that works.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But his endorsement carried little weight with Republicans who rejected the vaccine. According to a survey experiment conducted by <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/covid-vaccine-hesitancy-presidential-encouragement/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CBS News/YouGov</a> in March, Republicans — which include Republican-leaning independents — who were flat-out noes on getting a vaccine were not moved by Trump’s words or deeds. However, among Republicans who were undecided, hearing that Trump himself was vaccinated and encouraging others to do the same did move the needle. Unvaccinated Republicans were interviewed twice, and in the second survey, half were told that Trump had endorsed the vaccine. Per the findings, those who said yes or maybe on the first survey were 15 percentage points more likely to say they would get the jab after hearing about Trump’s endorsement, compared with the group who didn’t hear the cue. However, those who said no on the first survey largely weren’t influenced by Trump’s statements.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1432" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/samuels-radcliffe1.GOP-VAX-RHETORIC.0805.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/samuels-radcliffe1.GOP-VAX-RHETORIC.0805.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/samuels-radcliffe1.GOP-VAX-RHETORIC.0805.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/samuels-radcliffe1.GOP-VAX-RHETORIC.0805.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">A similar dynamic was at play among Democrats and Democratic-leaning independents, just with President Biden. That group was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/covid-19-vaccines-optimism-pandemic-opinion-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">less likely</a> overall to say no or maybe when asked whether they would get the vaccine, but CBS News/YouGov found that Biden’s endorsement made them less certain; it both softened some noes to maybes and moved some yeses to maybes.<strong> </strong>However, in follow-up questioning, most of those “maybe” respondents said they would “probably” get the vaccine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Likewise, an <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/8w7calyx30/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economist/YouGov survey</a> from late July/early August showed that Republicans who said they didn’t plan to get the vaccine wouldn’t be swayed even if they were told that Trump had gotten it and encouraged others to do the same. Just 3 percent of respondents who told the pollster they didn’t plan to get vaccinated said they would be persuaded to get the shot if Trump urged them to do so, including only 5 percent of Republicans. In a <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2021/06/29/could-trump-boost-vaccination-rate" target="_blank" rel="noopener">separate survey from June</a>, The Economist/YouGov found that among adults who said they would not get the vaccine, a larger share said they trusted medical advice from Trump (53 percent) than from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (14 percent), Dr. Anthony Fauci (9 percent) and Biden (7 percent). Still, only 3 percent said that Trump’s endorsement would sway them to get the vaccine themselves.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/partisanship-isnt-the-only-reason-why-so-many-americans-remain-unvaccinated/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A sign for a COVD-19 vaccine check-in waiting area, set against a blue grid background." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/0730_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/0730_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/0730_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/0730_POLLA-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Partisanship Isn’t The Only Reason Why So Many Americans Remain Unvaccinated <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/partisanship-isnt-the-only-reason-why-so-many-americans-remain-unvaccinated/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s also working against Republicans’ new pro-vaccine push is that hesitancy and refusal rates have been stagnant so far, especially in red states. According to <a href="https://morningconsult.com/covid19-vaccine-dashboard/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult’s tracking</a>, the share of Americans who said they were either unsure or unwilling to get vaccinated has decreased by only 3 points in two months, from 34 percent in May to 31 percent in July. That trend is particularly entrenched in states that heavily supported Trump. On average, in the 20 states that backed him by more than 10 points in the 2020 election, 25.2 percent of respondents said in the July survey that they were unwilling to get vaccinated (essentially unchanged from 25.9 percent in May). By contrast, in the 16 states that voted for Biden by more than 10 points, an average of only 15.0 percent of respondents in the July survey said they were unwilling to get vaccinated, similar to the 15.4 percent who said the same in May. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, the future is unknowable, and some newly released research suggests the opposite of what these polls were finding: that <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/32/e2106559118" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccine endorsements from elite Republicans</a> may in fact have a positive impact on everyday voters. But that research is based on a study from March, a time when <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/dashboard/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-dashboard/?gclid=CjwKCAjwr56IBhAvEiwA1fuqGjTjKjKbxgjc8ItKnZKZyfOPB7GnzRF91gOP7Mam52xkxpaGflQIuxoCzaMQAvD_BwE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a greater share of unvaccinated Americans were on the fence</a> about the vaccine. Yet new Morning Consult polling shows that vaccine skepticism <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/08/04/fox-news-viewers-covid-vaccine-hesitancy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has decreased slightly</a> among Fox News viewers after more hosts began promoting vaccinations, suggesting that the network’s new attitude may be having some impact on its audience — though Fox News Republicans were already less hesitant about vaccines than Republicans who get their news from more far-right sources. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, it’s possible that hesitancy might decrease as the delta variant continues its spread, and <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccination-trends" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccine rates had been ticking up slightly</a> in the last half of July. However, <a href="https://echeloninsights.com/in-the-news/july-omnibus-covid/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a July survey from Echelon Insights</a> suggests the increase may be due more to Democrats getting vaccinated than to any changes among Republicans: The share of Republicans saying they probably wouldn’t get the vaccine increased by 3 points from their June survey, while the share of Democrats who said the same decreased by 3 points. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that GOP leaders touting vaccines will have the opposite effect and cause some Republicans to double-down on their anti-vaccine sentiments. That’s because when people resist persuasion, they can become <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2002-08203-005" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more firm in their beliefs</a>. Plus, public figures <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/05/13/celebrity-vaccine-covid-influencers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t typically influence people’s actions</a>. As the Kaiser Family Foundation previously noted, pro-vaccine messages from doctors, family members and friends <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/19/briefing/vaccine-skepticism-vaccination-drive.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have the greatest impact</a> on vaccine skeptics. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, if nothing else, it’s objectively a good sign that some elected Republicans are beginning to take the pandemic seriously. It shows their concern about the country’s stalled progress, and represents a broader acknowledgment that a complete return to normalcy requires their base to step up. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/voters-react-scandals-cuomos-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79271602</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/anti-establishment-sentiment-ballot-parties-week-79248883</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628162101858821</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: How Democrats Are Reacting To Cuomo’s Harassment Scandal</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-democrats-are-reacting-to-cuomos-harassment-scandal/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Andrew Cuomo</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>New York Politics</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Sexual Harassment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-how-democrats-are-reacting-to-cuomos-harassment-scandal/">
	<div data-podcast-id="313897" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: How Democrats Are Reacting To Cuomo's Harassment Scandal">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9631032865.mp3?updated=1628100015"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">On Tuesday, New York Attorney General Letitia James released the results of an investigation into Gov. Andrew Cuomo’s history of alleged sexual harassment. The report found evidence that Cuomo sexually harassed at least 11 women and created a hostile workplace. He apologized but flatly denied the allegations. Cuomo is now facing overwhelming pressure to resign from numerous elected officials, including President Biden. According to a <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/marist-poll-results-analysis-governor-andrew-cuomo/#sthash.n8XGuWuU.dpbs">snap poll</a> following the report, 59 percent of New Yorkers said Cuomo should resign. In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew talks about what the report means for Cuomo and the political future of New York.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 19:01:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628103601678716</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Will Andrew Cuomo Resign?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-andrew-cuomo-resign/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Andrew Cuomo</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>New York Politics</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<category>Sexual Harassment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>UPDATE (Aug. 4, 2021, 9:53 a.m.): </strong>This story has been updated to <a href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/marist-poll-results-analysis-governor-andrew-cuomo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">include the first poll we have</a> after Attorney General Letitia James’s report into the sexual harassment allegations facing Gov. Andrew Cuomo was released.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Back in March, New York Gov. Andrew Cuomo’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/4-ways-andrew-cuomos-political-future-could-play-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political future hung in limbo</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://lindseyboylan4ny.medium.com/my-story-of-working-with-governor-cuomo-e664d4814b4e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Several</a> <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/article/andrew-cuomo-sexual-harassment-albany-reporter.html?utm_campaign=nym&amp;utm_source=tw&amp;utm_medium=s1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">women</a> had <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/27/nyregion/cuomo-charlotte-bennett-sexual-harassment.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">come</a> <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/third-former-andrew-cuomo-aide-describes-inappropriate-workplace-treatment-11615081956" target="_blank" rel="noopener">forward</a> with <a href="https://www.timesunion.com/news/article/Female-aide-said-Cuomo-aggressively-groped-her-at-16015863.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">detailed</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/cuomo-toxic-workplace/2021/03/06/7f7c5b9c-7dd3-11eb-b3d1-9e5aa3d5220c_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">allegations</a> of sexual harassment <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/01/nyregion/cuomo-harassment-anna-ruch.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">against</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/19/nyregion/alyssa-mcgrath-cuomo-harassment.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cuomo</a>, and in light of these allegations, there was a growing consensus among Democratic lawmakers that Cuomo should resign. (Both of New York’s U.S. senators, at least 20 of its 27 U.S. representatives, at least 45 of its 63 state senators and at least 55 of its 150 assembly members had all <a href="https://www.cityandstateny.com/politics/2021/03/notable-lawmakers-calling-for-cuomo-to-resign/175124/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">called on Cuomo to resign from office</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But <a href="https://twitter.com/Kimjeanpierre/status/1368982802897702912?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some Democrats</a> — most prominently <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/cuomo-resign-allegations-confirmed-biden-exclusive-abc-news/story?id=76499093" target="_blank" rel="noopener">President Biden</a> — said they would withhold judgment until state Attorney General Letitia James conducted an independent investigation into the allegations. And after months passed with no news about the scandal, even some politicians who had condemned Cuomo <a href="https://www.ny1.com/nyc/all-boroughs/news/2021/04/21/senate-majority-leader-appears-alongside-cuomo-after-calling-for-his-resignation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seemed to have moved on</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That changed on Tuesday when James released a <a href="https://ag.ny.gov/sites/default/files/2021.08.03_nyag_-_investigative_report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">report</a> concluding that Cuomo violated state and federal law by <a href="https://www.timesunion.com/state/article/Attorney-general-concludes-Cuomo-sexually-16359949.php?IPID=Times-Union-HP-CP-Spotlight" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sexually harassing 11 women</a>, in addition to retaliating against the first woman who publicly accused him and creating a hostile work environment for women. In a <a href="https://www.c-span.org/video/?513912-1/ny-governor-cuomo-denies-sexual-harassment-allegations-independent-report" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video statement</a> later in the day, Cuomo denied making inappropriate sexual advances, but this did not stop <a href="https://twitter.com/JerryZremski/status/1422615177808261132?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">several lawmakers</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/luisferre/status/1422598783754440705?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">renewing</a> their <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewSolender/status/1422595029655240720?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">calls</a> for him to step down. Indeed, he is now under more pressure to resign than ever, as some <a href="https://westfaironline.com/139039/breaking-news-latimer-cuomo-must-resign-in-wake-of-ags-sexual-harassment-report/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new names</a>, including <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/08/03/biden-calls-on-cuomo-to-resign-after-bombshell-sexual-harassment-report.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden</a> and <a href="https://www.speaker.gov/newsroom/8321-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Speaker Nancy Pelosi</a>, have <a href="https://twitter.com/sahilkapur/status/1422606310324023297" target="_blank" rel="noopener">joined the chorus</a> as well. <em>[Editor’s note: After publication, Biden said Cuomo should resign, as did Pelosi.]</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The political consensus around calls for Cuomo’s resignation reflects just how much <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/247901/americans-views-sexual-harassment-workplace-victimization-trends.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Americans’ attitudes about the seriousness of sexual harassment</a> have changed — especially among Democrats. In 1998, Gallup found that 50 percent of Americans thought that sexual harassment was a major problem; by 2019, that number had risen to 62 percent. And among Democrats that number had risen even higher: 80 percent said sexual harassment was a major problem. Those kinds of numbers make it very difficult for any Democratic politician to stand by Cuomo and explain why even some of his <a href="https://twitter.com/chriscquinn/status/1422594300471296000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">closest allies</a> have now broken with him.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So will Cuomo heed his colleagues’ calls for him to resign? A lot could depend on whether public opinion turns against him as a result of this report. The <a href="https://scri.siena.edu/2021/07/01/only-one-third-of-voters-say-cuomo-should-run-for-re-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last poll</a> before James’s report, conducted June 22-29 by Siena College, found that, while New York registered voters were divided in their opinion of Cuomo (45 percent had a favorable view of him, while 47 percent had an unfavorable view), only 23 percent wanted him to resign immediately. And that wasn’t just because New Yorkers had moved on from or forgotten about the allegations; even in <a href="https://scri.siena.edu/2021/03/15/voters-say-cuomo-should-not-resign-50-35/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early March</a>, in the immediate aftermath of the allegations, New York registered voters told Siena 50 percent to 35 percent that they did not think he should resign. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Wednesday morning, however, <a href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/marist-poll-results-analysis-governor-andrew-cuomo/#sthash.3QPgSB3r.dpbs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marist College</a> released the first poll conducted since James’s report, and it found that 59 percent of New Yorkers wanted Cuomo to resign — and if he doesn’t resign, the same share thinks the state legislature should impeach him. This is just one poll, but it could suggest that many New Yorkers have found the report’s findings disturbing enough to change their mind. Then again, in the June Siena survey, a plurality (42 percent) of voters thought James’s investigation would uncover evidence that Cuomo committed sexual harassment — and yet only 23 percent wanted him to resign.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, Cuomo seems as if he will <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/4-ways-andrew-cuomos-political-future-could-play-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">try to hold onto power</a> as long as he feels he still has a public mandate. He may reason that resignation would forever tarnish his political legacy, whereas if he serves out his term, the scandal may fade into the background — as it did from March through July, and as Virginia Gov. Ralph Northam’s <a href="https://richmond.com/news/local/government-politics/resisting-calls-to-resign-northam-denies-hes-in-racist-yearbook-photo-admits-he-appeared-in/article_f75d342d-e028-586e-8631-70d52424d604.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blackface scandal</a> did (in fact, Northam’s popularity has <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/virginia-politics/northam-job-approval-poll/2020/10/22/1e6e7bc8-13c5-11eb-ad6f-36c93e6e94fb_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fully recovered</a>). Cuomo may even still be entertaining thoughts of running for reelection. He has a whopping <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/news/politics/new-york-elections-government/ny-cuomo-campaign-disclosure-scandals-fundraising-20210715-mkfwqjhzmrhqdeiwo7jisajkvm-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$18.5 million</a> in his campaign war chest, and New Yorkers still approve of many aspects of his governorship, including his handling of the COVID-19 pandemic (despite his administration’s alleged <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/cuomo-advisers-altered-report-on-covid-19-nursing-home-deaths-11614910855" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cover-up</a> of thousands of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/28/nyregion/nursing-home-deaths-cuomo.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID-19-related deaths</a> at New York nursing homes).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Cuomo’s fate also may not be fully in his own hands. Back in March, Democratic legislators raised the possibility of <a href="https://www.syracuse.com/state/2021/03/how-would-a-cuomo-impeachment-work-a-look-at-new-yorks-process.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">impeaching Cuomo</a> for his misdeeds, and several <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/andrew-cuomo-impeachment-sexual-harassment" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reiterated their support for impeachment</a> on Tuesday. According to state Assembly Speaker Carl Heastie, James’s report has been <a href="https://twitter.com/ShannanFerry/status/1422590234735353856?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">referred</a> to the Assembly committee in charge of impeachment, which Newsday <a href="https://twitter.com/YanceyRoy/status/1422596548857405442" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reports</a> will meet on Monday. Clearly, this is a fast-moving story, and Cuomo’s future is still very much up in the air.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 20:37:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1628022602481177</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Everything You Need To Know About Ohio’s Two Special Primary Elections</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/everything-you-need-to-know-about-ohios-two-special-primary-elections/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2021 Elections</category>
			<category>Nina Turner</category>
			<category>Ohio</category>
			<category>Special Elections</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Whether you’re a Democrat or a Republican, there’s a major battle over the future of your party taking place today in Ohio. Voters in two Buckeye State congressional districts will go to the polls on Tuesday for a pair of special primary elections that will effectively decide their next congresspeople. In the deep-blue 11th District, Democrats will once again choose between a progressive icon or an establishment stalwart. And in the red 15th District, the power of former President Donald Trump’s endorsement in Republican primaries will be put to the test for the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-special-election-in-texass-6th-district-will-test-trumps-influence-on-the-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">second consecutive week</a>. Here’s what to expect in each contest.</p>



<h2><strong>Ohio’s 11th District</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Former Ohio state Sen. Nina Turner has been a major figure in the progressive wing of the Democratic Party ever since she defected from former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton’s orbit to <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2015/11/nina-turner-endorses-bernie-sanders-215809" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorse Sen. Bernie Sanders</a> in the 2016 Democratic presidential primary. She then became president of Our Revolution, a group devoted to electing progressive candidates, in 2017 and co-chair of Sanders’s presidential campaign in 2020. Turner, however, didn’t seek higher office herself until then-Rep. Marcia Fudge left Congress earlier this year to become President Biden’s secretary of housing and urban development.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Not long after Turner got into the race for Fudge’s <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/members/OH/11" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cleveland-based seat</a> last December, she <a href="https://ninaturner.com/endorsements/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">earned the backing</a> of virtually the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/progressive-groups-are-getting-more-selective-in-targeting-incumbents-is-it-working/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">entire progressive apparatus</a>: Our Revolution, Justice Democrats, the Working Families Party, Sanders and every member of “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Squad_(United_States_Congress)" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Squad</a>.” Her national profile — and access to <a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2021/04/nina-turner-shontel-brown-tout-a-significant-fundraising-edge-in-11th-congressional-district-democratic-primary.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national money</a> — helped her jump out to a wide lead in the early days of the Democratic primary, too.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the race is hardly entirely a done deal for Turner, who faces tough competition in Cuyahoga County Council Member Shontel Brown. Either Turner or Brown would be the third consecutive Black woman to represent the 11th District, but they represent very different wings of the party. As chair of the county Democratic Party, Brown has developed strong relationships with local power brokers — including Fudge. Though Fudge hasn’t issued a formal endorsement, a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gatqZzHC9ao" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brown campaign ad</a> features none other than Fudge’s mother saying “Shontel Brown is Marcia’s protegee” and “we’re voting for Shontel Brown.” But perhaps more importantly, Brown has also become the candidate of choice for Turner’s nemeses in the national party establishment. In June, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/16/hilary-clinton-ohio-special-election-494953" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Clinton endorsed Brown</a>, followed by <a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2021/06/south-carolina-rep-james-clyburn-endorses-shontel-brown-for-congress.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Majority Whip Jim Clyburn</a> and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/07/congressional-black-caucus-ohio-special-election-498596" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congressional Black Caucus PAC</a>. And the Democratic Majority for Israel PAC, a group that supports pro-Israel Democrats, has spent almost $2 million to help Brown with messaging that <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/4945195" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attacks Turner</a> for criticizing Biden. (The DMFI PAC <a href="https://www.timesofisrael.com/divides-on-israel-among-democrats-highlighted-in-ohio-special-congressional-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed Brown in February</a> partly in response to Turner’s <a href="https://twitter.com/ninaturner/status/1392328115909664774?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Palestinian sympathies</a>.) Brown herself has leaned into the establishment branding, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qezc954Gk18" target="_blank" rel="noopener">airing ads</a> emphasizing how closely she will <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rhUoBo-F7pQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">work with Biden</a> and trying to make the race a referendum on <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/4952328?link_id=35&amp;can_id=5f27a3767bd4756f5c4ec89f31b71bbe&amp;source=email-morning-digest-why-one-candidates-fealty-to-trump-has-pennsylvania-republicans-looking-elsewhere&amp;email_referrer=email_1242982&amp;email_subject=morning-digest-why-one-candidates-fealty-to-trump-has-pennsylvania-republicans-looking-elsewhere" target="_blank" rel="noopener">party loyalty</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To hear Brown and her allies tell it, this has helped Brown <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000017a-9b36-dffc-a5fa-db7665bc0001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">close the gap</a> with Turner in the final month of the race. For instance, a <a href="https://jewishinsider.nyc3.digitaloceanspaces.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/22210942/FILE_8871.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">July 13-17 poll</a> from the Mellman Group on behalf of the DMFI PAC put Turner at 41 percent and Brown at 36 percent. However, that still suggests that Turner is the front-runner, especially when you consider that internal polls tend to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-don-blankenship-really-surging-in-west-virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overestimate the side that sponsors them</a>. (There has been no independent polling of the race, unless you count a <a href="https://freebeacon.com/elections/beacon-poll-shows-brown-and-turner-tied-in-ohio-11/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">July 8-10 poll</a> by TargetPoint Consulting for the conservative Washington Free Beacon — but the wording of some of that poll’s questions suggests they are rooting against Turner.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Fundraising numbers tell a similar story: Brown has undeniably picked up the pace in recent months, <a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2021/07/nina-turner-leads-shontel-brown-in-fundraising-as-out-of-state-money-bolsters-both-congressional-campaigns.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raising $1.3 million</a> from April 1 through July 14, bringing her total haul through July 14 to <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH11169/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$2.1 million</a>. But Turner has been a consistent financial powerhouse and raised more than twice as much for the cycle: <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH11151/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$4.5 million</a>. Eleven other candidates are also in the race, but both polling and fundraising suggest they are no threat to win; no other active candidate has polled higher than 4 percent or raised more than $65,000.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s easy to boil this race down to another progressive vs. establishment fight — and it is that — but if Turner wins, it will be important not to draw the wrong conclusions. The majority-Black 11th District is no progressive stronghold (it voted <a href="http://www.thegreenpapers.com/P16/OH-D" target="_blank" rel="noopener">68 percent to 32 percent</a> for Clinton in the 2016 primary), and as such, Turner has <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/nina-turner-democratic-primary-cleveland_n_60e60c37e4b0fe5f06a7d9b7?lrc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">run a correspondingly meat-and-potatoes campaign</a> despite her national profile as an outspoken progressive. For instance, instead of touting her post-2016 career, she has emphasized her tenure in the state legislature, where she had a reputation as a productive team player. (Case in point: The first section on her endorsements page is “Ohio Elected Officials.”) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A Turner victory would certainly represent a win for the national progressive movement, both in terms of the efficiency of its campaign apparatus and the addition of another prominent voice in Congress. But it wouldn’t necessarily be a sign that nonwhite voters, a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-do-black-democrats-usually-prefer-establishment-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">traditionally moderate group</a>, are warming to progressive ideas, although it might point toward a winning strategy for progressives in areas where nonwhite voters are the majority.</p>



<h2><strong>Ohio’s 15th District</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ohio’s other vacant congressional district is the conservative 15th, which takes in a <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/congress/members/OH/15" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wide swath of south-central Ohio</a> from the Columbus suburbs to Appalachia. The race that matters here is on the Republican side, but the contest is just as unpredictable as in the 11th. Eleven candidates are running here, but there is no clear front-runner; instead, a case can be made that around a half-dozen are in the hunt.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Former Rep. Steve Stivers resigned from this seat in May to lead the Ohio Chamber of Commerce, and he quickly <a href="https://www.lancastereaglegazette.com/story/news/2021/06/02/steve-stivers-endorses-jeff-lare-replace-him-congress-15th-district/7511217002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed state Rep. Jeff LaRe</a> to be his successor. But LaRe has struggled with fundraising (he took in only <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH15145/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$239,299</a> from April 27 through July 14); luckily for him, though, Stivers put his money where his mouth is: In an unusual move, the former congressman spent <a href="https://twitter.com/MediumBuying/status/1420370862541246465?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$300,000</a> of his leftover campaign funds on ads urging people to vote for LaRe. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But then came what is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/almost-everyone-trump-endorses-wins-their-primary-but-is-he-padding-his-record/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">usually the coup de grâce</a> in a GOP primary: On June 8, Trump <a href="https://www.dispatch.com/story/news/2021/06/08/trump-endorses-mike-carey-ohio-15th-congressional-district-race/7611520002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed</a> coal lobbyist Mike Carey. And Make America Great Again Action, a super PAC run by former Trump campaign manager Corey Lewandowski, <a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2021/07/trump-aligned-pac-makes-last-minute-buy-in-special-election-for-ohios-15th-congressional-district.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">backed up the endorsement</a> with over $400,000 in spending on Carey’s behalf. Carey has also raised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH15228/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$460,404</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Notably, Trump’s endorsement has not <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/14/trump-allies-special-election-499655" target="_blank" rel="noopener">coalesced other conservative influencers</a> around his pick, though. For example, Conservative Outsider PAC, which is <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/outsidespending/contrib.php?cmte=C00748475&amp;cycle=2020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">funded</a> partly by the anti-tax group the Club for Growth, has spent $232,000 against Carey. And Sen. Rand Paul has endorsed a third candidate, former state Rep. Ron Hood. Hood hasn’t raised much cash himself (just <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H0OH18101/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$153,801</a>), but he’s benefited from $678,357 in spending from Paul’s allies at Protect Freedom PAC. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Also in the race are state Sen. Bob Peterson, golf-course owner Tom Hwang and minister Ruth Edmonds. Peterson has a healthy number of <a href="https://www.bobpetersonforcongress.com/endorsements" target="_blank" rel="noopener">local endorsers</a> and has raised more money from individual contributions than any other candidate ($441,500; his total fundraising stands at <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH15129/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$555,700</a>). Hwang, though, has raised the most money overall (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH15202/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$578,560</a>), thanks almost entirely to self-funding. For her part, Edmonds has raised little money (<a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2OH15160/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$162,327</a>) but does boast the endorsement of Debbie Meadows, the wife of Trump’s former White House Chief of Staff Mark Meadows.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There have been no independent polls of the race; a <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewJTobias/status/1408544144461533189" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fabrizio, Lee &amp; Associates poll</a> released by the Carey campaign in late June did find Carey in the lead with 20 percent and no one else in double digits, but this survey tells us very little about who will win. First, of course, internal polls are to be taken with grains of salt; second, the poll is at least five weeks old and was conducted before most of the race’s campaigning and advertising took place. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But after Susan Wright, the Trump-endorsed candidate, <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/news/politics/2021/07/27/jake-ellzey-leading-trump-backed-susan-wright-in-race-to-replace-the-late-ron-wright-in-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lost</a> what was effectively a Republican primary in Texas’s 6th Congressional District last week, the political stakes are high for Trump in this race. If Carey loses, it will raise questions about whether Trump’s influence over the GOP has diminished since leaving office. It won’t answer those questions, though. Two Trump losses in a row would indeed <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/almost-everyone-trump-endorses-wins-their-primary-but-is-he-padding-his-record/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">be unusual</a>, but it would not yet be proof that his endorsement has lost its <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-looked-at-hundreds-of-endorsements-heres-who-republicans-are-listening-to/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">predictive power</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And even if Trump’s influence is on the decline, it might not be for the reason you might assume. A Carey loss <em>could</em> signal that Republican voters are ready to move on from Trump — or it could mean simply that other Republican leaders have agency, too. Whether because Trump now lacks the awesome power of the presidency or simply the ability to angrily tweet, some Republican politicians and organizations clearly feel comfortable expressing a different preference from him in both Ohio and Texas. And since we know that <a href="https://scholar.princeton.edu/sites/default/files/mgilens/files/elite_cues_and_political_decision_making.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">elite cues can shape public opinion</a>, this may give voters permission to break from Trump; more cynically, it might just be the case that when Republican financiers are willing to spend money against a Trump-endorsed candidate, he or she is likelier to lose. On the flip side, if Carey wins in the face of so much coordinated opposition, it would be a strong signal that Trump (who often endorses candidates who are shoo-ins in an apparent attempt to pad his record) is still top dog in the GOP. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So our advice for following the primaries in both the Ohio 11th and Ohio 15th is not to read too much into the results. The 2022 election cycle is just barely underway, and there are dozens of Democratic and Republican primaries (both special and regular) that will give us a lot more data soon enough. It won’t be long until we know a lot more about the direction each party is headed.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1627986603733683</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Why The California Recall Has Grown More Competitive</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-the-california-recall-has-grown-more-competitive/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>American Community Survey</category>
			<category>California</category>
			<category>California Governor Recall</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Ohio</category>
			<category>Ohio Primary</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Republicans</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-the-california-recall-has-grown-more-competitive/">
	<div data-podcast-id="313809" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Why The California Recall Has Grown More Competitive">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP8994738729.mp3?updated=1627942867"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">Two special primary elections are taking place in Ohio on Tuesday, each with implications for Democrats and Republicans as they consider how tightly to embrace their respective parties’ establishment politicians. On this week’s episode, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a> crew talks about what these races may mean for the 2022 midterm races. They also discuss the California recall election — which, according to a <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://escholarship.org/uc/item/27x9k5qt">recent poll</a>, shows greater support for recalling Gov. Gavin Newsom — and the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/press-releases/2021/changes-2020-acs-1-year.html">U.S. Census Bureau’s decision</a> not to release its standard one-year estimates from the 2020 American Community Survey.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 23:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1627946102011485</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Response To The Jan. 6 Select Committee Paints A Worrying Picture Of Our Democracy</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-response-to-the-jan-6-select-committee-paints-a-worrying-picture-of-our-democracy/</link>
						<dc:creator>Sarah Frostenson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Insurrection</category>
			<category>Jan. 6 Investigation</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<category>Kevin McCarthy</category>
			<category>Nancy Pelosi</category>
			<category>Slack Chat</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/sarah-frostenson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah Frostenson</a>, politics editor): Initially, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/03/03/republicans-condemned-trump-after-capitol-attack-now-they-are-opening-door-him-future-party/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">both Republican and Democratic lawmakers</a> condemned the mob of Trump supporters that attacked the Capitol on Jan. 6. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But those days are long gone.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A House-led investigation into <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/jan-select-committee-meet-steps-move-subpoenas/story?id=79118740" target="_blank" rel="noopener">what happened that day is currently underway</a> in the form of a select committee, but it is for all intents and purposes a Democratic-led effort. (In May, Senate Republicans <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/05/28/1000524897/senate-republicans-block-plan-for-independent-commission-on-jan-6-capitol-riot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blocked the creation of a bipartisan, independent commission</a> to investigate what happened, and although the select committee does have two Republicans on it, House Republicans have otherwise refused to cooperate following House Speaker Nancy Pelosi’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/21/pelosi-vetoes-banks-jordan-for-jan-6-select-committee-500424" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rejection of two</a> of House Minority Leader <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/21/pelosi-vetoes-banks-jordan-for-jan-6-select-committee-500424" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kevin McCarthy’s picks for the committee</a>, Reps. Jim Jordan of Ohio and Jim Banks of Indiana.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Understanding what happened on Jan. 6 and making sure that it doesn’t happen again — the guiding principle behind the 9/11 Commission, which <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/05/26/999930573/why-a-9-11-commission-is-popular-but-may-not-happen-for-the-jan-6-capitol-attack" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this investigation was originally modeled on</a> — is unlikely. Let’s unpack what this says about <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-much-danger-is-american-democracy-in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the health of our democracy</a> and the power of political investigations in our deeply politicized era.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First, let’s talk about democracy. The Republican Party has increasingly moved in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/in-americas-uncivil-war-republicans-are-the-aggressors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an anti-democratic, illiberal direction</a>. Take this 2020 report from <a href="https://www.voterstudygroup.org/publication/democracy-maybe" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Democracy Fund’s Voter Study Group</a>. It found that a third of Americans had supported authoritarian ideas at some point in the previous three years, but as the chart below shows, Republicans were more likely than Democrats and independents to support unilateral action on every scenario asked about.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1200" height="1190" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/chat.JAN-6COMMITTEE-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/chat.JAN-6COMMITTEE-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/chat.JAN-6COMMITTEE-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/chat.JAN-6COMMITTEE-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">How does this growing disconnect between Democrats and Republicans factor into investigating an attack on democracy?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kaleigh Rogers</a>, tech and politics reporter):<strong> </strong>The issue here is that you cannot divorce the insurrection from politics. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Individuals who have been charged for participating in the attack have repeatedly stated that they did so <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/in-depth/news/2021/02/10/trump-blamed-capitol-riot-some-who-were-arrested/4361411001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">because former President Donald Trump encouraged them</a>. Trump’s role in this is hard to deny, so naturally any attempt to peel back the layers may result in the former leader of the Republican Party looking not so great. As such, many Republican lawmakers aren’t interested in taking on this investigation.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nathaniel Rakich</a>, elections analyst):<strong> </strong>+1 to that, Kaleigh.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/covid-19-cases-rising-americans-thoughts-steps-fivethirtyeight-79188933</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Republican voters also don’t really <em>want</em> to investigate what happened. According to <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/images/polling/us/us05272021_ussb63.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent Quinnipiac poll</a>, 74 percent of Republicans believed “too much is being made of the storming of the U.S. Capitol on January 6th and it is time to move on”; only 18 percent thought it “was an attack on democracy that should never be forgotten.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alex Samuels</a>, politics reporter):<strong> </strong>And no matter what Pelosi does, most Republicans are going to view any probe into Jan. 6 as inherently partisan — despite <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/27/kinzinger-cheney-republican-leaders-jan-6-hearing-500847" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican Reps. Adam Kinzinger of Illinois and Liz Cheney of Wyoming</a> also being part of the committee. (They’re <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/26/us/politics/insurrection-committee-republicans.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unlikely to sway pro-Trump Republicans</a> to believe the committee’s findings, given that they’ve been so outspoken in their criticism of Trump.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s important to remember, though, that Democrats are in a difficult position here. Their initial attempt to create a bipartisan, independent commission to investigate what happened was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/january-6-commission-bill-capitol-riot-senate-republicans-block/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shot down by Senate Republicans</a> — many of whom claimed that even that investigation would be too politically motivated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>Republicans seem to have been strategic in their opposition to a 9/11 Commission-type investigation. Now, they can <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/january-6-republicans-trump/2021/07/27/79a29e38-eef4-11eb-bf80-e3877d9c5f06_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chalk the whole thing up to a partisan witch hunt</a> and discredit it. Had they agreed to an independent commission, that would’ve been a lot harder to do.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>The space that investigations have come to occupy in Congress is interesting. NPR published a piece in May that argued that even an independent commission <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/05/26/999930573/why-a-9-11-commission-is-popular-but-may-not-happen-for-the-jan-6-capitol-attack" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was always going to be a hard sell for Republicans</a> given that even the independent 9/11 Commission carried a lot of political risk for Republicans. That commission, held just months before the 2004 presidential election, charged that the Bush administration had been underprepared for the terrorist attacks.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It goes back to the point Kaleigh<strong> </strong>made earlier — you can’t separate the politics from this, and Republican lawmakers and voters just don’t seem interested in engaging with what happened on Jan. 6. They’re either convinced it wasn’t a big deal and/or are <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/05/19/politics/republican-reaction-january-6-probe/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more interested in the 2022 midterm elections</a>.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An illustration of a wrecking ball smashing a wall made up to look like the American flag." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Why The Two-Party System Is Effing Up U.S. Democracy <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Is <em>not</em> participating in the investigation a risky move for Republicans, though?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex: </strong>I don’t think non-participation will impact Republicans politically. And that’s largely because most Republican voters want to move on. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A Morning Consult poll from June found that <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/06/28/capitol-riots-six-months-later-polling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a majority of Republicans</a> (68 percent) believed the attack on Jan. 6 has received too much attention. This compares to just 23 percent of Democrats who felt the same way. Republicans were also far less likely than all voters (17 percent versus 47 percent) to think the rioters were representative of the GOP. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the flip side, I have seen the argument that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2021/06/29/republicans-would-only-hurt-themselves-by-not-participating-pelosis-jan-6-select-committee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans benefit by participating in the commission</a> — even if they’re 100 percent loyal to Trump — because it gives the GOP a means to act as Trump’s defense counsel. It also would allow members to ask witnesses their own questions and make their own requests for lines of questioning. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>I wonder if that’s a risk Republicans were worried about, Sarah, given how they’ve responded to the investigation. I expected them to largely ignore it, but they’ve aggressively criticized it, and so have <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/hannity-january-6-commission-donald-trump-gop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">right-wing news pundits</a>. Fox News personalities Tucker Carlson, Laura<strong> </strong>Ingraham and Sean Hannity have all gone hard <a href="https://twitter.com/Acyn/status/1420209713644331009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">against the testimony of Capitol Police officers</a> and have made a concerted effort to <a href="https://twitter.com/justinbaragona/status/1420180649395302404?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">frame these hearings in a particular way</a>, rather than just brushing them off.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>There’s also the way they’ve tried to shift the blame for what happened on Jan. 6 to Democrats. I’m thinking of a popular line of attack among Republicans: the false claim that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/27/us/insurrection-pelosi-claims-fact-check.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pelosi didn’t do enough to secure the Capitol</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>There’s also been <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/false-equivalency-black-lives-matter-capitol-siege-experts/story?id=75251279" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a lot of false equivalence and whataboutism</a>, saying this kind of investigation should have happened for some of the vandalism that occurred after and surrounding Black Lives Matter demonstrations last summer.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s truly bizarre to see people within the right-wing communities I follow online who typically express support for police now mocking these officers.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>Let’s talk about the power of political investigations, given the current polarization of American politics. Historically, political science research has found that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/could-a-slew-of-new-congressional-investigations-erode-trumps-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">investigations can significantly weaken presidencies</a>, namely, by driving down a president’s approval rating. But despite the many investigations against Trump during his presidency, his approval rating didn’t really change. And although Trump’s approval rating <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/since-the-capitol-attack-trumps-approval-rating-has-plummeted-at-a-record-rate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">plummeted after Jan. 6</a> — including among Republicans — it <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/01/19/trump-approval-senate-impeachment-conviction-polling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has largely bounced back</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What, if anything, can this investigation really change in terms of how people view Trump?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex: </strong>I’m skeptical it’ll do much, largely because Trump still has <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/was-attack-our-capitol-murkowski-criticizes-gop-colleagues-opposing-jan-n1268906" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a pretty strong hold over the Republican base</a>. Back in May, when Senate Republicans rejected an investigation resembling the 9/11 Commission to investigate the attacks, only <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/poll-73-percent-of-republicans-blame-left-wing-protesters-for-jan-6-attack-just-23-percent-blame-trump-191520343.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">41 percent of Republicans</a> said supporters of Trump who congregated at the Capitol on Jan. 6 bear “some” or “a great deal” of the blame for the ensuing riot. Less than a quarter of Republicans (23 percent) blamed Trump himself, and a majority (52 percent) said he was “not at all” to blame.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>Agreed. I think you saw Trump’s approval drop in January because even a lot of Republicans — for example, Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell and McCarthy — criticized Trump for his role in the attack. And political science research has shown that <a href="https://scholar.princeton.edu/sites/default/files/mgilens/files/elite_cues_and_political_decision_making.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">elite cues can drive public opinion</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But since then, Republican politicians have had a chance to get their story straight, and maybe reconsider what breaking from Trump meant for their political futures (exhibit A: Cheney), so they have closed ranks again — and their voters have followed suit.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And if you subscribe to that theory, then having some credible Republicans on an independent commission might have lowered Trump’s numbers again. But with just Cheney and Kinzinger, who are perceived as anti-Trump, on a “Pelosi-led” commission, there are no Republican leaders left to sway Republican voters’ opinions against Trump.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>Honestly, ever since special counsel Robert Mueller’s investigation into Russian interference in the 2016 election, it has seemed as though even independent investigations have gotten politicized, to the point where it is very hard to convince either side to budge.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Take the Justice Department’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/07/16/hunter-biden-probe-prosecutor-499782" target="_blank" rel="noopener">investigation into Hunter Biden’s dealings with China</a>. Republicans think this is a significant investigation and will undoubtedly make hay over whatever the findings are — they <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2020/04/senate-republican-continue-hunter-biden-investigation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">went hard on Hunter in 2020</a> in the lead-up to the election. Democrats think it’s inconsequential since Hunter Biden isn’t an elected official.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are always independents or swing voters who might be open to seeing what these inquiries turn, but it’s hard to find a significant investigation that remains truly un-politicized.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>I <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2018/09/the-starr-report-20th-anniversary-trump-age" target="_blank" rel="noopener">blame the Starr Report</a>, Kaleigh. (That was a four-year, wide-ranging investigation into then-President Bill Clinton, which ultimately resulted in his impeachment.)</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/mysterious-case-2020s-polling-error-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79104379</p>


<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>Fair! Wayback playback.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>Is there a risk for President Biden or Democrats in this investigation, though? We know from the polls that both Republicans in Congress and Republican voters are ready to move on from the investigation, but what about Democratic voters or independents?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>Per that Quinnipiac poll I cited earlier, 84 percent of Democrats believed Jan. 6 “was an attack on democracy that should never be forgotten,” compared with just 12 percent who thought “too much is being made of the storming of the U.S. Capitol on January 6th, and it is time to move on”; independents felt the same way, but by a much narrower margin, 54 percent to 42 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex: </strong>Other polls show much of the same thing. Per Morning Consult, support for a congressional investigation into what happened on Jan. 6 <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/07/27/capitol-riot-panel-probe-polling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropped 11 percentage points among Republicans in the last month</a> — from 45 percent in June to 34 percent last week. Among independents, there was a 13 percentage point drop, with just 52 percent of independent voters saying they supported a congressional probe versus 65 percent in June. Democrats, though, have always been overwhelmingly in favor of investigating what happened that day, with over 80 percent saying they backed an investigation.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>It’s interesting that support among independents for an investigation is already so tepid. Seems as if many Americans may just want to move on.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Speaking of the Mueller investigation, it’s also noteworthy that when it originally started in 2017, there was actually <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-politics-of-the-mueller-report/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pretty notable support</a> for it among both Democrats and Republicans.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1082" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Mehta-MUELLER-POLLS-02.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Mehta-MUELLER-POLLS-02.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Mehta-MUELLER-POLLS-02.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Mehta-MUELLER-POLLS-02.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That, of course, changed over the course of the investigation, but it had more cross-party appeal initially than the current Jan. 6 select committee.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>It’s interesting that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/27/us/insurrection-pelosi-claims-fact-check.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some Republicans who have said</a> they have questions about the attack and the events leading up to it have also blocked the kind of investigation that may have answered those questions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>How do Democrats combat the GOP criticism that the commission isn’t bipartisan?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex: </strong>Having Cheney and Kinzinger on the committee, by default, makes it bipartisan. Of course, since the two have taken some pro-democracy stances as of late — like speaking out against <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/leadership-backing-stefanik-house-republicans-poised-oust-liz/story?id=77601583" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the lie that the election was stolen from Trump</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/01/14/956621191/these-are-the-10-republicans-who-voted-to-impeach-trump" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voting to impeach Trump</a> — they might be viewed as out of touch with the current GOP. But, if nothing else, their participation forces the media to describe the findings as bipartisan.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And oddly enough, Pelosi’s rejection of Jordan and Banks may have helped build credibility, too. Not only did both vote in January <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/07/23/pelosi-just-rejected-two-republicans-jan-6-investigation-here-are-three-takeaways/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">against certifying Biden’s election victory</a>, but they’re also supporters of the “Big Lie.” Pelosi’s decision not to give them a voice on the commission could help shore up credibility because it saves members from having to deal with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/07/20/power-up-mccarthy-taps-jim-jordan-3-big-lie-supporters-jan-6-committee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bad-faith attacks about the nature of the violence</a> that occurred.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>McCarthy appointing Banks and Jordan definitely put Pelosi in a difficult position for the reasons you cite, Alex. It’s interesting, though, that she only chose to block Jordan and Banks from being included on the committee, while Rep. Troy Nehls of Texas, who also voted against certifying Biden’s election victory, was not barred.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, of course, this move was unprecedented and angered McCarthy to the point that he <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/pelosi-rejects-mccarthy-nominations-banks-jordan-jan-6-commission-1611930" target="_blank" rel="noopener">yanked the remaining members</a>. It also put Pelosi in the position of having to appoint Republicans to the committee. Hence why McCarthy has <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/mccarthy-calls-cheney-kinzinger-pelosi-republicans" target="_blank" rel="noopener">derided them as “Pelosi Republicans.”</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>As Alex is getting at<strong>, </strong>the media plays a big role here, too. I get the instinct to dismiss Cheney and Kinzinger as not “real” Republicans — I’ve done that myself. But it’s also objectively true that the commission is bipartisan and that there is a wide ideological gulf between Cheney/Kinzinger and the committee’s Democrats. That shouldn’t be dismissed. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, what the committee <em>doesn’t</em> have is pro-Trump representation. And I think that’s what people really mean when they say the commission should be “bipartisan.” But as we’ve seen, being pro-Trump is functionally equivalent to acting in bad faith re: Jan. 6.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>One question I want to revisit here — earlier we said there wasn’t much political risk for Republicans in not participating, given that most Republican voters want to move on/aren’t interested in investigating what happened on Jan. 6. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Is it possible that Republicans are overestimating the power of Trump’s influence?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is one data point, but I’m thinking of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-special-election-in-texass-6th-district-will-test-trumps-influence-on-the-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the special election in Texas’s 6th Congressional District</a> earlier this week. The Trump-endorsed candidate and widow of the late congressman ended up losing by over 6 points. It’s one election — and you know what we say about a sample size of one — but maybe there is less appetite for some of Trump’s most bald-faced lies?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>Well, Sarah, I’m not ready to use that election result as evidence for anything just yet. Sure, it could signal a weakening in Trump’s hold over the party now that he’s no longer in office, but we need to wait for more data.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">More broadly, though, I do think Republicans overestimate Trump’s influence — but it’s a self-fulfilling prophecy. I think if Republicans in Congress adopted a united front in favor of an independent commission, at least some Republican voters would follow their cue. But because congressional Republicans think they need to toe Trump’s line, they do so, and public opinion doesn’t move.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>Well, I also don’t know that avoiding a Jan. 6 commission is only about Trump’s influence. He still has a significant hold on the party, to be sure, but there are no absolutes in politics: Eighteen percent of Republicans think Trump shouldn’t have any influence on the direction of the Republican Party, according to <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ap-poll-trump-republicans-future-ba85f8d2a572c553b621f86e991ee197" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a July 27 poll from the Associated Press- NORC Center for Public Affairs Research</a>, and 34 percent think he should have only “a little” influence. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">You can imagine that there are some GOP voters who just want to put this all behind us, who worry about it making the party look bad or just think the whole thing was overblown, regardless of whether they particularly like Trump.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>That could be true, Kaleigh, but a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/w1um475jkt/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/Economist poll</a> from early July implied that non-Trump-voting Republicans weren’t ready to put Jan. 6 behind them. Those who voted for Trump in the 2020 election opposed the commission 69 percent to 17 percent, while Republicans overall opposed it 60 percent to 24 percent. That suggests that the small sample of anti-Trump Republicans are still fairly supportive of the commission.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>It goes back to what you said at the outset, Kaleigh. It’s impossible to separate the politics from the attack at the Capitol. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That means, though, there can both be a contingency of Republicans who don’t believe what happened on Jan. 6 was a big deal and a contingency who just want to move on because they think it’s bad for them politically. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Both things can be true.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But OK, to wrap — what will you be watching as the investigation makes its way forward?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex</strong>: This might be a cop-out answer, but I’m watching how Republicans outside the room react and how Cheney and Kinzinger will work with Democrats.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich</strong>: I’ll be watching media coverage of the investigation: how much it receives, and how it is framed (i.e., is it a “bipartisan committee” or is it dismissed from the get-go because it’s not the full-on independent commission?). I’ll also be watching Trump’s favorability ratings, I guess, even though I don’t expect much movement there.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh:</strong> Honestly, I’m most interested in the ongoing court cases and investigation into the attack. I wonder if the testimony and evidence shared in Congress will shed any light on who participated, what their motivations were and what they did exactly.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-concerns-inflation-inflated-fivethirtyeight-79023124</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/america-lot-political-parties-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78968487</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1627901101606166</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Partisanship Isn’t The Only Reason Why So Many Americans Remain Unvaccinated</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/partisanship-isnt-the-only-reason-why-so-many-americans-remain-unvaccinated/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">It’s easy to blame partisanship for everything these days. Including the speed with which COVID-19 is raging through the U.S., causing cases to spike and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/cdc-backtracks-masks-guidance-vaccinated-people-schools/story?id=79089396" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CDC guidance to shift</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The delta variant is spreading rapidly in part because around 30 percent of Americans remain entirely unvaccinated. About 60 percent of adults <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are fully vaccinated</a> and another 9 percent are partly vaccinated,<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of July 29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> which puts the country just short of — and behind schedule for — President Biden’s <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/watch-live-biden-aims-for-vaccinating-70-percent-of-adult-americans-by-july-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">70 percent goal</a> set for July Fourth.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And as we’ve seen for months, Americans’ willingness to get vaccinated can become a proxy for their politics. Republicans are more likely than Democrats and independents to say they won’t get a vaccination. Depending on the poll, somewhere <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/religious-vaccines-covid-vaccination/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">around 20 percent</a> to <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/v60y11605p/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">30 percent of Republicans</a> say they won’t get vaccinated, whereas only about 5 percent of Democrats say the same. Independents who are refusing to get the vaccine range from around 10 percent to 25 percent in surveys. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/mysterious-case-2020s-polling-error-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79104379</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But partisanship isn’t the only thing that has shaped Americans’ vaccination status. Unvaccinated Americans tend to be younger, less well-educated and poorer; they are also more likely to be a person of color. The situation we’re in is not just because of politics but also because of access to the vaccine and broader skepticism of the health care system.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Age is an even more significant dividing line for vaccinations than politics is. Older Americans are far more likely to be vaccinated, undoubtedly because <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-do-we-get-back-to-normal-fastest-prioritize-access-to-the-vaccine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they were prioritized in the vaccination rollout</a> since they’re more at risk from coronavirus infections. About 80 percent of Americans age 65 or older are fully vaccinated, <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a>, compared with about 55 percent of Americans 18 to 64. Within that 18-64 range, the younger the age group, the less likely it is to be vaccinated relative to its share of the population.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some degree of skepticism or uncertainty may be playing a role in why young people are not as likely to be vaccinated. The <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2021/06/21/young-adults-covid-vaccine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CDC reported in June</a> that from March to May, nearly half of American adults under 40 either were unsure about the vaccine or didn’t plan on getting one. Polls suggest that there may be less skepticism now, as the <a href="https://www.prri.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/PRRI-IFYC-Jul-2021-Vaccine.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Public Religion Research Institute recently found</a> that the share of Americans under age 50 who were hesitant or opposed to getting the vaccine fell from slightly more than 50 percent in March to 35 percent in June. Still, just under half of that group of 35 percent remained opposed to getting vaccinated in the June survey.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extremes-of-the-gop-have-moved-beyond-fox-news/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An illustration of a red CRT TV set, with logos from Fox News, NewsMax, and OANN splattered on the screen." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/NEWSMAX-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/NEWSMAX-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/NEWSMAX-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/NEWSMAX-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Whether Republicans Get Vaccinated Has A Lot To Do With If They Watch Fox News … Or OANN <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extremes-of-the-gop-have-moved-beyond-fox-news/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">The younger someone is, <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/07/30/most-common-age-among-us-racial-ethnic-groups/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the more likely they are to be a person of color</a>, so it’s also unsurprising that Black and Hispanic Americans have lower vaccination rates than non-Hispanic white Americans. In the <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/v60y11605p/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">latest weekly survey from The Economist/YouGov</a>, slightly less than half of Black and Hispanic adults reported being fully vaccinated, while more than 60 percent of white adults said they were. And even when you include those who are still in the process of being vaccinated or intend to be vaccinated, a larger share of white Americans than Black or Hispanic Americans are vaccinated, are partly vaccinated or plan to get vaccinated.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The lag among people of color isn’t just about an unwillingness to get the jab. The <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-april-2021/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kaiser Family Foundation</a> found in April that significantly more unvaccinated Black and Hispanic adults than white adults didn’t know where or when they could get a vaccine. More fundamentally, unvaccinated people of color were far more likely than white Americans to say they hadn’t gotten the vaccine because they didn’t have enough time or were worried about missing work, <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-june-2021/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to KFF’s June survey</a>. Similarly, PRRI found that Black Americans were slightly more likely than Americans as a whole to say a lack of child care or transportation was a barrier to getting vaccinated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It does seem like more outreach about the relatively minor side effects could pay dividends as well. KFF found in June that 60 percent of Hispanic adults and 55 percent of Black adults were concerned about side effects, slightly more than the 51 percent of white adults who said the same. And slightly more people of color mentioned being wary of getting vaccinated as a reason for not having had the shot, which may have something to do with their <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/12/20/948614857/race-and-the-roots-of-vaccine-skepticism" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long history of experiencing inequities in the health care system</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are still more complicating factors than just race, age or partisanship. Socioeconomic status is playing a role, too. KFF’s June survey found that about 4 in 5 college graduates had at least one dose of the vaccine, compared with 3 in 5 of those without a degree. The education gap also exists among white Americans, too, as The Economist/YouGov survey showed that around 80 percent of white Americans with a college degree had been fully vaccinated, compared with about 55 percent of those without a degree. In addition, only 52 percent of those making under $50,000 said they were fully vaccinated, compared with 63 percent of those making $50,000 to $100,000 and 72 percent of those making $100,000 or more. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, to recap: Americans sure are a complicated bunch. But there’s still hope for getting more people vaccinated. PRRI found that about half of those who were hesitant about getting the vaccine were more likely to get it after hearing that it would help protect human life, help protect the most vulnerable people in their community or allow them to safely visit family and friends. And according to KFF’s June survey, some other changes might also encourage more people to get vaccinated, including implementing vaccine lotteries (already used by some states), using mobile vaccine units in undervaccinated neighborhoods and providing free child care during the vaccination and recovery process.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, we have a long way to go, and many people will get seriously ill before we get there. It’s easy to imagine that only another deadly wave of COVID-19 cases might spur some uncertain Americans <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2021/07/america-covid-19-vaccine-decline/619474/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to get the vaccine</a> — and those who are younger, less affluent or people of color could be more at risk considering they’re more likely to be unvaccinated.</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>According to a new <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/outside-covid-19-biden-receives-mixed-approval-ratings">ABC News/Ipsos poll</a>, 63 percent of Americans approve of Biden’s handling of COVID-19, but that’s 9 percentage points lower than the share who approved at the end of March. Meanwhile, Biden’s numbers on other issues were much lower, particularly those on crime, immigration and gun violence. </li><li>In light of Biden’s <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/07/09/1014512171/president-biden-defends-decision-to-withdraw-troops-from-afghanistan">decision to withdraw U.S. combat troops</a> from Afghanistan, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/352793/americans-split-whether-afghanistan-war-mistake.aspx">Gallup found</a> that Americans were evenly divided over whether U.S. involvement there — which began in October 2001 under President George W. Bush — was an error in the first place. Forty-seven percent told the pollster the U.S. made a mistake sending military forces into Afghanistan, while 46 percent said it wasn’t a mistake. Americans have usually been more likely to say U.S. involvement wasn’t a mistake, although Gallup found a near-even divide in 2014, too. In the new poll, a majority of Democrats and independents said they thought U.S. involvement was a mistake, while fewer than 3 in 10 Republicans felt the same way.</li><li>As for possible intervention in Haiti, three-fourths of registered voters told <a href="https://thehill.com/hilltv/what-americas-thinking/564824-poll-75-percent-say-us-should-not-get-involved-after-haitian">The Hill/HarrisX</a> that the U.S. should not get involved following <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-57762246">the assassination</a> of the Caribbean nation’s president, Jovenel Moïse, earlier this month. Biden <a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-government-and-politics-haiti-42975e871627d635ae3e6d7fdac83f1a">stated he had no intention</a> of sending U.S. troops there even though Haiti’s interim government requested that the U.S. and U.N. send security forces <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/colombian-suspects-haiti-presidents-killing-arrived-via-dominican-republic-2021-07-09/">to help protect Haiti’s critical infrastructure</a> during this time of political instability.</li><li><a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/07/27/capitol-riot-panel-probe-polling/">Morning Consult/Politico found</a> that 58 percent of registered voters supported a congressional commission investigation of the Jan. 6 assault on the U.S. Capitol, which comes as the House select committee looking into the insurrection <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/07/27/1020713409/here-are-the-9-lawmakers-investigating-the-jan-6-capitol-attack">held its first hearing on Tuesday</a>. Support was down from 66 percent in June, however, as only 34 percent of Republicans and 52 percent of independents backed the congressional investigation, down from 45 percent and 65 percent, respectively. </li><li>Nevada recently made waves by passing a law <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/06/11/politics/nevada-law-caucus-primary/index.html">to establish a presidential primary</a> as opposed to its usual caucus. Per a <a href="https://blog.ohpredictive.com/press-releases/most-nevada-voters-are-ready-to-move-on-from-caucuses">poll from OH Predictive Insights</a>, Nevadans are very much on board with this change, as 52 percent say they prefer a primary, compared with only 13 percent who prefer the caucus system. In an unusual show of bipartisanship, majorities of both Republican and Democratic voters say they back a primary system. However, the law also sets the primary for the first Tuesday in February starting in 2024, which could put Nevada in conflict with Iowa and New Hampshire over which states lead the presidential nomination process. While Nevada Republicans in the OHPI poll backed the change to a primary, the state party actually opposed the move to avoid upsetting the nomination calendar.</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-3.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> 51.4 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 43.3 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of +8.1 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-world-feels-about-holding-the-tokyo-olympics-amid-covid-19/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 52.2 percent approved and 42.8 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of +9.4 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 52.7 percent and a disapproval rating of 41.9 percent, for a net approval rating of +10.8 points.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-concerns-inflation-inflated-fivethirtyeight-79023124</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/america-lot-political-parties-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78968487</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1627640101899602</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What Americans Think About Vaccines, Mask Mandates And Shutdowns As COVID-19 Cases Spike</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-americans-think-about-vaccines-masks-and-shutdowns-as-covid-cases-spike/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Pandemic</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Vaccination</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-americans-think-about-vaccines-masks-and-shutdowns-as-covid-cases-spike/">
	<div data-podcast-id="313672" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What Americans Think About Vaccines, Mask Mandates And Shutdowns As COVID-19 Cases Spike">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP7582159285.mp3?updated=1627594702"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">Cases of COVID-19 are surging in the U.S., largely due to the spread of the delta variant. Earlier this summer, an average of <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#trends_dailytrendscases" data-type="URL" data-id="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#trends_dailytrendscases" target="_blank" rel="noopener">11,000-15,000 cases per day</a> were reported to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, but that average is now surpassing 60,000 per day. The federal government and some states have started taking measures to try to increase vaccination rates, particularly among public employees and health care workers. A <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://thehill.com/hilltv/what-americas-thinking/563893-poll-74-percent-support-reinstating-mask-mandates-if-their-area">recent Hill-HarrisX poll</a> showed that a solid majority of voters would support the reinstatement of mask mandates in their area if COVID-19 cases started to spike, but overall, Americans are split on what to do about the rise in cases. In this installment of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew talks about where Americans stand on mitigation efforts, how politicians are responding and what public health experts are saying about the current state of the pandemic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/mysterious-case-2020s-polling-error-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-79104379</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/americans-concerns-inflation-inflated-fivethirtyeight-79023124</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 22:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1627595101701045</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
