<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:06 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 08:29:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Presidents Used To Be The Faces Of Their Political Parties. Is That No Longer The Case?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/presidents-used-to-be-the-faces-of-their-political-parties-is-that-no-longer-the-case/</link>
						<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Julia Azari</dc:creator>
			<category>Barack Obama</category>
			<category>Bill Clinton</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>George W. Bush</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidency</category>
			<category>Presidential History</category>
			<category>Presidents</category>
			<category>Ronald Reagan</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">In our polarized political era, presidents have increasingly become the faces of their parties, operating as symbols of what their parties value — and what the opposing party rejects.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Recent Republican presidents have doubled down on ideology and conservative social issues. Democratic presidents after Ronald Reagan have been a bit <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2018/08/22/clinton-signs-welfare-to-work-bill-aug-22-1996-790321" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more cautious</a> on <a href="https://www.politico.com/blogs/under-the-radar/2014/10/obama-evolves-again-on-same-sex-marriage-197348" target="_blank" rel="noopener">social issues</a> but have still served as symbolic party leaders focused on identity and the connections Democrats have to a range of demographic groups.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But with President Biden, this analogy begins to break down. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Yes, he is popular with some of the party’s core supporters, in particular Black Americans, who <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/04/joe-biden-owes-it-all-to-african-american-voters.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">helped him win the Democratic primary</a>, but he’s not really a cultural figure like former Presidents Barack Obama and Donald Trump — one reason Republicans have found Biden <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/04/28/republicans-messaging-biden-personal-484812" target="_blank" rel="noopener">so difficult to demonize</a>. Rather, he has adopted a <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/22b39e9b-9b21-4d82-ba5b-8cc427c13cd8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“quiet” approach</a> to the presidency, in which he seems more content with keeping an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/bidens-team-and-priorities-show-how-the-democratic-party-changed-in-the-trump-era/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ideological coalition</a> together than with advancing any one perspective.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, though, it’s hard to know just how much of a shift this marks — it’s possible that Biden is just a blip — but is his presidency a potential shift in the relationship between presidents and their political parties?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To answer this question, it’s helpful to look at how this relationship has evolved over time. For instance, presidents <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-is-a-19th-century-president-facing-21st-century-problems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">weren’t always party leaders</a>. Through the 19th and early 20th centuries, presidents were often <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/27552726" target="_blank" rel="noopener">creatures of their parties</a>, dependent on state and local party leaders to nominate them, and as such, often obligated to <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/studies-in-american-political-development/article/abs/patronage-logrolls-and-polarization-congressional-parties-of-the-gilded-age-18761896/E39C08CDB2F3193434EEBE519C61D911" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reward them with appointments</a> in the federal government. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Scholars <a href="https://global.oup.com/ushe/product/the-president-and-the-parties-9780195084252?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t agree</a> on exactly <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/paperback/9780691178172/the-rhetorical-presidency" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when or why this changed</a>, but <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/pdf/27552439.pdf?casa_token=jlKy9Z9e_SgAAAAA:Rsey_U2RxEdLJsGASSmynsOAdmmxvaSJBrFdyX-CDrf3QJ1MmbVCHi02NtaDYubtTAgXjGbXcqQOhdGNws5iz8P5_C6bRptgWkoLdzj6P_W5sJd5Wgo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">travel</a> and <a href="https://millercenter.org/the-presidency/teacher-resources/recasting-presidential-history/presidency-television-era" target="_blank" rel="noopener">telecommunications</a> certainly helped presidential candidates — and presidents once in office — directly build support in the electorate without going through the parties. What’s more, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/how-a-raucous-convention-revolutionized-our-primary-system/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reforms to the primary system</a> in the early 1970s gave voters more influence over the nomination process. Together, these changes did a lot to make presidents the faces of their parties.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now the president’s role is essentially to support the party’s cultural values and priorities. For Republican presidents like Reagan and George W. Bush, this has meant adopting the rhetoric and priorities of the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/outlook/2021/03/22/reagan-tied-republicans-white-christians-now-party-is-trapped/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">evangelical conservative movement</a>, an important <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">faction of the GOP</a>.<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, George H.W. Bush struggled with this kind of political symbolism and had trouble consolidating support in the party, harming his 1992 bid for reelection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> For Democratic presidents like Bill Clinton and Obama, it was about identity. Both were younger — Clinton represented a generational shift in leadership — and Obama made history as the first Black president.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These connections spoke to the parties’ priorities, but they were also at least somewhat symbolic. Reagan, for example, was the preferred candidate of the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/43285333?seq=1#metadata_info_tab_contents" target="_blank" rel="noopener">religious right</a>, but he advanced <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/23921480?seq=1#metadata_info_tab_contents" target="_blank" rel="noopener">few legislative accomplishments that reflected its agenda</a> and also appointed a moderate justice to the U.S. Supreme Court who <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0022009417699865" target="_blank" rel="noopener">supported abortion rights</a>. Bush, in the meantime, was an <a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/jesus/president/spirituality.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">evangelical</a>, and although he delivered for Christian conservatives by successfully <a href="https://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2006/07/20060719-6.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">banning most stem-cell research</a> and appointing two conservative justices to the Supreme Court, he fell short in his <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/24/politics/bush-backs-ban-in-constitution-on-gay-marriage.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">efforts to pass a constitutional amendment</a> that <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2013/07/george-w-bushs-forgotten-gay-rights-history/277567/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prohibited same-sex marriage</a>. It did set off <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2004/ALLPOLITICS/11/02/ballot.samesex.marriage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a wave of similar bills on the state level</a> — many of which were successful — but ultimately, this marked a defeat for the religious right, as the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/change-doesnt-usually-come-this-fast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tides dramatically turned</a> in favor of same-sex marriage. And although Clinton showed youthful irreverence by playing the saxophone on late-night television and answering questions <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bs-xpm-1994-04-20-1994110050-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">about his underwear on MTV</a>, these were campaign tactics with little connection to governing priorities. Obama spoke about his family background often but <a href="https://apnews.com/article/jackie-robinson-barack-obama-chicago-politics-il-state-wire-29b24a7985a442d8b890261da99cad86" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t talk about race bluntly</a>, and <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/book/76582" target="_blank" rel="noopener">there’s disagreement</a> as to how much <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/theories-of-race-and-ethnicity/getting-over-the-obama-hope-hangover-the-new-racism-in-postracial-america/0E90E5DFF59400D9A88AA753971D7FC5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his presidency helped</a> Black Americans. Finally, Trump’s appeal was clearly rooted in symbolism. Despite being <a href="https://www.npr.org/2016/01/18/463528847/citing-two-corinthians-trump-struggles-to-make-the-sale-to-evangelicals" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an unlikely mouthpiece</a> for <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/09/trump-secretly-mocks-his-christian-supporters/616522/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the religious right</a>, he was <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/11/17/935910276/the-white-elephants-in-the-room" target="_blank" rel="noopener">popular</a> with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/religion/2020/08/21/black-and-white-evangelicals-trump-racial-reconciliation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">white evangelicals</a> nonetheless. His rhetoric around immigrants and other minority groups also addressed <a href="https://www.voterstudygroup.org/publication/story-of-trumps-appeal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a politics of grievance and racial resentment</a> that has become increasingly salient among Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s worth noting, however, how these culturally symbolic presidents were often reactions to one another. Clinton was morally flexible and tough to pin down, while Bush was resolute and religious. At the same time, though, where Bush was incurious and parochial, Obama was intellectual and cosmopolitan. In contrast with those traits, Trump presented himself as straightforward and nationalistic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Biden isn’t really any of these. And that’s not an accident. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Many Democratic voters and leaders favored Biden precisely because <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2019/07/19/joe-biden-isnt-only-electable-candidate-heres-what-democratic-primary-voters-are-thinking-how-change-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he was seen</a> as a “<a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2020/04/20/some-democrats-are-bothered-nominee-is-an-older-white-man-and-they-solidly-back-biden-in-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">safe, old white guy</a>,” as <a href="https://psmag.com/news/no-democrats-do-not-need-to-nominate-a-white-man-in-order-to-defeat-trump" target="_blank" rel="noopener">problematic as that thinking is</a>. It’s not just about demographics, though. Compared with his immediate predecessors, Biden has also stayed out of the limelight as president. In the new book “<a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-ubiquitous-presidency-9780197520635?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Ubiquitous Presidency</a>,” political communication experts Joshua Scacco and Kevin Coe trace how presidents have used the changing media landscape over the past few decades. Clinton, for instance, appeared on various entertainment shows. Obama harnessed the power of digital media. And Trump, before being banned, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/11/02/us/politics/trump-twitter-presidency.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">used Twitter prolifically</a> to talk directly to the American people. But so far, Biden has been pretty conventional in how he communicates, holding traditional televised addresses and touring the country but not really doing anything new.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ideologically, Biden has always been at the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/29/us/politics/biden-democrats.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">center of his party</a>, too, which makes it harder for him to operate symbolically — he was already the consensus candidate. During the 2020 presidential campaign, he engaged with both the diversity and identity in the Democratic coalition by choosing as his running mate Kamala Harris, the first person of Indian descent and the first Black woman on a major-party presidential ticket, and by working with former 2020 contender Sen. Bernie Sanders and Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez on <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/05/12/politics/ocasio-cortez-biden-campaign-task-force-climate-change/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">climate change</a> and other issue priorities. But it’s unclear how representative these issues are of Biden versus him working to keep the Democratic Party’s coalition in line.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For example, Biden’s COVID-19 stimulus package broke ground by offering <a href="https://www.povertycenter.columbia.edu/news-internal/2021/presidential-policy/biden-economic-relief-proposal-poverty-impact" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expanded tax credits and direct payments</a>, embracing the idea of an <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/03/22/the-stimulus-bill-is-the-most-economically-liberal-legislation-in-decades" target="_blank" rel="noopener">active, big government</a> — something Democrats <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/bidens-push-for-big-government-solutions-is-popular-now-but-it-could-backfire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have skirted around since the Reagan years</a>. But it’s unclear so far how many other liberal priorities will make it through the legislative process. This is especially true of Biden’s efforts to tackle <a href="https://www.nbcboston.com/news/politics/biden-vows-to-address-institutional-racism-in-first-100-days-as-president/2134938/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">structural racism</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/10/us/politics/biden-transgender-patient-protections.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ensure rights for transgender Americans</a>. He has spoken about these issues more directly than his predecessors, but whether he’ll have the political capital to make real, lasting changes on these fronts remains an open question.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One reason Biden’s presidency seems like such a departure could be the timing. He is serving in an era when the two main political parties have pretty clearly <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/05/21/under-trump-republicans-democrats-moved-even-farther-apart-quickly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">split on many issues</a> and the presidency itself is polarizing. In other words, Biden might not need to do much symbolic leadership for Democrats to know where the party stands. It may be that just as growing polarization created the expectation that the president would serve in this symbolic and cultural role, it has now grown to the point where the president’s symbolic leadership is unnecessary. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Another reason could be that Biden is filling another need in the electorate — the demand to return to a quieter, more “normal” politics that many still associate with the mid-20th century.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The age of social media, cable news and nationalized congressional politics has also allowed a variety of other actors to lead the party symbolically and advance its agenda on cultural and economic issues. These include national progressive icons in Congress like Ocasio-Cortez, Sanders and Sen. Elizabeth Warren, <a href="https://www.msnbc.com/reidout" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as well as</a> <a href="https://www.msnbc.com/rachel-maddow-show" target="_blank" rel="noopener">media</a> <a href="https://crooked.com/podcast-series/pod-save-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">figures</a> and <a href="https://www.dataforprogress.org/who-we-are" target="_blank" rel="noopener">activists</a>. Maybe these kinds of figures will serve as the party’s cultural face while presidents can do more of the mundane work of governance. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s perhaps more difficult to imagine this happening for Republicans given the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/07/11/politics/cpac-trump-speech-straw-poll/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">continued influence</a> of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-gop-might-still-be-trumps-party-but-that-doesnt-mean-theres-room-for-him/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump</a> and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/24/culture-war-critical-race-theory-496087" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prominence of cultural appeals</a> for the party brand, but the conservative movement also has no shortage of <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/culture/archive/2021/07/tucker-carlson-today-americana-fake-log-cabin/619411/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">media figures</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/07/07/politics/marjorie-taylor-greene-brown-shirts-vaccine/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">camera-seeking</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2021/05/11/senator-josh-hawley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">members</a> of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2021/04/29/cruz-sleeps-biden-boring-speech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congress</a> eager to step into that role. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible, then, that Biden is a different kind of president and the end of the symbolic presidency is nigh. Then again, maybe Biden is just a brief throwback, before another culturally savvy media darling seeks the presidency.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626174902131955</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>CPAC Emphasized Republicans’ Obsession With 2020</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/cpac-emphasized-republicans-continued-obsession-with-2020/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Conservative Political Action Committee</category>
			<category>CPAC</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Fraud</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>The Republican Party</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">Donald Trump is still the undisputed leader of the Republican Party. But you probably already knew that. The medley of conservative voters, politicians, activists and political commentators that descended on Dallas this past weekend for this year’s second <a href="https://cpac.conservative.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Conservative Political Action Conference</a> certainly did. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But some things are less clear. Namely, ahead of the midterm elections, GOP voters seem to be casting about for the best path forward and debating whether their energy would be better utilized by <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/12/10/ken-paxton-donald-trump-election-lawsuit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relitigating the results of last year’s presidential race</a> (again) or chugging forward to what’s expected to be a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republican-trump-2022-midterms-election-falsehoods/2021/07/04/3a43438c-d36f-11eb-ae54-515e2f63d37d_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">grueling midterm cycle</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This schism amongst Republicans was on display throughout the weekend. Take, for example, a conversation I had with James Scott, a once-reluctant Trump supporter who’s now all in. After retrieving a hot coffee on the second day of CPAC, he sheepishly admitted to me that, back in 2016, he “held his nose” before voting for the now-former president. Standing across from me with a “<a href="https://thechosengifts.com/products/come-and-see-chosen-hat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Come and See</a>” baseball cap, the bespectacled retiree described his past self as a “Marco Rubio aficionado” who joined Team Trump only after Trump announced an ultra-conservative <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/19/us/politics/donald-trump-supreme-court-nominees.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Supreme Court shortlist</a> ahead of the 2016 general election. And now, Scott is so devoted that he believes assessing Trump’s <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/05/19/politics/donald-trump-big-lie-explainer/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">baseless lies</a> about rampant election fraud is critical to the GOP’s future. “We must have election integrity,” he told me. The truth, he added, “must be brought out because the future depends on it.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Compare that, though, to 20-year-old Aaron Genus, a college student, Instagram personality and restaurant worker who came to the conference from Michigan. Genus made clear that he, too, believed the 2020 election was “an absolute joke;” but unlike Scott, he’s ready for the party to move on. “In America, there’s no such thing as an election do-over,” he said. “Once Trump got in that helicopter and waved goodbye, it was over. There’s no way to undo what happened. All we can do is fight for our election integrity come the next two cycles.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Heading into CPAC, I was curious where voters’ heads were at. How preoccupied would attendees be with rehashing 2020 versus looking ahead to 2022? In years past, CPAC has been a <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/cpac-brief-history-conservative-movement-120815471.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">useful barometer</a> for the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/feb/25/donald-trump-cpac-republicans-allies" target="_blank" rel="noopener">base of the Republican Party</a> and its most fervent activists — even if it <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/02/cpac-straw-poll-winners-dont-always-become-gop-nominees/448083/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t always indicative</a> of the party’s future. This year was no exception, although the choice of whether to press on from the previous election is arguably a new one.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A bevy of speakers decried claims of a stolen election (though they are false), and <a href="https://cpac.conservative.org/agenda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at least two events</a> were devoted exclusively to how to spot and guard against election fraud. Other panels focused on how to expand the party’s base, and ahead of Trump’s culminating speech, an emcee declared that “2022 starts right here.” What I found, though, is that only a small handful of attendees were actually ready to move on.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/07/us/politics/democrats-republicans-house.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">losing the U.S. House in 2018</a> and the Senate and White House in 2020, Republicans are eager to identify candidates who can help them successfully reclaim Congress in 2022 and the presidency in 2024. But if this weekend’s CPAC conference is any indication of the party’s priorities, some of the staunchest Republicans are more concerned about challenging the last election than winning the next. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“I still feel we were so cheated in 2020 and I don’t think that’s been resolved,” attendee Pat DeLange, who turned 63 on Saturday, told me. “So when there is cheating involved it needs to be exposed. I think we need to get the rightful president back in office so he can fix this and wake people up.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump, for his part, seemed more concerned with the past, too. If nothing else, it’s one way for <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/11/07/trump-post-presidency-plans-434324" target="_blank" rel="noopener">him to maintain relevance</a> as the party’s de facto leader while he irons out his future plans. During a roughly 90-minute speech on Sunday, he mentioned — <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/06/12/politics/analysis-trump-election-lies-blog-post-presidency/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">similar to prior interviews and appearances</a> — a “rigged election” and sarcastically quipped that he “lost” last year’s race. (The crowd went wild at these bits, repeatedly booing at claims of fraud.) But perhaps most notably, he continued to tease supporters on whether he’ll run again. (“I will never stop fighting for you,” he told a brimming crowd, which chanted back, “Four more years!”)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the one hand, considering Trump’s grip on the party — 53 percent of self-identified Republicans said in a May <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/53-republicans-view-trump-true-us-president-reutersipsos-2021-05-24/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reuters/Ipsos</a> opinion poll that they believe he is the “true president”  — it’s not surprising that supporters are still overwhelmingly taking cues from the former president. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-republicans-still-wont-accept-that-biden-won/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Recent polls on who won the 2020 election confirm</a> that much of the party <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-republicans-distrust-this-years-election-results-than-democrats-after-2016/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t over last year</a>, either. In November, roughly three in four Trump supporters said Biden’s win was due to voter fraud, per a <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/documents/monmouthpoll_us_111820.pdf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monmouth University poll</a>. And those numbers have barely budged. According to that May Reuters/Ipsos <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2021-05/Ipsos%20Reuters%20Topline%20Write%20up-%20The%20Big%20Lie%20-%2017%20May%20thru%2019%20May%202021.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey</a>, 56 percent of Republicans still believe the election was rigged. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Experts I spoke to ahead of the convention said they’ve never seen a past president maintain his position as head of a political party as Trump has, but they weren’t shocked with the crowd’s obsession with the past either. “It’s not a real future-oriented crowd. I’d say they’re more interested in what they see as [a] fraudulent election and litigating all that,” said <a href="http://hs.umt.edu/polsci/people/default.php?s=Saldin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Robert Saldin</a>, a professor of political science at the University of Montana. “But it’s always been a backwards looking thing. ‘Make America Great Again’ is casting a tide to the past, so I think, in a way, there’s always been a backwards focus there that’s been relatively rare in American politics.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, fealty to Trump (and, by virtue, his false claims of fraud) were a key theme of the weekend. Not only were attendees there wearing a sea of red, white and blue outfits and accessories bearing Trump’s face and name, they overwhelmingly selected Trump as their preferred candidate for the 2024 GOP presidential nomination <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/562472-trump-desantis-lead-cpac-straw-poll" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the CPAC straw poll</a>. He captured 70 percent of the ballots in the anonymous survey — a boost from the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/jemimamcevoy/2021/02/28/trump-wins-cpac-straw-poll-with-florida-gov-ron-desantis-his-closest-contender/?sh=f67a23934ea9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">55 percent</a> he won in a similar poll at the Orlando CPAC conference in February. Also during the conference, <a href="https://twitter.com/scottbraddock/status/1413904794335420417" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attendees circulated</a> a seven-point plot to reinstate Trump as president in a matter of days. (There’s <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/why-trump-cant-be-reinstated-as-president-by-august-2021-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no constitutional mechanism</a> for reinstating a former president.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, those who want to leave 2020 behind were at the conference, too, but they were a minority. On the last day of CPAC, I found Grizzly Joe, a Trump supporter who received national attention <a href="https://www.cnn.com/videos/business/2021/07/10/cpac-trump-supporters-dallas-osullivan-sot-nr-vpx.cnn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for telling CNN</a> he believed Biden was the true winner of the November election. (While he had media credentials for the event, he told me he was half there for coverage and half there as an attendee.) “Looking in the rearview mirror isn’t going to help us move forward,” he told me. When I asked him whether there’s too much focus right now on debunked claims of fraud, he told me that, “some people are like a dog with a bone. If there’s fraud let’s find it, root it out and fix it. … But people jumping up and down bellyaching about Trump being the real president isn’t going to put Trump back in the White House.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A second conversation with Barbara Lewis, 65, who wore a Trump 2024 shirt and blue leggings with red and white stars, yielded much of the same sentiment. “They fought the [last] election enough, and the fight kind of just needs to end. I don’t think they can go any further with the fight.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s too early to say where the Republican Party will go from here, but at least for now, it’s clear that Trump and the 2020 election are still very resonant in voters’ minds. And that makes perfect sense considering Trump himself has a foot in both the past and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trump-endorsements-republicans/2021/06/26/86228924-d465-11eb-ae54-515e2f63d37d_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the future</a>. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 20:33:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167294</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>First It Was Sex Ed. Now It’s Critical Race Theory.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/first-it-was-sex-ed-now-its-critical-race-theory/</link>
						<dc:creator>Alex Samuels</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Alex Samuels and Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Critical Race Theory</category>
			<category>Education</category>
			<category>High School</category>
			<category>Public Schools</category>
			<category>The Republican Party</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">In the 1960s and 70s, conservatives were waging a war against what they considered an existential threat infiltrating America’s public schools. Pamphlets were circulated by the John Birch Society, a right-wing extremist group, declaring it a “<a href="https://pdxscholar.library.pdx.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2613&amp;context=open_access_etds" target="_blank" rel="noopener">filthy Communist plot</a>.” And then-Governor Ronald Reagan of California decried it as a “moral crisis” that needed to be eradicated. What was poisoning the minds of America’s youth? Sex education.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These days, sex ed is <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5495344/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more widely accepted</a>, especially <a href="https://time.com/3578597/aids-sex-ed-history/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">following the HIV/AIDS epidemic</a> (though conservatives have still managed <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/conservatives-propose-revised-sex-ed-rules-lgbtq-pushback-77073959" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to beat back more progressive school curricula</a> when it comes to sexual health), but the Republican Party’s habit of identifying a bogeyman in America’s education system hasn’t wavered. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then it was sex ed. Now, it’s critical race theory.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Critical race theory is <a href="https://www.edweek.org/leadership/what-is-critical-race-theory-and-why-is-it-under-attack/2021/05" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a legal scholarship framework</a> that has been around in academia for four decades and asserts that racism is systemic and embedded in many American institutions. But over the past few months, the term has been co-opted by Republicans as a catch-all buzzword to signify <a href="https://www.al.com/news/2021/06/what-is-critical-race-theory-is-it-really-taught-in-schools.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the perceived threat</a> of anti-white indoctrination in American schools. This has motivated a slate of proposed legislation outlawing a wide range of teachings. Since the start of this year, at least six states have enacted bans on the teaching of critical race theory or discussions of racism in the classrooms, according to a <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2021/07/02/why-are-states-banning-critical-race-theory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brookings Institute</a> analysis, while almost 20 other states have introduced similar bills. Moreover, <a href="https://nonprofitquarterly.org/republicans-in-5-states-seek-to-keep-1619-project-curriculum-out-of-schools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a handful of states</a>, like <a href="https://apnews.com/article/florida-race-and-ethnicity-government-and-politics-education-74d0af6c52c0009ec3fa3ee9955b0a8d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida</a> and <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/06/15/abbott-critical-race-theory-law/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Texas</a>, have also successfully banned the teaching of the <a href="https://pulitzercenter.org/lesson-plan-grouping/1619-project-curriculum" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York Times’s 1619 Project</a> curriculum, which explores the central role of slavery in the development of the U.S. The project <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/05/why-conservatives-want-cancel-1619-project/618952/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been harshly criticized</a> by conservatives who have accused its writers of recasting history through a racial lens. To be sure, the bills vary. Some bills mention critical race theory directly, while others only reference bans on “<a href="http://webserver.rilin.state.ri.us/BillText/BillText21/HouseText21/H6070.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">divisive concepts</a>” or any teachings that imply “<a href="http://webserver1.lsb.state.ok.us/cf_pdf/2021-22%20ENR/hB/HB1775%20ENR.PDF" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one race or sex is inherently superior</a>.” But this concerted effort to limit what can be taught in our schools isn’t new — it’s the latest chapter in the GOP’s long-standing push to target curricula that goes against its political ideology. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republican attacks on cultural issues within America’s public schools follow a familiar pattern. First, they’re usually in response to a vague idea of what <em>might </em>happen — that is, teaching sexual health <a href="https://www.kqed.org/education/534518/sex-education-in-america-the-good-the-bad-the-ugly" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>might</em> lead to more school-aged teenagers having sex</a> (although there’s actually <a href="https://ifstudies.org/blog/fewer-american-high-schoolers-having-sex-than-ever-before" target="_blank" rel="noopener">been a decline</a> in the percentage of American high schoolers having sex since the early 1990s). Second, when there is a debate over teaching often taboo, complex social issues, like <a href="https://apnews.com/article/race-and-ethnicity-racial-injustice-business-education-government-and-politics-905c354a805cec1785160cf21f04c7ec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">racism</a>, <a href="https://www.pewforum.org/essay/darwin-in-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">evolution</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2015/04/28/whats-the-best-way-to-teach-sex-ed-today" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sex</a>, elected school board members can exert an outsized amount of control. Considering school board members are <a href="https://www.edweek.org/leadership/why-school-board-diversity-matters/2020/11" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to be white and are often partisan</a>, Republicans’ political agenda <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2332858418818074" target="_blank" rel="noopener">can get a disproportionate amount of weight</a> in school board decisions. And if the contemporary Republican Party has taught us anything as of late, it’s that “anti-wokeness” is political <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-attacking-cancel-culture-and-woke-people-is-becoming-the-gops-new-political-strategy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">catnip for its base</a>, so it’s unlikely that this crusade goes away any time soon. In fact, because critical race theory deals so explicitly with racism and discrimination, it has arguably <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2021/05/gops-critical-race-theory-fixation-explained/618828/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">animated the GOP base</a> in a way that previous education battles haven’t. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/racial-justice-protests-started-contemporary-culture-war-77883986</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">One of the oldest education battles revolves around the teaching of evolution. It’s one that until recently didn’t have clearly drawn partisan lines. After all, the most famous example of a legislative attempt to prohibit teaching evolution in schools was actually introduced by a Democrat: a 1925 Tennessee state law to ban teaching evolution in schools. That <a href="https://www.npr.org/2005/07/05/4723956/timeline-remembering-the-scopes-monkey-trial" target="_blank" rel="noopener">law was later challenged in a showy court case</a> (complete with chimpanzees) that same year, where it was upheld, and ultimately not repealed until 1967. (It was also a Democrat who introduced a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1986/12/10/creationism-case-raises-issues-of-faith-freedom/ce2bf87f-513d-4ea3-95f8-dab73dfc93a8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1981 bill in Louisiana’s state legislature</a> that mandated the teaching of “creation science” — which presents religious beliefs as alternative scientific theories — whenever evolution was taught. The Supreme Court has since banned states from <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1987-06-20-mn-8487-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">requiring creation science</a> to be taught, but it has remained <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/jun/24/bobby-jindal-republican-creationism-2016-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a popular conservative cultural flashpoint</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the last two decades, Republicans at the state level have introduced <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ssqu.12267" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over 100 bills</a> aimed at undermining evolution, through tactics such as <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/316487-new-wave-of-anti-evolution-bills-hit-states?rl=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">allowing teachers to “question” established scientific concepts</a>. Most of these bills never go anywhere — a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ssqu.12267" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2016 study</a> found just six anti-evolution bills out of 110 introduced between 2000 and 2012 were enacted into law — but the fact that legislatures keep proposing them means one of the U.S. public education system’s oldest bogeyman is still alive and well.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-trump-has-redefined-conservatism/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An illustration of a red elephant that on the side reads “Make America Great Again”" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CONSERVATISM-REDEFINED-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CONSERVATISM-REDEFINED-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CONSERVATISM-REDEFINED-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CONSERVATISM-REDEFINED-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				How Trump Has Redefined Conservatism <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-trump-has-redefined-conservatism/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Similarly, sex education in public schools has long been a target of Republicans, although once it became clear that sex education programs actually help <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/healthyyouth/whatworks/what-works-sexual-health-education.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reduce the risk of teen pregnancy and STIs and delay the age</a> when teens become sexually active, sex ed became more socially accepted. This means that Republicans opposed to sex ed have had to change their strategy to curtailing what’s taught. Sixteen states, for instance, <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/state-policy/explore/sex-and-hiv-education" target="_blank" rel="noopener">require educators to “stress” abstinence education</a> and do not require anything be taught about contraception, according to the Guttmacher Institute, a research organization that advances sexual and reproductive health and rights.<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not every bill was introduced by Republican lawmakers, but the majority were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> Another popular strategy is giving <a href="https://www.wfla.com/news/education/florida-parents-can-opt-their-students-out-of-sex-education-with-newly-signed-law/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">parents the right</a> to opt their child out of sex ed, or making <a href="https://azednews.com/senate-hears-bill-that-would-require-parents-to-opt-in-not-opt-out-for-sex-education/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sex ed opt-in</a> to begin with. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And more recently, <a href="https://www.vox.com/2014/10/7/18088680/common-core" target="_blank" rel="noopener">beginning in the late 2000s</a>, a culture war clash emerged following the adoption of the <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/the-debate-over-common-core/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Common Core State Standards Initiative</a> — a set of K-12 academic standards that was aggressively pushed by the federal government. While the initiative was designed to promote a good education by giving students specific guidelines about what they should know, grade by grade, in subjects like math and English language arts, it <a href="https://www.motherjones.com/politics/2014/09/common-core-education-reform-backlash-obamacare/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">faced fierce opposition from Republicans</a> and Democrats alike. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But around 2015, the Core standards became especially politicized by <a href="https://slate.com/human-interest/2015/08/gop-education-summit-six-candidates-meet-with-campbell-brown-in-new-hampshire.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politicians on the right</a> who thought curriculum standards should be left to local officials. For instance, when Donald Trump <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/ed/2016/09/25/494740056/donald-trumps-plan-for-americas-schools" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ran for the White House in 2016</a>, his early ads argued that “education has to be at a local level.” And in 2018, Trump’s former Secretary of Education Betsy DeVos falsely declared the Common Core was “<a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/speeches/prepared-remarks-us-education-secretary-betsy-devos-american-enterprise-institute" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dead</a>” — even though it’s up to individual states, and not the federal government, whether to ditch the Core standards.<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally, more than 40 states passed laws adopting the Common Core standards in their schools. But &lt;a href="https://www.achieve.org/files/StrongStandards_032919.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;more than 20 states&lt;/a&gt; have now revised, repealed or rolled back parts of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>3</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s clear culture war issues have always had a place in how Republicans think about education, but as Terry Moe, a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution, a conservative think tank, told us, Republicans also used to advocate for more policy-focused solutions. He pointed to Republican-led initiatives like the <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/ed/2015/10/27/443110755/no-child-left-behind-what-worked-what-didnt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">No Child Left Behind Act</a>, which, in part, sought to use standardized testing to help improve student achievement. These kinds of initiatives have since <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/no-child-has-failed/2015/02/13/8d619026-b2f8-11e4-827f-93f454140e2b_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">received their own criticism</a>, but they represent a very different strategy than the one that currently dominates the Republican Party. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The Republican Party has really gotten further and further away from being a party of ideas about how to solve social problems — one of them being an education system that does not perform very well — and becoming a party of anger and resentment. That’s what they specialize in now,” Moe said. “They are, for the most part, fighting a culture war against the Democrats and trying to pander to their base.”</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-cancel-culture-became-an-issue-for-young-republicans/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A poster that says “Culture War, feat. Charlie Kirk” surrounded by fake political buttons that say “Socialism Sucks” and “Culture War.”" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/GettyImages-1179231895-4x3-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/GettyImages-1179231895-4x3-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/GettyImages-1179231895-4x3-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/GettyImages-1179231895-4x3-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				How ‘Cancel Culture’ Became An Issue For Young Republicans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-cancel-culture-became-an-issue-for-young-republicans/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">In that sense, critical race theory fits perfectly into the Republicans’ agenda, as it’s a cultural bugbear that conservatives have co-opted to encompass a range of trends they think are unpopular with Americans. (One of the lead architects pushing the anti-critical race theory backlash, Christopher Rufo, a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute, a conservative think tank, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210609235759/https://twitter.com/realchrisrufo/status/1371541044592996352" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has said as much</a>.) This is particularly true for topics centered specifically around race. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“They’re worried about what happens when a reckoning takes hold in their kids’ schools where their kids might learn some things about American history — or about themselves or people like them — that are uncomfortable truths,” said Hakeem Jefferson, a FiveThirtyEight contributor and professor of political science at Stanford University. “This is merely another example of white Americans using schools as sites of their racial political projects, which set out to maintain dominance and do so by way of not telling the full truth of American history.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Many Americans still don’t know what the debate over critical race theory is really about at this point. Just 24 percent have heard “a lot” about it, 25 percent know “some” and 51 percent know little or nothing at all, according to a June <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000017a-36ee-d33b-a37f-3eee757a0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nrid=2fabe135-eaca-4acf-a36a-a0e8fde3c741&amp;nlid=630318" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult/Politico</a> poll. But tellingly, Republicans were more likely than Democrats to have seen, heard or read a lot about critical race theory, 30 percent versus 21 percent. What’s more, those Republicans familiar with critical race theory overwhelmingly dislike it — 78 percent have a negative opinion of it compared to 7 percent of Democrats. When asked to <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2021/06/23/critical-race-theory-polling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">describe</a> critical race theory in that same survey, one Republican respondent called critical race theory “a farce,” while another said it was a “Marxist proposal.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Considering how much more exposure Republicans have had to it — a <a href="https://www.mediamatters.org/fox-news/fox-has-mentioned-critical-race-theory-nearly-1300-times-past-35-months" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Media Matters analysis</a> shows Fox News has mentioned critical race theory 1,300 times in less than four months, and a query of data on the social media tool CrowdTangle <a href="https://twitter.com/KevinReuning/status/1401166962575749123" target="_blank" rel="noopener">from researchers</a> at Miami University and Wright State University found that the share of posts that mention critical race theory on the Facebook pages of local Republican parties has risen exponentially — the blowback among members of the GOP is not entirely surprising. It’s also not just the volume of coverage: The <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/msnbc-joy-reid-conflates-opposing-critical-race-theory-supporting-qanon-radicalized-parent-activists" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conservative media’s coverage</a> <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/opinion/tucker-carlson-critical-race-theory-crazed-ideologues-attack-hurt-children" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of critical race theory is</a> <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/cnn-critical-race-theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overwhelmingly negative</a>, too, as it’s <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/janicegassam/2021/05/09/the-war-on-critical-race-theory-continues-as-some-call-it-anti-white/?sh=6c0fba1373a7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decried by some on the right</a> as anti-white.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans have long fought specters within education that they claim threaten the American way of life. The current blowback against critical race theory follows in that tradition, but it also represents a broader transformation of the GOP into a populist party focused on waging culture wars. Though it may seem like a misguided crusade-du-jour, the tumult around critical race theory is both a reflection of the Republican Party’s past — and a glimpse at its future. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-happy-stoke-culture-wars-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-76546643</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-starting-make-climate-agenda-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78546775</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167292</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why The Gender Gap May Have Shrunk In The 2020 Election</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-gender-gap-may-have-shrunk-in-the-2020-election/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2020 Election</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Education</category>
			<category>Gender Gap</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>White Voters</category>
			<category>Women Voters</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong><div><hr><span></span></div>
</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s been said that women are from Venus and men are from Mars. Broadly speaking, that’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Men_Are_from_Mars,_Women_Are_from_Venus" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a laughable bit of pop psychology</a>, but there’s a measure of truth to it when it comes to politics. That’s because women have voted notably more Democratic than men in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/women-won-the-right-to-vote-100-years-ago-they-didnt-start-voting-differently-from-men-until-1980/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">every presidential race since 1980</a> — and the 2020 contest between Joe Biden and then-President Donald Trump <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-so-many-men-stuck-with-trump-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was no different</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new study of validated voters from the Pew Research Center</a> suggests, however, that the gender gap — or how women voted compared with men — meaningfully narrowed from 2016 to 2020. Pew found that 55 percent of women supported Biden compared with 48 percent of men, a gender gap of 7 percentage points.<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Calculating the gender gap is tricky, as it &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-2018-gender-gap-was-huge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;has been measured&lt;/a&gt; several ways. Sometimes it is calculated in terms of vote share margin (or the distance between the relative advantage one candidate or party has among men and the relative advantage that candidate or party has among women). The &lt;a href="https://cawp.rutgers.edu/facts/voters/gender_gap" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Center for American Women and Politics&lt;/a&gt; at Rutgers University recommends measuring the gender gap by the difference in male and female support for a particular candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>4</sup></a> This marked a 6-point reduction from the 13-point gap Pew found in 2016, when 39 percent of women and 52 percent of men backed Trump. And the gender gap seems to have shrunk for two main reasons. First, Biden significantly improved his standing among men — he won 48 percent of men versus Hillary Clinton’s 41 percent. Second, Trump significantly improved his standing among women — he won 44 percent of women in 2020 versus 39 percent in 2016.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s harder to pinpoint exactly <em>why</em> the gender gap shrunk from 2016 to 2020, but Pew’s numbers point to a couple of possible explanations, particularly <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2020/06/02/in-changing-u-s-electorate-race-and-education-remain-stark-dividing-lines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the influence that educational attainment has on vote choice</a>. Consider Biden’s improvement among college-educated men. He won 58 percent of this group, a giant leap from Clinton’s 49 percent in 2016. And his performance among college-educated men marked a 10-point advantage over how he did among men overall. Conversely for Trump, his gains among women were largely concentrated among those without a four-year college degree. His support among that group grew from 43 percent in 2016 to 50 percent in 2020. Taken together, this reflects the recent trend of Americans with higher education levels <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-know-about-how-white-and-latino-americans-voted-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shifting toward the Democrats</a>, and less-well-educated Americans <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2020/06/02/in-changing-u-s-electorate-race-and-education-remain-stark-dividing-lines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">moving toward the GOP</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This shift was especially notable among white voters,<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this article, we mean non-Hispanic white voters specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> as educational attainment <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2018/03/20/wide-gender-gap-growing-educational-divide-in-voters-party-identification/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has tended to be a larger cleavage</a> for them than for other racial or ethnic groups. Biden won 54 percent of white men with a college degree, up from Clinton’s 47 percent in 2016, while white women without a four-year degree moved in the other direction, as Trump’s support grew to 64 percent, up from 56 percent in 2016. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-electorate-78700694</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Yet, educational attainment isn’t the whole story, as white men without a college degree also shifted significantly toward Biden in 2020. Although Trump still won that group by a huge margin, Biden won 31 percent of them compared with Clinton’s 23 percent — an improvement that may have been foreshadowed by Biden’s performance in the presidential primary, in which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-is-joe-biden-remaking-the-2016-primary-map/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he did notably better</a> than Clinton in many parts of the country with higher shares of white voters without a college degree.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, another factor in the narrowing gender gap, especially for men, may have been the nature of Biden’s candidacy. As a white man in his late 70s, he <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-clintons-loss-paved-the-way-for-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may have simply come across</a> as <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2020/09/16/liberal-moderate-conservative-trump-biden-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more moderate</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-say-they-would-vote-for-a-woman-but/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may have also been less likely</a> to elicit sexist reactions among male voters than <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-unconscious-sexism-could-help-explain-trumps-win/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Clinton did in 2016</a>. This is reflected in the gains Biden made among men — there isn’t one clear pattern. Biden gained among men with and without a college degree. But he also gained among white men overall, winning 40 percent of that group, up from Clinton’s 32 percent in 2016. Additionally, Biden won 44 percent of married men — married voters <a href="http://www.inquiriesjournal.com/articles/127/the-effect-of-marriage-on-political-identification" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tend to be more conservative-leaning</a> than unmarried voters — which marked a major improvement over Clinton’s 32 percent in 2016. </p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-laws-let-americans-with-disabilities-vote-online-theyve-also-resurrected-the-debate-about-voting-access-vs-election-security/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A person helping a disabled person at a voting booth" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-614267646-4x3-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-614267646-4x3-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-614267646-4x3-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-614267646-4x3-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				New Laws Let Americans With Disabilities Vote Online. They’ve Also Resurrected The Debate About Voting Access vs. Election Security. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-laws-let-americans-with-disabilities-vote-online-theyve-also-resurrected-the-debate-about-voting-access-vs-election-security/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">More broadly, Biden won 52 percent of independents, up from Clinton’s 42 percent, and 16 percent of moderate or liberal Republicans, doubling Clinton’s 8 percent. In other words, in an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-a-biden-blowout-didnt-happen-and-why-a-2024-blowout-is-unlikely-too/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">era of political trench warfare</a>, elements of Biden’s identity and political profile may have been just enough for him to appeal to a broad swath of the electorate, narrowing the gender gap <em>and</em> winning the election in the process.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2021/07/2020-voter-demographics/619337/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other surveys don’t align as neatly</a> with some of Pew’s findings, and the reality is we’ll never know with absolute certainty how different groups voted last November. Nevertheless, this study offers another look at what happened in 2020 and the broader trends in the American electorate, including the possibility that the longstanding gender gap may have narrowed last November.</p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>In June, Republican pollster Echelon Insights <a href="https://echeloninsights.com/in-the-news/june-omnibus-quadrants/">examined how cultural and economic attitudes</a> relate to partisanship, and one survey question asked which sort of political party respondents would back if the U.S. had more than two major parties. Twenty-four percent of registered voters said they identified with a Trump-like nationalist party bent on stopping illegal immigration and “putting America first,” while 19 percent said they would support a more traditional conservative party that would “defend” free enterprise and “promote traditional family values.” Tellingly, 83 percent of nationalist party supporters and 78 percent of conservative party supporters backed Trump in the 2020 election. Meanwhile, 26 percent of voters said they would support a labor-oriented party looking to expand the social safety net, while 9 percent would back a green party promoting environmental, social and economic justice. Lastly, 10 percent said they would support a socially liberal but fiscally conservative “<a href="https://www.travel-industry-dictionary.com/acela-corridor.html">Acela</a>” party. At least 80 percent of those who identified with the latter three parties voted for Biden in 2020.</li><li>As vaccinations against COVID-19 become widespread and the economy reopens, <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/351932/americans-life-ratings-reach-record-high.aspx">Gallup’s measure</a> of how Americans evaluate their own well-being found a record 59.2 percent “thriving,” according to the pollster’s categorization. This represented a marked shift from the low of 46.4 percent who said the same in April 2020, when the coronavirus was causing shutdowns and thousands of deaths. Notably, though, Americans’ reported life satisfaction and anticipated well-being is higher now than it was even before the pandemic.</li><li><a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/most-americans-now-comfortable-being-unmasked-indoors-public">Newsy/Ipsos found</a> that a large majority of Americans were at least somewhat comfortable behaving as they did before the COVID-19 pandemic hit. Overall, 86 percent of employed workers said they were comfortable working outside the home, and 69 percent of all respondents said they were OK with being in a public place indoors without a mask. In terms of personal interactions, 64 percent said they were comfortable hugging another person, and 60 percent said they were comfortable shaking hands.</li><li>The latest weekly survey from <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/y4ic1h9zy9/econTabReport.pdf">The Economist/YouGov</a> asked Americans about climate change, and 61 percent said the world’s climate was changing due to human activity, while 30 percent said the climate was changing but not because of human activity (9 percent said the climate wasn’t changing at all). Considering the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-jay-inslee-could-win-the-2020-democratic-nomination/">political divide over climate change</a>, there were notable partisan splits on this question. Eighty-six percent of Democrats, 60 percent of independents and 32 percent of Republicans agreed that human activity was behind climate change, while 50 percent of Republicans, 32 percent of independents and 11 percent of Democrats said the climate was changing but humans weren’t responsible. Overall, though, the pollster didn’t find much movement on this question, as responses were similar back in <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2018/03/09/westerners-are-most-likely-have-felt-climate-chang">March 2018</a>.</li><li>According to <a href="https://thehill.com/hilltv/what-americas-thinking/561850-poll-51-percent-of-voters-say-indictment-of-trump-org-cfo">The Hill/HarrisX</a>, Americans are pretty evenly divided over why <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/manhattan-da-charges-trumps-company-cfo-tax-fraud/story?id=78535462">Trump Organization chief financial officer Allen Weisselberg</a> was indicted. Fifty-one percent of registered voters said the charges for tax fraud and other alleged crimes were politically motivated, while 49 percent said that prosecutors had uncovered criminal behavior. Unsurprisingly, 75 percent of Republicans said the indictment was politically motivated versus 70 percent of Democrats, who said the charges were due to criminal behavior.</li><li><a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/lifestyle/articles-reports/2021/07/07/wedding-traditions-poll">YouGov</a> asked Americans who have been married whether they thought certain marriage traditions should be preserved or dropped. Overall, most traditions were still widely popular, but pluralities of respondents did want to drop two long-standing practices: 50 percent wanted to quit having the bride promise to obey her husband (32 percent wanted to preserve that tradition), and 43 percent wanted to stop having the bride’s family pay for the wedding (25 percent wanted to preserve this). However, women — and not men — seemed to be the ones primarily driving this: 61 percent of women wanted to do away with promising to obey their husbands (versus 38 percent of men), and 52 percent didn’t want the bride’s family to have to pay for the wedding (versus 34 percent of men).</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=700" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a> 51.7 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 42.1 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of +9.6 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-a-shot-girl-summer-but-america-is-still-not-fully-back-to-normal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 52.1 percent approved and 42.2 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of +9.9 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 53.1 percent and a disapproval rating of 40.5 percent (a net approval rating of +12.6 points).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/pandemic-changed-sex-work-industry-fivethirtyeight-78621101</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167291</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Why The Conspiracy Theories Behind Jan. 6 Haven’t Gone Away</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-the-conspiracy-theories-behind-jan-6-havent-gone-away/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke and Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Capitol</category>
			<category>Conspiracy Theories</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Q Anon</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-the-conspiracy-theories-behind-jan-6-havent-gone-away/">
	<div data-podcast-id="312483" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Why The Conspiracy Theories Behind Jan. 6 Haven’t Gone Away">

					<span>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/galen-druke/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke and Kaleigh Rogers</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke and Kaleigh Rogers</a></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP1013836929.mp3?updated=1625787944"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">This week marks six months since pro-Trump extremists attacked the U.S. Capitol in an effort to stop Congress from certifying the electoral votes in the 2020 election. It was an attempt to overturn a free and fair election, as the people involved in the attack wrongly believed it was not free or fair. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, technology and politics reporter Kaleigh Rogers discusses the influence of conspiracy theories on the events that led to the Jan. 6 riot, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-people-fall-for-conspiracy-theories/">why people believe in conspiracy theories</a> in the first place and what it means for the future of American politics.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-electorate-78700694</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 00:44:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167290</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Whether Republicans Get Vaccinated Has A Lot To Do With If They Watch Fox News … Or OANN</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-extremes-of-the-gop-have-moved-beyond-fox-news/</link>
						<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Natalie Jackson</dc:creator>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Election Fraud</category>
			<category>Fox News</category>
			<category>News Media</category>
			<category>Newsmax</category>
			<category>OAN</category>
			<category>QAnon</category>
			<category>Republican Party</category>
			<category>Republicans</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">It’s no secret that <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/321116/americans-remain-distrustful-mass-media.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans <em>really</em> distrust the media</a>. In fact, that distrust is increasingly <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-being-anti-media-is-now-part-of-the-gop-identity/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an important part of their political identity.</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For a long time, understanding where Republicans primarily got their news was pretty straightforward, too. Unlike Democrats, Republicans, by and large, turn to <a href="https://www.journalism.org/2020/01/24/u-s-media-polarization-and-the-2020-election-a-nation-divided/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">just one source for all their news</a>: Fox News. But with <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/us/could-fox-news-lose-its-grip-on-far-right-conservative-viewers-to-newsmax-oan/ar-BB1c6fc4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the advent of news networks even further to the right</a> than Fox News — One America News Network and Newsmax — that’s changing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">OANN and Newsmax still <a href="https://www.journalism.org/2021/03/23/large-majorities-of-newsmax-and-oan-news-consumers-also-go-to-fox-news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">make up just a small sliver of Americans’ overall media diet</a>, and there’s, of course, a lot of overlap in viewership between those two networks and Fox News. But there are some signs that OANN and Newsmax are replacing Fox News as the primary news sources for at least some Republicans. I’m the research director at the Public Religion Research Institute, and <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/prri-ifyc-covid-vaccine-religion-report/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in a March survey we conducted with Interfaith Youth Core on COVID-19 and conspiracy beliefs</a>, we found that Fox News had fallen in popularity among Republicans, with just 27 percent saying it was their go-to news source versus <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/trumpism-after-trump-how-fox-news-structures-republican-attitudes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">40 percent last September</a>. What’s more, 7 percent of Republicans listed a far-right news network they preferred instead. That means they took the time to type in an “other” response in our text-box field, as it was not provided as a choice.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some respondents listed other conservative media outlets like The Blaze, The Daily Wire or The Epoch Times, but OANN and Newsmax were by far the most commonly provided outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> Only a handful did this in September 2020.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be sure, this shift is small — Fox News is still king among Republicans. But the growing popularity of OANN and Newsmax is important: According to our research, Republicans’ stances on certain issues might be better predicted by their television news habits than by whether they identify as conservative, moderate or liberal.<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be sure, we did find a correlation between ideology and which news sources Republicans trust, with Republicans who turn to far-right news sources identifying as more conservative, but even after accounting for ideology and demographics in our analysis, we found that which media sources Republicans trust explain at least some of the variation we see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We found in our survey, for instance, that Republicans who got their news from OANN or Newsmax were generally more extreme in their beliefs around QAnon and in their refusal to get vaccinated than those who got their news from Fox News. Meanwhile, Fox News Republicans were often more in line with Republicans who got their news from other mainstream outlets.<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We included all major broadcast (ABC, CBS, NBC), local television, and public broadcast networks (PBS, CSPAN), in addition to CNN and MSNBC in our “mainstream” news category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> Considering<a href="https://www.prri.org/research/trumpism-after-trump-how-fox-news-structures-republican-attitudes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"></a> Fox News Republicans <a href="https://www.prri.org/research/trumpism-after-trump-how-fox-news-structures-republican-attitudes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were once touted as the Republicans with the most extreme views</a>, this signals a real change in the conservative media landscape and suggests that media habits are as important for understanding Republican voters as ideology. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-electorate-78700694</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Some of the most substantial daylight we observed between Fox News Republicans and far-right news Republicans was on their beliefs around conspiracy theories — especially the core beliefs of QAnon. Overall, 23 percent of Republicans mostly or completely agree with the core QAnon tenet that “the government, media, and financial worlds in the U.S. are controlled by a group of Satan-worshipping pedophiles who run a global child sex trafficking operation.” But Republicans who trust mainstream news sources or Fox News were actually the least likely to believe in the main QAnon conspiracy theory, with just 19 percent and 17 percent, respectively. Meanwhile, Republicans who don’t watch television news, which notably includes those who get news solely from online sources, were considerably more likely to believe in a system run by Satanist pedophiles (27 percent). But by far, the Republicans who were most likely to believe in QAnon were those who trusted far-right news sources (39 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We found a similar gap in Republicans’ willingness to get a COVID-19 vaccine. Overall, Republicans were among those most likely to say they’re hesitant or resistant to getting vaccinated. But 58 percent of Republicans who get their news from mainstream outlets and 54 percent of Republicans who get their news from Fox News said they had either already received a dose of a COVID-19 vaccine or would get vaccinated as soon as possible. Just 32 percent of Republicans who get their news from far-right news sources said the same. What’s more, 32 percent of these Republicans said they would refuse the vaccine, versus 11 percent of Republicans who get their news from mainstream outlets and 16 percent of Republicans who get their news from Fox News. That said, all three groups of Republicans expressed similar levels of hesitancy about getting vaccinated — 31 percent of mainstream news Republicans and 29 percent of Fox News Republicans said they weren’t sure if they’d get vaccinated, compared to 37 percent of far-right news Republicans who said the same.</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-being-anti-media-is-now-part-of-the-gop-identity/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="An elephant sitting on top of a broken CRT TV. The guts of the TV are spilled out in front of the television set." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/ANTI-MEDIA-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/ANTI-MEDIA-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/ANTI-MEDIA-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/ANTI-MEDIA-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Why Being ‘Anti-Media’ Is Now Part Of The GOP Identity <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-being-anti-media-is-now-part-of-the-gop-identity/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">There was also less of a difference between Fox News Republicans and far-right news Republicans when it came to the lie that the 2020 election was stolen from former President Donald Trump. The vast majority of both groups — 86 percent of Fox News Republicans and 96 percent of far-right news Republicans — said the election was stolen, compared to 66 percent of Republicans who do not watch television news and only 44 percent of mainstream news Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This underscores just how <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/11/30/upshot/republican-voters-election-doubts.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">central the “Big Lie” and baseless allegations of election fraud</a> are to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-republicans-still-wont-accept-that-biden-won/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republicans’ political identity</a>. While media diets explain some differences that Republicans have, there is still an overlap between those who trust far-right news outlets versus Fox News — especially where Trump is concerned. That said, we did find differences in how strongly Republicans believed the election had been stolen from Trump based on their media preferences: Forty-six percent of Fox News Republicans <em>completely </em>agreed that the election was stolen (whereas 40 percent mostly<em> </em>agreed), but among far-right news Republicans, 74 percent completely<em> </em>agreed (22 percent mostly agreed).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Media preferences don’t explain all the differences we see among Republicans; as noted, on the question of the “Big Lie,” Fox News Republicans are very much not in sync with Republicans who get their news from mainstream news outlets, even if they do hold this belief less strongly than Republicans who get their news from far-right outlets. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Clearly, though, Republicans are sorting by news sources in a way that independents and Democrats are not,<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We did not find such effects found among the media sources measured for independents and Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a> and that’s shaping at least some of their beliefs in ways that ideology and partisanship alone don’t explain. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We don’t yet know whether Republicans are choosing their different media sources based on preexisting views, or whether the media sources are actively shaping those views. It’s likely that both forces are at play. But what we do know is that far-right news sources are attracting a small but growing proportion of Republicans — many of whom either already held or developed extreme views — while Fox News, once the go-to source for many on the fringe of the party, may no longer be a hotbed for some of the GOP’s most extreme beliefs.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-starting-make-climate-agenda-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78546775</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167289</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Did New York’s Mayoral Primary Tell Us About Ranked-Choice Voting?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorks-mayoral-primary-has-put-ranked-choice-voting-under-the-microscope/</link>
						<dc:creator>Sarah Frostenson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</dc:creator>
			<category>Election Reform</category>
			<category>Maine</category>
			<category>New York City Mayoral Election</category>
			<category>Ranked-choice voting</category>
			<category>Slack Chat</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main"><strong> </strong>Welcome to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/slack-chat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politics chat</a>. The transcript below has been lightly edited.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/sarah-frostenson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah Frostenson</a>, politics editor): Things got a bit harried in the New York City mayoral primary election last Tuesday afternoon after the Board of Elections <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/29/nyregion/adams-garcia-wiley-mayor-ranked-choice.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accidentally counted 135,000 test ballots</a> and released results including those ballots. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Board removed the results from its website that evening citing a “discrepancy,” but the erroneous results had shown the race between front-runner Eric Adams and his closest contenders, Kathryn Garcia and Maya Wiley, significantly tightening. This, in turn, sparked accusations around the role ranked-choice voting played in this error, as <a href="https://www.politico.com/states/new-york/albany/story/2020/11/21/top-mayoral-candidate-admonishes-new-voting-system-amidst-efforts-to-delay-it-1337593" target="_blank" rel="noopener">candidates such as Adams</a> are not <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/19/nyregion/yang-garcia-endorsement.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fans of the system</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But while ranked-choice voting isn’t the culprit for last week’s mishap — it was Board mismanagement — it did serve to expose some of the debates around ranked-choice voting, including whether it’s a fair system of voting and whether voters even want it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s start there. Why <em>is</em> ranked-choice voting such a hot topic of debate?</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-electorate-78700694</p>


<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alex Samuels</a>, politics reporter): Well, for one, it’s still a relatively new system in the U.S., and there are <a href="https://www.politicopro.com/blog/2020-ranked-choice-voting-explained" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conflicting theories</a> on whether it is beneficial (i.e., it helps ensure the winner has the approval of the majority of voters) or detrimental (i.e., it is too complicated or expensive).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But right now, at a time when there’s disillusionment with our election system, the Board of Elections error provides fodder for former President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/may/24/republicans-2020-election-poll-trump-biden" target="_blank" rel="noopener">and his supporters</a> that U.S. elections are inherently fraudulent or illegitimate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geoffrey Skelley</a>, elections analyst): It’s a change to how we conduct elections, and in a country where most elections are won by the candidate with the most votes without any question about secondary preferences, this is a big change! </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.fairvote.org/where_is_ranked_choice_voting_used" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York City is also far and away the largest jurisdiction</a> to employ ranked-choice voting, so the system is very much under the microscope because it’s no longer a curiosity used by a few cities and Maine. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Do we have any sense of whether New Yorkers supported making their elections ranked-choice voting?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Well, New Yorkers overwhelmingly backed the referendum to implement ranked-choice voting in 2019 — <a href="https://vote.nyc/sites/default/files/pdf/election_results/2019/20191105General%20Election/00050100000Citywide%20ELECTIONS%20Citywide%20Recap.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">74 percent voted in favor</a>. Granted, 2019 was a low-turnout election in New York considering no major offices were on the ballot. Still, that was a pretty overwhelming vote in support of ranked-choice voting. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex: </strong>Before the Board of Elections error, <a href="https://www.ny1.com/nyc/all-boroughs/decision-2021/2021/06/09/exclusive--80-percent-of-voters-comfortable-using-ranked-choice-voting--ny1-ipsos-poll-finds" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a NY1/Ipsos poll</a> found that 80 percent of likely Democratic voters said they were comfortable using ranked-choice voting. The New York Times also <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/21/nyregion/nyc-voters-ranked-choice.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">interviewed dozens of early voters</a> in New York and found that many people were OK with ranked-choice voting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And a day before the Board of Elections fiasco, a poll from Common Cause New York and Rank The Vote NYC found <a href="https://newyork.cbslocal.com/2021/06/28/poll-finds-new-yorkers-overwhelmingly-support-ranked-choice-voting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than 75 percent of voters</a> want to use a ranked system again.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> OK, so it seems fair to say that polls show that New Yorkers overwhelmingly support the idea of ranked-choice voting. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why then has ranked-choice voting emerged as a flashpoint in the race with Adams speaking out against it?</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/eric-adamss-lead-in-the-new-york-mayoral-primary-was-just-too-big-to-overcome/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="Eric Adams standing at a podium with his campaign sign on the front of it." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1325261913_4x3.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1325261913_4x3.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1325261913_4x3.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1325261913_4x3.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Eric Adams’s Lead In The New York Mayoral Primary Was Just Too Big To Overcome <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/eric-adamss-lead-in-the-new-york-mayoral-primary-was-just-too-big-to-overcome/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nathaniel Rakich</a>, elections analyst): I think it’s as simple as this: Adams would very likely have won under a first-past-the-post system (31 percent of New York Democrats <a href="https://web.enrboenyc.us/rcv/024306_1.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ranked him first</a>, while only 21 percent ranked Wiley first and only 20 percent ranked Garcia first), while Garcia came very close to winning under ranked-choice voting. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, if Adams’s chances were improved by ranked-choice voting, then I think he’d be singing a different tune.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Adams’s campaign <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2020/12/democrats-election-ranked-choice-voting-new-york/617461/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spoken out against ranked-choice voting</a> and even <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/york-city-leaders-sue-postpone-ranked-choice-voting/story?id=74629165" target="_blank" rel="noopener">backed a lawsuit seeking to halt its implementation</a> since he has argued that the system disenfranchises both non-English speakers and voters of color, who might not have the time or resources to properly research every candidate or how the new system works. (According to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-were-watching-in-the-new-york-city-mayoral-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our previous analysis of 2019 U.S. Census data</a>, 62 percent of New York City citizens of voting age are nonwhite.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it’s not entirely clear that ranked-choice voting affects voters of color negatively, at least on the ballot. For example, in California, the voting-reform advocacy group FairVote found that in districts with ranked-choice voting, <a href="https://infogram.com/ranked-choice-voting-and-racial-minority-voting-rights-1hxr4zgwmpk52yo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">plurality-white districts that were not white-majority elected a nonwhite representative 60 percent of the time</a>. Before ranked-choice voting, it was only 35 percent of the time.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> On the question of turnout, though, this <a href="https://news.sfsu.edu/news-story/ranked-choice-voting-linked-lower-voter-turnout" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2015 study of San Francisco’s mayoral races</a> found that ranked-choice voting did, in fact, decrease turnout among Black and white voters, younger voters and voters who lacked a high school education, while the same wasn’t true of more experienced or educated voters, perhaps backing up some of Adams’s claims.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How mixed is the research on whether ranked-choice voting negatively affects voters of color?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> It’s definitely still an open question to whether ranked-choice voting can help or hurt candidates of color. While <a href="https://19thnews.org/2021/06/how-ranked-choice-voting-elevates-women-and-people-of-color-seeking-office/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some experts say the former</a>, others argue the system could lead to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/02/10/us/politics/ranked-choice-voting.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a lone candidate of color getting edged out</a> by opponents who conspire against him or her. As far as voters of color go, though, I’m less clear on that.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There is definitely an age gap in who seems to understand how to use ranked-choice voting. A <a href="https://cpb-us-w2.wpmucdn.com/web.sas.upenn.edu/dist/7/538/files/2019/07/McDaniel-RCV-Voter-Turnout-Revised-ESRA-2019.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2019 research paper</a> from Jason McDaniel, a professor at San Francisco State University, argues that ranked-choice voting leads to lower voter turnout overall. He cites three researchers who looked into the implementation of ranked-choice voting in Minneapolis, and they found that while most voters understood ranked-choice voting “perfectly” or “fairly well,” older voters were less likely than younger voters to understand the system. Higher education levels were also associated with a better understanding of ranked-choice voting.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, as Alex noted, some research has found a pretty pronounced age effect, but <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdfdirect/10.1111/ssqu.12651" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other research</a> has <a href="https://www.cogitatiopress.com/politicsandgovernance/article/download/3913/3913" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pushed back</a> on the idea that nonwhite voters are more likely to struggle with ranked-choice voting than voting for only one candidate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> What about other research on ranked-choice voting? That is, does it <a href="https://www.fairvote.org/rcvbenefits" target="_blank" rel="noopener">help reduce partisanship</a> in elections, as proponents claim? Or make elections less acrimonious?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich</strong>: It doesn’t really live up to the promise of making campaigns less acrimonious. The Democratic primary for New York City mayor was a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/21/nyregion/nyc-mayor-primary.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nasty affair</a>, and there was still plenty of negative campaigning in the 2018 Maine gubernatorial primary, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maine-is-trying-out-a-new-way-to-run-elections-but-will-it-survive-the-night/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as I wrote at the time</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Although as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/19/nyregion/yang-garcia-endorsement.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we saw with Garcia and Andrew Yang</a>, ranked-choice voting can lead to candidate alliances that <em>could</em> be an indication of less negativity in a way. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>It’s true that ranked-choice voting may encourage minor candidates to play nice with one another in hopes of picking up the others’ supporters, but it ultimately doesn’t remove the incentive to tear down the front-runner. At the end of the day, a lower-polling candidate still needs to overtake the front-runner to win. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> What about this idea that ranked-choice voting boosts some of the non-major-party vote share? That is, by having multiple choices, voters are encouraged to vote for candidates based on their sincere beliefs versus just voting for the candidate they think will win.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Does ranked-choice voting live up to that promise?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich: </strong>There is some evidence that ranked-choice voting helps third-party candidates, which could be an indication that it makes voters more comfortable voting for their true first choices instead of feeling like they have to choose between Democrats and Republicans for their vote to matter. MIT political scientist Jesse Clark has <a href="https://medium.com/mit-election-lab/the-effect-of-ranked-choice-voting-in-maine-44bbb7374847" target="_blank" rel="noopener">studied Maine’s elections under ranked-choice voting</a> and found that non-major-party candidates gained 5-6 percentage points because of ranked-choice voting. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, to Nathaniel’s point, <a href="https://www.maine.gov/sos/cec/elec/results/results18.html#Nov6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the 2018 election</a> for Maine’s 2nd Congressional District, about 8 percent of the vote initially went to third-party candidates, but after reallocation in the ranked-choice voting process, Democrat Jared Golden ultimately narrowly defeated Republican Rep. Bruce Poliquin. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, ranked-choice voting does seem to boost third-party vote share, as that 8 percent figure would be high for a more typical winner-take-all election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> FairVote did find, however, that ranked-choice voting doesn’t necessarily increase the chances of <a href="https://www.fairvote.org/third_party_and_independent_representation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a third- or independent-party candidate winning</a>. Rather, the benefits, they argue, is that it allows third-party and minor-candidate supporters to rank their preferred candidate first without feeling like their votes are wasted — as third-party votes might be in a more traditional election. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/politics-podcast-summer-mailbag-edition-fivethirtyeight-78499147</p>


<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, the most obvious point in ranked-choice voting’s favor is that it can produce a winner who is truly the preference of a majority of voters in situations when one side’s vote would otherwise be split by a strong third-party challenger.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Golden-Poliquin race is a great example of that. Even though Poliquin won a plurality of first-place votes, it was pretty clear that, once you factored in the preferences of third-party voters, a majority of voters in Maine’s 2nd District that year liked Golden better than Poliquin.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, this kind of results inversion doesn’t happen very often. FairVote has <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1lU6viuXfay323Gl6zkH5itwmrUIUo9rAzalK_ntu-ZY/edit#gid=1126870020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tracked</a> 398 single-winner ranked-choice voting races in the U.S. since 2004, and 97 percent of them (383) were won by the candidate who got a plurality of first-place votes. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Nathaniel, I’ve seen some opponents of the system claim that ranked-choice voting doesn’t necessarily lead to <a href="https://qz.com/1676718/the-pros-and-cons-of-ranked-choice-voting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a candidate who represents the majority</a>. For example, some voters might end up with their ballots essentially eliminated and <a href="https://cpb-us-w2.wpmucdn.com/u.osu.edu/dist/e/1083/files/2014/12/ElectoralStudies-2fupfhd.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no say in the final outcome</a> if they ranked three out of five candidates, for example, and all three were eliminated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In a 2016 essay, writer Simon Waxman <a href="https://democracyjournal.org/arguments/ranked-choice-voting-is-not-the-solution/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">argues some of the same points</a>. “[T]here are reasons for skepticism when it comes to [ranked-choice voting] — and not just RCV itself, but the larger notion that what is broken in American politics, and therefore what will fix it, is procedure.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Another concern is that ranked-choice voting <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2519723" target="_blank" rel="noopener">risks tiring voters out</a> — what’s known as “ballot fatigue” — if they have to rank, say, five candidates for a large number of offices, that could lead them to leave some spots blank or to not even finish voting for all offices or other ballot questions.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, no voting system is perfect. Imagine, too, a scenario where there are three candidates: a liberal, a moderate and a conservative. The moderate might be the second choice of both liberal and conservative voters, but if the moderate doesn’t also get more first-place votes than one of the other two, the moderate will be the first one eliminated under ranked-choice voting! That said, ranked-choice voting does seem less imperfect than a straight-up plurality system like most of the U.S. uses — at least when it comes to determining the rightful winner. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are other ways in which ranked-choice voting may be worse, though. For instance, the MIT researcher Clark also found that ranked-choice voting in Maine “produced significantly lower levels of voter confidence, voter satisfaction, and ease of use. It also increased the perception that the voting process was slanted against the respondent’s party.” As we mentioned earlier, that kind of voter confusion could lead to depressed turnout. Plus, further undermining public confidence in our elections is the last thing we need right now.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the other hand, ranked-choice voting is a new innovation in most of the jurisdictions now using it, including Maine. So I’d guess that those problems could be mitigated once voters start getting used to the system. Better voter education and ballot design could also help.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, I think it’s too early in ranked-choice voting’s lifespan to reach a definitive conclusion about it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Right, as Nathaniel said, ranking candidates is definitely more complicated than selecting just one. But I don’t think there’s sufficient evidence to say it’s a barrier to voting. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In Maine, turnout for both the <a href="https://www.pressherald.com/2018/06/12/new-voting-system-credited-for-good-primary-turnout/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2018</a> and <a href="https://bangordailynews.com/2020/11/25/politics/maines-2020-election-turnout-was-among-highest-in-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 elections</a> — the first elections to use ranked-choice voting — was incredibly strong. And in New York, too, <a href="https://www.thecity.nyc/2021/6/27/22552850/voter-turnout-2021-nyc-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">primary turnout was incredibly high</a>; plus, as I mentioned earlier, New Yorkers have said they found <a href="https://queenseagle.com/all/queens-voters-say-ranked-choice-is-as-easy-as-one-two-threefour-five" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ranked-choice voting to be pretty easy</a> and <a href="https://nypost.com/2021/06/22/nyc-voters-like-easy-ranked-choice-voting-on-primary-day/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">straightforward</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Personally, I think the evidence suggests that other factors are more important to turnout than the use or non-use of ranked-choice voting. Turnout was super high all across the country in 2018 and 2020, not just in Maine. (It remains to be seen whether that will carry into the 2021-22 cycle.)</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="Artwork of a wrecking ball blasting through a wall that looks like the American flag." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/DEMOCRACY-EFFED-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Why The Two-Party System Is Effing Up U.S. Democracy <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-two-party-system-is-wrecking-american-democracy/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> It does seem as if ranked-choice voting could especially help in primary elections such as New York’s, where there are multiple candidates on the ballot and voters might not know that much about all the candidates. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Imagine if the Democratic primary for president in 2020 had been a ranked-choice election … or the Republican primary for president in 2016. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Well, a few states did use ranked-choice voting in the 2020 Democratic primary. Voters in Alaska, Hawaii, Kansas and Wyoming <a href="https://www.fairvote.org/where_is_ranked_choice_voting_used" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cast ranked-choice ballots</a> in their party-run primaries (their states didn’t have state-run primaries available to use), but all of those states finished voting after the nomination race was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-is-joe-biden-remaking-the-2016-primary-map/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">essentially over in late March</a>, which makes it hard to say just how those rules might have shaped the contest.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, I’m not sure if there’s been any primary-specific research, Sarah, but it stands to reason that ranked-choice voting will be more powerful in races with more than two strong candidates, or multiple candidates who come from the same side of the political spectrum. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, a far-left candidate, a center-left candidate, and a right candidate. Or a Republican primary with four serious contenders.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it may also not make a huge difference there either. The Virginia GOP just used ranked-choice voting to <a href="https://www.vpap.org/electionresults/20210508/governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pick its governor, lieutenant governor and attorney general candidates</a> for this fall, and the first-round leader wound up being the final winner in all three races. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah: </strong>Yeah, it’s interesting considering there are some downsides to ranked-choice voting — or at least mixed evidence on its effectiveness in solving some of our underlying election problems — that so many municipalities and states are trying ranked-choice voting out. Why?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Voters seem interested in trying it out! (Maybe because they perceive that the current system isn’t producing great results, given how polarized and dysfunctional our politics is.) Maine, New York City, and Alaska, three of the largest American jurisdictions to adopt ranked-choice voting so far, have all done so via ballot measure in the last few years. (Although Massachusetts also <em>rejected</em> a ballot measure to adopt ranked-choice voting <a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2020/11/04/question-two-ranked-choice-voting-massachusetts-no" target="_blank" rel="noopener">just last year</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> And in Australia, for example, which uses ranked-choice voting prolifically, <a href="https://bangordailynews.com/2018/08/28/opinion/a-century-of-ranked-choice-voting-in-australia-offers-lessons-for-maine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">people seem to really like it</a>. The 2018 election marked the 100th anniversary of ranked-choice voting in its national elections. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Motivations for why cities or states have adopted ranked-choice voting may differ, but fundamentally it does seem like an issue if a city or state often elects someone with less than 50 percent of the vote. Such a result makes it harder to say a candidate has the true backing of the electorate. In Maine, for instance, the state had often elected governors <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/compare.php?year=2018&amp;fips=23&amp;f=0&amp;off=5&amp;elect=0&amp;type=state" target="_blank" rel="noopener">with less than 50 percent</a>, which was <a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/6/12/17448450/maine-ranked-choice-voting-paul-lepage-instant-runoff-2018-midterms" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one reason</a> for the drive to implement ranked-choice voting there. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> (Ironically, though, the ranked-choice voting system there doesn’t apply to gubernatorial general elections — just primaries and federal general elections — <a href="https://legislature.maine.gov/lawlibrary/ranked-choice-voting-in-maine/9509" target="_blank" rel="noopener">due to a ruling</a> by the Maine Supreme Court.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Logically that makes sense to me, Geoffrey, but it’s interesting how that runs counter to the research Nathaniel cited from Clark finding that ranked-choice voting in Maine “produced significantly lower levels of voter confidence, voter satisfaction, and ease of use.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It raises the question of whether any voting reform can really solve some of the underlying ills in America’s electoral system.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Well, the challenge is voters wouldn’t necessarily know they felt that way about ranked-choice voting without first trying it out. And again, as Nathaniel has pointed out, this is a very new thing. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s see where people are in a decade. Not all voters <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2020-10-11/us-election-voting-changed-by-secret-australian-ballot-history/12726686" target="_blank" rel="noopener">necessarily liked</a> the secret ballot in the late 19th century (<a href="http://umich.edu/~lawrace/disenfranchise1.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sometimes with very good reason</a>), but we all got pretty used to it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Deep cut.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Sharing Waxman’s piece again where <a href="https://democracyjournal.org/arguments/ranked-choice-voting-is-not-the-solution/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he essentially argues</a> that ranked-choice voting is not the answer to fixing electoral woes.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> I’m not sure anyone is claiming that ranked-choice voting can fix democracy all on its own. Issues of polarization and divisiveness run deeper than that, right into the hearts of voters themselves. The real question is whether it’s better than a first-past-the-post system.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Is it, Nathaniel?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> It does seem like ranked-choice voting has momentum. As I mentioned, several new jurisdictions have adopted it in recent years.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">New York City is an important test case, though, because so many political and media elites live there. So a bad experience with ranked-choice voting there could halt that momentum. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Is there anything we’ve learned so far in the New York City experiment that helps our understanding of ranked-choice voting moving forward? Do we think more states or cities will move to adopt it?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Eh, I’m less inclined to say yes after the Board of Elections snafu.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, Alex, but it’s important to note that the Board screw-up and the delay in getting results weren’t due to ranked-choice voting per se. And as you’ve mentioned, New Yorkers seem to be satisfied with the actual voting experience.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Maybe it will come down to whether the media covers this post-election turbulence as a side effect of ranked-choice voting or not. Hopefully they won’t, because that’s not fair.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Right, Nathaniel, but I think the error might have repercussions beyond New York — even though the error was Board-specific. Generally speaking, the state of public confidence in elections nationwide right now is at a record low, per <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/321665/confidence-accuracy-election-matches-record-low.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup</a>. So when a highly publicized event, like the New York City mayor’s race, takes place and there are <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/06/30/politics/board-of-elections-nyc-analysis/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">serious errors in counting ballots</a>, that can add more anxiety in the public mind about whether elections (or ranked-choice voting) can be trusted or not. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/pandemic-changed-sex-work-industry-fivethirtyeight-78621101</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167288</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New Laws Let Americans With Disabilities Vote Online. They’ve Also Resurrected The Debate About Voting Access vs. Election Security.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-laws-let-americans-with-disabilities-vote-online-theyve-also-resurrected-the-debate-about-voting-access-vs-election-security/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Disability</category>
			<category>Voting</category>
			<category>Voting Rights</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">Since the dawn of the internet, someone has inevitably raised this question every election cycle: Why can’t we vote online? (The question was particularly apt in 2020, when states had to grapple with how to run an election during a pandemic.) And every time, election security experts dutifully answer that there is currently <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-a-voting-app-wont-solve-our-problems-this-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no technological way to guarantee a secure online ballot</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Despite that, some Americans <em>are</em> able to vote online — namely, military and overseas voters — and they have been for more than a decade. Now a handful of states have started expanding this access to include voters with disabilities. Colorado <a href="https://leg.colorado.gov/bills/sb21-188" target="_blank" rel="noopener">passed a law</a> in May allowing voters with certain disabilities to return ballots online, <a href="https://www.leg.state.nv.us/App/NELIS/REL/81st2021/Bill/7442/Overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada</a> passed a similar law in June and other states like <a href="https://www.weirtondailytimes.com/news/local-news/2020/09/military-overseas-disabled-voters-have-electronic-absentee-voting-option/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">West Virginia</a> are piloting the option. Last month in North Carolina, a federal judge <a href="https://www.acb.org/NC-accessible-voting-2021" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ordered the state to permanently expand access</a> to online ballot return to voters with vision disabilities — access that was temporarily granted for the November 2020 election, after a coalition of groups including the North Carolina Council of the Blind filed a lawsuit against the state board of elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These new laws have reinvigorated a longstanding debate over whether there should be exceptions to the no-online-voting stance. That debate gets at one of the core tensions in election infrastructure: Voting access and voting security are both essential for democracy, but prioritizing one often comes at the expense of the other. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“There is a conflict typically between accessibility and security,” said the University of Florida’s Juan Gilbert, who chairs the computer, information science and engineering department there and studies accessible voting systems. “If you think about it, the most secure thing in the world, whatever it is, is going to be the most inaccessible thing, just by definition.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since 1986, the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act has required U.S. states and territories to <a href="https://www.justice.gov/crt/uniformed-and-overseas-citizens-absentee-voting-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">allow military and overseas voters to cast absentee ballots</a>. In the 2000s, UOCAVA was updated to include a provision so voters could receive their ballots electronically (to be returned by mail). Though there was never any federal mandate to do so, over the years some<strong> </strong>states began expanding their rules to also allow this group of voters to return their ballots online, by email or through web portals.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But just because the infrastructure is there doesn’t mean it’s ready for mass use. Voting security experts have consistently argued the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-a-voting-app-wont-solve-our-problems-this-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">technology is not yet advanced enough</a> to allow for a private, secure online voting system. The question is whether even a small allowance for voters serving in the military, residing overseas or living with a disability makes our elections too vulnerable. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The benefits are clear. Michelle Bishop, the voter access and engagement manager for the National Disability Rights Network, said having the option to return ballots electronically could break down some of the myriad barriers that voters with disabilities face. “There are existing challenges in every step of the process,” she said, “from the time you get registered to the time you cast your ballot.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For Christopher Bell, the president of the North Carolina Council of the Blind who helped lead last year’s lawsuit against the state’s board of elections, the pandemic highlighted the need for this access. He typically votes in person but like millions of other Americans was less keen on that option during the pandemic. Yet the only alternative — absentee voting by mail — didn’t work for Bell, a blind voter.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“A paper ballot means you have to get a sighted person to sit down and help you record your vote. A sighted person can vote absentee privately and independently, but a blind person could not,” Bell said. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After the online return was made available to voters with sight disabilities, Bell was able to vote from home. He received his ballot through an online portal, completed it on his own computer using text-to-voice software and returned the ballot electronically through the same portal. Then, an election worker at the local precinct office printed a paper version of the ballot to be counted. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not just voters with sight disabilities who may need to cast their ballots online. Voters with physical disabilities that prevent them from holding or manipulating a paper ballot can’t vote absentee privately either if the only option is by mail. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Advocates of electronic ballot return also say that not all voters with a disability will choose to use this method — many are able to or prefer to vote in person or by mail — but having that option is key for voters who would otherwise be disenfranchised. Because so few voters will use this method, making it a less tempting target, advocates argue the risk of an outside attack is lower (though some security experts disagree). Likewise, the risk of overturning a result is lower too. Bishop called it a “limited, calculated risk.” Critics, however, are concerned not only about the inherent risks of voting online but also about the specific risks of the technology typically used. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democracy Live, a Seattle-based voting-technology company, developed a cloud-based portal that many states currently use to receive absentee ballots from overseas and military voters, and that is now being extended to voters with disabilities. But cybersecurity experts at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and University of Michigan said its platform, OmniBallot, <a href="https://internetpolicy.mit.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/OmniBallot.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has critical flaws</a> that make it vulnerable to attacks and risk voters’ privacy. Bryan Finney, the founder and president of Democracy Live, told FiveThirtyEight that no voting system is 100 percent secure but that the company is constantly working to improve OmniBallot. He noted that OmniBallot uses the Amazon cloud platform, which is also used by the <a href="https://thehill.com/policy/technology/496624-dhs-moving-biometrics-database-to-amazon-cloud" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Department of Homeland Security</a> and the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/federal/us-intelligence-community/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CIA</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some experts believe, however, that there are options that don’t require compromising security <em>or</em> access. Gilbert, from the University of Florida, has spent his career investigating ways to bridge the gap between these two necessities and has developed technological solutions he says could provide alternatives to online voting. One principle of his technology is universality: having all voters, regardless of ability, cast ballots using the same technology, which would allow security and accessibility to work in tandem. Take, for example, his concept called televoting. All absentee voters would send their ballots electronically and watch via livestream as they are printed at a local voting precinct. A machine would both show and read aloud what’s marked on the ballot for the voter’s verification before it is submitted, according to Gilbert. If the machine was hacked to say you voted for candidate A when the ballot says you voted for candidate B, for instance, all the sighted voters would notice it.  </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The machine wouldn’t know if I’m blind or sighted, it would just read it back. If it reads something different and I’m sighted, we know there’s a problem,” Gilbert said. “That’s why universal design works. If people with varying abilities all use the same thing, it’s hard to target them.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, so far, Gilbert’s ideas haven’t gained much traction, whereas the much simpler — but also riskier — option of online voting is spreading. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, trying to balance security, privacy and access is a tricky puzzle to solve, and technology hasn’t quite nailed it yet. Make our voting systems super-secure and we risk disenfranchising voters. Make them ultra-accessible and we risk undermining our elections. Bell, from the North Carolina Council of the Blind, is keenly aware of the security risks at play but said preventing voters with disabilities from having these tools doesn’t solve the problem alone. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We need to fix the issue,” he said. “But don’t try to fix it on the backs of people with disabilities.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>CORRECTION (July 7, 2021, 10:38 a.m.):</strong> A previous version of this article stated that the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act mandated the electronic return of ballots from overseas and military voters. While some states allow electronic return, the federal act requires only the option to electronically transmit blank ballots to voters.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167287</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>We Have A Lot Of Data From The 2020 Election. Here’s What It Means For Democratic And Republican Strategies.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/we-have-a-lot-of-data-from-the-2020-election-it-points-to-more-highly-competitive-elections/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke， Sarah Frostenson， Alex Samuels and Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Video</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p>In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses the most notable data points from a <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">verified voter survey</a> by the Pew Research Center and what it means for Democratic and Republican strategies going forward. They also talk about ranked-choice voting and why the final vote count in New York City’s Democratic mayoral primary has been delayed.</p>
<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorks-mayoral-primary-has-put-ranked-choice-voting-under-the-microscope/?cid=_inlinerelated">[Related: What Did New York’s Mayoral Primary Tell Us About Ranked-Choice Voting?]</a></p>
<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>
<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/pandemic-changed-sex-work-industry-fivethirtyeight-78621101</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 03:16:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167286</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Eric Adams’s Lead In The New York Mayoral Primary Was Just Too Big To Overcome</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/eric-adamss-lead-in-the-new-york-mayoral-primary-was-just-too-big-to-overcome/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Absentee Voting</category>
			<category>Eric Adams</category>
			<category>Kathryn Garcia</category>
			<category>Maya Wiley</category>
			<category>New York City Mayoral Election</category>
			<category>New York Politics</category>
			<category>Ranked-choice voting</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">It was worth the wait for Eric Adams. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Tuesday, July 6 — two weeks after election day — the Brooklyn borough president all but locked up a victory in the Democratic primary for mayor of New York City. With almost all ballots now accounted for, Adams now leads former Sanitation Commissioner Kathryn Garcia <a href="https://web.enrboenyc.us/rcv/024306_8.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">50.5 percent to 49.5 percent</a> in the final round of ranked-choice voting. As a result, the Associated Press has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ny-state-wire-government-and-politics-9c564828a29831747f9c2e6f52daf55e?utm_campaign=SocialFlow&amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;utm_medium=AP" target="_blank" rel="noopener">projected</a> Adams as the primary winner (he now enters the Nov. 2 general election as a heavy favorite in this very blue city).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These results aren’t 100 percent final, but despite that narrow margin, it’s very likely that there aren’t enough outstanding ballots to change the outcome. That’s because almost all of the Democratic absentee ballots known to have been returned have now been counted — 118,085 of 125,794. And even if there are still 7,709 ballots left to count in the mayor’s race, that isn’t enough to erase Adams’s 8,426-vote lead in the final round.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one wild card is that there may be an unknown number of provisional ballots yet to count — but even then, Garcia would need to win an astounding percentage of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Not that Garcia didn’t make Adams sweat. Adams’s lead is actually much bigger if you look only at <a href="https://web.enrboenyc.us/rcv/024306_1.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voters’ initial preferences</a>. According to the new totals, Adams was the first choice of 31 percent of New York Democrats, attorney Maya Wiley of 21 percent, Garcia of 20 percent and businessman Andrew Yang (who <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/former-presidential-candidate-andrew-yang-concedes-nyc-mayoral-race-2021-06-23/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conceded on election night</a>) of 12 percent. (This is notable because conventional wisdom held that absentee ballots would help Garcia, but these first-round results <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-know-about-new-yorks-mayoral-primary-results-so-far/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are little changed</a> from where they stood on election night, before any absentees were counted.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Garcia gained a ton of ground on Adams once the New York City Board of Elections ran its ranked-choice-voting tabulations. Under this new system, adopted by New York City last year, voters can <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/nyregion/ranked-choice-voting-nyc.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rank up to five candidates</a> in the order of their preference. Then, the candidate with the fewest first-choice votes is eliminated, and his or her votes are redistributed to the candidates ranked second on their ballots. This process repeats until there are only two candidates left; whoever has the most votes in the final round is the winner. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After you perform these calculations for the mayoral race, Garcia goes from an 11.2-point deficit to Adams to just a 1.0-point deficit. Garcia is able to pull that off in large part because a majority of Wiley supporters ranked Garcia ahead of Adams on their ballots (Wiley was one of the race’s most progressive candidates, Adams one of its most conservative), and Wiley ends up being the last candidate eliminated the way the ranked-choice rounds currently play out.<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, the last few remaining ballots could change this — for example, Wiley could edge out Garcia for second place in the penultimate round and Wiley, not Garcia, could be the one who goes on to lose to Adams in the final round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> Garcia’s gain is clear after the penultimate round of ranked-choice voting, when Adams has 353,664 votes (40.5 percent), Garcia has 265,461 votes (30.4 percent) and Wiley has 253,094 votes (29.0 percent). To get to the last round, 129,446 of those Wiley votes were redistributed to Garcia while only 49,669 went to Adams (the remaining 73,979 ballots did not rank either Garcia or Adams and were therefore <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/Ballot_exhaustion" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exhausted</a>).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, though, Adams’s lead in initial preferences was just too great for Garcia to overcome. It’s hard for <em>any</em> candidate who trails in the first round of a ranked-choice voting election to come back and win: According to the voting-reform advocacy group FairVote, the first-round leader won 383 out of <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1lU6viuXfay323Gl6zkH5itwmrUIUo9rAzalK_ntu-ZY/edit#gid=1126870020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">398 single-winner ranked-choice voting races nationwide from 2004 through February 2021</a>. And of the <a href="https://www.fairvote.org/research_rcvwinners#come_from_behind_wins" target="_blank" rel="noopener">15 come-from-behind winners</a>, the largest first-round deficit overcome to win was 9.3 points. So in the end, it would have been unprecedented in a modern ranked-choice election for Garcia to win. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 01:14:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167285</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What The Best 2020 Post-Mortem Tells Us About The Electorate</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-the-best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-about-the-electorate/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke， Alex Samuels， Nathaniel Rakich and Sarah Frostenson</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-the-best-2020-post-mortem-tells-us-about-the-electorate/">
	<div data-podcast-id="312335" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What The Best 2020 Post-Mortem Tells Us About The Electorate">

					<span>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/galen-druke/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke, Alex Samuels, Nathaniel Rakich and Sarah Frostenson</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke, Alex Samuels, Nathaniel Rakich and Sarah Frostenson</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke, Alex Samuels, Nathaniel Rakich and Sarah Frostenson</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/sarah-frostenson/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke, Alex Samuels, Nathaniel Rakich and Sarah Frostenson</a></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP3124554672.mp3?updated=1625609319"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">The Pew Research Center released its <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">verified voter survey</a> looking at how different groups in the electorate voted in 2020. It’s generally considered one of the most comprehensive pictures of trends within the electorate. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew talks about the most notable data points in this analysis and what it means for Democratic and Republican strategies going forward. They also discuss ranked-choice voting and the reasons for delays in New York City’s final vote count in the Democratic mayoral primary.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 23:05:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167284</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How A 6-3 Conservative Majority Shaped The Supreme Court This Term</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/how-a-6-3-conservative-majority-shaped-the-supreme-court-this-term/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p>On Thursday, the Supreme Court began its summer recess with a 6-3 conservative majority on the bench, giving some insight into its new ideological orientation after the addition of Justice Amy Coney Barrett in October. Analysts have described the court this term as largely avoiding a hard right turn, with more unanimous decisions and idiosyncratic splits than expected. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, FiveThirtyEight contributor Laura Bronner shares what the data can tell us about the ideological direction of the court, and legal scholar Kate Shaw digs into some of the specifics of the term’s major cases, particularly on election law.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 15:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167283</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What We Learned From This Supreme Court Term</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-we-learned-from-this-supreme-court-term/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<category>Voting Laws</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-we-learned-from-this-supreme-court-term/">
	<div data-podcast-id="312232" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What We Learned From This Supreme Court Term">

					<span>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/galen-druke/" title="" rel="author">Galen Druke</a></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls"><source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9351852934.mp3?updated=1625255414"></source></audio></div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside><div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside><p data-paragraph="main">On Thursday, the Supreme Court began its summer recess with a 6-3 conservative majority on the bench, giving some insight into its new ideological orientation after the addition of Justice Amy Coney Barrett in October. Analysts have described the court this term as largely avoiding a hard right turn, with more unanimous decisions and idiosyncratic splits than expected. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, FiveThirtyEight contributor Laura Bronner shares what the data can tell us about the ideological direction of the court, and legal scholar Kate Shaw digs into some of the specifics of the term’s major cases, particularly on election law. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 20:46:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167282</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Supreme Court’s Conservative Supermajority Is Just Beginning To Flex Its Muscles</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-conservative-supermajority-is-just-beginning-to-flex-its-muscles/</link>
						<dc:creator>Laura Bronner</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Laura Bronner and Elena Mejía</dc:creator>
			<category>Amy Coney Barrett</category>
			<category>Brett Kavanaugh</category>
			<category>John Roberts</category>
			<category>Neil Gorsuch</category>
			<category>SCOTUS</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">In many ways, the recently completed Supreme Court term was our first comprehensive look at one of the most consequential legacies of the Trump presidency: his imprint on the court. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Understanding the full impact of former President Donald Trump’s<strong> </strong><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-conservative-6-3-majority-would-reshape-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">6-3 conservative supermajority</a> is challenging at this point, though. On the one hand, this term saw the highest share of unanimous rulings in the last three years. On the other hand, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/supreme-court-strikes-californias-donor-disclosure-requirement-charities/story?id=78613877" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the court’s last two</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">major rulings</a> broke down along 6-3 ideological lines.<strong> </strong>But<strong> </strong>that seeming inconsistency<strong> </strong>may have more to do with divisions among the court’s conservatives over how fast to move — not in what direction. Make no mistake, the court <em>is</em> moving in a conservative direction, and the conservative justices are in the driver’s seat.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To understand the court’s rightward shift, look no farther than the justice now at the center of the court: Justice Brett Kavanaugh. A position <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/roberts-is-the-new-swing-justice-that-doesnt-mean-hes-becoming-more-liberal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">once held by Chief Justice John Roberts</a>, this year’s preliminary <a href="https://mqscores.lsa.umich.edu/measures.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Martin-Quinn scores</a>, a prominent measure of the justices’ ideology, suggest Kavanaugh, not Roberts, was this term’s median justice. What’s most striking here, though, is not that Kavanuagh is at the center of the court, but the lack of daylight between where Roberts, Kavanaugh and even Justices Amy Coney Barrett and Neil Gorsuch are estimated to fall on the court. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1108" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-1-use.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-1-use.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-1-use.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-1-use.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">One way to interpret the justices’ ideological scores this term is that there <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-might-have-three-swing-justices-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are actually multiple “median” justices</a> on this court, as any split decision in which the liberal justices are part of the majority involves at least two conservative justices voting with the liberals. At the very least, Kavanaugh’s position at the center of the court doesn’t suggest he’s getting more liberal: Neither Kavanaugh nor Roberts are estimated to have moved to the left at all compared to where they fell last year. Rather, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-the-supreme-courts-unusually-big-jump-to-the-right-might-look-like/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">replacement of the late Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg</a> by Barrett, whose ideological score this term is estimated to fall to the right of that of Roberts and Kavanaugh, has shifted the center of the court — and shifted it in a more conservative direction.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the Martin-Quinn scores are not a perfect measure of the justices’ ideology. <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/supreme-courts-many-median-justices/0D0F8DA0810580019FA521D145DC75D1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Other work</a> has shown that there is no <em>single</em> median justice on the court. Instead, different issues before the court often attract different “median” justices.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><p data-paragraph="main">Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/conservative-majority-shaped-supreme-court-term-fivethirtyeight-78655673</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"> “The Supreme Court <a href="https://cornelllawreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/Fischman-final.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t quite as one-dimensional</a> as everyone says it is,” <a href="https://www.law.virginia.edu/faculty/profile/jf3pe/1163305" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Josh Fischman</a>, a law professor at the University of Virginia, told us.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, a conservative quad made up of Roberts, Kavanaugh, Barrett and Gorsuch has dominated the court’s decisions this term. Kavanaugh was in the majority in 97 percent of all cases this term — and in the majority in a whopping 95 percent of divided cases. Roberts wasn’t that far behind. He was in the majority in 91 percent of all cases and 84 percent of divided cases.<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And in Roberts’s case, some of this might have been strategic, because as the chief justice he gets to decide who writes the majority opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> Barrett and Gorsuch also were in the majority in more than 80 percent of divided cases. And in another sign that the court is moving in a rightward direction: Justices Thomas and Alito were in the majority 80 and 83 percent of the time, respectively, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/BL-LB-53282" target="_blank" rel="noopener">despite their images as the perennial dissenters</a>. In fact, it was the three liberal justices who dissented most this term, perhaps unsurprisingly given the makeup of the court.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Kavanaugh is most often in the majority</h5>
 <p>Share of justices’ decisions in the October 2020 term that fell in the majority in divided cases and among all cases, by justice</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="bronner.end-of-term.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="2">CASES</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1">justice</th>
 <th colspan="1">all</th>
 <th colspan="1">divided</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Brett Kavanaugh</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">97.0%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">94.6%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>John Roberts</td>
 <td>90.9</td>
 <td>83.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Amy Coney Barrett</td>
 <td>90.7</td>
 <td>83.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Neil Gorsuch</td>
 <td>89.4</td>
 <td>81.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Samuel Alito</td>
 <td>83.1</td>
 <td>69.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Clarence Thomas</td>
 <td>80.3</td>
 <td>64.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Stephen Breyer</td>
 <td>77.3</td>
 <td>59.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Elena Kagan</td>
 <td>75.8</td>
 <td>56.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Sonia Sotomayor</td>
 <td>69.7</td>
 <td>46.0</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Barrett’s stats are based on 12 fewer cases, as she was recused from cases argued before she joined the court.</p>
 <p>Source: Kal Golde for SCOTUSBLOG</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">There was a lot of hype this term <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/supreme-court-defies-critics-wave-unanimous-decisions/story?id=78463255" target="_blank" rel="noopener">around the number of unanimous decisions issued —</a> <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/statistics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">44 percent</a> in all — but that wasn’t actually all that unusual. In the previous <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/Merits-cases-by-vote-split-7.20.20.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">10 terms (2010-19)</a>, an average of 47 percent of cases were decided unanimously. And as you can see in the chart below, the rate at which the justices agreed with each other is still telling. The three liberal justices agreed with each other far more than with any of the other justices; the same was true of the five conservative justices. In fact, the two justices who are the most in lockstep are Roberts and Kavanaugh (they went the same way in 94 percent of all cases).</p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A person leaving a polling building and walking past a “Vote Here” sign." width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1229443852_4x3.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1229443852_4x3.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1229443852_4x3.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/GettyImages-1229443852_4x3.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				The Supreme Court Just Made It Harder To Overturn Voting Restrictions <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Barrett also was often lockstep with Gorsuch and Kavanaugh (she agreed with each of them in 91 percent of the cases in which she participated).<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were 12 cases this term in which Barrett didn’t participate as they were mostly argued before she joined the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> It’s worth noting, though, that justices’ first years can be a bit misleading — in Kavanaugh’s first term on the court, for instance, he agreed as much with Justice Elena Kagan as he did with Gorsuch (70 percent), but in his second term he agreed far more with Gorsuch (88 percent) than with Kagan (72 percent), a pattern that has held true this past year as well. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="1246" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-2.png?w=700" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-2.png?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/bronner.mejia_.ENDOFTERM.0706-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Here, though, is where we can see Thomas and Alito earn their reputations as the two justices least likely to agree with the other justices. This term, they both agreed with Gorsuch the most (88 percent of the time), and although Alito voted in line with the other conservative justices (at least more so than Thomas), both conservative justices stand out for just how infrequently they agreed with the liberal justices — underscoring how intractable some members of the court’s conservative majority are. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, what does this tell us about the court overall? As we said at the outset, it’s too early to evaluate just how far Trump’s conservative majority will fundamentally shift law in this country to the right. But we would caution that it’s important <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/07/05/the-supreme-courts-surprising-term" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not to confuse</a> disagreement among the conservative justices — which evidently exists — with disagreement over the direction the court is moving. <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/20pdf/19-840_6jfm.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alito’s dissents</a>, for instance, <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/20pdf/20-391_2c83.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">show impatience</a> with the speed the court is moving at, but a closer look at some of the conservatives’ opinions reveal that even when they find themselves on opposite sides of Alito and Thomas, they still largely agree with them on the merits. Take Kavanaugh on the court’s decision to uphold the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s nationwide <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2021/06/29/us/joe-biden-news/the-supreme-court-keeps-in-place-the-moratorium-on-evictions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">moratorium on evictions</a> because of the COVID-19 pandemic. He joined the majority opinion, even though he thinks the CDC exceeded its authority in issuing the moratorium, saying he ultimately didn’t think it was worth overturning the moratorium because it ends July 31 anyway — hardly a ringing endorsement of the merits of the case. Or take Barrett on Fulton: She joined the majority opinion, but issued a separate concurrence with Kavanaugh, where both suggested they remain open to <a href="https://lawliberty.org/the-emfulton-em-opinion-and-the-originalist-future-of-religious-freedom/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overturning the ruling in Employment Division v. Smith</a>, which would dramatically change how courts evaluate laws that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-has-carved-out-one-religious-exemption-after-another-the-next-may-be-a-blow-to-lgbtq-rights/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">impose restrictions on religious groups</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Additionally, one caveat of the data we’ve looked at is that the justices’ ideology scores or how much they agree with each other don’t account for the types of cases the justices hear. For instance, this term, several of the highest-profile cases still resulted in the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/06/01/us/major-supreme-court-cases-2021.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expected 6-3 ideological split.</a> The <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Voting Rights Act of 1965 will now be less enforceable.</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/23/us/supreme-court-unions-farms-california.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Union access to workplaces will be restricted.</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/01/us/supreme-court-donor-privacy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Disclosure requirements</a> for some political donations will have less oversight. And there won’t be any <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/22/us/supreme-court-life-terms-youths.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">constraints on life sentences</a> for juvenile offenders.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, the conservative supermajority on the court has really just begun to flex its capabilities. What kinds of cases the justices decide to take on is as important as how they rule, and many of the cases decided this term were taken while Ginsburg was still on the court. The current court has <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/us-law-week/supreme-court-delights-conservatives-with-action-on-wish-list" target="_blank" rel="noopener">already decided to take up cases on abortion and gun rights</a> next term — two hot-button issues that might give us better insight into just how far, and quickly, the court is willing to move law to the right.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/pandemic-changed-sex-work-industry-fivethirtyeight-78621101</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/politics-podcast-summer-mailbag-edition-fivethirtyeight-78499147</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 20:24:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167281</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>It’s A ‘Shot Girl Summer.’ But America Is Still Not Fully Back To Normal.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-a-shot-girl-summer-but-america-is-still-not-fully-back-to-normal/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>Fourth of July</category>
			<category>Pandemic</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Summer</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">With <a href="https://www.climate.gov/news-features/event-tracker/record-breaking-june-2021-heatwave-impacts-us-west" target="_blank" rel="noopener">temperatures soaring</a> around the country, it certainly feels like summer (though worrying whether this extreme weather is the <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/heat-wave-west-coast-hints-climate-change-scientists-say-rcna1297" target="_blank" rel="noopener">result of climate change</a> is hardly contributing to a relaxed summer vibe). A growing share of the U.S. population is <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2021/01/28/960901166/how-is-the-covid-19-vaccination-campaign-going-in-your-state" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fully vaccinated</a> against the novel coronavirus, states are <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/storytelling/coronavirus-reopening-america-map/#restrictions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lifting or relaxing pandemic-related restrictions</a> and the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/covid-data/covidview/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overall number of new COVID-19 cases is in decline</a>. But will the next couple of months feel like a “normal” summer — barbecues, beach vacations and all? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Not quite, according to recent polls. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Back in the halcyon pre-pandemic days of summer 2019, 69 percent of Americans said they planned to attend a barbecue to celebrate the Fourth of July according to a <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_070119/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monmouth University poll</a> from June of that year. But this year, in a <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/MonmouthPoll_US_062821/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll conducted June 9-14</a>, Monmouth asked the same question and found just 54 percent of Americans planned to go to a cookout. An <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/fourth-july-celebrations-wont-be-bigger" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ipsos survey from June 22-23</a> captured similar sentiments, with a majority of Americans (55 percent) saying they planned to celebrate Independence Day in a way similar to last year, in a smaller way than before COVID-19 or not at all. However, 36 percent said they planned to celebrate the way they did before COVID-19, and 8 percent said they planned to go bigger than ever before. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Plans for other July Fourth celebrations are also down this year according to Monmouth, with 26 percent of Americans saying they planned to go to a professional fireworks display (compared with 51 percent in 2019) and 18 percent saying they were going to a parade (versus 28 percent in 2019). Summer vacation plans haven’t quite bounced back either: 34 percent of Americans said their plans were more or less the same as any other year, while 26 percent said they had scaled back or canceled their usual getaway. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/politics-podcast-summer-mailbag-edition-fivethirtyeight-78499147</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Though Americans may not be totally ready for a “normal” summer, polls do show they are feeling more relaxed about the pandemic. In a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/351650/three-americans-think-pandemic.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup poll from June 14-20</a>, a majority (62 percent) said their life was “somewhat back to normal” while only 15 percent said “completely back to normal.” That same poll found that 71 percent of Americans didn’t think the pandemic was over yet, but most were optimistic about the direction it was heading: 89 percent said the coronavirus situation in the U.S. was getting a lot or a little better, compared with only 33 percent who felt that way in February. And for the first time since the start of the pandemic, the COVID-19 outbreak didn’t rank among the top two problems facing the U.S. according to a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/351779/sharply-fewer-cite-covid-nation-top-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 1-18 Gallup poll</a>: 8 percent of Americans cited COVID-19 as the top problem in the country versus 22 percent who cited the government and 11 percent who cited race relations. </p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-was-always-going-to-be-a-struggle-for-the-cdc/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="The CDC sign shot from below so it is backgrounded by a blue cloudy sky" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CDC-4x3-1.png?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CDC-4x3-1.png?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CDC-4x3-1.png?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CDC-4x3-1.png?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				COVID-19 Was Always Going To Be A Struggle For The CDC. But Trump Sure Didn’t Help. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-was-always-going-to-be-a-struggle-for-the-cdc/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even the emergence of the <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-dangerous-is-the-delta-variant-and-will-it-cause-a-covid-surge-in-the-u-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more transmissible delta variant</a> of the coronavirus — which is causing public health experts to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/29/health/coronavirus-delta-variant-masks.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">second-guess the lifting of mask mandates</a> — hasn’t raised Americans’ concerns about COVID-19. Forty-eight percent said they were very or somewhat familiar with the variant, according to an <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/en-us/news-polls/axios-ipsos-coronavirus-index" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Axios/Ipsos poll from June 25-28</a>, but few claimed to be changing their behavior: 68 percent had visited friends or family in the past week, 65 percent had gone out to eat and 65 percent had gone to a store for something other than groceries. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It may be a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/style/post-vaccination-summer-partying-dating-sex/2021/05/17/a04ca36e-b43c-11eb-9059-d8176b9e3798_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“shot girl summer”</a> — and things are certainly easing back into a more normal routine than last year — but we might not see a full return to the before times until 2022. However you choose to celebrate the holiday (or not), here’s to a safe and hopeful long weekend. </p>



<h2><strong>Other Polling Bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>While we continue to await the results of New York City’s Democratic <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2021/06/30/nyregion/nyc-mayor-election">mayoral primary</a>, Boston’s nonpartisan mayoral race is just heating up. City Councilor Michelle Wu and Acting Mayor Kim Janey are the <a href="https://www.suffolk.edu/-/media/suffolk/documents/academics/research-at-suffolk/suprc/polls/massachusetts2/2021/6_29_2021_tables_pdftxt.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=18D3CE050F66D9DCBA5069C1FFEEB7CD6DD2411A">current front-runners</a>, with 23 percent of likely voters favoring Wu and 22 percent favoring Janey, according to a June 23-26 poll by Suffolk University and The Boston Globe. In a crowded field of eight candidates, 22 percent were still undecided, but tellingly, 70 percent backed one of the four female candidates, all women of color. “Clearly the respondents are telling us that history will be made,” David Paleologos, director of the Suffolk University Political Research Center, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2021/06/29/metro/boston-mayoral-poll-shows-michelle-wu-kim-janey-pulling-ahead/">told The Boston Globe</a>. Janey became the first woman and the first Black person to lead the city when she was <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2021/03/25/kim-janey-boston-first-black-female-mayor/6994362002/">sworn in as acting mayor</a> in March, but Boston has yet to elect a woman or Black person to the position.</li><li>As the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/post-election-audits-are-normal-whats-happening-in-arizona-is-anything-but/">partisan inquisition</a> into the 2020 election results in Arizona <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/arizona-maricopa-2020-audit-review/2021/06/28/98da5e64-d863-11eb-9bbb-37c30dcf9363_story.html">comes to a close</a>, distrust in the election remains high among Republicans. According to a <a href="https://thehill.com/hilltv/what-americas-thinking/560857-poll-56-percent-of-gop-voters-said-biden-won-the-2020-election">Hill-HarrisX poll</a> from June 24-25, 56 percent of registered GOP voters said President Biden had won the election through “voter fraud,” despite the lack of evidence. In addition, 27 percent agreed with the statement that “state-level reviews of the 2020 election results [would] change who is President of the United States,” even though reviews like the one wrapping up in Arizona are partisan and not being conducted with local election officials.</li><li>Last week, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2021-06-23/britney-spears-speaks-conservatorship-hearing-takeaways">Britney Spears took the (virtual) stand</a> in court to remove her father from her conservatorship, delivering an emotional 24-minute testimony where she claimed her conservators refused to let her remove her IUD, marry her boyfriend, travel freely or choose her own therapist. On Thursday, the <a href="https://variety.com/2021/music/news/britney-spears-conservatorship-request-denied-remove-father-1235009486/">judge denied her request</a> to remove her father as co-conservator (though Spears may choose to file a request to dissolve the conservatorship entirely), but most Americans seem to be on the <a href="https://www.harpersbazaar.com/celebrity/latest/a34113034/why-longtime-britney-spears-fans-are-demanding-to-freebritney/">#FreeBritney train</a>: In a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/h9vjw7u633/tabs_Britney_Spears_20210625.pdf">YouGov poll conducted from June 25-28</a>, 65 percent “strongly” or “somewhat” supported her request to terminate the conservatorship. </li><li><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/09/success/remote-work-covid-pandemic-one-year-later/index.html">Working from home</a> has monumentally changed how many Americans have done their jobs during the pandemic, and as offices begin to reopen, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/06/29/more-people-plan-to-quit-as-return-to-work-plans-go-into-effect-.html">many workers are saying they’d rather quit</a> than go back to a cubicle. Some companies are considering more flexible options, such as working from home <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-05-17/hybrid-work-may-not-be-flexible-when-you-return-to-office-after-lockdown">a few days a week</a> or even shortened work weeks: Kickstarter <a href="https://www.inc.com/gabrielle-bienasz/kickstarter-four-day-workweek-pilot.html#:~:text=Kickstarter%20is%20launching%20one%20of,called%204%20Day%20Week%20U.S.">recently announced</a> it was switching to a four-day workweek, a notion that many Americans find appealing. A <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2021/06/29/0262a/3">YouGov poll</a> found that 66 percent of Americans preferred the idea of a four-day, 10-hour-a-day workweek compared with five eight-hour workdays, and a plurality of respondents (38 percent) said that a four-day workweek would increase their productivity (although 34 percent said they’d be no more productive compared with working a five-day week). </li><li>The U.S. intelligence community <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/03/us/politics/ufos-sighting-alien-spacecraft-pentagon.html">released a report on “unidentified aerial phenomena” last week</a>, acknowledging that it couldn’t explain or categorize 143 of 144 such events. While the report notes there is no evidence that these sightings are indicative of alien visitors, Americans are more willing to believe that they are. A majority of Americans (51 percent) said that military sightings of UFOs are “definitely” or “probably” evidence that intelligent life exists beyond Earth, according to a <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/06/30/most-americans-believe-in-intelligent-life-beyond-earth-few-see-ufos-as-a-major-national-security-threat/">Pew Research Center survey</a> conducted from June 14-24. Sixty-five percent of adults said their best guess was that intelligent life does exist on other planets, but 51 percent said that UFOs are not a threat to national security. Keep your eyes peeled for more than just fireworks in the sky this weekend. </li></ul><p data-paragraph="main"></p>



<h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=700" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=1400 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> 52.1 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 42.2 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of +9.9 percentage points). At this time last week, 52.6 percent approved and 42.2 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of +10.5 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 53.7 percent and a disapproval rating of 39.8 percent (a net approval rating of +13.9 points).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-starting-make-climate-agenda-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78546775</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-election-reform-dont-votes-78431465</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167280</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Supreme Court Just Made It Harder To Overturn Voting Restrictions</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Arizona</category>
			<category>John Roberts</category>
			<category>SCOTUS</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<category>Voting Restrictions</category>
			<category>Voting Rights</category>
			<category>Voting Rights Act</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">In a <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/20pdf/19-1257_g204.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">6-3 decision</a> that broke down along ideological lines, the U.S. Supreme Court on Thursday overturned a lower court’s ruling that two election laws in Arizona were racially discriminatory. But the case has implications far beyond Arizona: The ruling also seriously limits the power of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 to block voting restrictions like those <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-have-made-it-harder-to-vote-in-11-states-so-far/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">currently being passed in Republican-led states</a> — and that could make it harder for voting-rights advocates to win similar lawsuits in the future.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The case, Brnovich v. Democratic National Committee, dealt with two Arizona voting restrictions: one that made it a felony (with a few exceptions, like for family) to deliver another person’s absentee ballot, and one that threw out provisional ballots cast by voters who showed up at the wrong precinct. In early 2020, the 9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals sided with the Democratic plaintiffs and <a href="https://www.azcentral.com/story/news/politics/elections/2020/01/27/arizona-ballot-harvesting-law-discriminates-minority-voters-ninth-circuit/4589610002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">invalidated both restrictions</a> on the grounds that they disproportionately harmed nonwhite voters, <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2021/02/justices-to-consider-whether-arizonas-voting-rules-discriminate-against-minorities/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">noting</a> that only 18 percent of Native American voters in Arizona have access to regular mail service and that African American, Hispanic and Native American Arizonans were twice as likely as white Arizonans to vote at the wrong precinct. However, on Thursday, the Supreme Court ruled that these two voting restrictions do not violate Section 2 of the Voting Rights Act, which prohibits racial discrimination in voting, and reinstated them. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Crucially, the court also identified “guideposts” for interpreting Section 2 that it used to arrive at its decision. While the court made a point of saying it was not establishing a test to govern all Voting Rights Act Section 2 cases, these guideposts are essentially a template for future courts to follow when ruling in voting-rights cases. And that template is a decidedly conservative one. For example, “courts must consider the opportunities provided by a State’s entire system of voting when assessing the burden imposed by a challenged provision,” the court wrote — claiming that Arizona, on the whole, “makes it very easy to vote.” (It’s worth noting, however, that Arizona got a below-average grade in the <a href="https://www.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/elj.2020.0666" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 Cost of Voting Index</a>, a metric in political science used to measure the ease of voting in and across states.) The Supreme Court also suggested another factor should be “the size of the burden imposed by a challenged voting rule” — specifically, the court asserted that making it inconvenient to vote does not rise to the level of taking away a person’s right to vote. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In addition, the court noted that the “the size of any disparities in a rule’s impact on members of different racial or ethnic groups is an important factor to consider.” But the burden of proof the court requires for racial discrimination to have occurred is high. “Even neutral regulations may well result in disparities in rates of voting and noncompliance with voting rules. The mere fact that there is some disparity in impact does not necessarily mean that a system is not equally open or that it does not give everyone an equal opportunity to vote.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/reason-gop-make-harder-people-vote-silver-76734563</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Thanks to these guideposts, this ruling has implications for not only the two Arizona regulations, but for laws like them around the country. So far in 2021, Republican-controlled state governments have enacted at least 33 new voting restrictions, from <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-have-made-it-harder-to-vote-in-11-states-so-far/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">limits on absentee voting to tighter voter-ID laws</a> to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-states-where-efforts-to-restrict-voting-are-escalating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">drop-box restrictions to early-voting cuts</a>. And up until now, Section 2 of the Voting Rights Act was a key tool for liberals who had failed to block these laws in the legislature to keep fighting them in court. Voting-rights advocates have already used Section 2 to <a href="https://www.democracydocket.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/45/2021/04/show_temp-7.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">file suit</a> against <a href="https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/justice-department-files-lawsuit-against-state-georgia-stop-racially-discriminatory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">these new restrictions</a>, including a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-georgias-new-voting-law-is-such-a-big-deal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">controversial Georgia law</a> that required proof of identity to vote absentee and prohibited giving food or water to voters waiting in line. But now those lawsuits will likely need to clear higher bars in order to be successful, even in courts that might otherwise be sympathetic (and, of course, the decision in Brnovich v. DNC strongly hints at how such lawsuits may be decided if one eventually winds up in front of the Supreme Court). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Brnovich v. DNC marks the second major blow the Supreme Court has dealt to the Voting Rights Act under Chief Justice John Roberts, who has <a href="https://www.vox.com/21211880/supreme-court-chief-justice-john-roberts-voting-rights-act-election-2020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">worked against the act</a> since his days as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2015/08/john-roberts-voting-rights-act-121222/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">young staffer in Ronald Reagan’s Department of Justice</a>. In 2013, the case <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/shelby-county-v-holder/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shelby County v. Holder</a> neutered Section 5 of the act, which requires jurisdictions with a history of racial discrimination to preclear new voting rules with the federal Department of Justice. The court called the formula for determining those jurisdictions — outlined in Section 4(b) — outdated and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/supreme-court-strikes-portion-voting-rights-act/story?id=19459258" target="_blank" rel="noopener">struck it down</a>, with the result that Section 5 no longer covers any jurisdictions at all until Congress passes a new formula (which it has not yet done).<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the proposed &lt;a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2021/06/what-would-the-john-lewis-voting-rights-act-actually-do.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;John Lewis Voting Rights Act&lt;/a&gt; would change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>16</sup></a> The impact of that ruling was significant: According to an <a href="https://www.motherjones.com/politics/2021/06/eight-years-ago-the-supreme-court-gutted-the-voting-rights-act-widespread-voter-suppression-resulted/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">analysis by Mother Jones</a>, 26 states passed new voting restrictions once the preclearance requirement was struck down — <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/sites/default/files/2019-11/New%20Voting%20Restrictions.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">including one of the Arizona laws</a> at issue in Brnovich v. DNC. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Indeed, this ruling is just the latest indication that one of the Roberts-led court’s main legacies will be curbing the federal government’s say in states’ voting laws (and instead, deferring more to states, which, in Republican-controlled states, has meant more restrictions in recent years). From 2009 to 2019, there were <a href="http://scdb.wustl.edu/analysisOverview.php?sid=2001-LONGJOHN-1969" target="_blank" rel="noopener">five 5-4 Supreme Court decisions on voting-rights cases</a>, and the conservative bloc was in the majority in all five of them. In addition to its decisions in Brnovich v. DNC and Shelby County v. Holder, the court has made it easier for states to purge voters from the rolls (<a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/husted-v-philip-randolph-institute/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Husted v. A. Philip Randolph Institute</a>) and repeatedly declined to get involved in fixing gerrymandering (<a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/abbott-v-perez-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Abbott v. Perez</a>, <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/rucho-v-common-cause-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rucho v. Common Cause</a>). With its new 6-3 conservative majority, it’s early yet to know how rightward the Roberts-led court will push the country, but there is no denying it has already had a deeply conservative impact on election law.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/voting-restrictions-states-76759234</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-starting-make-climate-agenda-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78546775</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 17:54:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167279</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>More People Are Buying Guns. Fewer People Are Getting Background Checks.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-people-are-buying-guns-fewer-people-are-getting-background-checks/</link>
						<dc:creator>Joshua Eaton</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Joshua Eaton</dc:creator>
			<category>Background Checks</category>
			<category>FBI</category>
			<category>Gun Control</category>
			<category>Gun Sales</category>
			<category>Gun Violence</category>
			<category>Guns</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">America’s gun background check system, designed to keep weapons out of the hands of people who might use them in crimes, has struggled to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/01/us/shootings-in-us.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">keep up with record firearms sales over the past year</a> — <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/01/us/shootings-in-us.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even as violent crime has risen dramatically in many U.S. cities</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In recent years, the FBI — which manages the system that vets gun buyers — processed an average of 8.6 million gun background checks annually, according to historical data analyzed by FiveThirtyEight.<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data goes back to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a> But last year, the bureau processed 12,761,328 background checks, according to FBI data obtained by FiveThirtyEight through a public records request.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Perhaps most alarming, the FBI never finished over 316,000 background checks in the first nine months of 2020 alone — far more than in any other year on record. And that number doesn’t include October, November and December — usually the <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/6444698-Roof-FBI-report-PACER#document/p21/a573849" target="_blank" rel="noopener">busiest months</a> for gun sales, when 3.4 million background checks were opened last year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, it’s impossible to know how many guns were sold to people in 2020 who couldn’t legally own them because those background checks were never completed.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/support-gun-control-led-legislation-77033996</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Asked why it didn’t finish so many background checks in 2020, the FBI said in a statement that it “depends on the availability of relevant information and records provided by federal, state, local, and tribal agencies.” The bureau also said that it has “reallocated resources to help ensure that it can continue processing background checks efficiently.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Gun sales have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/gun-sales-are-surging-but-background-checks-arent-keeping-up/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">surged since April 2020</a>, thanks, at least in part, to the pandemic, protests last summer for racial justice and the election of President Biden in November. The FBI data shows how the background check system has struggled to keep up. And, at this point, it’s unclear when the problem is going to get better.</p>



<h2><strong>A growing problem</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The share of background checks the FBI never completes has ticked up slowly since 2014, the first year on record, when it processed 8,256,688 checks and didn’t complete 172,879, or just under 2.1 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But by 2019, the bureau was failing to complete about 2.5 percent of the background checks it processed, and it didn’t finish almost 3.4 percent in the first nine months of 2020.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those numbers only include gun background checks run by the FBI, so they don’t count the 20 states that <a href="https://www.fbi.gov/file-repository/nics-participation-map.pdf/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">process some or all background checks themselves</a>. It’s also important to remember that the number of background checks isn’t the same as the number of guns sold — many <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/7008276-2019-Nics-Operations-Report.html#document/p8/a573798" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are also run</a> when people apply for gun permits, for example, or when states check on the status of gun permit holders. A single background check can also <a href="https://www.nraila.org/articles/20200210/2020-starts-with-another-nics-record" target="_blank" rel="noopener">represent multiple gun sales</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, the background check numbers for 2020 are staggering. </p>


<div>
	<p>
		<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/militias-pose-a-serious-threat-so-why-is-it-so-hard-to-stop-them/?cid=_inlinerelated"><img alt="A militia member shot from behind gesturing out at a blue sky and green field. The patch on his hat says “Three Percenter”" width="153" height="115" data-sizes="(min-width: 440px) 153px, 100vw" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/RTS1A17S-4x3-1.jpg?w=153&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 153w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/RTS1A17S-4x3-1.jpg?w=306&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 306w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/RTS1A17S-4x3-1.jpg?w=405&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 405w, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/RTS1A17S-4x3-1.jpg?w=810&amp;quality=100&amp;strip=all 810w"></a>
	</p>
	<p>
				<strong>related:</strong>
				Why Militias Are So Hard To Stop <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/militias-pose-a-serious-threat-so-why-is-it-so-hard-to-stop-them/?cid=_inlinerelated">Read more. »</a>
	</p>
</div>



<p data-paragraph="main">The consulting firm Small Arms Analytics &amp; Forecasting uses the total number of federal and state background checks to estimate how many represent actual gun sales, rather than concealed-carry permits or other processes that go through the background check system.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There were a total of more than 39.3 million federal and state background checks in 2020, <a href="https://www.fbi.gov/file-repository/nics_firearm_checks_-_year_by_state_type.pdf/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to the FBI</a>. From that, the firm estimates that <a href="http://smallarmsanalytics.com/v1/pr/2021-01-05.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost 23 million</a> guns were sold last year, compared to <a href="http://smallarmsanalytics.com/v1/pr/2020-01-06.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">just 13.9 million</a> in 2019.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The firm’s chief economist, Jurgen Brauer, said he hasn’t seen anything like it in his 15 years working with the background check data.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“Nobody has,” Brauer said. “Everyone you talk with in the industry is perplexed.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, before the pandemic, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/02/23/business/media/guns-sales-advertising-strategy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gun sales were so low</a> observers called it the “Trump slump.” But they then spiked dramatically in March 2020, and have remained high over the last year, overwhelming the background check system.</p>



<h2><strong>From bad to worse</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Three numbers highlight the size of the problem we’re dealing with: (1) how many background checks take longer than three business days; (2) how many checks the FBI never completes; and (3) how many people who can’t legally own a gun are able to buy one anyway because of those delays.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The FBI responds to most gun background checks with an immediate “yes” or “no.” But sometimes, it has to delay the check to do more research because its records are incomplete. After three business days, the dealer can sell the gun anyway. Many, including large chains like Walmart, choose not to. But ones that do don’t have to tell the FBI about it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In an average year, almost 275,000 background checks take longer than three business days. In 2020, there were 535,786 such checks, according to FBI data. That number doesn’t include background checks for things like concealed-carry permits or explosives licenses, which aren’t subject to the three-business-day rule.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, the FBI keeps researching. But after 90 days, the bureau’s regulations require it to stop work and delete the background check from its computers. To make sure it doesn’t violate that policy, the bureau actually deletes unfinished background checks on day 88 just to be safe.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the first nine months of 2020, the FBI deleted 316,912 unfinished background checks — 3.4 percent of all the checks it processed. In an average year, it deletes about 202,000. Again, this only includes background checks that are subject to the three-business-day rule.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If the FBI discovers that the potential buyer can’t own a gun in between day three and day 88, it contacts the dealer to see if the sale went through anyway. If it did, the FBI asks the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (the ATF) to retrieve the weapon.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Between 2014 and 2019, there were on average at least 3,800 of these so-called “delayed denial” sales annually, <a href="https://everytownresearch.org/documents/2021/02/2021-0075-final-response-packet-_atf_everytown_redacted.pdf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to ATF data</a> obtained by the gun-control advocacy group Everytown for Gun Safety. But there were at least 5,807 in all of 2020, according to the ATF data — the most since 2006, the first complete year on record.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s no evidence that delayed denial sales are a major driver of crime, and some point to the relatively small number that ATF records each year as proof that the law doesn’t need to change.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/US/video/remembering-george-floyd-year-protest-77890592</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But the ATF data is just the part of the iceberg that’s above the water. The FBI does not finish most gun background checks that take longer than three business days. Because it deletes those unfinished background checks, it’s impossible to know how many would have been denied — and how many of those people were able to buy a gun anyway.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And even if the numbers are relatively small, they can have tragic consequences. In April 2015, Dylann Roof <a href="https://archive.thinkprogress.org/exclusive-the-fbi-allowed-over-300-000-gun-purchases-last-year-before-completing-a-background-9d380d53aa1d/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bought a .45-caliber Glock handgun</a> a few days after the FBI delayed his background check because of incomplete records about his prior drug arrest. Two months later, Roof used the gun to kill nine people during a Bible study at a historically Black church in Charleston, South Carolina.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The three-business-day deadline is <a href="https://www.thetrace.org/2015/07/brady-bill-amendment-default-proceed-loophole-amendment-nra/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">written into federal law</a>. But deleting unfinished background checks after 88 days is a matter of FBI regulations and policy, according to Rob Wilcox, federal legal director for Everytown.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“There’s no law that requires the FBI to delete delayed background checks,” Wilcox said. “The regulation sets the deletion date at 90 days, and that regulation could be changed through the administrative process.”</p>



<h2><strong>Few answers and fewer solutions</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The question of why so many background checks go unfinished, and why the numbers haven’t improved over time, doesn’t have a clear answer.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The FBI poured millions into upgrading and automating parts of the gun background check system from 2012 to 2016, and Congress passed new legislation aimed at fixing the system in 2018. But every year, the delays keep piling up.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The 2015 FBI report on Roof’s background check <a href="https://www.rollcall.com/2019/10/10/charleston-mass-murderer-got-his-gun-because-of-background-check-gaps-internal-report-shows/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found that</a> slow responses and incomplete records were the biggest cause of delays. It also singled out FBI policies that limited how inspectors from the National Instant Criminal Background Check System (NICS) could do research on a background check and how the system prioritized keeping the immediate response rate at 90 percent rather than clearing the relatively small number of open cases.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The report <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/6444698-Roof-FBI-report-PACER#document/p21/a573849" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also found</a> that NICS had trouble handling the normal volume of background checks without resorting to an “escalation plan” that involved surging all available staff to handle background check requests.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight asked the FBI whether it has enough staff to process the current volume of background checks. In response, the bureau pointed to two-year supplemental funding it received in the fiscal year 2021 budget that it said will help pay for additional staff, IT resources and other productivity enhancements. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The ongoing system improvements being performed with the supplemental funding enhance the efficiency of processing gun background checks,” the bureau said in a statement.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The National Shooting Sports Foundation, which represents the firearms industry, has worked to get more state and local records — especially ones related to mental health — into the background check system in order to cut down on delays. It’s also working with appropriations committees on the Hill to get more resources for NICS and the ATF, according to Lawrence Keane, the organization’s senior vice president for government and public affairs.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“They have told us they need more resources,” Keane said. “They need more bodies as well as technology, to meet the growing demands.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“The industry wants NICS to function properly,” he added.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But others, like Connecticut Sen. Richard Blumenthal, think Congress needs to change the law so dealers can’t sell a gun without a completed background check. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Democratic congressman has sponsored a bill, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/senate-bill/591" target="_blank" rel="noopener">S. 591</a>, that would require a completed background check for a gun sale. The bill, which the National Shooting Sports Foundation opposes, is currently pending in the Senate Judiciary Committee. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Another bill, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-bill/1446" target="_blank" rel="noopener">H.R. 1446</a>, which passed the House earlier this year, would replace the three-business-day window with a 10-day window after which the potential buyer would have to certify that they’re not prohibited from owning a gun. It’s also pending in the Senate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But as long as the filibuster stands, the hope for any new gun legislation is thin. A <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/1112/all-actions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">similar bill</a> that passed the House during the last Congress died in the Senate. And a <a href="https://www.rollcall.com/2020/02/21/lawmakers-seek-to-tighten-gun-background-checks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">third bill</a> that would have kept the FBI from deleting unfinished background checks died in the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ultimately, it’s not clear what the solution is. Gun-control advocates would like to see the law changed so dealers can’t sell guns until a background check is complete. Opponents say that even with all the time in the world, the FBI can’t complete background checks if it doesn’t get the right records from state and local officials.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What is clear is that even if the current surge in gun sales wanes, as some in the industry predict, the long-term trajectory is pointing up. The question is how to build a system that can handle an ever-growing number of guns.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“One uncompleted check is a problem,” Blumenthal said in a statement, “but 316,000 uncompleted checks is a systemic failure of an already overburdened system.”</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/politics-podcast-summer-mailbag-edition-fivethirtyeight-78499147</p>

<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/republicans-starting-make-climate-agenda-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-78546775</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167278</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>COVID-19 Was Always Going To Be A Struggle For The CDC.  But Trump Sure Didn’t Help.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-19-was-always-going-to-be-a-struggle-for-the-cdc/</link>
						<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<category>CDC</category>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">The newspapers had been filled with <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2016/feb/02/zika-virus-spreads-across-americas-in-pictures" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bleak photo essays</a> for months, but Dr. Sonja Rasmussen was still struggling to take the plunge and tell the world that the Zika virus was causing birth defects. It was 2016, and as the director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s division of public health information dissemination, she had to decide when there was <em>enough</em> evidence to prove that Zika was harming babies. She knew there was no turning back once she decided there was. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Like everyone else, Rasmussen had seen the heartrending pictures of babies with microcephaly, a condition in which the brain stops growing early, resulting in a smaller-than-normal head. She knew that <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-35368401" target="_blank" rel="noopener">thousands of babies</a> had been born with this condition in Brazil, the epicenter of the Zika outbreak, compared with only 150 a year before. And she knew that Americans, particularly pregnant women, were scared — canceling travel plans as cases of the virus were identified in Latin America and the Caribbean. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To a layperson, it was easy to look at those media reports from the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/31/world/americas/alarm-spreads-in-brazil-over-a-virus-and-a-surge-in-malformed-infants.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">winter of 2015</a> and <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-35368401" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2016</a> and <a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2015/12/fast-spreading-virus-may-cause-severe-birth-defects" target="_blank" rel="noopener">assume that Zika was the cause</a> of this and other permanent disabilities in children — and that everyone knew it. But Rasmussen, the expert, wasn’t as certain as the media narrative, even as the evidence mounted. She knew how science always contained nuance and how a risk of something bad happening was almost never 100 percent. And she knew that new evidence could easily turn a past warning into a false alarm. For the sake of the public’s understanding — and for the sake of the CDC’s reputation — she didn’t <em>want</em> to be too certain. “It was my job to waffle,” said Rasmussen, now a professor in the departments of pediatrics and epidemiology at the University of Florida College of Medicine and College of Public Health and Health Professions. “Saying something was definitely causing birth defects, I felt like I was truly jumping off the high dive headfirst.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/nejmsr1604338" target="_blank" rel="noopener">She jumped anyway</a>. When she did, some scientists and journalists thought there wasn’t enough evidence yet and criticized the CDC’s hastiness. Others asked why it hadn’t gone public sooner. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That time, the CDC was right, and things generally worked out OK — Zika, by luck mostly, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/health/what-is-zika-virus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">never gained a major foothold in the continental U.S.</a>, after all. But the CDC’s struggles with uncertainty, risk communication, public critique and public trust didn’t vanish when fears of Zika did. The past 18 months have made that very clear.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Public statements about health risks are themselves a risk — both for the agency making them and for the public that desperately needs information it can trust. It’s terrifying to think that the people who are in charge can feel disoriented and uncertain about the choices they have to make and the information they have to communicate. But it also makes what happened during the COVID-19 pandemic a lot clearer. We all watched the CDC waffle in real time on numerous occasions over the past year and a half. And more often than not, when the agency jumped, it crashed to the ground. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Why that happened, though, is complicated. The CDC itself didn’t respond to interview requests. Talking to people who have worked for the CDC and know it well, however, suggests that the agency’s problems weren’t some totally unpredictable anomaly — or purely the work of bad actors in the administration of then-President Donald Trump. Instead, we watched what happens when an organizational culture of caution meets truly toxic politics during an emergency. And the people I talked to said the same issues that have haunted the CDC in the past are still looming over its future. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1299" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1207923344-cc.jpg?w=700" alt="An electronic billboard sponsored by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention provides tips for the public on ways to prevent the spread of coronavirus." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1207923344-cc.jpg?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1207923344-cc.jpg?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1207923344-cc.jpg?w=1400 2x"><figcaption>Early in the pandemic, the CDC emphasized good hygiene over mask-wearing because the science hadn’t confirmed that masks were highly effective at stopping the spread of COVID-19. <p>PAUL HENNESSY / NURPHOTO VIA GETTY IMAGES</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>THE MASK MUDDLE</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The classic example of the CDC’s confused approach during the COVID-19 pandemic is the one that’s literally right in front of our faces: masks. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Questions like whether to wear them, what kind to wear, and when they matter have been a major source of conflict and contradictory information since the earliest days of the pandemic. In February 2020, the U.S. surgeon general famously <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/27/science/face-mask-guidelines-timeline.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pleaded with Americans to stop buying masks</a>. The next month, the CDC issued guidelines for COVID-19 protections that made no mention of masks at all. Meanwhile, other countries’ public health officials were <a href="https://time.com/5799964/coronavirus-face-mask-asia-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">distributing masks</a> or actively making them mandatory, and the Pan American Health Organization/World Health Organization <a href="https://www.paho.org/en/news/28-2-2020-face-masks-during-outbreaks-who-when-where-and-how-use-them" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recommended masks only for people experiencing symptoms of illness</a> and <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/03/who-should-wear-a-face-mask-30-march-who-briefing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their caregivers</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even when the CDC did begin to <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/69/wr/mm6928e3.htm?s_cid=mm6928e3_w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recommend mask-wearing for everyone</a> in early April 2020, a National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine report came out less than a week later that <a href="https://www.nap.edu/catalog/25776/rapid-expert-consultation-on-the-effectiveness-of-fabric-masks-for-the-covid-19-pandemic-april-8-2020" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found little evidence</a> to support cloth mask-wearing as an effective way to prevent the spread of disease. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If it seemed as though no one knew what they were doing, that’s because no one really did, said Dr. Richard Besser, a former acting director of the CDC who sat on a subcommittee that prepared the National Academies’ mask report. Public health recommendations are built on scientific evidence, and at the time, there just wasn’t much research on the effects of community-wide mask usage or cloth masks at all, he told me. What evidence did exist wasn’t very promising — but that didn’t mean you could rule out masks’ usefulness. The Great Mask Debacle wasn’t an issue of who was telling the truth. It was an issue of there just not being much truth to tell. </p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="767" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1204957936-cc.jpg?w=700" alt="A woman wearing a face mask" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1204957936-cc.jpg?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1204957936-cc.jpg?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1204957936-cc.jpg?w=1400 2x"><figcaption>
A lack of guidance on mask-wearing from the CDC contributed to the novel coronavirus spreading unchecked in the early days of the pandemic. <p>TAYFUN COSKUN / ANADOLU AGENCY VIA GETTY IMAGES</p></figcaption></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">In a public health emergency, especially one involving a completely new virus, scientific evidence is going to be limited and what it tells us will change. The problem, experts said, wasn’t so much that there was uncertainty about mask usage — that kind of initial lack of data is par for the course in a crisis that involves a completely new virus. The problem was in how the CDC and other groups communicated about that uncertainty. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It’s that, ‘Hey, we’re going to level with you that we don’t know,’ that’s really important,” Besser said. Foreshadowing the reality that information will change is something he himself remembered doing in press conferences during the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic. This time, though, he watched as the CDC first didn’t really talk about its own uncertainty and then slowly disappeared from press conferences altogether. “Then, when new guidance would come forward, it seemed like it was dropped from the sky. Because we hadn’t been brought along on that journey,” he said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Besser was relieved that he was merely summarizing the smattering of mask data rather than trying to make decisions about what to do with it. The people on his subcommittee worried that a masking recommendation would send Americans out in public, perhaps inadequately prepared, at a time when they needed to just avoid other humans entirely. But the lack of a recommendation from the CDC early on, when other countries were already masking — or a clear explanation of why guidelines differed — helped set a tone, contributing to a larger zeitgeist of Americans being unsure whether the CDC knew what to do, or if it did, whether it would tell them. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2021-04/rc-pti040521.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an effect we can see</a> playing out in <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/05/13/996331692/poll-finds-public-health-has-a-trust-problem" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling data</a>. Morning Consult, for example, <a href="https://morningconsult.com/views-on-the-pandemic/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has tracked Americans’ net approval</a> — that is, positive approval ratings minus negative approval ratings — of several government roles and agencies since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic, and while the CDC has remained the group with the highest net approval for its handling of COVID-19, the agency still lost trust during this pandemic. The tracking poll began on March 1, 2020, with a +63 percentage-point net approval and ended on June 20, 2021, at +37. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="Public approval of the CDC fell during the pandemic" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/1I27B/4/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="377" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">It’s an enormous drop, especially compared with public health agencies in other countries, such as Taiwan, Vietnam and South Korea, which gained trust during the COVID-19 pandemic, said Gil Eyal, a professor of sociology at Columbia University who studies the history and sociology of public health.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This finding is particularly significant because those countries’ public health agencies are based on the CDC. The way those other organizations are structured, the work they do, how they communicate with the public — everything about them right down to the name in many cases — were patterned on our CDC, according to Jennifer Nuzzo, a professor at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. For the CDC to lose trust as badly as it did when other countries were using the tools the CDC had left them to build trust in their nations suggests something must have really gone wrong. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1365" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1211656447-cc.jpg?w=700" alt="Dr. Anthony Fauci, director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Dr. Deborah Birx, White House coronavirus response coordinator, Dr. Robert Redfield, director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and U.S. Surgeon General Jerome Adams listen as President Donald J. Trump speaks during a COVID-19 briefing." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1211656447-cc.jpg?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1211656447-cc.jpg?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1211656447-cc.jpg?w=1400 2x"><figcaption>President Trump’s administration pushed public health officials to the side throughout the pandemic. Outside experts say that a lack of visibility hurt the CDC when it needed to issue new guidance. <p>JABIN BOTSFORD / THE WASHINGTON POST VIA GETTY IMAGES</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>POLITICS AND THE PEANUT GALLERY</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Should schools be open? Should they be closed? In summer 2020, everyone had an opinion, and the CDC appeared to be caught in the middle. The <a href="https://kstp.com/health/american-academy-of-pediatrics-strongly-supports-students-returning-to-schools-in-fall/5777226/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">American Academy of Pediatrics</a> and the <a href="https://www.chalkbeat.org/2020/7/8/21317419/trump-devos-schools-pandemic-reopening-funding" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump administration</a> pushed for reopening schools. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/29/us/teacher-union-school-reopening-coronavirus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Teachers unions</a> pushed to keep them closed. There really wasn’t much evidence to prove what <em>was</em> safe until later in the fall, and in the meantime, public health experts, education experts and scientists debated on Twitter and in the nation’s op-ed pages. At first, the CDC’s guidance on what schools could do to reopen safely was influenced by and edited to conform to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/15/us/cdc-coronavirus-checklists-decision-trees.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump administration priorities</a>, resulting mostly in the same nonspecific advice it offered all public buildings plus a few administration-inserted reminders that reopening schools was important for kids. Later, when the agency included a safety checklist, the administration <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/07/08/888898194/trump-blasts-expensive-cdc-guidelines-for-reopening-schools" target="_blank" rel="noopener">publicly criticized it as extreme</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How much of that school problem, and others like it, was attributable to Trump administration interference and pressure on the CDC is something experts don’t agree on. Some, such as Patrick McConnon, who headed up the agency’s Emerging and Reemerging Infectious Disease Program from 1994 to 2002, thought Trump was the main problem. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And, to be sure, the Trump administration did things that not only were well outside established norms but also undermined the CDC and the entire field of public health. For example, on April 3, 2020, while <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/03/trump-cdc-recommends-cloth-face-covering-to-protect-against-coronavirus.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announcing the agency’s recommendation</a> to wear masks, the president <a href="https://www.rev.com/blog/transcripts/donald-trump-coronavirus-briefing-transcript-april-3-new-cdc-face-mask-recommendations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">repeatedly emphasized that no one <em>had</em> to wear masks</a> and explicitly said that he personally wasn’t going to wear one.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The administration also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/09/11/exclusive-trump-officials-interfered-with-cdc-reports-on-covid-19-412809" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pushed for edits to the CDC’s Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Reports</a>, long the primary means for communicating scientific data to other researchers and the broader medical community. These edits were political, designed to downplay the growing number of COVID-19 deaths and support decisions the administration had already made about issues like school reopenings. Emails revealed that members of the Trump administration were accusing the CDC of trying to make the administration look bad by releasing data disclosing the dire nature of the pandemic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Those kinds of actions by a presidential administration were unprecedented. And they contributed to a loss of morale and a sense within the CDC that everyone just needed to keep their heads down and not make waves. But the political issues weren’t just about what the administration did — they were also about what it didn’t do. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By early March 2020, the CDC had all but disappeared from press briefings on the COVID-19 pandemic. No one in the Trump administration ever explicitly said that the agency wouldn’t be speaking to the public. But, quietly, that’s exactly what happened. By May 2020, the <a href="https://www.ucsusa.org/sites/default/files/2020-05/let-scientists-speak-fig-3-thumb.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Union of Concerned Scientists could graph the disappearance of the CDC</a>. And this was a completely different situation from what had happened in past pandemics, when presidents let the CDC take the lead. </p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe title="White House, not CDC, led early pandemic press events" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/k3lD4/2/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="400" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">At the same time, the Trump administration did not seem to facilitate communication between the CDC and outside experts — something the scientists I spoke to said had been the norm for past administrations faced with a public health crisis. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">During the 2009 H1N1 pandemic, for example, the CDC had regular press conferences that involved briefing documents developed with outside experts, Nuzzo said. There was also a Team B — outside experts brought into the CDC to hash out the pros and cons of possible guidelines and decisions before they were announced. None of those things happened during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That had real consequences, said Dr. James Lawler, a director of the University of Nebraska Medical Center’s Global Center for Health Security, because the CDC is fundamentally an institution of academic researchers, not people with expertise in health care delivery and administration. Since there were no formalized systems for outside input, the rollout of monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19 was bungled, he said, as the CDC and Food and Drug Administration distributed those medications in ways that made it <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/31/opinion/covid-monoclonal-antibodies-treatment.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">harder to get them to the right people</a> at the right time. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“What people didn't realize is the way you identify a potential person who would need the therapeutic, and give it [as] an IV infusion in an outpatient setting, is completely outside of how the normal workflow of health care operates,” said Lawler. This lack of expertise within the federal government made it extremely <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/authorized-monoclonal-antibody-rarely-treat-covid-19/story?id=74787113" target="_blank" rel="noopener">difficult to get lifesaving medications to patients</a> who needed them. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The absence of press conferences and outside consultation left a vacuum that was filled by social media commentary, and that became a more important source of scientific criticism of the CDC’s choices. Take the debate over the <a href="https://www.contagionlive.com/view/cdc-guidelines-shift-amid-coronavirus-aerosol-debate--" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CDC’s September 2020 statement</a> that the novel coronavirus was airborne — information <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2020/09/21/cdc-covid-aerosols-airborne-guidelines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it then removed from its web page three days later</a>. Social media <a href="https://twitter.com/jljcolorado/status/1288932022547656704?lang=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was full</a> of posts from <a href="https://twitter.com/angie_rasmussen/status/1303353169234124800" target="_blank" rel="noopener">different experts</a> with <a href="https://twitter.com/DFisman/status/1388124916478795783" target="_blank" rel="noopener">different perspectives</a> either critiquing or praising these moves. That way of debating science was to everybody’s detriment.</p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="767" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1228112682-cc.jpg?w=700" alt="A person in a vehicle holds a sign that reads 'The Virus Isn't Over Just Because You're Over It!&quot;." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1228112682-cc.jpg?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1228112682-cc.jpg?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1228112682-cc.jpg?w=1400 2x"><figcaption><p>SCOTT EISEN / GETTY IMAGES</p></figcaption></figure></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Twitter and other social media platforms brought conversations that had been done in scientific spaces into a very public, very contentious and very advocacy-influenced world. In that environment, disagreements could turn into virulent arguments, and some scientists took off their research hats and put on the mantle of hashtag activism, said Dr. Vinay Prasad, a professor of epidemiology and biostatistics at the University of California San Francisco. Prasad has <a href="https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/title/ending-medical-reversal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">studied the difficulty of changing medical advice to match new evidence</a>, and he told me that social media battles and the way that medium hardened lines made it difficult for scientists to communicate about nuanced issues with one another and with the public. The evidence around a new virus is always going to change, and if people have come to the conclusion that they have to hold a hard line as being pro-mask in a world where the only other option is anti-mask, there’s no space left to talk about (or fund research on) whether masks are more useful in some situations than in others. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Public health has always been fundamentally political. But in this case, politics and social media helped fuel a real politicization of both the CDC and the information it produced. By fall 2020, views on the CDC and its leadership were <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/09/10/trust-cdc-fauci-evaporating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">splitting along party lines</a>. In May 2021, there were visible partisan splits in both <a href="https://thehill.com/policy/healthcare/554204-overnight-health-care-state-vaccine-rates-fall-along-red-blue-divide-cdc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vaccination rates</a> and <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/poll-finding/kff-covid-19-vaccine-monitor-may-2021/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">understanding the CDC’s updated mask guidance</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, those splits aren’t huge or hardened, but we’ve seen regulatory science agencies — and the fields they study — quickly go from trusted bipartisan sources of information to symbols of political affiliation. The <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/donald-trump-paris-climate-agreement/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Environmental Protection Agency, for example, became politicized</a> in the span of only a few years, beginning around 1990. That shift precipitated others. Over the past few decades, we’ve watched as the U.S. has gone from a reliable cosigner of international environmental treaties, ratifying protection measures easily, to a holdout country where environmental stewardship is seen as politically suspicious. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Suspicion of the CDC has made some Americans <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-53327906" target="_blank" rel="noopener">question how involved the U.S. should be</a> in global public health. That distrust doesn’t go away with Trump out of office. Enough has happened that the era of the CDC being a trusted government agency even for people who don’t trust the government in general may be over. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2048" height="1365" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1323895322-cc.jpg?w=700" alt="Welcome sign at a hardware store with new mask guidelines for vaccinated and unvaccinated shoppers." data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1323895322-cc.jpg?w=700" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1323895322-cc.jpg?w=700 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/GettyImages-1323895322-cc.jpg?w=1400 2x"><figcaption> After the CDC issued new masking guidance with seemingly no warning, businesses and governments scrambled to establish new rules. <p>MICHAEL SILUK / UCG / UNIVERSAL IMAGES GROUP VIA GETTY IMAGES</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>MOVING SLOWLY TOWARD A SUDDEN DECISION</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">When the CDC changed its mask guidance again in spring 2021, the move came quickly. By then, evidence showed that mask usage prevented the transmission of COVID-19, and the CDC had recently reaffirmed its guidelines that everyone, vaccinated or not, should be wearing masks in most public settings. Then, on May 13, that changed. <a href="https://time.com/6049612/cdc-mask-guidance-mistake/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fully vaccinated people didn’t need masks</a> anywhere, the CDC said. There was <a href="https://www.webmd.com/lung/news/20210527/doctors-nurses-blast-cdcs-mask-guidance-change" target="_blank" rel="noopener">little warning</a> of this switch. Even the Biden administration appeared to be <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/surprise-cdc-reversal-masks-leaves-states-businesses-scrambling/story?id=77691769" target="_blank" rel="noopener">caught off guard</a>. Multiple states dropped public mask mandates just as quickly, and the public — and the CDC’s public image — reeled. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It was another moment of chaos in a long year and a sign that whatever your beliefs about the Trump administration, its demise didn’t magically right the floundering CDC. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In fact, several experts pointed to this sudden shift as, ironically, an example of how the agency’s tendency to be slow and cautious was hurting its public trust. That’s because, while the decision came quickly, there wasn’t much new evidence to prompt it. We had <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/05/14/health/cdc-masks-vaccines-variants.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">known for months that vaccinated people were well-protected</a> from contracting or spreading COVID-19. As with implementing masks — or describing Zika as a cause of birth defects — you could easily criticize the choice as both too fast <em>and</em> too slow. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“If it takes six months for somebody to say, ‘Vaccines are so good, you don't need to mask anymore,’ you may start to wonder why they took that time,” Prasad said. “Was there any substantive new evidence? Or was it just sort of a reluctance to say what may have been initially unpopular but might have been right all along?”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The CDC’s risk aversion had complicated its messaging yet again. Most of the experts I spoke to also thought the roots of some of the CDC’s problems during the pandemic year lay in the way the agency wants to get things right and not deem science definitive too soon. “CDC is an extremely academic institution,” Besser said. “And in settings where science is incomplete, where we just don't have the studies, the agency frequently finds it very hard to make guidance that is useful. Because if you don't have the science, it can be hard to tell people what they want to know, which is 'Well, how risky is this?'” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But what counts as enough proof? And what if the data never comes? Several researchers told me there hasn’t been the data collection necessary to understand which non-pharmaceutical interventions — masks, distancing, etc. — worked to reduce the spread of COVID-19, and under what conditions. Effective March 10, Texas became the first state in 2021 to abolish its masking requirements and other COVID-19 restrictions — at that time, only 11 percent of the state’s population age 16 and older was fully vaccinated. <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w28804" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Recent preliminary research</a> has shown that this decision neither improved the state’s economy (as politicians there predicted) nor increased COVID-19 case rates (as scientific experts feared). And no one knows why. This is the kind of question that experts said the data hadn’t been collected to answer. Without that, the public health community will be no better equipped to reduce uncertainty during the next pandemic. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“We did a hundred thousand different things to combat the virus,” Prasad said. “At the end of it, for [most everything], we will never have any more clarity. We will never know if, you know, we should have closed that mall in Vermont. And, to me, that is a type of science failure.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This isn’t just a CDC problem. Evidence-based medicine in general can have a tendency to delay decisions and wait for more evidence despite no clear point at which the new evidence will be sufficient. There’s an idea that staying conservative is what preserves trust. But it’s not surprising to experts to see that idea backfire — it just shows that risk analysis is a thing that even scientists have a hard time coming to grips with. Scientists are, after all, people. And research shows that all people are uncomfortable with ambiguity. “People want public health, including the CDC, to tell them exactly what they can and cannot do, and that’s not possible,” said Saskia Popescu, professor of public health at the University of Arizona. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To not make the same mistakes in the future, the CDC needs better communication with more foreshadowing of the change that accompanies any crisis. It needs better mechanisms taking in advice and having conversations with outside experts. And it needs systems that can collect epidemiological data and start answering questions that will reduce ambiguity in the first place. Nuzzo suggested having a pot of money set aside for sociological and epidemiological research that could go through approval processes in advance of a disaster and be launched immediately when the conditions those researchers want to study happen. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We grappled with uncertainty during the COVID-19 pandemic — and in important ways, we lost. Now, as the crisis winds down, the CDC and the public health community will need to deal with that and change course. Otherwise, Prasad said, “I don’t think we’re any better-positioned for the next crisis, whatever that may be.” </p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional research by Mary Radcliffe. Art direction by Emily Scherer. Charts by Jasmine Mithani. Copy editing by Jennifer Mason. Story editing by Chadwick Matlin.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167277</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Republicans Are Starting To Make Their Own Climate Agenda</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/why-republicans-are-starting-to-make-their-own-climate-agenda/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Galen Druke， Nate Silver， Sarah Frostenson and Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Video</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p>In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew looks at the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/24/biden-meeting-senate-bipartisan-infrastructure-talks-495941" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/24/biden-meeting-senate-bipartisan-infrastructure-talks-495941" data-sk="tooltip_parent">Senate’s $600 billion infrastructure plan</a> and discusses the value of a bipartisan strategy, the motivations behind it and the likelihood of Congress reaching a compromise. Science reporter Maggie Koerth also joins to talk about Republicans’ <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/23/us/politics/a-growing-number-of-republicans-are-working-to-address-climate-change.html?partner=slack&amp;smid=sl-share" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/06/23/us/politics/a-growing-number-of-republicans-are-working-to-address-climate-change.html?partner=slack&amp;smid=sl-share" data-sk="tooltip_parent">shifting attitudes</a> on climate change.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 12:38:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167276</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Peer Pressure, Not Politics, May Matter Most When It Comes To Getting The COVID-19 Vaccine</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/peer-pressure-not-politics-may-matter-most-when-it-comes-to-getting-the-covid-19-vaccine/</link>
						<dc:creator>Daniel Cox</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Daniel Cox</dc:creator>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<category>COVID-19 Vaccine</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>Friendship</category>
			<category>Republicans</category>
			<description><![CDATA[
<p data-paragraph="main">As the COVID-19 vaccination rate slows down in the U.S. — according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, only about <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/us/covid-19-vaccine-doses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">54 percent of the eligible population was fully vaccinated</a> as of Monday morning — <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/06/09/1004430257/theres-a-stark-red-blue-divide-when-it-comes-to-states-vaccination-rates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">red states are falling behind</a>. The lowest vaccination rates are in deep-red states like <a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#vaccinations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mississippi and Alabama</a>, while deep-blue states like Vermont and Massachusetts have had far more success in vaccinating their residents. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This widening gulf between red and blue states has <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/06/12/politics/vaccinations-blue-red-states-analysis/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reignited</a> <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/blue-state-red-state-vaccine-142600412.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fears</a> that politics is seriously undermining the nation’s vaccination efforts. And for good reason: There is a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/05/partisan-divide-vaccinations-491947" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stark and growing divide</a> in the vaccination rates in Republican- and Democratic-leaning parts of the country. But the singular focus on politics ignores the critical role that social pressure plays in deciding whether to get the COVID-19 vaccine.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For starters, Republicans are simply less likely to have friends who have been vaccinated. In <a href="https://www.americansurveycenter.org/research/the-state-of-american-friendship-change-challenges-and-loss/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a May survey</a> conducted by the American Enterprise Institute’s Survey Center on American Life, where I serve as director, less than half of Republicans (46 percent) said that most or all of their friends had received at least a single dose of the vaccine. For Democrats, meanwhile, vaccination is the norm among their peers. Two-thirds said that most or all of their friends had been at least partially vaccinated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, Republicans were far less likely than Democrats in this survey to have received any encouragement from friends or family members to get vaccinated (28 percent versus 55 percent, respectively). In fact, one in three Republicans reported that friends or family had advised them not to get the vaccine or that they had received mixed messages about the importance of getting one. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This finding is noteworthy because while partisanship is a factor in influencing our behaviors, social science research consistently shows that our friends exert a profound — and often invisible — influence on us. For instance, if you have friends who smoke or are obese, your <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2016/04/why-the-poor-die-young/477846/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chances of smoking or being obese</a> increase significantly.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So it may be for getting the COVID-19 vaccine. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Americans whose immediate social circle was entirely vaccinated were far more likely than those with fewer vaccinated friends to have gotten the vaccine themselves per the study by the Survey Center on American Life. And despite reporting higher rates of vaccine hesitancy overall, this was true among Republicans as well. Ninety-three percent of Republicans whose friends were at least partially vaccinated had also been vaccinated. By contrast, only 19 percent of Republicans with just a few or no friends who were partially vaccinated said that they had gotten the jab.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>If your friends are vaccinated, you probably are too</h5>
 <p>Share of respondents who are at least partially vaccinated by how many of their friends are also at least partially vaccinated, overall and by party</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="cox.vaccine-hesitancy-0630.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1"></th>
 <th colspan="3">% vaccinated respondents</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1">Share of vaccinated Friends</th>
 <th colspan="1">All</th>
 <th colspan="1">Republicans</th>
 <th colspan="1">Democrats</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>All of them</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">98%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">93%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">100%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Most of them</td>
 <td>90</td>
 <td>85</td>
 <td>93</td>
 </tr><tr><td>About half</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>52</td>
 <td>70</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Just a few or none</td>
 <td>27</td>
 <td>19</td>
 <td>35</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Respondents self-reported the vaccination status of their social group.</p>
 <p>Source: Survey Center on American Life</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, self-selection may play a role in this relationship, as our friends generally share our values, but even when this study controlled for personal factors such as age, gender, race, ethnicity and political affiliation, the results indicated that the vaccination status of our friends strongly predicts our own.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We should not dismiss the role of politics in vaccine hesitancy, but among Republicans, this reluctance is not universal. Nor are the reasons for this reluctance uniformly political. A May <a href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/issue-brief/vaccination-rates-are-relatively-high-for-older-adults-but-lag-in-counties-in-the-south-in-counties-with-higher-poverty-rates-and-in-counties-that-voted-for-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kaiser Family Foundation survey</a> found, for instance, that the political gap among people age 65 and older was relatively modest. Older Americans in Trump-voting counties did not lag far behind those in Biden-voting counties in getting vaccinated (63 percent versus 71 percent). Rather, the age group expressing the greatest level of vaccine hesitancy was younger adults<a href="https://morningconsult.com/covid19-vaccine-dashboard/#section-23" target="_blank" rel="noopener">:</a> A June <a href="https://morningconsult.com/covid19-vaccine-dashboard/#section-23" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult survey</a> found that 43 percent of 18- to 34-year-olds were unwilling to get or uncertain about getting vaccinated.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Because COVID-19 is so much more dangerous for <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02483-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">older people</a>, they likely have greater personal incentives to get vaccinated, but they also probably face more social pressure as well. Again, the Survey Center on American Life study found that older Americans — Democrats and Republicans alike — were far more likely than younger Americans to have vaccinated friends.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Americans experience widely different levels of social pressure to get the COVID-19 vaccine. And for better or worse, our friends exercise considerable influence over the information we have and the decisions we make. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1626126815167275</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
