<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 04:59:06 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 03:59:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Trust In Institutions Is Eroding On Both Sides Of The Pond, And The Queen Was Not Exempt</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/strongtrust-in-institutions-is-eroding-on-both-sides-of-the-pond-and-the-queen-was-not-exempt-strong/</link>
						<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>Democracy</category>
			<category>Monarchy</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Queen Elizabeth II</category>
			<category>Societal Distrust</category>
			<category>United Kingdom</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/monarchy/" name="">Monarchy</a></p>
						
													<h1>Trust In Institutions Is Eroding On Both Sides Of The Pond, And The Queen Was Not Exempt</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Zoha Qamar</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 16, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0916_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0916_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Last Thursday, word of Queen Elizabeth II’s ailing health captured an international audience. In the United States, media outlets breathlessly covered the story for hours until the announcement of her death unleashed an even larger outpouring from leaders and citizens across the globe. Condolences eulogizing the life of the queen, however, <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2022/09/twitters-messy-mourning-of-queen-elizabeth-ii.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">buzzed alongside commentary</a> criticizing the institution of the monarchy itself. And stateside, some wondered why <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/14/us/america-queen-death-royal-family.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a sizable share of Americans</a> seemed so invested in the life of the leader of a country from which early Americans sought independence. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That tendency is particularly confusing when we don’t have nearly as much positive emotional investment in our own government institutions. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-americans-dont-trust-institutions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trust in American political structures</a> is plummeting, and there is a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/national-media-coverage-of-black-lives-matter-had-fallen-during-the-trump-era-until-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">growing awareness of societal inequities</a>. But some dynamics at play in the United Kingdom may not be so removed from the existential crossroads Americans are facing in the States culturally and politically. An increasing disapproval of the monarchy among younger Britons suggests a common plot of crumbling institutional faith is unfolding in parallel on both sides of the pond. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the whole, the crown isn’t necessarily in immediate crisis. According to a mid-May <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/society/articles-reports/2022/06/01/platinum-jubilee-where-does-public-opinion-stand-m" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> that surveyed Britons on whether they thought the monarchy should continue or be replaced with an elected head of state, 62 percent favored the crown, while a mere 22 percent preferred an elected leader. In the modern era, the monarch is by and large a ceremonial figurehead who symbolically oversees the army, heads the Church of England and sits as an aspirational, dignified role model meant to inspire the best of the British. Many Britons saw the queen in this light, and while her son Charles has historically not been the most popular royal — in May, <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/05/31/platinum-jubilee-how-popular-are-royals" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov</a> reported that 54 percent of Britons held positive views of Charles and 47 percent held positive views of his wife, Camilla — Elizabeth II (81 percent), Prince William (75 percent) and Kate (70 percent) all clocked in much higher. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Following Elizabeth’s death, much of the news coverage has labeled the queen as a “stabilizing” or “steadfast” figure who represented continuity for Britain. After all, the vast majority of Britons (and the global population) living today were born after she inherited the crown. But some have pointed out that the gravitas of her reign <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/09/12/1122238140/queen-elizabeth-ii-death-commonwealth-countries-colonial-history" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whitewashed a lot of its colonial empire</a> aftermath, which <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2022/sep/13/queen-reign-death-elizabeth-ii-uk-minorities-british-empire" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wasn’t really so stable</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And the queen’s youngest subjects viewed her reign and her family in the least favorable light. While the overall popularity of the British monarchs has remained relatively stagnant in <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/gv41ilgxav/YouGov%20-%20Jubilee%20Tracker.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prior YouGov polling</a> over the past decade, a breakdown by age group reveals a dramatic, consistent shift among younger Britons in the years since. Whereas 64 percent of 18- to 24-year-olds favored the monarchy in a May-June 2012 survey, just 33 percent agreed in 2022. And while only 23 percent preferred an elected head of state in May-June 2012, that number rose to 31 percent this May. In other words, the gleaming facade of royalty appears to be tarnishing among Britain’s next generation, which various commentators attribute to a host of dynamics and events: calls to recognize <a href="https://time.com/6212824/queen-elizabeth-iis-reign-violence-british-empire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">colonialism’s damage</a>, Prince Andrew’s Jeffrey Epstein-affiliated <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/09/04/jeffrey-epstein-prince-andrew-royal-family-abuse-britain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sexual-assault case</a> and a general distaste for vastly unequal hereditary hierarchy facilitated by <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/king-charles-backlash-tax-exemption-queen-million-fortune-1742402" target="_blank" rel="noopener">taxpayer dollars</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, if you ask most Americans, the shiny promise of a governmental system anchored by an elected leader isn’t all it’s cracked up to be either. As in Britain, the dissatisfaction is especially strong among the young. According to <a href="https://int.nyt.com/data/documenttools/us0722-crosstabs-nyt071422/f034d2429900e8eb/full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a New York Times/Siena College poll</a> from July, about 67 percent of American voters under 30 said that this country’s governmental structure needs to be completely replaced or majorly reformed, and even 43 percent of U.S. voters 65 and over — by far the least likely to say such change was needed — agreed. Still, other responses from the survey broken down by age reveal just how cynical younger Americans are toward both the current state of the country and the possibility of remedying it. Just 28 percent of 18- to 29-year-olds thought that the nation’s political system could address its problems, versus 47 percent of those 65 and over who agreed. Meanwhile, only 49 percent under 30 have faith that voting in elections lets everyday people make a difference in their government, compared with a solid 81 percent of the oldest age group. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That open attitude toward change is something young Britons and young Americans have in common. Both groups voice a straightforward desire to see refreshed approaches in tackling key issues at the bedrock of national identity. Britons, echoing their American counterparts, display less loyalty toward institutions beyond Buckingham Palace. In 2021, the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/global/2021/05/05/6-tradition-vs-change/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center</a> found that, across the board, a similar percentage of 18- to 29-year-olds said their country would ultimately benefit from a willingness to change its traditions: 78 percent in the U.S. and 76 percent in the U.K. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the exact political priorities and opinions each cohort has varies based on different national issues and pasts, but both demonstrate a stronger willingness to look their respective histories in the eye, at least relative to their older counterparts. For example, according to a <a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/sites/default/files/RaceBLM100Crosstabs.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Massachusetts Amherst poll in April 2021</a>, 18- to 29-year-old Americans were almost twice as likely (57 percent) as those 55 and over (30 percent) to say that the United States should pay reparations to descendants of enslaved people. Meanwhile, a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/z7uxxko71z/YouGov%20-%20British%20empire%20attitudes.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov survey from 2019</a> reported that 18 percent of Britons age 18 to 24 consider the British empire a proud part of the country’s history; that number more than doubled among those over 65 (43 percent). </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The late queen was lauded during her life for her strong ability to stay “apolitical” and “neutral.” Looking ahead, however, younger Britons expressed in a <a href="https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/09/13/britons-first-impressions-king-charles-iii" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov poll</a> that they don’t see an issue with King Charles III taking a fresh approach: 70 percent of 18- to 24-year-olds said it would be appropriate for him to stay vocal on issues he’s cared about and spoken of before, while 51 of those over 65 said such conduct would be inappropriate, suggesting an approach in line with his mother’s. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At 73, Charles hardly counts as a “young person,” but if he chooses to maintain a personal norm on politics different from the queen’s, that could make him a monarch at least somewhat more in line with the younger generation’s views. Still, whether older political figures can bring the changes young people in the U.K. and U.S. clearly want remains to be seen. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>An Aug. 1-14 <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2022/09/08/republicans-and-democrats-have-different-top-priorities-for-u-s-immigration-policy/?utm_content=buffer13b2f&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer">study from Pew</a> highlights how partisan divides stack up on policy ideas surrounding immigration. A sweeping majority (79 percent) of Republicans said increasing deportations for undocumented immigrants was at least a somewhat important policy goal, while about half as many (39 percent) Democrats agreed. Additionally, a majority of Americans on both sides of the aisle support greater security at the Southern border, although that jumps to almost all (91 percent) Republicans versus about 3 in 5 (59 percent) Democrats. </li></ul><ul><li>As we mark two and a half years since many office workers first adjusted to new in-person, hybrid and remote protocols, American employees’ worries about COVID-19 have tapered overall, according to a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/400904/risk-covid-exposure-concern-employees.aspx">Gallup poll</a> conducted July 26-Aug. 2. The share of the American workforce very or moderately concerned about coronavirus exposure on the job has reached a low of 33 percent, down considerably from its peak of 51 percent in July 2020, although that number continues to look different across gender, party ID and job type. Working women (41 percent) are considerably more concerned than working men (26 percent) about exposure, and employed Democrats (51 percent) are more than three times as likely as their Republican counterparts (14 percent) to say they’re worried. Meanwhile, concern among blue-collar (24 percent) and white-collar (33 percent) employees has dwindled, although the survey did break out two specific fields where worries remain higher than that of the overall share of workers (33 percent): Americans working in health care (42 percent) and education (53 percent). </li></ul><ul><li>When it comes to healthy eating, most Americans would prefer to eat produce and fresh foods over going on diets. Per an Aug. 29-30 <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/09/12/the-paradox-of-healthy-eating/">Morning Consult poll</a>, 91 percent of adults agree that eating fruits and vegetables is at least somewhat necessary for a healthy lifestyle, whereas far fewer said the same about dieting (28 percent) or intermittent fasting (37 percent). Overall, 80 percent reported that major reasons to eat healthy included feeling good long-term, while 70 percent of baby boomers also said not getting sick was a huge motivation. Meanwhile, Gen Z and millennials were the most likely to note that eating healthy helped them feel their best mentally (73 percent), look their best (60 percent) and fuel fitness performance (46 percent). </li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> 42.3 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 53.1 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.8 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-is-more-unpopular-than-ever-that-could-help-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.4 percent approved and 53.2 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -10.8 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 40.2 percent and a disapproval rating of 55.2 percent, for a net approval rating of -15.0 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> Democrats currently lead by 1.4 points (44.8 percent to 43.4 percent). <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-is-more-unpopular-than-ever-that-could-help-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A week ago</a>, Democrats led Republicans by 1.2 points (44.9 percent to 43.7 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Democrats by 0.5 points (43.9 percent to 43.4 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663326001606776</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Will The Polls Overestimate Democrats Again?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-the-polls-overestimate-democrats-again/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Will The Polls Overestimate Democrats Again?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 16, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0916-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">As Democrats’ prospects for the midterms have improved — they’re now up to a 71 percent chance of keeping the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Senate</a> and a 29 percent chance of retaining the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House</a>, according to the 2022 FiveThirtyEight midterm election forecast<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forecast odds throughout are as of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> — I’ve observed a corresponding increase in concern among liberals that the polls might overestimate Democrats’ position again, as they did in 2016 and 2020. Even among commenters who are analyzing the race from an arm’s-length distance, there sometimes seems to be a <em>presumption</em> that the polls will be biased toward Democrats.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The best version of this argument comes from Other Nate (Nate Cohn, of The New York Times). He <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/12/upshot/polling-midterms-warning.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pointed out</a> in a piece on Monday that states such as Wisconsin and Ohio where Democratic Senate candidates are outperforming <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s fundamentals index</a> — like how the state has voted in other recent elections — were also prone to significant polling errors in 2020. Cohn’s analysis is worth reading in full.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here, I’m going to present something of a rebuttal. Not necessarily to Cohn’s specific claims, but rather to the <em>presumption </em>I often see in discussion about polling that polling bias is predictable and necessarily favors Democrats. My contention is that while the polls could have another bad year, it’s hard to know right now whether that bias will benefit Democrats or Republicans. People’s guesses about this are often wrong. In 2014, for example, there was a lot of discussion about whether the polls <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/are-the-state-polls-skewed/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">would have a pro-Republican bias</a>, as they did in 2012. But they turned out to have a pro-Democratic bias instead.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s one important complication to this, however.<em> </em>Our model actually assumes that current polling probably <em>does</em> overstate the case for Democrats. It’s just not necessarily for the reasons people assume.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As I mentioned, the Deluxe version of our forecast gives Democrats a 71 percent and 29 percent chance of keeping the Senate and House, respectively. But the Deluxe forecast isn’t just based on polls: It incorporates the fundamentals I mentioned earlier, along with <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/house-race-ratings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expert ratings</a> about these races. Furthermore, it accounts for the historical tendency of the president’s party to perform poorly at the midterms, President Biden’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mediocre</a> (although improving) approval rating and the fact that Democrats may not perform as well in polls of likely voters as among registered voters. As the election approaches, it tends to put more weight on the polls and less on these other factors, but it never zeros them out completely. (In this respect, it <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-2020-presidential-forecast-works-and-whats-different-because-of-covid-19/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">differs from our presidential forecast</a>.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By contrast, the Lite version of our forecast, which is more or less a “polls-only” view of the race, gives Democrats an 81 percent chance of keeping the Senate and a 41 percent chance of keeping the House. It also suggests that they’ll win somewhat more seats: There are 52.4 Democratic Senate seats in an average Lite simulation as compared with 50.8 in a Deluxe simulation, or 212 Democratic House seats in an average Lite simulation versus 209 in a Deluxe simulation. Notably, this corresponds to current polls overstating Democrats’ position by the equivalent of 1.5 or 2 percentage points. Put another way, we should think of a race in which the polling average shows Democrats 2 points ahead as being tied.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s not quite the same thing as saying that the polls are systematically biased, though. Polls reflect a snapshot of what is happening today, and Democrats might indeed do very well if the election were held now instead of in November. In states like Ohio, for instance, they’ve <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/can-tim-ryan-really-win-ohios-senate-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">enjoyed a significant advertising advantage</a> thanks to superior fundraising, but that will probably even out to some extent by Election Day. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, Biden and Democrats have also been on something of a winning streak lately, between a series of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/16/business/biden-climate-tax-inflation-reduction.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">policy accomplishments</a>, inflation trending downward and the political backlash to the Supreme Court’s <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/07/06/majority-of-public-disapproves-of-supreme-courts-decision-to-overturn-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpopular</a> decision to overturn Roe v. Wade. But a <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/why-a-single-u-s-inflation-report-roiled-global-financial-markets-11663185895" target="_blank" rel="noopener">worse-than-expected inflation report</a> this week and a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/15/business/rail-strike.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narrowly averted rail workers’ strike</a>, which could have caused substantial supply chain disruptions, are reminders that uncertain real-world events won’t necessarily continue to play out in Democrats’ favor.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also the case that in individual races, information besides the polls can help make a more accurate prediction, even when you have a lot of polls. For example, the <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/tree/master/partisan-lean" target="_blank" rel="noopener">partisan lean</a> of a state still tells you something. Let’s say the polling average has the Democrat ahead by 10 points in a state where the fundamentals put the Republican up by 2. Empirically, the best forecast in a race like this uses a blend of <em>mostly</em> polls and <em>some</em> fundamentals (exactly how much weight is given to the polls depends on how many polls there are and how close it is to the election). And you might end up with a forecast that has the Democrat winning by 7 or 8 points rather than 10 points, for instance. In that sense, in races such as Wisconsin and Ohio where there is a significant divergence between polls and fundamentals, Democrats probably should have concerns.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What I resist, though, is the implication that it can be presumed that the polls have a predictable, persistent, systematic bias toward Democrats. Is Rep. Tim Ryan going to underperform his current polls in Ohio’s Senate race? We’ll see, but more likely than not, the answer is yes. But is it just a thing now<em> </em>that polls <em>always</em> overrate Democrats?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">I’m skeptical. Here are seven reasons why:</p>



<h2>1. Polling bias hasn’t been predictable historically</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Our historical database of polls shows that there’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-death-of-polling-is-greatly-exaggerated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">not much in the way of consistent polling bias</a>. Two cycles of a pro-Republican bias in 1998 and 2000 were followed by a Democratic bias in 2002. A fairly sharp Republican bias in 2012 reversed itself, and the polls were biased toward Democrats in both 2014 and 2016.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Polling bias isn’t consistent</h5>
 <p>Weighted-average statistical bias in polls in final 21 days of the campaign</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="silver.pollsterratings2018.13"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Pres.</th>
 <th colspan="3" scope="colgroup">State Level</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Cycle</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">General</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Governor</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">U.S. Senate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">U.S. House</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Combined</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1998</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+5.8</td>
 <td>R+4.5</td>
 <td>R+0.9</td>
 <td>R+3.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>1999-2000</td>
 <td>R+2.4</td>
 <td>R+0.2</td>
 <td>R+2.8</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>R+1.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2001-02</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+3.5</td>
 <td>D+2.0</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 <td>D+2.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2003-04</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 <td>D+1.9</td>
 <td>D+0.8</td>
 <td>D+2.1</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2005-06</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+0.4</td>
 <td>R+2.1</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 <td>D+0.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2007-08</td>
 <td>D+1.0</td>
 <td>R+0.1</td>
 <td>D+0.1</td>
 <td>D+1.4</td>
 <td>D+0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2009-10</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+0.2</td>
 <td>R+0.8</td>
 <td>D+1.3</td>
 <td>D+0.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2011-12</td>
 <td>R+2.5</td>
 <td>R+1.6</td>
 <td>R+3.1</td>
 <td>R+3.2</td>
 <td>R+2.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2013-14</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>D+2.3</td>
 <td>D+2.7</td>
 <td>D+3.9</td>
 <td>D+2.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2015-16</td>
 <td>D+3.3</td>
 <td>D+3.1</td>
 <td>D+2.8</td>
 <td>D+3.4</td>
 <td>D+3.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2017-18</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>R+0.9</td>
 <td>EVEN</td>
 <td>R+0.8</td>
 <td>R+0.5</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2019-20</td>
 <td>D+4.2</td>
 <td>D+5.6</td>
 <td>D+5.0</td>
 <td>D+6.1</td>
 <td>D+4.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>All years</td>
 <td>D+1.3</td>
 <td>D+0.9</td>
 <td>D+0.7</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>D+1.1</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Bias is calculated only for races in which the top two finishers are a Democrat and a Republican. Therefore, it is not calculated for presidential primaries. Pollsters that are banned by FiveThirtyEight are not included in the averages. So as not to give a more prolific pollster too much influence over the average, polls are weighted by one over the square root of the number of polls each pollster conducted in a specific category.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Historically, the correlation between the polling bias in a given cycle and the bias in the previous cycle is either essentially zero or slightly negative, depending on whether you define “previous cycle” as “two years ago” or “four years ago.”<a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meaning, the bias is, if anything, more likely to reverse itself than sustain itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a></p>



<h2>2. Pollsters have a strong incentive to be unbiased</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Pollsters get a lot of crap from people, but one nice thing about their job is that they regularly get to compare their results against reality. Sure, it’s possible for a pollster to get unlucky because of <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/PollingUnit/sampling-error-means/story?id=5984818" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sampling error</a> — if you survey 500 people, sometimes you’ll draw a sample showing the Republican winning even if the Democrat is really up by 5 points. For the most part, though, pollsters can and do consider changes to their methodology based on errors in past elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And precisely because pollsters are subject to public scrutiny and there are relatively objective ways to measure their performance, they have strong financial and professional incentives to scrutinize their methods for potential sources of error and fix them if they can. It’s the same incentive that a professional golfer has to fix his swing: If he’s consistently hitting every shot to the left side of the fairway, for instance, at some point he’ll make adjustments. Maybe he’ll even overcompensate and start hitting everything to the right side instead.</p>



<h2>3. The way polling averages weight pollsters changes</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even if pollsters don’t change their methods, the market will change the polling landscape on its own, at least to some degree. Pollsters who performed well in previous elections will get more business, and those who performed poorly will lose it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For instance, we’ve seen relatively few traditional “<a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/04/19/politics/democrats-falling-lead-generic-ballot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gold standard</a>” polls sponsored by major media organizations this cycle, perhaps because those polls tended to have a Democratic bias in 2020. That’s a shame, because most of these polling organizations have <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/pollster-ratings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">good long-term track records</a> despite some recent problems. But it does mean that polling averages are more weighted toward Republican-leaning firms that have done comparatively well in recent election cycles, such as Rasmussen Reports and Trafalgar Group. This is especially true for FiveThirtyEight’s polling averages, which weight polls in part based on their historical accuracy. Groups like Rasmussen, for instance, get more say in the polling average than they did in 2020 because their rating is now higher.</p>



<h2>4. Polls haven’t had a Democratic bias in elections without Trump on the ballot</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">As you can see in the table in the first point, polls did <em>not</em> have a systematic Democratic bias in 2018. That seems relevant, considering that was the most recent midterm.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Polls have also generally not had a Democratic bias in other elections in the Trump era when Trump himself was not on the ballot. They didn’t have one in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_United_States_Senate_special_election_in_Alabama" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alabama Senate special election in 2017</a>, for instance, or the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/georgia-senate-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia Senate runoffs in January 2021</a>, or in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/virginia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last year’s Virginia gubernatorial race</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There have also been some races where Democrats have overperformed their polls, such as in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/california-recall-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last year’s California gubernatorial recall election</a> and in the <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/2017/governor/va/virginia_governor_gillespie_vs_northam-6197.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2017 governor’s race in Virginia</a>. But these errors don’t tend to get as much attention from the media as those that underestimated Republicans.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It may be that Republicans benefit from higher turnout only when Trump himself is on the ballot. A certain number of voters were willing to walk over glass to vote for Trump: Would they do the same for J.D. Vance, Mehmet Oz, Ron Johnson or Blake Masters? Evidence from non-Trump elections in the Trump era suggests maybe not. I tend not to buy the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-11-19/-shy-trump-voters-re-emerge-as-explanation-for-pollsters-miss" target="_blank" rel="noopener">so-called “shy Trump” theory</a>, or that voters are reluctant to state their preference for Trump. But it may <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-supporters-arent-shy-but-polls-could-still-be-missing-some-of-them/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nonetheless be hard to reach Trump voters</a>, who may be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/could-social-alienation-among-some-trump-supporters-help-explain-why-polls-underestimated-trump-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more socially isolated</a>, or who may be irregular voters who are screened out by likely voter models. </p>



<h2>5. Polls have been unbiased or underestimated Democrats in recent elections in 2022</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had a lot of success in elections since the Supreme Court’s Dobbs decision</a> — and importantly for our purposes, they’ve done as well or better than polls predicted in these races:</p>



<ul><li>In the Kansas abortion referendum, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-abortion-vote-in-kansas-looks-like-its-going-to-be-close/">only poll</a> showed the “yes” side — which would have enabled the Kansas Legislature to implement additional abortion restrictions — winning by 4 percentage points, but it lost by 18 points (!) instead.</li><li>Meanwhile, the only <a href="https://www.surveyusa.com/client/PollReport.aspx?g=6a557ea4-bde8-49df-a0f0-9d077812693f">nonpartisan poll</a> of the special election in Minnesota’s 1st Congressional District showed Republican Brad Finstad winning by 8 points, but he actually won by 4, although an internal poll released by his opponent <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/579258412/MN-01-Poll-Results-Memo-Ettinger-Campaign">did underestimate Finstad’s margin</a>.</li><li>That said, polls of the special election in Alaska’s at-large House seat were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2022_Alaska%27s_at-large_congressional_district_special_election">quite accurate</a> in predicting both the first-round vote and that Democrat Mary Peltola would narrowly defeat former Alaska Gov. Sarah Palin if they were the final two candidates using Alaska’s ranked-choice system.</li><li>Finally, of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2022_New_York%27s_19th_congressional_district_special_election">five polls</a> of the special election in New York’s 19th Congressional District, which were from a mix of Democratic and Republican firms, all showed Republican Marc Molinaro winning by margins ranging from 3 points to 14 points. But Democrat Pat Ryan <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/">won by 2 points instead</a>.</li></ul><p data-paragraph="main">I couldn’t find any polls for the special elections in New York’s 23rd Congressional District or Nebraka’s 1st Congressional District, also held since the Dobbs decision.</p>



<h2>6. Pollsters have a semi-decent excuse for 2020: COVID-19</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Ironically, polls conducted before large parts of the country were shut down in March 2020 in response to the COVID-19 pandemic were more accurate than those conducted immediately before Election Day in 2020. Take the FiveThirtyEight polling average on March 1, 2020. It showed <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden up by 4.1 percentage points nationally</a>, very close to his eventual 4.5-point popular vote margin. Our polling averages also correctly showed a very close race in states such as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pennsylvania</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wisconsin</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This may be because the pandemic <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2020/11/10/21551766/election-polls-results-wrong-david-shor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">profoundly affected who answered the polls</a>. Specifically, Democrats were more likely to be in jurisdictions that implemented stay-at-home orders, and liberals were otherwise more likely to voluntarily limit their social interactions. Having more time at home on their hands, they may have been more likely to respond to polls. That’s less of a concern this year, with <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1675/most-important-problem.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">few voters treating COVID-19 as a high priority</a> and few government restrictions in place.</p>



<h2>7. People are too hung up on polls from 2016 and 2020</h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/Politics-Voices/2014/1121/Elections-have-consequences-Does-Obama-regret-saying-that-now" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Elections have consequences</a>, and they’re relatively infrequent events. So the second-guessing and recriminations tend to linger for a while.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that doesn’t change the fact that people’s concerns about the polls stem mostly from a sample of exactly two elections, 2020 and 2016. You can point out that polls also had a Democratic bias in 2014. But, of course, they had a Republican bias in 2012, were largely unbiased in 2018, and have either tended to be unbiased or had a Republican bias in recent special elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">True, in 2020 and 2016, polls were off the mark in a large number of races and states. But the whole notion of a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-need-a-systematic-polling-error-to-win-the-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">systematic polling error</a> is that it’s, well, systematic: It affects nearly all races, or at least the large majority of them. There just isn’t a meaningful sample size to work with here, or anything close to it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Again, that doesn’t mean you should expect the polls to be spot-on. It may be that we’re living in a universe with larger polling errors than before in response to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/02/27/response-rates-in-telephone-surveys-have-resumed-their-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">declining response rates</a>. And there are some decent reasons to suspect that Democrats won’t perform as well in November as they would in an election right now. Still, I’ll stick to my usual advice: Prepare for the polls to be wrong — in either direction.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663326001606775</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: It’s Not Yet Time To Start Worrying About The Polls</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-its-not-yet-time-to-start-worrying-about-the-polls/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Model Talk</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-its-not-yet-time-to-start-worrying-about-the-polls/">
	<div data-podcast-id="344296" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: It's Not Yet Time To Start Worrying About The Polls">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP9025875590.mp3?updated=1663270621">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Why have Democrats’ odds of winning the House and Senate improved so consistently in recent months? Can the polls be trusted? In this installment of “Model Talk” on the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, Nate Silver and Galen Druke discuss what’s behind the recent movement in the forecast and answer questions from listeners.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 20:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663272001329716</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>This Candidate Thinks The 2020 Election Was Illegitimate. But He’d Rather You Didn’t Know That.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/this-candidate-thinks-the-2020-election-was-illegitimate-but-hed-rather-you-didnt-know-that/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Colorado Politics</category>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>This Candidate Thinks The 2020 Election Was Illegitimate. But He'd Rather You Didn't Know That.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 14, 2022, at 3:15 PM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="ELECTIO-DENIERS-AADLAND-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ELECTIO-DENIERS-AADLAND-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ELECTIO-DENIERS-AADLAND-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ELECTIO-DENIERS-AADLAND-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ELECTIO-DENIERS-AADLAND-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES / AADLAND FOR CONGRESS</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/republicans-trump-election-fraud/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Roughly 200 Republican candidates</a> running for Senate, House, governor, attorney general or secretary of state have indicated publicly that the 2020 presidential election was illegitimate, despite <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2103619118" target="_blank" rel="noopener">all the evidence</a> to <a href="https://apnews.com/article/voter-fraud-election-2020-joe-biden-donald-trump-7fcb6f134e528fee8237c7601db3328f" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the contrary</a>.<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FiveThirtyEight drew on news reports, debate footage, campaign materials and social media and reached out to every single Republican nominee for these offices to determine their position on the 2020 election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That number, though, is almost certainly an undercount. For example, according to audio the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee shared with FiveThirtyEight, Army veteran Erik Aadland, the Republican candidate for Colorado’s 7th Congressional District, told members of the <a href="https://mountainrepublicans.org/events" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mountain Republicans Club</a> on June 21 that he was concerned by how the 2020 elections were “undermined by fraud, how they were corrupted, and now how we have an illegitimate government in power.”</p>



<figure><audio controls="controls" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Aadland_Mountain-Republicans-Club_6-21-22_upload.mp3" preload="none"></audio></figure><p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight could not independently confirm the audio’s authenticity or the circumstances of its recording, though the voice in the audio is similar to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DkJJ55mGu3w" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Aadland’s</a>. However, FiveThirtyEight was able to independently confirm that Aadland spoke at the monthly meeting of the Mountain Republicans Club, a local conservative group, in Evergreen, Colorado, on June 21. His campaign did not respond to several requests for comment. We also reached out to the Mountain Republicans Club to ask about the event, but received no response.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Many candidates, like Aadland, may now be hesitant to say the 2020 election was fraudulent out of fear that it could cost them at the polls. The voice purported to be Aadland’s admitted in that leaked audio to being strategic in how he talks about the 2020 election, saying, “I don’t always use this kind of language on the campaign trail because I am so deliberate with what I say, because the consequences of not winning are so significant. So I am strategic. I don’t go out and talk about election integrity on and on and on because it’s not an issue that wins us this race.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Case in point: Colorado’s 7th District is competitive, but it is also 6 percentage points bluer than the nation as a whole, according to <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/tree/master/partisan-lean" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s partisan lean metric</a>.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> According to the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/colorado/7/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight House forecast</a>, Democratic state Sen. Brittany Pettersen has an 87-in-100 chance of winning the seat, which is open due to the retirement of Democratic Rep. Ed Perlmutter. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But at the same time, this is the exact kind of seat that could become more competitive if the national environment improves for Republicans. The district has a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/election-update-the-house-districts-that-swing-the-most-and-least-with-the-national-mood/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight elasticity score</a> of 1.14, meaning that for every 1 percentage point the national political mood moves toward a party, Colorado’s 7th District is expected to move 1.14 percentage points toward that party.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans who have denied the legitimacy of the 2020 election have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/at-least-120-republicans-who-deny-the-2020-election-results-will-be-on-the-ballot-in-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">won primaries</a> across the country and up and down the ballot this cycle, especially in House races and in Western states like Arizona and Nevada. But Colorado Republicans largely bucked this trend in their June primaries, backing businessman Joe O’Dea, who <a href="https://coloradosun.com/2022/06/01/ron-hanks-joe-odea-senate-race-issues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accepted the results of the 2020 election</a>, over state Rep. Ron Hanks, who <a href="https://coloradosun.com/2021/01/12/capitol-riot-colorado-lawmaker-ron-hanks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attended the Jan. 6, 2021, riot</a>, for U.S. Senate. Similarly, former Jefferson County Clerk Pam Anderson, who <a href="https://coloradosun.com/2022/06/08/2022-republican-secretary-of-state/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">accepted the results of the 2020 election</a>, defeated Mesa County Clerk Tina Peters, who was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-happens-when-an-election-official-believes-the-big-lie/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">indicted on charges related to a security breach allegedly stemming from her ties to election deniers</a>, in the secretary of state primary. Even Aadland himself wasn’t the most pro-Trump option in his primary; that distinction went to <a href="https://www.cpr.org/2022/06/09/colorado-congressional-district-7-election-republicans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">former Trump campaign staffer Laurel Imer</a>, who was more open about her belief that Trump was the rightful winner in 2020.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This could be one reason Aadland’s public stance on election integrity has evolved so much. He started off the election cycle running for the U.S. Senate and fully denying the 2020 election. In June 2021, he <a href="https://coloradotimesrecorder.com/2021/07/colorados-2022-u-s-senate-candidates-who-are-the-confirmed-and-potential-bennet-challengers/38017/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told the Jefferson County Men’s Club</a>, “The 2020 election, it was rigged. Absolutely rigged.” But in December of that year, he <a href="https://www.coloradopolitics.com/elections/2022/republican-erik-aadland-jumps-from-us-senate-race-to-take-on-perlmutter-in-cd-7/article_cc928bc2-66e9-11ec-814d-6f345cc6d59e.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">switched to running for the House</a>, and somewhere along the way, he started to backpedal. In April 2022, he <a href="https://omny.fm/shows/the-george-show/brauchler-4-7-22-9am" target="_blank" rel="noopener">danced around the question on conservative talk radio</a>, ultimately answering, “I’m certain there was fraud in the 2020 elections. I have a sense that it influenced the outcome. Can I say definitively? No.” (This was enough for us to reclassify him as “raised questions” and not “fully denied” in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/republicans-trump-election-fraud/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our tracker of Republicans’ stances on the 2020 election</a>.) And in August 2022 — after the Colorado primary — a <a href="https://coloradonewsline.com/briefs/gop-video-aadland-rigged-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reporter for Colorado Newsline noticed</a> that the Jefferson County Men’s Club had taken down the video with Aadland’s previous, more extreme comments.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As we enter the thick of general-election season, more candidates may distance themselves from their previous actions or rhetoric relating to the 2020 election. We’ve already identified a few examples: Virginia state Sen. Jen Kiggans, who is the Republican nominee for the commonwealth’s competitive 2nd District, was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/03/30/virginia-2nd-district-kiggans-bell/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of only four state senators</a> to vote for a “forensic audit” of the 2020 election in Virginia in early 2022, but a campaign spokesperson told FiveThirtyEight in August that Kiggans “believes Joe Biden is president.” And in January 2021, Michigan state Sen. Tom Barrett <a href="https://www.mlive.com/politics/2021/01/more-than-half-of-michigans-gop-senators-air-unfounded-election-concerns-in-letter-to-congress.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">joined with 10 other state senators</a> to send a letter to members of Congress urging them to investigate election-fraud claims. But then he started running for Congress in the swingy 7th District, and last month he responded to FiveThirtyEight’s inquiries on the 2020 election via email, acknowledging, “Joe Biden is the President.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a result of this new reporting on Aadland, we have switched his designation back to “fully denied” in our tracker. And if other candidates change their tune — either because new comments come to light or they change their position for the general election — it will be reflected on the tracker too. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 20:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663186501716092</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Went Down During The Final Primary Night Of 2022</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/live-blog/new-hampshire-ri-election/</link>
						<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>2022 House Elections</category>
			<category>2022 House Primaries</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<category>Election Results</category>
			<category>Live Blog</category>
			<category>New Hampshire Politics</category>
			<category>New Hampshire Primary</category>
			<category>New Hampshire Senate</category>
			<category>Rhode Island Election results</category>
			<category>Rhode Island Primary</category>
			<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 23:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663114501518372</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Does The Monarchy Rely On Public Approval?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-does-the-monarchy-rely-on-public-approval/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Debates</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<category>Queen Elizabeth II</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-does-the-monarchy-rely-on-public-approval/">
	<div data-podcast-id="343936" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Does The Monarchy Rely On Public Approval?">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP1334312721.mp3?updated=1663021836">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Only two midterm debates for Senate races are scheduled so far. Plenty of candidates say they’re open to debating their opponents, but only on their terms, setting up stalemates as a result. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew analyzes how debates can affect campaigns and why Senate candidates seem to be avoiding them this year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Next, the team breaks down how GOP lawmakers and candidates have been approaching potential policies on abortion after the Supreme Court’s Dobbs decision. While Republican lawmakers can’t agree on how restrictive abortion legislation should be in South Carolina and West Virginia, candidates running in the midterms are trying to distance themselves from the stricter abortion bans they supported earlier in their campaigns.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, we turn to the recent death of Queen Elizabeth II and the succession of her eldest son, King Charles III, whose popularity is significantly lower than the late monarch’s.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 23:27:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1663024501960917</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Republicans Keep Failing To Pass Abortion Bans</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-keep-failing-to-pass-abortion-bans/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Roe V. Wade</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Republicans Keep Failing To Pass Abortion Bans</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
							<p>Graphics by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/humera-lodhi/" rel="author">Humera Lodhi</a></p>
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 12, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="Abortion South Carolina" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP21034664382941-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP21034664382941-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP21034664382941-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP21034664382941-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>Jeffrey Collins / AP Photo</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Republican legislators have been waiting for years to ban abortion. But now that their moment is here, they can’t agree about what to do with it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The latest round of this drama just played out in the South Carolina Legislature, where Republicans spent two weeks debating <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/wireStory/exceptions-split-republicans-south-carolina-abortion-ban-89518740" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a full ban on abortion in the state</a> — only to deadlock on the details.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A full ban didn’t seem like it would be an especially hard sell, at least in theory. South Carolina is a red state, with <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a partisan lean</a> of R+18.6. And when the bill was introduced, most Republicans in the conservative legislature, where they outnumber Democrats nearly 2-to-1, seemed to support the general concept of banning abortion. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But they quickly splintered over the details. A group of Republicans <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/south-carolina-house-approves-total-abortion-ban-with-exceptions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">introduced a bill that banned abortion without exceptions for rape, incest and lethal fetal abnormalities</a>, but that failed after a day of pleading and accusations on the House floor. A bill with a limited set of exceptions passed the House, but those exceptions were then <a href="https://apnews.com/article/abortion-health-legislature-south-carolina-government-and-politics-6498221b8d4d48dde993d3a5a9deb1b7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stripped out of the bill</a> as soon as it landed in the state Senate. Just like that, back to square one. Late Thursday night, Senate Republicans still couldn’t agree on what form the bill should take. After a Republican briefly filibustered the full ban, the Senate settled on adding more restrictions to the state’s six-week abortion ban, which is temporarily blocked by the state Supreme Court, and sent the bill back to the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This stalemate reflects the broader conundrum facing Republican lawmakers now that the Supreme Court is no longer stopping them from outlawing abortion. The highly restrictive laws that anti-abortion advocates want to pass <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/07/30/politics/west-virginia-legislature-abortion-discussion/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are forcing</a> messy — and public — conversations about <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/07/30/republicans-roe-abortion-lgbt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">just how restrictive to be</a>. Are any exceptions — like those for rape and incest — acceptable? And how should Republicans weigh the broader political backlash against abortion bans, which has reshaped the landscape of the midterm elections?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So far, Republicans are bitterly divided over whether to push forward with the kinds of laws that passed before the Supreme Court overturned Roe v. Wade. According to a FiveThirtyEight analysis of every pre-viability abortion ban, preexisting bans very rarely included exceptions for circumstances like rape and incest. But now, more Republicans want to back away from a highly unpopular approach — sparking accusations from fellow party members that they are pro-life in name only. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="1084" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="670" height="1436" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed-mobile.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed-mobile.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed-mobile.png?w=670 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atd.south-carolina-abortion.0908_1-fixed-mobile.png?w=1340 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">When we examined the text of each law banning abortion before 20 weeks of pregnancy<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We only looked at bans that restrict abortion before 20 weeks of pregnancy. This is a little earlier than medical professionals generally define fetal viability (24 weeks), but we selected this benchmark because many 20-week abortion bans went into effect under Roe v. Wade, while bans before 20 weeks were presumed to violate the Supreme Court’s standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a> that is currently in effect or being fought in the courts, we found that 17 of the 23 states with a pre-20 week ban have no exceptions for rape and incest, and five of the states have only partial exceptions, limiting how far along in a pregnancy an abortion can be obtained, requiring victims of rape and incest to file a police report — or both.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, the calculus may be changing. <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=0658522648" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gil Gatch</a>, a South Carolina Republican legislator who opposes abortion but advocated for exceptions to rape and incest during the recent legislative debate, told FiveThirtyEight that, before the Dobbs ruling, abortion bans before 20 weeks were mostly a matter of rhetoric, as Supreme Court precedent meant they were all but guaranteed not to go into effect. Now, not so much. “It’s much more difficult — to be honest, it’s scarier — because if we get the wrong thing done, it’s on us,” he said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">South Carolina Republican lawmakers aren’t the first to fracture over how far abortion bans should go. In August, <a href="https://www.indystar.com/story/news/politics/2022/08/04/indiana-abortion-ban-law-house-republicans-tried-removing-rape-incest-exceptions/65391546007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than half</a> of the Republicans in the Indiana House of Representatives voted to remove rape and incest exceptions from the near-total ban they were considering. (The law <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2022/09/08/south-carolina-abortion-ban-proposal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eventually passed</a> with limited rape and incest exceptions and will go into effect on Sept. 15.) The same month, <a href="https://www.wvpublic.org/government/2022-07-29/legislature-fails-to-pass-new-abortion-law-will-return-in-august" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the West Virginia Legislature deadlocked</a> on its own sweeping abortion ban because Republicans couldn’t agree on the penalties for doctors, leaving the procedure legal in the state. (Part of the legislature <a href="https://wvmetronews.com/2022/09/06/special-session-might-resume-but-progress-might-not/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">will return</a> next week, but it’s not clear whether the GOP has come to a consensus about the abortion bill.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Similar debates could unfold in other states like <a href="https://www.cincinnati.com/story/news/2022/06/29/ohio-abortion-law-what-know-six-week-ban-ectopic-pregnancy/7748045001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ohio</a>, <a href="https://www.desmoinesregister.com/story/news/politics/2022/08/11/kim-reynolds-asks-reinstate-fetal-heartbeat-iowa-abortion-law-without-roe-v-wade/10297123002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Iowa</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/08/10/1116716749/a-nebraska-woman-is-charged-with-helping-her-daughter-have-an-abortion" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nebraska</a>, which have conservative legislatures but no law that fully bans abortion. Already, some red lines have become visible. Earlier this summer, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/nebraska-governor-call-special-session-discuss-12-week/story?id=88140763" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nebraska’s Republican governor announced</a> that despite wanting to amend the state’s abortion laws he would not be calling a special session of the legislature because not enough state senators were willing to vote for a 12-week abortion ban.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For Republicans, the question of whether rape and incest victims should be exempted from an abortion ban has turned into an especially raw divide. Some anti-abortion advocates and lawmakers think those exemptions simply don’t make sense. If abortion is morally wrong, why should an unborn fetus be killed because of the circumstances of its conception? Allowing a carveout for rape and incest would be “turning one tragedy into two,” said state Rep. <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=1217045309" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John McCravy</a>, as he introduced the bill in the South Carolina House. Before the Senate committee vote to remove rape and incest exceptions from the House bill, Republican Sen. Richard Cash compared abortion to slavery. “I don’t mean to be insensitive to anyone’s past, but is the human being in the womb nothing more than the property of the woman?” he said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Some anti-abortion lawmakers and advocates see this as a kind of test — a way to see who isn’t espousing pro-life principles just for the sake of politics. “I was elected for what my constituents want, and the majority of them are telling me, just like I believe, that life begins at conception. So no, I’m not for exceptions,” <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=1432386192" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rep. Melissa Oremus</a>, another South Carolina Republican, told FiveThirtyEight. The challenge, she said, is that even Republicans were surprised by the Supreme Court’s ruling. “We never thought we’d see Roe overturned in our day,” she said. “So now [that] you have the ability, what are you going to do about that?”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That position — while ideologically consistent — is exceptionally unpopular. In <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-birth-control-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll after poll</a>, large majorities of Americans have said that abortion should be legal in at least some circumstances. That includes many people who are opposed to abortion most of the time. <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2022/05/06/americas-abortion-quandary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A recent Pew Research Center poll</a> conducted in March found that only 37 percent of abortion opponents wanted the procedure to be completely illegal in cases of rape. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Other conservative lawmakers told me that they’re offended by the idea of making rape and incest exceptions into an anti-abortion litmus test. “I’m very much a conservative on this issue, but you have to acknowledge the fact that there are tragic and cruel circumstances where it’s presumptive, edging on hubris, to say that people can’t make their own decisions,” Rep. <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=0329545415" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Micah Caskey</a>, who proposed an amendment that would have created a limited exception for rape and incest victims who are minors, told FiveThirtyEight. “Yet there are purists who want to paint me as not pro-life for saying that,” he added. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On the first day of debate in the South Carolina Senate, all three Republican women in the chamber said they refused to vote for the bill if it didn’t contain rape and incest exceptions. “Are we simply baby machines? Are you pregnant with a dead baby? Too bad. Raped at 11 by your grandfather and got pregnant? That’s just too bad,” said Sen. Penry Gustafson, a Republican.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As they went back and forth about potential amendments, some South Carolina Republicans seemed a little shocked by the arguments they were having. Republican <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=0456818127" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state Sen. Tom Davis</a>, who ended up leading the filibuster against the bill, proposed another exception for fatal fetal abnormalities — a version of which appears in five other states’ abortion bans that are currently in effect or being litigated, according to our analysis — only to be accused of advocating for euthanasia by several other Republicans. “We have 170 legislators, mostly white men, saying to a woman that even though your doctor diagnoses your child with a congenital defect that isn’t compatible with life outside the womb, you have to carry that child to term,” he said. “Even though the child is going to be born dead! That doesn’t make any sense to me.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The gulf between Republicans feels unbridgeable, even though the exceptions they’re arguing over are actually very small. <a href="https://www.guttmacher.org/sites/default/files/pdfs/pubs/psrh/full/3711005.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">According to the Guttmacher Institute</a>, a research organization that advocates for abortion rights, only about 1 percent of women in 2004 sought abortions because of rape, and less than 1 percent sought abortions because of incest. Republicans are not fighting, for the most part, about whether abortion should be legal — they’re arguing over how to handle the tiny subset of cases that force an unpleasant choice between ideological purity and political reality. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But just as morality can shape politics, politics can also shape morality — and in South Carolina, several Republicans warned their colleagues that going too far on abortion could spur a massive backlash. “To those of you who feel that women are inferior, remember you were warned when you are challenged by a female,” said state <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/member.php?code=1649431621" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sen. Sandy Senn</a>, a South Carolina Republican. “I think it’s going to be interesting to see what happens in the November elections. Because this issue is huge. You don’t think that women will vote single-issue on something like this? Because they will.”</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662979501608712</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>5 Races To Watch In New Hampshire And Rhode Island</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/5-races-to-watch-in-new-hampshire-and-rhode-island/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Delaware Primary</category>
			<category>New Hampshire Primary</category>
			<category>Rhode Island Primary</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>5 Races To Watch In New Hampshire And Rhode Island</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 12, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="USA-ELECTION-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-4-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-4-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-4-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-4-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						New Hampshire and Rhode Island both have competitive primaries on Tuesday. Delaware … not so much.													<p>REUTERS / Brian Snyder</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">We made it! After six months of voting — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-watch-texass-primaries-like-a-pro/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remember Texas</a>? — Tuesday marks the final primary day of the 2022 election cycle, with New Hampshire, Rhode Island and Delaware all set to choose their party nominees.<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Tuesday, every state &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; Louisiana will have held a primary. Louisiana uses a unique “&lt;a href="https://www.theadvocate.com/baton_rouge/opinion/article_e511e3ee-4eb9-11eb-a0b6-a74de1a3468c.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;jungle primary&lt;/a&gt;” electoral system in which &lt;a href="https://www.sos.la.gov/ElectionsAndVoting/GetElectionInformation/ReviewTypesOfElections/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;all candidates appear on the same ballot&lt;/a&gt;, regardless of party affiliation, and all voters may participate, and in presidential and midterm election years, the state holds its initial vote on the general election date in November. If one candidate wins a majority, that candidate is elected; if no candidate wins a majority, a runoff is held in December between the top-two vote recipients in the first round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>8</sup></a> And while these states are some of the nation’s smallest in both land area and population, New Hampshire and Rhode Island are making up for their size by hosting five big primaries that could have repercussions for control of the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives, as well as decide the next governor of Rhode Island. (Sorry, Delaware, there’s just not much happening in the First State.)</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22161759227138-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22161759227138-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22161759227138-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22161759227138-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Republicans’ choice of who should face Democratic Sen. Maggie Hassan this fall seems to have narrowed to either retired Army Brig. Gen. Don Bolduc or state Senate President Chuck Morse. <p>Kristopher Radder / The Brattleboro Reformer / AP</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>New Hampshire</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> U.S. Senate; 1st and 2nd congressional districts</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>7 p.m. Eastern in most of the state, 8 p.m. in some localities</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All the action in New Hampshire is on the Republican side, and the most closely watched race is undoubtedly the one for <strong>Senate</strong>. Democratic Sen. Maggie Hassan could be vulnerable in purple New Hampshire, which is roughly 1 percentage point more Democratic than the country as a whole, according to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://github.com/fivethirtyeight/data/tree/master/partisan-lean" target="_blank" rel="noopener">partisan lean index</a>.<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean based on the statewide popular vote in the last four state House elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>9</sup></a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Early polls</a> suggested Republican Gov. Chris Sununu could have seriously threatened Hassan, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/11/09/sununu-wont-run-for-senate-520413" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to the chagrin</a> of national Republican leaders, <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/sununu-to-make-long-awaited-announcement-on-political-future-today/38193976" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he announced late last year</a> that he would not run for the Senate and would instead seek reelection. As a result, the Senate race attracted a <a href="https://www.sos.nh.gov/2022-republican-cumulative-filings" target="_blank" rel="noopener">crowded field of less-notable Republican contenders</a> that has since turned into a two-man race between retired Army Brig. Gen. Don Bolduc and state Senate President Chuck Morse. The candidates <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/28/us/politics/don-buldoc-new-hampshire.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">differ markedly</a>, too: <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/07/politics/new-hampshire-senate-republican-primary/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bolduc is known</a> as a “loose cannon” who has promoted former President Donald Trump’s false claim that the 2020 election was stolen, while Morse is a longtime public official who <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/morse-emerges-as-top-alternative-to-bolduc-in-gop-senate-primary/41069392" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has highlighted his experience</a> on the campaign trail. Sununu, <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2022-08-19/sununu-says-he-wont-endorse-conspiracy-theory-type-bolduc-in-senate-republican-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who last month labeled Bolduc</a> as a “conspiracy-theory type” candidate, made a splash on Sept. 8 <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/08/politics/sununu-endorsement-morse-new-hampshire/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">when he endorsed Morse</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, while Bolduc lost in the 2020 GOP Senate primary, limited primary polling shows him to be the front-runner this time. A <a href="https://www.publicpolicypolling.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NewHampshireRepublicanSurvey.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll released on Sept. 9</a> by Democratic pollster Public Policy Polling found Bolduc ahead of Morse by 10 points, 33 percent to 23 percent, but with 25 percent undecided. PPP’s survey showed a closer race than a <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1701&amp;context=survey_center_polls" target="_blank" rel="noopener">late-August poll</a> from the University of New Hampshire Survey Center that found Bolduc leading Morse 43 percent to 22 percent and <a href="https://www.anselm.edu/sites/default/files/Documents/NHIOP/Polls/SACSC_NHSW_0822_Book_Pres.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an early-August poll</a> from Saint Anselm College Survey Center that found Bolduc up 32 percent to 16 percent. And while Bolduc led in each poll, Morse has a major fundraising edge that could help him close that gap. As of Aug. 24, Morse had raised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/S2NH00249/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$1.6 million</a> to Bolduc’s <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/S0NH00326/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$579,000</a>, and the state-legislative leader also had almost seven times as much money for the final stretch of the campaign, $582,000 to Bolduc’s $84,000.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Outside groups have also spent millions as the parties jockey to help their chances in November. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/31/republican-super-pac-2-million-new-hampshire-senate-primary-00054402" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A super PAC backed by national Republicans</a> has helped Morse <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00823989/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by spending</a> $4.6 million <a href="https://twitter.com/AdImpact_Pol/status/1565330420610338816" target="_blank" rel="noopener">portraying him</a> as “one tough conservative” who’ll fight for border security, and <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/ac38ec73-0769-4cd2-896d-f741f9ec3519" target="_blank" rel="noopener">calling Bolduc’s ideas</a> “crazy” by highlighting some of his controversial past statements, including <a href="https://nhjournal.com/bolduc-i-drove-communist-sympathizer-sununu-out-of-senate-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">calling Sununu</a> a “Chinese Communist sympathizer.” But Senate Majority PAC, the Democrats’ principal outside group, <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00484642/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent</a> $3.1 million <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/5837a471-6d44-40c0-a42b-18b62d686530" target="_blank" rel="noopener">attacking Morse</a> as a “sleazy politician” who is Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell’s choice in the race. These ads haven’t mentioned Bolduc, but they’ve hit Morse for taking money from lobbyists, including one with connections to the Chinese Communist Party and another group that lobbied for pharmaceutical companies amid the opioid epidemic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Hassan awaits the Republican primary winner, and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s 2022 midterm election forecast</a> currently gives her a clear edge. But her advantage will depend on who wins, as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polling suggests</a> Morse would give Hassan a more competitive race than Bolduc.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Republicans may have a better chance of flipping the <strong>1st District</strong>, an R+1 seat <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">covering eastern New Hampshire</a> held by two-term Democratic Rep. Chris Pappas. Had Republicans in the state legislature <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/new-hampshire/house_gop_proposal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gotten their way</a>, this seat would have become more clearly GOP-leaning, but Sununu’s lack of support for it <a href="https://twitter.com/toddbookman/status/1531657591490846720" target="_blank" rel="noopener">led to a map</a> that made both of New Hampshire’s seats highly competitive.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251644056288-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251644056288-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251644056288-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251644056288-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Gail Huff Brown and Matt Mowers debated earlier this month, and while both are hoping to secure the Republican nomination for New Hampshire’s 1st District, Mowers is in a much better position than Huff Brown. <p>AP Photo / Mary Schwalm</p></figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">The two leading Republican contenders in this district appear to be former Trump White House adviser Matt Mowers and former White House press aide Karoline Leavitt, but also in the race are former TV reporter Gail Huff Brown, whose husband is former Massachusetts Sen. Scott Brown (who also had a failed Senate bid in New Hampshire in 2014), and state Rep. Tim Baxter.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Mowers has led in polls from independent outlets, but his margin has varied from the double digits to well within the margin of error. Most recently, the late-August UNH poll <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1702&amp;context=survey_center_polls" target="_blank" rel="noopener">found him ahead</a> of Leavitt only 26 percent to 24 percent, similar to Saint Anselm College’s poll from earlier in August, which found Mowers leading Leavitt 25 percent to 21 percent. By comparison, though, a <a href="https://nhjournal.com/exclusive-nh-01-gop-poll-trump-faves-high-mowers-holds-big-lead/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mid-August co/efficient poll</a> for NH Journal found Mowers ahead of Leavitt 31 percent to 16 percent. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Naturally, recent polls on behalf of the campaigns or their outside allies have either given <a href="https://nhjournal.com/another-poll-gives-mowers-commanding-lead-in-nh-01-gop-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mowers a bigger lead</a> or <a href="https://nhjournal.com/nh-01-update-new-poll-shows-leavitt-mowers-neck-and-neck/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shown Leavitt running even</a> with Mowers. For the most part, Huff Brown and Baxter have polled in the high single digits, although the UNH poll did find Huff Brown at 16 percent.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-2-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-2-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-2-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/USA-ELECTION-2-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Also running in the Republican primary for New Hampshire’s 1st District, Karoline Leavitt has embraced the more combative language of politicians like Texas Sen. Ted Cruz.</figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Interestingly, this race <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/this-house-race-is-new-ground-zero-in-the-maga-civil-wars" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has sparked divisions</a> within the House GOP’s leadership. Minority Leader Kevin McCarthy and Minority Whip Steve Scalise <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/kevin-mccarthy-house-gop-matt-mowers-endorsement/40204163" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have backed Mowers</a>, while GOP Conference Chair Elise Stefanik has endorsed Leavitt, her former press secretary. This split is particularly revealing when it comes to the candidates’ <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2022-09-07/candidates-in-n-h-1st-district-gop-primary-share-core-beliefs-but-offer-different-tone-experience" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presentation and tone</a>. Although Mowers and Leavitt are both supporters of Trump and touch on leading conservative concerns, Mowers <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/10/28/politics/gop-candidates-young-guns-big-lie/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has said President Biden got the most votes</a>, even though Mowers has also called for audits, while Leavitt has <a href="https://www.seacoastonline.com/story/news/politics/2022/09/08/candidates-nh-gop-congress-district-1-baxter-huff-brown-leavitt-prescott-mowers/7993077001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fully denied</a> the outcome of the 2020 election. Mowers <a href="https://youtu.be/0JKf8J4waXo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has also run ads</a> that look ahead to the general election and attack Pappas and Biden for inflation and wasteful spending, while Leavitt has embraced <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/karoline-leavitt-hopes-show-young-voters-democrat-policies-blame-out-reach-american-dream" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the more combative language</a> of the right.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Mowers’s outside backers have more monetary muscle, which could put Mowers over the top, especially because he and Leavitt have <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/NH/01/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">run pretty even in campaign fundraising</a>. The Congressional Leadership Fund, the House GOP’s main outside arm, <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/pacs/indexpend.php?cmte=C00504530&amp;cycle=2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent</a> $1.3 million boosting Mowers, <a href="https://youtu.be/-O8uxPSpb7c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">promoting him</a> as a conservative who will secure the border and halt the trafficking of opioids. Meanwhile, Defending Main Street, which <a href="https://www.defendingmainstreet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">backs more moderate Republican candidates</a>, has spent <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00540203/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly $1.3 million</a> attacking Leavitt, who is 25 years old, as a “<a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/be6e0441-7f70-413e-9619-fc1b9562fcb7" data-type="URL" data-id="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/be6e0441-7f70-413e-9619-fc1b9562fcb7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">woke Gen-Zer</a>” who has mooched off her parents. For her part, Leavitt <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/pacs/indexpend.php?cmte=C00796045&amp;cycle=2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has received</a> $204,000 in support from Truth &amp; Courage PAC, a group connected to Texas Sen. Ted Cruz, while New Hampshire Principles PAC <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/pacs/indexpend.php?cmte=C00790808&amp;cycle=2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent</a> $437,000 attacking Mowers.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Next door, in the <strong>2nd District</strong>, a D+2 seat, Democratic Rep. Annie Kuster is seeking her sixth term, and she’ll probably face either Keene Mayor George Hansel or former Hillsborough County Treasurer Robert Burns. Polling here has found a large share of undecided voters, but the UNH poll gave Burns a 14-point lead over Hansel, 32 percent to 18 percent, while Saint Anselm College’s survey found them both at around 10 percent.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22249863844924-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22249863844924-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22249863844924-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22249863844924-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>In the Republican primary for New Hampshire’s 2nd District, voters are once more choosing how far to the right to go, with George Hansel (left) in the more moderate lane and Robert Burns (right) in the diehard Trump lane. <p>AP Photo / Mary Schwalm</p></figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">On paper, Hansel looks like a stronger general-election candidate than Burns. Hansel just jumped in the race three months ago, but he has already raised <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NH02294/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$377,000</a>. <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2022-08-30/a-cross-section-of-republican-ideology-on-offer-in-n-h-s-2nd-congressional-district-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">He also identifies</a> as “pro-choice” on abortion, which could help him in a state that <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2016/02/29/how-religious-is-your-state/?state=new-hampshire" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isn’t super religious</a> and has <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/articles/the-republican-advance-in-the-south-and-other-party-registration-trends/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a lot of independents</a>. Finally, <a href="https://youtu.be/qBVEHS7wFeo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hansel’s ads</a> have <a href="https://youtu.be/pQsSSMY76Xw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gone after Kuster</a> on inflation, opioid trafficking and home heating bills, which may play more to a general-election audience. But Burns may have the inside track with GOP primary voters, despite <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/H2NH00025/?cycle=2022&amp;election_full=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">having raised</a> about half what Hansel has. <a href="https://www.facebook.com/burnsfornh/videos/568994734956073" target="_blank" rel="noopener">He’s highlighted</a> his “pro-life” stance on abortion and pro-Trump views. He’s <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/2nd-cd-gop-candidates-spar-225400476.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also attacked</a> Hansel as a “liberal, woke mayor.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats have noticed that Burns might be the weaker general-election choice, too, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/29/new-hampshire-gop-primary-00054137" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have meddled accordingly</a>. Democrats Serve, which typically supports Democratic candidates with public-service backgrounds, <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/races/outside-spending?cycle=2022&amp;id=NH02&amp;spec=N" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent</a> $561,000 <a href="https://youtu.be/IQ2TujiBLSs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ostensibly attacking</a> Burns as an “unapologetic conservative,” an approach <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-3-pro-impeachment-house-republicans-survive-tuesdays-primaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">used by Democrats elsewhere this cycle</a> to help more right-leaning candidates win in the GOP primaries. But Hansel <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/political-action-committees-pacs//C00821652/independent-expenditures/2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has received</a> $664,000 in outside support from American Liberty Action, which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/13-races-to-watch-in-florida-and-oklahoma/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has spent large sums</a> in other <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-york-is-holding-another-primary-heres-everything-you-need-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican primaries</a> this cycle to take down strongly pro-Trump candidates. We’ll find out on Tuesday which party got what it wanted.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251582727215-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251582727215-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251582727215-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22251582727215-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>
In the Democratic primary for governor of Rhode Island, incumbent Dan McKee (second from right) should be a shoo-in, but he faces an unexpectedly competitive and crowded field. <p>AP Photo / David Goldman</p></figcaption></figure><h2><strong>Rhode Island</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Races to watch:</strong> governor; 2nd Congressional District</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Polls close: </strong>8 p.m. Eastern</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The big-ticket race in Rhode Island is the primary for <strong>governor</strong>, where Democratic Gov. Dan McKee is seeking a full term after succeeding to the office as lieutenant governor following then-Gov. Gina Raimondo’s appointment to Biden’s Cabinet in 2021. But McKee is not the presumptive nominee; he’s now caught up in a mostly three-way primary with Secretary of State Nellie Gorbea and former CVS Health executive Helena Foulkes, although former Secretary of State Matt Brown is also in the mix.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The polls suggest it’s a wide-open contest, too. Most recently, <a href="https://www.wpri.com/democratic-primary-poll-results-august/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an early August poll</a> from Fleming &amp; Associates/WPRI/Roger Williams University found McKee at 28 percent and Gorbea at 25 percent. Yet, a <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/22068770/boston-globe-suffolk-university-poll-ri-topline-june-2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June survey</a> from Suffolk University/The Boston Globe put Gorbea slightly ahead of McKee, 24 percent to 20 percent, similar to the results of a <a href="https://twitter.com/TedNesi/status/1554214875840266243" target="_blank" rel="noopener">late-July survey</a> conducted for Gorbea’s campaign by Lake Research Partners that found her leading McKee 27 percent to 22 percent. In each of these polls, Foulkes was in the mid-teens while Brown was down in the single digits. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">McKee isn’t benefiting much from incumbency, which isn’t actually that shocking: Historically, incumbent governors who ascended to the governorship because of resignation or death have been <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/articles/stepping-up-how-governors-who-have-succeeded-to-the-top-job-have-performed-over-the-years/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more likely to lose renomination</a> than elected ones. McKee also has <a href="https://www.wpri.com/news/elections/mckee-under-fire-in-contentious-dem-primary-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his own vulnerabilities</a>, particularly <a href="https://www.wpri.com/target-12/fbi-joins-investigation-into-controversial-ilo-consulting-contract/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an ongoing federal investigation</a> into whether his administration improperly awarded a multimillion-dollar contract to a firm connected to a longtime McKee ally. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">More broadly, though, McKee isn’t very popular: In the second quarter of 2022, Morning Consult found that <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/19/democratic-governors-are-resisting-bidens-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more voters disapproved</a> of him (43 percent) than approved (38 percent). Still, McKee has tried to <a href="https://youtu.be/sXAWfRS02Bw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">play up his accomplishments</a>, such as <a href="https://www.wpri.com/news/politics/ri-car-tax-set-to-be-eliminated-one-year-early/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ending</a> the annual tax <a href="https://economicprogressri.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/car-tax-fact-sheet-final.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on motor vehicles</a>, <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2022/08/11/metro/mckee-signs-legislation-dedicating-250m-affordable-housing-low-income-ri-residents/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">investing in affordable housing</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/7cXAUROBxZY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raising the minimum age to purchase a gun</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As for McKee’s main challengers, Gorbea <a href="https://www.wpri.com/news/elections/gorbea-wants-ri-to-hike-corporate-tax-rate-mckee-foulkes-balk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wants to raise corporate taxes</a> to fund social programs and help small businesses, and she’s highlighted her <a href="https://youtu.be/QttwFabZVqk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">experience in housing development</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/zz8fP18dcYw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">running Rhode Island’s elections</a>. She <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/09/08/rhode-islands-first-latina-governor-00055115" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could also become the first Latina</a> to be elected governor in New England. But Gorbea <a href="https://www.providencejournal.com/story/news/politics/2022/08/25/nellie-gorbea-dan-mckee-governor-candidates-commercial-right-wing-attack/7892723001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">landed in hot water last month</a>, when her campaign cited a conservative commentator in an ad attacking McKee, drawing liberal criticism and <a href="https://youtu.be/4_AyvKNVLxw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prompting McKee’s campaign to call her “desperate.”</a> </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Foulkes, meanwhile, <a href="https://www.providencejournal.com/story/news/politics/2022/09/08/rhode-island-primary-one-week-away-and-campaign-spending-up/8010194001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has led the money race</a> with $3.9 million in spending since last year (helped out by $1.3 million in self-funding), compared with McKee’s $2 million and Gorbea’s $1.8 million. Foulkes has tried to portray herself as <a href="https://youtu.be/DqzUWTkTNLs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an outsider</a> who can get “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z0TJiZub3Ho" target="_blank" rel="noopener">big things done</a>,” and she’s <a href="https://youtu.be/CTI1KoB31MI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">promised not to run for reelection</a> if children’s education levels haven’t improved after her first term. Regardless of who wins, the Democratic primary winner will enter <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/rhode-island/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the general election as a favorite</a>, with health-care executive Ashley Kalus looking to be the likely GOP nominee.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The other race of note in Rhode Island is the Democratic primary in the <strong>2nd District</strong>, a D+16 seat in the western part of the state. Longtime Democratic Rep. Jim Langevin is retiring, leaving this seat open. Rhode Island General Treasurer Seth Magaziner looks like the favorite in the Democratic primary, but he still has to fend off opposition from former Commerce Department lawyer Sarah Morgenthau and former state Rep. David Segal.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="948" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22039610029940-3x2-1.jpg" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22039610029940-3x2-1.jpg" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22039610029940-3x2-1.jpg?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/AP22039610029940-3x2-1.jpg?w=1424 2x"><figcaption>Rhode Island General Treasurer Seth Magaziner is the favorite in the Democratic primary for the state’s 2nd Congressional District. Not only is he leading in fundraising, but he also landed the endorsement of the district’s retiring incumbent.</figcaption></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Magaziner started out running for governor but <a href="https://www.wpri.com/news/elections/seth-magaziner-announces-run-for-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">switched races</a> following Langevin’s retirement, and he’s built up a <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/house/RI/02/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">major fundraising edge</a> since then. He’s raised $2.4 million, far outpacing Morgenthau ($978,000) and Segal ($528,000), and he <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/races/outside-spending?cycle=2022&amp;id=RI02&amp;spec=N" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has also attracted</a> $562,000 in outside support compared with none for his primary opponents. Magaziner has also earned endorsements <a href="https://www.abc6.com/langevin-to-join-magaziner-to-address-race-for-2nd-congressional-district-seat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">from Langevin</a> and <a href="https://www.providencejournal.com/story/news/local/2022/06/26/seth-magaziner-wins-ri-democratic-party-endorsement-congress/7742306001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the state party</a>, and he’s played up <a href="https://youtu.be/0ZgjjxUngRM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his opposition to Trump</a> and his intention to protect abortion rights and <a href="https://youtu.be/r6wV1UlsgAg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Social Security</a>. But Morgenthau has sought to break through <a href="https://youtu.be/VIBZSGmXuXM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by arguing that</a>, in the wake of the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn the constitutional right to abortion, it’s time for Rhode Island to send a Democratic woman to Congress <a href="https://youtu.be/UUfDyH68Ar8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for the first time</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On paper, the winner of this primary should be very likely to win in November, but former Cranston Mayor Allan Fung is hoping to give Republicans a shot at winning here. <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/rhode-island/2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Our forecast gives Democrats an edge</a>, but it’s also the bluest district in the entire country to only “lean” toward Democrats, so there’ll be plenty to watch here after the primary.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Please join us for our final primary live blog in 2022 on Tuesday starting at 7 p.m. Eastern. We’ll react to the results in New Hampshire and Rhode Island and talk about the contours of the upcoming general election now that we’re less than two months from November.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662979501608711</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why A State Like Michigan Might Actually Be A Blue State</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-a-state-like-michigan-might-actually-be-a-blue-state/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Partisan Lean</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why A State Like Michigan Might Actually Be A Blue State</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 9, 2022, at 9:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0909-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0909-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0909-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0909-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0909-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Is Michigan a red state or a blue state?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“It’s a purple state,” you might say! But sorry, I’m not going to let you off so easily. You have to pick the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_pill_and_blue_pill" target="_blank" rel="noopener">red pill or the blue pill</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As a Michigan native, I’d say Michigan is a blue state. Not that this assessment requires any particular local knowledge. It has voted Democratic for president all but once since 1992 (it voted for former President Donald Trump in 2016). Its governorship has bounced back and forth more, but its current governor, Gretchen Whitmer, is a Democrat and a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/michigan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">clear favorite for reelection</a>, according to the FiveThirtyEight 2022 midterm election forecast. Democrats have also controlled both of its U.S. Senate seats since the 2000 elections. The state legislature is Republican-controlled, but Democrats should be <a href="https://www.bridgemi.com/michigan-government/michigan-redistricting-drafts-could-make-state-senate-toss" target="_blank" rel="noopener">competitive this year</a> after redistricting. So it’s a close call, but I’m going with Michigan as a “blue state.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But according to FiveThirtyEight’s partisan lean index, Michigan is <em>Republican</em>-leaning. Specifically, it’s 1.2 percentage points more Republican than the country overall.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>11</sup></a> It’s close, but Michigan’s partisan lean nods toward “red state.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, who’s right in this case? Me or the algorithm?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Well, I’m a wee bit biased here, but I think I’m right. Michigan is more a blue state than a red state, and the distinction reveals something important about the balance of power in politics today and the strategies of the major political parties.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">FiveThirtyEight’s partisan lean index classifies Michigan as Republican-leaning because it has been less blue than the country as a whole in recent elections. Case in point: In 2020, now-President Joe Biden won Michigan by 2.8 points, less than his 4.5-point margin in the national popular vote.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then again, the national popular vote might not be the best baseline. After all, it depends in part on states where Democrats win by huge margins, without getting any additional benefit in the Electoral College. For instance, Biden won California by more than 5 million votes. But suppose he’d won it by <em>only</em> 1 million votes. It would still be a comfortable margin, but in that case, Biden would have won the national popular vote by only 1.9 points, and Michigan would have been to the left of the country as a whole, without changing the Electoral College outcome at all.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is somewhat complex, so let me state my hypothesis as clearly as possible — there are two of them, really:</p>



<ol><li>Parties are trying to win control of the presidency and Congress. But since the popular vote doesn’t determine control of these, parties don’t actually care about the popular vote. Therefore, measures like FiveThirtyEight’s partisan lean index that are calibrated based on the popular vote may be flawed.</li><li>Republicans currently have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/advantage-gop/">a structural advantage in many of America’s political institutions</a>. However, it doesn’t necessarily follow that Republicans will win more than half the time.</li></ol><p data-paragraph="main">Let’s start with that second point. One important but easy-to-overlook facet of American elections is that each party wins about half the time. Over the past 40 years, for example, Democrats have controlled the presidency for 18 years (two years and counting for Biden, eight each for former Presidents Barack Obama and Bill Clinton) while Republicans have had it for 22. Also in the past 40 years, Democrats have held the U.S. Senate for just short of 20 years,<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vermont Sen. James Jeffords &lt;a href="https://vtdigger.org/2021/05/23/way-ahead-of-his-time-jim-jeffords-2001-political-switch-back-in-the-spotlight/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;began caucusing with the Democrats&lt;/a&gt; about 6 months into the 107th Congress, giving Democrats majority control. So more precisely, Democrats have controlled the Senate for about 19.5 of the past 40 years, and Republicans 20.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>12</sup></a> and Republicans for just slightly more than 20 years. The House? Democrats have been in charge for roughly 20 years and the GOP for 20.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s true that Republicans currently enjoy a structural advantage <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/2020/12/wisconsin-was-the-electoral-college-tipping-point-state-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the Electoral College</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-senates-rural-skew-makes-it-very-hard-for-democrats-to-win-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the U.S. Senate</a>, such that they can expect to win both with less than half of the popular vote. (They also had an advantage in the U.S. House for most of the 2010s, although that has <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">been reduced somewhat following redistricting</a>.) But I don’t think it necessarily follows that Republicans can expect to win those offices more than half the time.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">After all, Republicans haven’t done a great job of winning these offices recently. They lost the presidency in 2020. They don’t control the Senate — and they may not get it back this year. The FiveThirtyEight forecast now shows Democrats with a 70 percent chance of <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/?cid=rrpromo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">keeping control of the Senate</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, some votes are more valuable than others. In a presidential election, for instance, the marginal vote in Michigan matters a lot more than the marginal vote in California. And in the Senate, a voter in North Dakota has a lot more power than one in Texas, since Texas has the same number of senators despite having more than 37 times the inhabitants. This creates <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-senates-rural-skew-makes-it-very-hard-for-democrats-to-win-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a significant bias in the Senate toward white, rural voters</a>, who are overrepresented in low-population states, and moreover, Republicans in the Trump era have adopted a particularly potent strategy of catering to those voters. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/abortion-stay-legal-pennsylvania-fivethirtyeight-89543566</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Put another way, the upshot of the structural bias toward Republicans may not be that they can attain some permanent supermajority, but rather that they are able to win elections half the time <em>despite</em> advancing policies that are significantly to the right of the <a href="https://www.cantorsparadise.com/the-median-voter-theorem-c81630b57fa4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">median voter</a>, especially on issues like abortion, gun control and environmental regulation. It’s likely not a coincidence either that these issues have <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2018/05/22/urban-suburban-and-rural-residents-views-on-key-social-and-political-issues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strong urban-rural divides</a>, which speak to the GOP’s current advantage in the Senate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And yet it’s not as though Republicans are in some untenable position. Their structural advantages give them a much bigger margin for error, and so they still have decent chances in the Senate despite nominating a poor slate of candidates. They’re also <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/?cid=rrpromo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">favored to win the House</a> according to the FiveThirtyEight forecast. And they <a href="https://electionbettingodds.com/PresidentialParty2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have plenty of hope of winning the presidency back in 2024</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It may seem strange to talk about the parties in such an abstract manner, as though they’re rational actors pursuing some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nash_equilibrium" target="_blank" rel="noopener">game-theory-derived Nash equilibrium</a>. Indeed, this description leaves a lot to be desired. The Republican Party and the Democratic Party are not simple entities. Although there are formal party structures such as the Republican National Committee, in practice, much of a party’s power rests with current, former and aspiring elected officials, along with donors, other public figures who are influential within the party and, of course, the voters. These groups’ objectives don’t always align, and sometimes that can result in outcomes such as <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-hard-to-win-a-senate-race-when-youve-never-won-an-election-before/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nominating subpar candidates to key Senate races</a> or <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-trumps-presence-in-the-midterms-is-risky-for-the-gop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">having a former president interfere in a midterm in unhelpful ways</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But if neither party is particularly happy with its situation — well, that’s sometimes what an equilibrium looks like, in the same sense that both sides often walk away feeling a little unhappy after a tough negotiation.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, this has considerations for our partisan lean index. The implication we frequently take from it — in fact, this is an assumption built into our various forecast models — is over the long run, such as if you play out the next 40 years given current party coalitions, the <em>popular</em> vote for Congress and the presidency will be tied in an average year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">I don’t think that’s the correct implication, though. My assertion here, instead, is that each party will continue to win elections about half the time even though Democrats are likely to continue to win the popular vote <em>more</em> than half the time.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since 2016, for instance, Democrats have won the popular vote for the presidency by 2.1 points (Hillary Clinton) and 4.5 points (Biden). They also won the popular vote for the U.S. House by 3.1 points in 2020 and 8.6 points in 2018, but lost it by 1.1 point in 2016. This is a crude method, but if you average those five figures, you wind up with Democrats winning the popular vote by 3.4 points on average.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Here’s what our partisan lean index would look like in a year where Democrats win the national popular vote by 3.4 points. Note that a state like Michigan — along with Nevada and Pennsylvania — now rates as slightly blue rather than slightly red. Wisconsin, Georgia, North Carolina, Arizona and Florida are still red-leaning, however. </p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>The FiveThirtyEight partisan lean index, recalibrated</h5>
 <p>How each state votes in an election where Democrats win the popular vote by 3.4 percentage points</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.partisan-lean.2"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Partisan Lean</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col"></th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Partisan Lean</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Massachusetts</td>
 <td>D+36.0</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Arizona</td>
 <td>R+4.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Hawaii</td>
 <td>D+35.0</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Florida</td>
 <td>R+4.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Vermont</td>
 <td>D+30.9</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Iowa</td>
 <td>R+6.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maryland</td>
 <td>D+29.3</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Texas</td>
 <td>R+8.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>California</td>
 <td>D+28.9</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Ohio</td>
 <td>R+9.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Rhode Island</td>
 <td>D+27.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Alaska</td>
 <td>R+11.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New York</td>
 <td>D+23.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>South Carolina</td>
 <td>R+15.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Delaware</td>
 <td>D+17.1</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Indiana</td>
 <td>R+16.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Illinois</td>
 <td>D+16.8</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Montana</td>
 <td>R+16.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Washington</td>
 <td>D+15.8</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Mississippi</td>
 <td>R+16.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Connecticut</td>
 <td>D+15.5</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Louisiana</td>
 <td>R+17.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Jersey</td>
 <td>D+15.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Kansas</td>
 <td>R+17.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oregon</td>
 <td>D+14.0</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Missouri</td>
 <td>R+17.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Mexico</td>
 <td>D+10.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Nebraska</td>
 <td>R+21.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Colorado</td>
 <td>D+9.8</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Utah</td>
 <td>R+22.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Virginia</td>
 <td>D+8.0</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Kentucky</td>
 <td>R+23.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maine</td>
 <td>D+7.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Tennessee</td>
 <td>R+26.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Minnesota</td>
 <td>D+5.3</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Alabama</td>
 <td>R+26.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Hampshire</td>
 <td>D+3.7</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Arkansas</td>
 <td>R+28.4</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Michigan</td>
 <td>D+1.8</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>South Dakota</td>
 <td>R+28.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td>D+0.9</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>West Virginia</td>
 <td>R+32.1</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Pennsylvania</td>
 <td>D+0.5</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Idaho</td>
 <td>R+33.6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td>R+0.7</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Oklahoma</td>
 <td>R+33.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>North Carolina</td>
 <td>R+1.4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>North Dakota</td>
 <td>R+33.8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Georgia</td>
 <td>R+4.0</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Wyoming</td>
 <td>R+46.3</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.</p>
 <p>Sources: State election websites, Daily Kos Elections</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">That all seems fairly intuitive relative to how recent elections have gone — more so than the implication that Michigan is a red state. To be clear, this is not an official change to our partisan lean index; it’s just me playing out the logical implications of an idea. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also not a prediction for what will happen this year, but still, these figures may be more in line with how future elections will play out — both in theory and in practice.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662732001204105</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Supreme Court Is More Unpopular Than Ever. That Could Help Democrats.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-is-more-unpopular-than-ever-that-could-help-democrats/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Supreme Court Is More Unpopular Than Ever. That Could Help Democrats.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Zoha Qamar</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux and Zoha Qamar</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 9, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0909_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0909_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0909_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0909_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0909_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">The Supreme Court’s conservative justices aren’t on the ballot this November. But for Democratic voters, the upcoming midterms are looking more and more like a referendum on the country’s high court.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In late June, when the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overturned the constitutional right to abortion</a> in a contentious and divided ruling, Republicans had a solid 2-percentage-point lead over Democrats in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic-ballot polling</a>, which asks Americans whether they plan to support Republicans or Democrats in the upcoming congressional election. A little over two months later, though, and abortion is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2022/us/abortion-laws-roe-v-wade.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mostly or completely illegal in 14 states</a> — and those generic-ballot polls look very different. According to FiveThirtyEight’s average, Democrats now have more than a 1-point lead over Republicans.</p>



<figure><div>
<img src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/generic-ballot-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/newsletter-images/generic-ballot-2.png"></div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">That’s a remarkable shift in a year when Republicans should have the wind at their back — normally, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">president’s party loses seats</a> in the midterm elections. And although things could change in the months leading up to November, there’s mounting evidence that the Supreme Court’s ruling in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-abortion-is-becoming-a-winning-issue-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">galvanizing Democrats</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shaking up the political landscape</a> in the process. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/abortion-stay-legal-pennsylvania-fivethirtyeight-89543566</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">A <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/09/01/positive-views-of-supreme-court-decline-sharply-following-abortion-ruling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center poll</a> conducted Aug. 1-14 found that more Americans have an unfavorable view of the Supreme Court than at any other point since Pew began asking the question just over 35 years ago. Only 28 percent of Democrats and Democratic-leaning independents have a favorable view of the Supreme Court, down 18 points since January and nearly 40 points since August 2020. Republicans’ views of the court, meanwhile, have gotten a bit more positive since the beginning of the year, which has created a gaping 45-point partisan gap in the Supreme Court’s favorability rating.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Views of the Supreme Court are more polarized than ever" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/iO1YP/6/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="400" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not just that views of the court are changing — the importance of abortion as an issue priority is also skyrocketing for Democrats in the wake of the Supreme Court’s decision. According to the same <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/08/23/abortion-rises-in-importance-as-a-voting-issue-driven-by-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew survey</a>, the economy remains voters’ top issue overall, but the share of Democrats who say abortion is a very important issue for the midterm elections rose from 46 percent in March to 71 percent in August. Meanwhile, in a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/395408/abortion-moves-important-problem-list.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup poll</a> conducted July 5-26, 13 percent of Democrats said that abortion issues were the most important problem facing the country — driving record-high levels of concern among Americans overall. An additional 9 percent of Democrats said that the judicial system and the courts were the most important problem. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This heightened focus on abortion and the court seems to be having a real effect on the midterms, too, with Democrats and independents saying in polls that they have a greater desire to vote for candidates who share their views on abortion. According to a <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/poll-finding/kff-health-tracking-poll-july-2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kaiser Family Foundation poll</a> conducted July 7-17, for instance, nearly three-quarters (72 percent) of Democratic voters and 56 percent of independent voters say the Supreme Court’s decision in Dobbs has made them more motivated to consider a candidate’s position on abortion. However, 62 percent of Republicans said the decision hadn’t made a difference to them.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/democrats-performing-abortion-ruling-fivethirtyeight-88822518</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Americans can’t vote Supreme Court justices off the bench, of course, but the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2022/09/01/positive-views-of-supreme-court-decline-sharply-following-abortion-ruling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew survey</a> suggests that Democrats are more and more likely to think the court has too much authority. A solid majority (64 percent) of Democrats say the Supreme Court has too much power, up from only 23 percent in August 2020. Increasingly, Democrats also say that the justices are not making politically neutral decisions. Just over half (51 percent) of Democrats say the justices are doing a poor job of keeping their own politics out of their decision-making, up from 26 percent in January. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Even Republicans are somewhat divided on this question: One-third (33 percent) of Republicans said the court was doing an excellent or good job of keeping politics out of their decision-making, while 25 percent said the court was doing a fair job and 12 percent said it was doing a poor job. (An additional 15 percent of Republicans said they weren’t sure, and 13 percent said the Supreme Court justices <em>should</em> bring their own political views into their decision-making.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This isn’t the first time that anger surrounding the Supreme Court has reshaped a midterm election. In 2018, the fight over Justice Brett Kavanaugh’s confirmation to the court <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/is-kavanaugh-helping-republicans-midterm-chances/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">appeared to help</a> Republican candidates in some key Senate races. At the same time, however, there were <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-may-be-mobilizing-more-democratic-voters-than-republicans-now/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signs that year</a> that the changing makeup of the Supreme Court — and the possible impact on abortion rights — was raising the salience of the issue for Democrats. That didn’t seem to pay off for Democrats in the 2018 midterms since <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/11/01/a-look-at-voters-views-ahead-of-the-2018-midterms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their base</a> was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/are-republicans-losing-the-health-care-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">motivated by other issues</a>, but 2022 may be different. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul><li>While the Supreme Court understandably grabs a lot of attention for its decisions, few Americans are familiar with the process of confirming federal judges, according to an Aug. 17-18 survey conducted by <a href="https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2022/9/1/voters-affirm-the-senates-mandate-to-fill-judicial-vacancies">Data for Progress for Demand Justice</a>. As of Thursday, <a href="https://www.uscourts.gov/judges-judgeships/judicial-vacancies/current-judicial-vacancies">82 seats</a> were vacant, and many of them are expected to remain empty at the end of the year. While a majority (71 percent) of all likely voters agreed it’s at least somewhat urgent to fill these positions, only 11 percent said they knew a lot about the confirmation process — a figure which doesn’t vary much by party identification. Just over half (53 percent) of respondents said they supported holding additional Senate hearings to consider more of President Biden’s nominees, though that stance was highly partisan, with 80 percent of Democratic voters in support compared with just 26 percent of Republicans. </li></ul><ul><li>With the new academic year underway, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/education/2022/08/22/texas-schools-in-god-we-trust-signs/7865872001/">Texas is mandating</a> that public schools display donated signs bearing the national motto, “<a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/frontline/article/in-god-we-trust-reaffirmed-as-national-motto-again/">In God we trust</a>.” An Aug. 31 <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/survey-results/daily/2022/08/31/cbce2/2">poll by YouGov</a> found that a slim majority of Americans would strongly (35 percent) or somewhat (17 percent) support a similar policy in their own state’s schools. That number soared among Republicans (81 percent) but fell among Democrats (40 percent) and independents (46 percent). Regionally, support for such a measure was greatest in the South (55 percent). </li></ul><ul><li>Most Americans (54 percent) have a favorable view of labor unions, per a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/8r3sug5jju/toplines_Labor_and_Unions_20220824.pdf">YouGov survey</a> of adult citizens conducted Aug. 24-28, though only 10 percent reported that they are members themselves. (Another 9 percent say someone else in their household is a union member.) Almost half (47 percent) agreed that striking was an effective method in getting what they wanted from employers, although Democrats (66 percent) were much more likely to hold that view than Republicans (39 percent) or independents (38 percent). </li></ul><ul><li>Even though social media influencers seem to be <a href="https://www.salon.com/2022/04/30/influencer-culture-is-everywhere-even-in-academia/">monopolizing apps</a> like TikTok and Instagram, an Aug. 25-Sept. 1 <a href="https://civicscience.com/despite-low-levels-of-trust-influencer-marketing-continues-to-drive-purchases/">CivicScience study</a> revealed that only 3 percent of Americans trust influencers. That number ticks up slightly among adults under 25 (9 percent) and those between 25 and 34 (8 percent), although a sizable share of both groups (37 percent and 46 percent, respectively) report feeling distrustful of them. That said, influencers are, well, influencing spending habits somewhat among those age groups: 30 percent of adults under 25 and 21 percent of those 25 to 34 said they had purchased a product or service in the past six months after seeing it promoted by an influencer or blogger online. Only 6 percent of 35- to 54-year-olds and 3 percent of adults 55 and up said the same.</li></ul><h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> 42.4 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 53.2 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.8 points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-driving-bidens-approval-rating-up/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 42.7 percent approved and 53.0 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -10.3 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 39.6 percent and a disapproval rating of 55.7 percent, for a net approval rating of -16.1 points.</p>



<h2><strong>Generic ballot</strong></h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> Democrats currently lead by 1.2 points (44.9 percent to 43.7 percent). <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-driving-bidens-approval-rating-up/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A week ago</a>, Democrats led Republicans by 0.9 points (44.6 percent to 43.6 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Democrats by 0.1 points (44.3 percent to 44.1 percent).</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-favored-win-pennsylvania-senate-gubernatorial-races-89313612</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662718501092597</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Is Republicans’ Path To Winning The Senate?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-is-republicans-path-to-winning-the-senate/</link>
						<dc:creator>Sarah Frostenson</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Senate Elections</category>
			<category>Slack Chat</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>What Is Republicans' Path To Winning The Senate?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p><span>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</span></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 8, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="SlackChat_0908-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SlackChat_0908-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SlackChat_0908-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SlackChat_0908-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SlackChat_0908-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
						
		</figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/slack-chat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politics chat</a>. The transcript below has been lightly edited.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah</strong> (<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/sarah-frostenson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah Frostenson</a>, politics editor): Something we’ve <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maybe-dobbs-did-change-the-race-well-need-more-time-to-know-for-sure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">written about</a> pretty extensively <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-political-environment-might-be-improving-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at FiveThirtyEight</a> is the fact that Democrats are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-this-be-an-asterisk-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on the upswing</a>. Whether it’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">special elections</a> or <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the generic ballot</a>, which asks voters which party they’d support in an election, Democrats’ standing has steadily improved since the Supreme Court overturned the constitutional right to abortion in Dobbs v. Jackson, in June. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is especially true in the Senate, where Democrats currently have a 70 percent chance of winning in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the 2022 FiveThirtyEight midterm election forecast</a>.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="808" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-change-711-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Are Republicans in trouble in the Senate?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It certainly seems Minority Leader Mitch McConnell thinks that’s the case. In August, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2022-election/mcconnell-says-republicans-may-not-win-senate-control-citing-candidate-rcna43777" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he said at a Chamber of Commerce luncheon in Kentucky that</a> “I think there’s probably a greater likelihood the House flips than the Senate. Senate races are just different — they’re statewide, candidate quality has a lot to do with the outcome.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So let’s talk Senate races and the GOP’s best pickup chances, along with the races where they might be surprisingly weak (and yes, those often might be the same races). Let’s start with the four most competitive Senate seats that are the GOP’s best pickup opportunities this year — <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia</a>, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nevada</a>, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arizona</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Hampshire</a> — as well as two other Senate seats they need to hold onto — <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pennsylvania</a>, which is an open seat, and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wisconsin</a>, where Republican Sen. Ron Johnson is seeking reelection, although that seat is currently rated as a toss-up in our forecast.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First up, what’s going on with Wisconsin? Could Republicans lose it?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich</strong> (<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nathaniel Rakich</a>, senior elections analyst): Yes, Republicans could absolutely lose Wisconsin. According to the Deluxe version of the FiveThirtyEight forecast, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the race is a toss-up</a>: Johnson has a 51-in-100 chance of winning, and Democrat Mandela Barnes has a 49-in-100 chance of winning.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="848" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-WI-S3-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And if you use the Lite version of our forecast — which mostly uses just polls, no “fundamentals” or expert race ratings — Barnes is leading, with a 72-in-100 chance of winning.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The big question is whether those polls, which have generally shown Barnes ahead, get better for Republicans. We’ve seen only <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a few polls out of Wisconsin</a> so far this year, so the picture there is fuzzier than in other states. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> So few polls that we don’t even have a polling average yet! (For curious readers, our criteria is: at least five polls from three different pollsters conducted this year.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words … #trustthepolls but with a healthy dose of skepticism when it comes to Wisconsin?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yes, polls in Wisconsin were notoriously bad in 2020. Our <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/wisconsin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">final polling average</a> had Biden leading by 8.4 percentage points in Wisconsin, and he ended up winning by less than 1 point. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex</strong> (<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/alex-samuels/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alex Samuels</a>, politics reporter): From what polling I’ve seen, Johnson’s approval numbers leave a lot to be desired. A June <a href="https://law.marquette.edu/poll/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/MLSP70Toplines.html#Q3:_Biden%E2%80%99s_overall_job" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marquette University Law School</a> had his favorability at just 37 percent among registered voters, with 46 percent saying they viewed the two-term senator unfavorably. That same poll also showed a tight race between Johnson and Barnes, with the latter narrowly ahead, 46 percent to 44 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But I definitely don’t think we should count Johnson out. The national climate is still probably on his side, for one, and he’s defeated formidable opponents before. (Back in 2016, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/elections/2016/results/wisconsin-senate-johnson-feingold" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he narrowly bested</a> three-term Democratic Sen. Russ Feingold.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> I don’t know, Alex. I think Johnson is a pretty weak candidate. He has made some <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/05/03/ron-johnson-takes-his-anti-vaccine-rhetoric-weird-new-place/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">conspiratorial comments about vaccines</a>, and he was allegedly involved in the effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/06/21/jan-6-panel-trump-overturn-2020-election-00040816" target="_blank" rel="noopener">throw the 2020 election to Trump</a>. He did win in 2016, but I think he just got lucky — Wisconsin banked hard to the right that year, as Hillary Clinton can attest. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geoffrey Skelley</a>, senior elections analyst): Well, I’m not so sure, Nathaniel. Johnson is a Republican incumbent in a state that has a small lean toward the GOP, in a midterm in which Democrats hold the White House. Those sorts of conditions don’t usually work out for the challenging party. In fact, earlier this year, for CNN, former FiveThirtyEighter Harry Enten <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/01/12/politics/ron-johnson-republicans-senate-2022-analysis/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looked at midterms dating back to 1982</a> and found that incumbent senators in circumstances like Johnson’s have won 86 of 87 times since then.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> What could also work in Johnson’s favor is that Republicans are looking to paint Barnes <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/07/30/wisconsin-barnes-senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as too liberal</a> and out of touch with the state’s politics. In August, I wrote about why Minnesota Rep. Ilhan Omar is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-ilhan-omar-almost-lost-her-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a sort of bogey(wo)man for Republicans</a>, so if the GOP can successfully tie her brand of firebrand progressivism to Barnes, then he could be in real trouble considering what Nathaniel said earlier about Wisconsin only narrowly going for Biden in 2020.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Indeed, Alex! In fact, FiveThirtyEight’s video team did a whole video on Barnes and how he’s trying to cast himself as more of a moderate to voters.</p>



<figure><div>
<div><iframe loading="lazy" title="Mandela Barnes May Be Democrats’ Best Hope For Flipping A Senate Seat l FiveThirtyEight" width="712" height="401" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LMJqWDIkfbE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>
</div></figure><p data-paragraph="main">But let’s talk over the other seat that Republicans technically control — Pennsylvania — although it’s an open-seat race, with Sen. Pat Toomey retiring. How do things look for Republicans there?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Pennsylvania is problematic for the GOP, as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our forecast</a> currently gives Democratic Lt. Gov. John Fetterman about a 4-in-5 shot of winning over Republican Mehmet Oz.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="848" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-PA-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-PA-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-PA-S3-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-PA-S3-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Toomey’s retirement produced a highly competitive Republican primary, which Oz <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/dr-oz-wins-pennsylvania-senate-primary-951-votes-final-tally-shows/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">barely won</a>, and Fetterman now holds an <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">8-point lead in the polls</a>. But like Wisconsin, Pennsylvania has a slight Republican lean, so this really should be ground the GOP is better positioned to hold. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Pennsylvania is another state, though, where <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the polls weren’t exactly on target</a> in 2020. Although as we’ve <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-death-of-polling-is-greatly-exaggerated/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">written extensively at FiveThirtyEight</a>, just because the polls miss in one election, doesn’t mean they’ll miss in the following election — or even in the same direction!</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> This race has been a big surprise for me. I’d have thought that Oz’s more liberal past positions on issues like <a href="https://www.inquirer.com/politics/election/mehmet-oz-conservative-policy-pa-senate-race-20220419.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abortion and gun control</a> would be helping him in a general election. Instead, he’s had trouble improving his image after a really nasty Republican primary. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Oz also isn’t very well-liked in the state. A <a href="https://www.aarp.org/content/dam/aarp/research/surveys_statistics/politics/2022/aarp-pennsylvania-2022-elections-voter-survey.doi.10.26419-2Fres.00550.003.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll</a> by AARP/Fabrizio Ward/Impact Research in June, for instance, found that his favorability rating among likely voters in Pennsylvania was 33 points underwater — 30 percent favorable to 63 percent unfavorable. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Fetterman, on the other hand, had a net-positive favorability rating of 10 points: 46 percent to 36 percent. And the survey was <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-argument-for-overturning-roe-v-wade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">taken prior</a> to the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Roe v. Wade, so I’m wondering if some Republicans — and women, who were also not particularly keen on Oz, per the survey — have since soured on Oz even more.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> I am curious, though, how big of a problem Fetterman’s health is going to be for him in the general election. (He <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/15/us/politics/john-fetterman-stroke.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">suffered a stroke</a> in May.) The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette’s editorial board wrote on Monday that if <a href="https://www.post-gazette.com/opinion/editorials/2022/09/06/mehmet-oz-stroke-auditory-processing-debate-john-fetterman-election-senate-pennsylvania-health/stories/202209020009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fetterman isn’t able to debate Oz</a>, it should raise serious questions about whether he’s up for the task of being a U.S. senator. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s a challenging situation to discuss sensitively, and <a href="https://www.post-gazette.com/news/politics-state/2022/08/31/john-fetterman-dr-mehmet-oz-debates-stroke-health-concessions/stories/202208310107" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Oz’s campaign</a> definitely hasn’t always done that, but Fetterman’s health could be a real liability for him this fall. Fetterman, for the record, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/09/07/fetterman-to-politico-i-will-debate-oz-00055301" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told Politico on Wednesday</a> that he plans to debate Oz.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, no one should be writing off Oz. Besides the fact that Pennsylvania has a slight Republican lean, it’s possible Oz could better consolidate support among Republicans and move into a more competitive position in the coming weeks. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Two recent polls from <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/pennsylvania-2022-fetterman-holds-four-point-lead-over-oz-for-us-senate-shapiro-leads-mastriano-by-three/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emerson College</a> and <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/docs/2022/Topline-PAStatewide-Aug2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Susquehanna Polling and Research</a> found that Republican voters were likelier to be undecided than Democrats, so if those voters come home to Oz, the race could get <em>a lot</em> tighter. Both of those polls also found a closer race than our polling average, instead finding Fetterman with a 4- to 5-point edge. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> But OK. The two Senate races we’ve talked about so far are in states where Republicans currently have control. Let’s talk about some of their best pickup opportunities, starting with Georgia.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> I know <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/georgia-2022-walker-holds-two-point-lead-over-warnock-in-tight-senate-race-kemp-leads-abrams-by-four/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some recent polls</a> have given Republican Herschel Walker a slight edge over Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock, but I think it’ll be hard to take down the incumbent. For one, Walker has been dogged with not-so-great headlines that suggest <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/herschel-walker-lied-about-his-secret-kids-to-his-own-campaign" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he did not disclose</a> all of his children, despite previously <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/14/us/politics/herschel-walker-son.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">chastising absent Black fathers</a>. He also has <a href="https://www.ajc.com/news/investigations/herschel-walkers-business-record-reveals-creditor-lawsuits-exaggerated-claims/D3FRT4RA7NFKTN23423ENPUP7A/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">exaggerated his business</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/05/25/politics/fact-check-walker-university-of-georgia-graduated/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">academic record</a>. Moreover, Warnock has continued to be <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/raphael-warnock-fundraising-second-quarter-georgia-senate-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a fundraising behemoth</a>, raising more than $17 million in the second-quarter of the year, compared with Walker’s $6.2 million. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This race is tricky, though, because the national environment will probably be better for the GOP and Walker is <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/georgia-2022-walker-holds-two-point-lead-over-warnock-in-tight-senate-race-kemp-leads-abrams-by-four/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relatively well liked</a> in the state.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> If Republicans want to win the Senate, they basically have to defeat Warnock. Case in point: According to the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-flip-senate-house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">build-your-own version of the FiveThirtyEight forecast</a>, if Democrats win Georgia, they have a 91 percent chance of holding the Senate:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1592" height="958" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image00111.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image00111.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image00111.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image00111.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Put another way, according to the Deluxe version of our forecast, Georgia also has a 15 percent chance of being the tipping-point state in the Senate, or the state that decides control of the chamber — which is more than the tipping-point odds of any other state in our forecast.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> There’s a real push and pull here with Georgia, though. The state obviously is more politically competitive now than it’s been in a long time, which is helpful to Warnock. He is also a decently popular senator who could benefit at least a little bit from incumbency.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, Georgia is also a state with a racially polarized electorate that is, as we say, “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/election-update-the-house-districts-that-swing-the-most-and-least-with-the-national-mood/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">highly inelastic</a>” because it just doesn’t have a lot of swing voters. Historically, when major races like Senate and governor are on the ballot at the same time in Georgia, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/georgias-senate-race-is-much-closer-than-the-governor-election-will-that-hold-until-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">they usually wind up with pretty similar results</a>. So with Republican Gov. Brian Kemp <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/2022/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ahead by about 5 points in the polls</a> and Warnock <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">leading by roughly 2 points</a>, that 7-point gap would be an especially large gap between the two contests if it holds. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And that’s a big “if.” I’m inclined to think the races will converge as we get closer to November. And whether Kemp or Warnock loses ground is very important to keep an eye on. As things currently stand, Warnock needs some Kemp voters in order to win reelection, and given how polarized Georgia’s electorate is, I’m not sure there will be a ton of those.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> The one thing I think that’s a little challenging with Georgia is how much it’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2020-swing-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shifted toward Democrats</a>. In other words, a lot could come down to turnout, and it looks as if enthusiasm (on both sides of the aisle) <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/394628/americans-intensity-running-high-midterms.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">might be high</a> again this year.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> If Kemp has a strong performance against his Democratic opponent, Stacey Abrams, could he help pull Walker across the finish line, Geoffrey?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Alex, that’s a difficult question to answer. <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/19/democratic-governors-are-resisting-bidens-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kemp is pretty popular</a>, so he can definitely help buoy the GOP ticket. Ultimately, I don’t think the Senate and gubernatorial races are going to completely converge, but if it’s a difference of 2 to 3 points by Election Day, that’s probably good news for Walker, whereas if it’s like 5 points or more, that’s good news for Warnock. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> It’s also possible that we get another runoff! Another candidate on the ballot — Libertarian Chase Oliver — could <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/chase-oliver-could-send-georgias-senate-race-to-a-runoff-hes-ok-with-that/GGBXCZ4FZJDYLIWFKDVU6OX2VA/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">siphon off votes</a> from both candidates, and if neither clears 50 percent of the vote in November, the top two vote-getters will go head-to-head on Dec. 6. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, the Senate race looks to have about a 1-in-5 shot of going to a runoff. The forecast gives a slight edge to Walker in a runoff, but we obviously saw Democrats win both Senate runoffs in January 2021 by running ahead of where they were in the November vote, which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-democrats-won-the-georgia-runoffs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was at odds with most of Georgia’s recent electoral history</a>, so it would be far from a sure thing for the GOP. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> Let’s talk about Nevada, the other Senate race Republicans are heavily targeting as a pickup opportunity. Is Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto, like Warnock, perhaps in trouble?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> There are plenty of reasons to believe this race might not be as safe for Democrats as some polls suggest. For one, as we’ve reported before, Nevada is a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-nevada-polls-are-bad/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pretty transient state</a>, and according to The New York Times, the state’s share of registered Democrats <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/04/01/us/politics/nevada-midterms-democrats.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has dropped</a>. Moreover, Biden won Nevada by only <a href="https://www.politico.com/2020-election/results/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a little over 2 points</a> in 2020, so it’s very possible that Republicans do better here in a favorable midterm year. The COVID-19 pandemic — and the business shutdowns that came with it — <a href="https://www.ktnv.com/news/new-report-reveals-how-hard-pandemic-hit-las-vegas-tourism-industry" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were also particularly devastating</a> to Nevada’s tourism industry. That, plus low approval ratings for Biden, have definitely put Cortez Masto on the defensive.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, she is actually the second-most vulnerable Democrat after Warnock, per our forecast. She has just a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/nevada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">63-in-100 chance of winning</a>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="848" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-NV-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-NV-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-NV-S3-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-NV-S3-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> And, as Alex said, Nevada is maybe more challenging for Democrats than they realize, since <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2020-swing-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it has been shifting away from Democrats</a> in recent presidential elections.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><img src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/chat.SENATE.0908.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/chat.SENATE.0908.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/chat.SENATE.0908.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/chat.SENATE.0908.png?w=1424 2x"></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Nevada definitely has a couple trends potentially working in the GOP’s favor. For instance, <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Latino voters shifted to the right</a> in 2020, although it varied from place to place. But still, Nevada <a href="https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/NV,US/RHI725221" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has a sizable Latino population</a>, and moreover, only a <a href="https://data.census.gov/cedsci/table?q=s1501&amp;g=0100000US%240400000&amp;tid=ACSST5Y2020.S1501&amp;tp=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">small share of Nevada’s white population</a> has a four-year college degree, which is significant considering that we know <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-know-about-how-white-and-latino-americans-voted-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">education is a big dividing line</a> among white voters, with non-college-educated whites moving toward Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> I’ll be curious to see which way Latino voters in the state swing, though, Geoffrey. What’s working in the GOP’s favor is that Trump gained support among Latino voters, as you said; plus, like the rest of the country, <a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/03/24/latino-democrats-inflation-poll" target="_blank" rel="noopener">inflation and concerns about the economy</a> continue to be a top concern among Latino voters. If Republican Adam Laxalt can tap into that disillusionment and discontent, he’ll definitely make the race more competitive. But Cortez Masto, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/09/us/politics/nevada-senate-catherine-cortez-masto.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the first Latina</a> to serve in the U.S. Senate, so far has a slight edge with Latino voters in the state, <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/democrats-losing-support-hispanic-voters-215124538.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to one poll</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> What do we know about Laxalt as a candidate? We talked about this a little with Georgia and Pennsylvania, but part of the problem for Republicans in the Senate this cycle seems to be an issue of candidate quality. Does Laxalt fit into this mold?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Not really, Sarah. He has some extreme views, like believing the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/republicans-trump-election-fraud/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 election was stolen from Trump</a>. But unlike Walker and Oz, he has experience as an elected official — he won the Nevada attorney general’s office in 2014.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Yeah, Laxalt is probably one of the least problematic candidates the GOP has nominated. He has an electoral track record, as Nathaniel mentioned, for one thing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> I’m curious how much the Dobbs decision will play a role in whether Cortez Masto ultimately prevails. She’s <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/nevada-senate-race-emerges-as-test-of-abortion-issue-after-roe-v-wade-overturned-11661004000" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reportedly telling voters</a> that a GOP-led Senate could lead to a national law banning abortions, and polls suggest that Nevadans also favor abortion rights at higher rates than the national average. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Per a July <a href="https://thenevadaindependent.com/article/poll-abortion-trails-only-the-economy-as-a-motivating-issue-for-nevada-voters" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey from The Nevada Independent/OH Predictive Insights</a>, roughly 90 percent of the state’s registered voters believe abortions should be legal at least some cases. It also found that abortion rights were the most motivating issue to 17 percent of the state’s voters — second only to the economy, at 40 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> There are two more Senate races we should talk about: Arizona and New Hampshire. They’re also pick-up opportunities for the GOP, although perhaps a little bit more of a stretch for Republicans, at least according to the forecast. Republicans have about <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a 1-in-4 shot of winning Arizona</a> and a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1-in-5 shot of winning New Hampshire</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So … uh, what do we make of the Senate race in Arizona?</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1422" height="848" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-AZ-S3-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-AZ-S3-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-AZ-S3-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-senate-topline-711-AZ-S3-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Blake Masters <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/2022-live-primary-election-race-results/2022/08/03/1115185686/blake-masters-trump-pick-funded-by-billionaire-thiel-wins-arizona-senate-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">won the GOP primary</a> with Trump’s backing and millions of dollars in support from billionaire tech megadonor Peter Thiel. But Democratic Sen. Mark Kelly has regularly led in the polls, where <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he currently has an 8-point lead</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Kelly has a combination of things working for him at the moment. First, he’s raised a <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/candidate/S0AZ00350/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prodigious amount of money</a> that Masters simply cannot match on his own. In fact, this has <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/09/02/politics/peter-thiel-senate-republicans-blake-masters-jd-vance/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">created conflicts within the GOP</a>, as Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell wants Thiel <a href="https://puck.news/can-thiel-and-mcconnell-strike-a-deal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to keep spending money</a> on Masters’s behalf, but so far, Thiel appears unwilling. Second, Kelly seems to be winning at least a small portion of Republican voters in Arizona, and he leads among independents as well. A <a href="https://static.foxnews.com/foxnews.com/content/uploads/2022/08/AZ-crosstabs_Sen-Gov-General_conducted-August-12-16_released-Aug-18-2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fox News/Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Co. Research poll</a> from last month found Kelly attracting about 10 percent of GOP voters, which would make him tough to beat if that comes to pass.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> What’s interesting to me about this race is that, on paper, it should be an easy get for Republicans. Kelly won the special election that got him into Congress in 2020 by <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/11/03/us/elections/results-arizona-senate-special.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 points</a>, and Biden <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2020-elections/arizona-president-results" target="_blank" rel="noopener">barely eked out a win</a> that same year. But I think candidate quality will definitely play a role in this race, and Masters is carrying a lot of baggage. Just to name a few things: He once said that “<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/trump-backed-senate-candidate-blake-masters-blames-gun-violence-black-rcna32290" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Black people, frankly</a>” are to blame for gun violence in the U.S., has promoted <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/republican-senate-candidates-promote-replacement-theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the debunked “great replacement” theory</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/06/us/politics/blake-masters.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">once argued</a> that Iraq and al-Qaida did not “constitute substantial threats to Americans.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Some of this is stuff Masters said when he was younger, but I suspect part of the issue is that he’s only 36 years old, so these controversial comments are not really that far in the past!</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Yeah, I feel more confident in the forecast’s prediction of a Kelly win in Arizona than, say, Fetterman in Pennsylvania. Kelly has a king’s ransom in campaign cash (he’s raised more than $54 million), and the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-general/2020/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls in Arizona in 2020</a> were pretty accurate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> OK, that leaves us with one last state to discuss: New Hampshire. The primary there hasn’t yet happened yet, but how are things looking for Republicans?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> New Hampshire is the least competitive of the races we’ve discussed here, and honestly, it’s hard to see it flipping unless Republicans have already flipped places like Georgia and Nevada. Democratic incumbent Maggie Hassan has an <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">80-in-100 chance of winning</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One complication here is that New Hampshire hasn’t held its primary yet, as you noted, Sarah, and it looks like far-right candidate Don Bolduc could defeat more establishment-flavored state Senate President Chuck Morse. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Consider that the latest poll from the <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1701&amp;context=survey_center_polls" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of New Hampshire</a>, conducted in late August, gave Bolduc 43 percent and Morse 22 percent. Since then, the establishment Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/31/republican-super-pac-2-million-new-hampshire-senate-primary-00054402" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spent heavily on Morse’s behalf</a>, so the final result could be tighter. But if Republican primary voters elect Bolduc, Republican party leaders could write off New Hampshire completely.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> Republicans seem to have struggled to find a likable, well-known candidate who everyone could coalesce around — especially after Gov. Chris Sununu <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/11/09/sununu-wont-run-for-senate-520413" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decided against running for U.S. Senate</a> and instead decided to seek reelection. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">An August survey by <a href="https://htv-prod-media.s3.amazonaws.com/files/sacsc-nhsw-0822-book-1660663140.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Saint Anselm College Survey Center</a> found that 39 percent of Republican voters were still undecided ahead of next week’s primary. But, similar to Arizona, I think this could be an easier pickup opportunity for Republicans: Per the poll, Hassan has an underwater approval rating in the state — 44 percent who approve versus 51 percent who disapprove, with only 39 percent saying she deserved to be reelected.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> We do have some recent evidence, though, that Democrats can win a Senate race in New Hampshire even in a bad midterm. Take Democratic Sen. Jeanne Shaheen. She held onto her seat in 2014 despite a red wave.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>sarah:</strong> OK, phew — we’ve run down six of the big Senate races this year. What are folks’ concluding thoughts on the GOP’s path to winning back the Senate or Democrats’ chances to holding on?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>alex:</strong> This should be an easy year for Republicans, but problematic candidates with little to no political experience may well cost the party their chances of winning the chamber back.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>nrakich:</strong> Completely agreed about the weaker candidates, but I’m also struck by the tough path Republicans have to picking up even <em>one</em> seat. They need to defeat at least one of what looks like a formidable quartet in Warnock, Kelly, Cortez Masto and Hassan, while also not losing any of their own seats. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That’s hard to do, so I think the FiveThirtyEight forecast’s current estimation of a 70 percent chance of a Democratic hold sounds right to me.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley:</strong> Republicans may have an uphill battle to a Senate majority, considering the political environment isn’t proving to be as advantageous for the GOP as we might have expected (at least so far). They’ve also nominated some weaker candidates, as Alex mentioned. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, I think there’s reason to believe some of these races, like Arizona and Pennsylvania, are going to be closer than they currently appear to be. Our forecast definitely keeps that in mind, too. It’s why I’d love to see more polls, especially in Wisconsin.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">“More polls, please” — the constant FiveThirtyEight refrain.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-favored-win-pennsylvania-senate-gubernatorial-races-89313612</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662633001857878</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Georgia’s Senate Race Is Much Closer Than The Governor Election. Will That Hold Until November?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/georgias-senate-race-is-much-closer-than-the-governor-election-will-that-hold-until-november/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<category>Georgia Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Georgia’s Senate Race Is Much Closer Than The Governor Election. Will That Hold Until November?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 7, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0906-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0906-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0906-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0906-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0906-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
						
		</figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">After a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-georgia-turned-blue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">history-making 2020</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-democrats-won-the-georgia-runoffs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2021</a>, Georgia is once again <a href="https://youtu.be/ggGzE5KfCio" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on our minds</a> with two high-profile statewide races on the ballot this November: the U.S. Senate race, a <em>highly</em> competitive contest between Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock and Republican Herschel Walker, as well as the gubernatorial contest, a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-the-gop-could-make-or-break-its-chances-in-10-key-governors-races/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">high-octane rematch</a> between Republican Gov. Brian Kemp and Democrat Stacey Abrams.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But interestingly, these races have pretty different outlooks in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s 2022 midterm forecast</a>. The Senate race is currently rated <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as a toss-up</a>, while in the governor’s race <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kemp is a clear favorite</a> to win.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/herschel-walker-goodwill-georgia-win-senate-seat-89425858</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">Given how partisan our politics have become — especially in a state like Georgia where the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/swing-voters-and-elastic-states/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">electorate is highly polarized</a> — it’s pretty unusual that the two statewide races show such a large gap, as much as 13 percentage points in some polls. Historically, major contests in Georgia have run close together, which is why a sizable split between the Senate and governor’s races would be pretty remarkable.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">For starters, the gap between the two races varies depending on pollster, but on average, polls have found a 7-point difference between the margins in the Senate and gubernatorial contests. This pretty much matches what our <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more rigorous polling averages</a> found, too, with <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/senate/2022/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Warnock up around 2 points</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/2022/georgia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kemp leading by about 5 points</a><a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday at 5 p.m. Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>12</sup></a> — or a 7-point gap.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>The gap between Georgia’s marquee races is wide</h5>
 <p>The margin in Georgia’s Senate and governor races in polls that measured both, including the gap between the two contests, since the May 24 primary</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.ga-sen-vs-ga-gov.2"><thead><tr aria-hidden="true"><th colspan="2" scope="colgroup"></th>
 <th colspan="3" scope="colgroup">Margin</th>
 </tr><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Poll</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Date</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Senate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Governor</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Gap</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Emerson College</td>
 <td>Aug. 28-29</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Trafalgar Group (R)</td>
 <td>Aug. 24-27</td>
 <td>R+1</td>
 <td>R+6</td>
 <td>6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Phillips Academy/Abbot Academy Fund</td>
 <td>Aug. 3-7</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>R+8</td>
 <td>6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Research Affiliates/Charlie L. Bailey (D)</td>
 <td>July 26-Aug. 1</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>TIE</td>
 <td>3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>InsiderAdvantage/WAGA-TV</td>
 <td>July 26-27</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>8</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Co. Research/Fox News</td>
 <td>July 22-26</td>
 <td>D+4</td>
 <td>R+3</td>
 <td>7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>SurveyUSA/WXIA-TV</td>
 <td>July 21-24</td>
 <td>D+9</td>
 <td>R+1</td>
 <td>10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Univ. of Georgia/Atlanta Journal-Constitution</td>
 <td>July 14-22</td>
 <td>D+4</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Fabrizio, Lee &amp; Associates/Impact Research/AARP</td>
 <td>July 5-11</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>R+7</td>
 <td>10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Beacon Research/Environmental Voter Project</td>
 <td>July 5-20</td>
 <td>D+5</td>
 <td>R+8</td>
 <td>13</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Data for Progress</td>
 <td>July 1-6</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>R+9</td>
 <td>7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Change Research/Future Majority (D)</td>
 <td>June 24-27</td>
 <td>D+4</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Quinnipiac Univ.</td>
 <td>June 23-27</td>
 <td>D+10</td>
 <td>TIE</td>
 <td>10</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Moore Information/Herschel Walker (R)</td>
 <td>June 11-16</td>
 <td>TIE</td>
 <td>R+7</td>
 <td>7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>East Carolina Univ.</td>
 <td>June 6-9</td>
 <td>D+1</td>
 <td>R+6</td>
 <td>6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Average</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>7</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>The data is shown as rounded but was calculated based on the fully-reported info in cases where pollsters provided decimal points. A “(D)” or “(R)” beside a pollster’s name indicates their or their sponsor’s partisan affiliation.</p>
 <p>Source: polls</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But the fact that Georgia’s electorate is so polarized makes it unlikely that we’ll see <em>too</em> large of a gap between the two contests. Like most of the Deep South, Georgia <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ssqu.12149" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has a racially polarized electorate</a>, where most Black voters back Democrats and most white voters back Republicans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Take Georgia’s 2020 presidential vote: 88 percent of Black voters supported President Biden, while 69 percent of white voters supported former President Trump, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Elections/georgia-exit-polls-2020-us-presidential-election-results-analysis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to the 2020 exit polls</a>. This gives Georgia what we at FiveThirtyEight call an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/election-update-the-house-districts-that-swing-the-most-and-least-with-the-national-mood/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“inelastic” electorate</a>, or an electorate for which factors like the political environment and candidate traits are unlikely to sway voters because so few voters are swing voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This lack of a gap in Georgia’s statewide elections is clear when we examine elections dating back to 2002, which is arguably when Georgia’s current political era began — that year, Republicans <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/10/us/2002-election-georgia-bush-s-push-eager-volunteers-big-turnout-led-georgia-sweep.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">won the governorship and captured a state-legislative chamber</a> for the first time since Reconstruction. For instance, when we compare the outcomes in each pair of presidential, Senate and gubernatorial races in years when two of those races were on the ballot,<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just one year, 2020, had three statewide races since Georgia had a special election for Senate that November. It was a jungle primary, however, and is not listed in the table, though the runoff held in January 2021 is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>13</sup></a> the margins in these high-profile races usually differed only to a small extent, as the table below shows.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Top-tier Georgia races don’t usually differ much</h5>
 <p>Difference in margin between major statewide elections for president, Senate or governor in years when at least two of these offices were on the ballot, 2002 to present</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.ga-sen-vs-ga-gov.4"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Year</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Margin</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Race</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Margin</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Gap</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2021</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>D+1.2</td>
 <td>Senate*</td>
 <td>D+2.1</td>
 <td>0.9</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2020</td>
 <td>President</td>
 <td>D+0.2</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+1.8</td>
 <td>2.0</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2016</td>
 <td>President</td>
 <td>R+5.1</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+13.8</td>
 <td>8.7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2014</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+7.7</td>
 <td>Governor</td>
 <td>R+7.9</td>
 <td>0.2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2010</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+19.3</td>
 <td>Governor</td>
 <td>R+10.1</td>
 <td>9.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2008</td>
 <td>President</td>
 <td>R+5.2</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+2.9</td>
 <td>2.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2004</td>
 <td>President</td>
 <td>R+16.6</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+17.9</td>
 <td>1.3</td>
 </tr><tr><td>2002</td>
 <td>Senate</td>
 <td>R+6.9</td>
 <td>Governor</td>
 <td>R+5.2</td>
 <td>1.7</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>*Special election for U.S. Senate</p>
 <p>The 2020 Senate race is the regularly scheduled Class II seat, as the special election for the Class III seat was a jungle primary. No candidate won an outright majority in either Senate election, which by state law necessitated a January 2021 runoff, as shown in the 2021 row.</p>
 <p>Source: Dave Leip’s Atlas of U.S. Presidential Elections</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Although each year and race had its own set of particulars, six of these eight sets of elections saw only small differences in margin — less than 3 points. The exceptions were the 2010 midterms and 2016 presidential election, when there was a wide gap between the Senate election and the other statewide election. (Republican Sen. Johnny Isakson was up both years, so <a href="https://www.georgiapol.com/2016/11/22/deeper-dive-gwinnetts-election-results/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he may have given the GOP</a> a lift as an incumbent; also former Gov. Roy Barnes served as the Democrats’ nominee for governor in 2010, and <a href="https://www.atlantamagazine.com/news-culture-articles/roy-barnes-on-the-confederate-flag-and-where-the-south-needs-to-go-from-here/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his past appeal</a> in more conservative parts of the state may have made that race closer than it would’ve been otherwise.) But these elections were the exception, not the norm. Even the state’s most recent elections, the 2020 presidential election and 2021 Senate runoffs, featured elections with very similar margins — although they might be evidence that the overall political climate in Georgia is shifting toward Democrats.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s notable, then, that the FiveThirtyEight forecast shows such a large divide between the Senate and governor races in its average projected vote share. The forecast currently<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday at 5 p.m. Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> has Kemp with a 6-point lead and Warnock with about a 1-point lead, which would amount to a 7-point gap between the two races. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are a number of potential explanations for this gap, but the biggest factor might be incumbency and, more importantly, that Georgia’s top two races feature incumbents from different parties — Kemp is a Republican and Warnock a Democrat. <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Seth-Mckee/publication/326886553_Nationalization_in_US_Senate_and_Gubernatorial_Elections/links/5f221f58a6fdcccc4399348a/Nationalization-in-US-Senate-and-Gubernatorial-Elections.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Incumbency does not provide as strong</a> a tailwind as it once did, but both Kemp and Warnock are relatively popular politicians who could each win. From April through June, <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/19/democratic-governors-are-resisting-bidens-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult’s polling</a> gave Kemp a 52 percent approval rating and only a 39 percent disapproval rating; <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/25/murkowski-experiences-mid-campaign-approval-bump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Warnock</a>, meanwhile, had an approval rating of about 47 percent and a disapproval rating of 41 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, there isn’t <em>that</em> much difference between Kemp’s and Warnock’s standing in Georgia. However, given that the gap between the two races is unlikely to remain this large and that Kemp has a healthier lead over Abrams than Warnock has over Walker, voters who split their tickets could matter a lot for Warnock. And two polls, one from Emerson College <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/georgia-2022-walker-holds-two-point-lead-over-warnock-in-tight-senate-race-kemp-leads-abrams-by-four/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released last week</a> and a <a href="https://static.foxnews.com/foxnews.com/content/uploads/2022/07/ef9384ab-GA-crosstabs_Sen-Gov-General_conducted-July-22-26_released-July-28-2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">July survey</a> from Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Company on behalf of Fox News, show how different degrees of Kemp voters backing Warnock could matter. In Emerson’s poll, only 3 percent of Kemp supporters backed Warnock, and overall, Walker led by 2 points. In the Fox News survey, meanwhile, 8 percent of Kemp’s supporters backed Warnock, and overall, Warnock led by 4 points. The takeaway here is that higher levels of support for Warnock among Kemp voters would seemingly boost the incumbent senator’s chances of finishing ahead of Walker. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is not to say that only split-ticket voting will matter to the outcomes in each race; turnout and the overall political environment are also important. But Warnock would be in much better shape if he could capture 8 percent of Kemp’s voters versus just 3 percent: Based <a href="https://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/state.php?year=2018&amp;fips=13&amp;f=0&amp;off=5&amp;elect=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on the 2018 governor’s race</a>, that could be a difference of roughly 100,000 votes, or about 2.5 percent of ballots cast. In a close contest, that’s a big deal — case in point, Kemp defeated Abrams by just 55,000 votes four years ago.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, there’s one other wrinkle with Georgia: If no candidate wins an outright majority of the vote, a runoff between the top-two finishers <a href="https://www.sos.ga.gov/sites/default/files/forms/2022%20State%20Scheduled%20Elections%20Short%20Calendar.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">will take place</a> on Dec. 6, 2022.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a change from the 2020 cycle, when the Senate runoffs took place in January 2021. The &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/25/us/politics/georgia-voting-law-republicans.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Georgia voting law passed early in 2021&lt;/a&gt; contained many changes for voting rules, including a shift in the runoff date for federal elections to four weeks after the regular election, instead of nine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>15</sup></a> And considering each contest has a Libertarian candidate, which is notable because Libertarians have averaged a little over 2 percent in statewide races dating back to 2002, it’s entirely possible that if the Senate race is <em>especially</em> tight, a Libertarian candidate who gains 1 or 2 percent of the vote could trigger a Warnock-Walker runoff in December. Currently,<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday at 5 p.m. Eastern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> the FiveThirtyEight forecast gives the Senate race about a 1-in-5 chance of going to a runoff, while the governor’s race has about a 1-in-10 chance.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, it’s too soon to say how the races in Georgia will change, but with two months to go until Election Day, we’ll be keeping a close eye on Peach State polls to see whether the gap between the two contests remains large or narrows.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/buy-dems-favored-win-pennsylvania-senate-gubernatorial-races-89313612</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662547501433645</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: What To Expect Between Now And Election Day</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-expect-between-now-and-election-day/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Public Opinion</category>
			<category>Student Debt</category>
			<category>The Biden Administration</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-what-to-expect-between-now-and-election-day/">
	<div data-podcast-id="343610" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: What To Expect Between Now And Election Day">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP5620875797.mp3?updated=1662504910">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Labor Day traditionally marks the point at which general election campaigning truly ramps up — summer vacation is over, TV ads flood the airways and pollsters switch their models from registered voters to likely voters. In this installment of the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/politics-podcast/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast</a>, the crew discusses how they expect the next few months leading up to the midterm elections to play out, based on historical trends.​​ They then play a game of midterm trivia, reviewing the largest midterm election swings, key policy issues and how Americans have followed past midterm news.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The team also analyzes the media attention surrounding the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s recently published <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/vsrr/vsrr023.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">life expectancy report</a> for 2021 and the political implications of falling life expectancy beyond the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 23:52:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662507001201432</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Where Candidates Who Deny The 2020 Election Results Are On The Ballot — And Where They Could Win</title>
			<link>https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/republicans-trump-election-fraud/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight staff</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Deniers</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>From Connecticut to California, Montana to Florida, election denialism has spread across the country. Candidates who support former President Donald Trump’s false claims that the 2020 election was stolen will appear on ballots in nearly every state this fall. FiveThirtyEight drew on news reports, debate footage, campaign materials, social media and reached out to every single Republican nominee for the House, Senate, governor, secretary of state and attorney general to determine their position on the 2020 election.</p>
<p>There are a lot of election deniers on the ballot. Out of 529 total Republican nominees running for office, we found 195 who FULLY DENIED the legitimacy of the 2020 election. These candidates either clearly stated that the election was stolen from Trump or took legal action to overturn the results, such as voting not to certify election results or joining lawsuits that sought to overturn the election.</p>
<p>Moreover, an additional 61 candidates RAISED QUESTIONS around the results of the 2020 election. These candidates haven’t gone so far as to say explicitly that the election was stolen or take legal action to overturn it. However, they haven’t said the election was legitimate either. In fact, they have raised doubts about potential fraud.</p>
<p>There were 115 candidates whose position on the 2020 election we could not determine. They either had NO COMMENT on the 2020 election or AVOIDED ANSWERING when asked directly.</p>
<p>But not all Republicans running embrace Trump’s claims. A total of 71 have FULLY ACCEPTED the results of the 2020 election while another 87 have ACCEPTED WITH RESERVATIONS, meaning they think President Biden won, but still raised concerns about the integrity of the election.</p>
<p>In the House, many of these election deniers look poised to win. Using the latest data from the 2022 midterm election <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/">FiveThirtyEight forecast</a>, we can see that 118 election deniers and eight election doubters have at least a 95 percent chance of winning. Several additional candidates who have denied the election are in competitive races.</p>
<p>In the Senate, though, there will be far fewer election deniers. Only three election deniers are safe bets to join the seven senators not up for reelection who objected to the certification of the 2020 election. However, a handful more still have a real shot at winning.</p>
<p>In governors races, more election deniers stand to prevail. At least two election deniers and four election doubters are poised to be inaugurated as governors next year. And we can’t rule out election deniers being elected governor of swing states like Arizona and Pennsylvania.</p>
<p tabindex="0">We don’t forecast elections for attorney general or secretary of state, but there are also seven election deniers running for attorney general and six for secretary of state, the post that oversees election administration in most states.</p>
<p tabindex="0">Indeed, an election denier winning election and taking office is more than a symbolic concern. An election-denying secretary of state could refuse to certify an election that he or she believes was rigged. An election-denying governor could attempt to submit electoral votes that defy the will of the people. And election-denying senators and representatives could vote to count those electoral votes. The 2022 election will determine how many of these candidates get that chance.</p>
<h3>Are election deniers running in your state?</h3>
<p tabindex="0">See whether the Republicans running in your state have denied or accepted the legitimacy of the 2020 election</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662462001778460</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Massachusetts’s Governorship Is The Likeliest To Flip In 2022</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/massachusetts-governor-2022/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Governors Elections</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Massachusetts</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Massachusetts’s Governorship Is The Likeliest To Flip In 2022</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 6, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="State Democratic Party Convention" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241145856-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241145856-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241145856-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/GettyImages-1241145856-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Massachusetts Attorney General Maura Healey, who is essentially unopposed in the state’s primary today, would be Massachusetts’s second female governor if elected this fall.													<p>Craig F. Walker / The Boston Globe / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Massachusetts has an opening in its corner office. Republican Gov. Charlie Baker is retiring, and in a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2003/ALLPOLITICS/09/02/elec04.prez.kerry/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-elizabeth-warren-could-win-the-2020-democratic-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">with</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-seth-moulton-could-win-the-2020-democratic-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/mitt-romney-announces-2012-presidential-bid/2011/06/02/AG05iJHH_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shortage</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/12/01/marty-walsh-massachusetts-governor-523620" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/massachusetts-playbook/2022/03/28/clark-plays-coy-about-becoming-speaker-00020774" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ambitious</a> <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-deval-patrick-is-making-a-late-bid-for-the-democratic-nomination/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politicians</a>, you’d expect there to be a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Artery" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Central Artery</a>-worthy traffic jam to take his place. But instead, more than two months before Election Day, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/massachusetts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it’s already safe</a> for Democratic Attorney General Maura Healey to start picking out <a href="https://www.bostonherald.com/2013/11/20/its-curtains-for-govs-drapes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new drapes</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So how did the race to govern the nation’s <a href="https://www.icip.iastate.edu/tables/population/census-states" target="_blank" rel="noopener">15th largest state</a>, the <a href="https://historyofmassachusetts.org/massachusetts-american-revolution/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">birthplace of the American Revolution</a>, the hub of New England (if not the <a href="https://www.wgbh.org/news/2017/08/30/local-news/beantown-hub-how-did-boston-earn-its-nicknames" target="_blank" rel="noopener">universe</a>) — and, if you couldn’t already tell, my home state — get so uncompetitive?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It wasn’t always. A year ago, it looked like <a href="https://malegislature.gov/Laws/GeneralLaws/PartI/TitleI/Chapter2/Section35" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bay Staters</a> were in for not one, but two competitive gubernatorial primaries. <a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2021/06/14/massachusetts-danielle-allen-gubernatorial-run-announcement" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Harvard professor Danielle Allen</a>, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ri-state-wire-ma-state-wire-campaigns-race-and-ethnicity-health-13d18bd9989acdd046e9558c2b46b7a9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">state Sen. Sonia Chang-Díaz</a> and <a href="https://www.masslive.com/politics/2021/02/former-state-sen-ben-downing-launches-campaign-for-massachusetts-governor-says-leadership-to-tackle-states-big-challenges-is-sorely-lacking.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">former state Sen. Ben Downing</a> were all running on the Democratic side, while <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2021/07/04/metro/geoff-diehl-announces-bid-governor-first-republican-step-into-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">former state Rep. Geoff Diehl</a> was challenging Baker in the Republican primary.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Normally, a primary challenge to a sitting governor would be a fool’s errand, but Baker is <a href="https://www.bostonherald.com/2021/01/25/charlie-baker-faces-unrest-in-massgop-over-trumps-second-impeachment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">no favorite of the GOP base</a>. Part of a long-running tradition of <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2018/11/republican-governors-new-england-defy-blue-wave/574726/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">moderate, even liberal, Republican governors</a> in the Northeast, Baker has worked with the Democratic legislature to <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2022/08/11/science/baker-signs-major-climate-bill-into-law/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fight climate change</a> and <a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2022/07/29/gov-baker-signs-bill-protecting-abortion-access" target="_blank" rel="noopener">protect abortion rights</a>, and he even came out in favor of <a href="https://www.bostonherald.com/2021/01/13/charlie-baker-says-he-supports-second-trump-impeachment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">impeaching former President Donald Trump</a> for his role in the Jan. 6 attack on the U.S. Capitol. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Baker’s approval rating among Republicans, in other words, wasn’t great. It was only 35 percent in November 2021, according to a <a href="https://osf.io/gcuq4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID States Project poll</a>. And after Trump <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-charlie-baker-massachusetts-elections-e5148f198e3311106786e81cefc4568d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsed Diehl</a>, a <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1PNyPSWiD53_Q19bYlmXQaBmcakYJ1kjP/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Public Policy Polling survey</a> sponsored by the Democratic Governors Association (admittedly, not a disinterested party) found Diehl beating Baker in the GOP primary by 21 percentage points.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Baker denied that fear of losing the primary had anything to do with it, but he <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2021/12/01/metro/baker-telling-allies-he-isnt-running-reelection/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pulled the plug</a> in December 2021, and his decision not to run for reelection changed the trajectory of the race for both parties. On the very day of Baker’s retirement, speculation turned to whether Healey, a rising Democratic star, would <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2021/12/01/metro/bakers-decision-not-seek-reelection-rekindles-interest-some-public-denials-among-might-be-candidates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">launch a campaign</a>. With Healey’s candidacy (and $3.3 million war chest) looming, Downing <a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2021/12/28/ben-downing-out-race-governor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropped out of the race</a> a few weeks later. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Healey officially <a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2022/01/19/attorney-general-healey-announces-gubernatoril-run" target="_blank" rel="noopener">threw her hat into the ring</a> in January, and she immediately crowded out the remaining candidates. A <a href="https://www.massincpolling.com/the-topline/poll-release-new-numbers-on-2022-democratic-primary-races" target="_blank" rel="noopener">January poll</a> of the Democratic primary from MassINC Polling Group gave her 48 percent to Chang-Díaz’s 12 percent and Allen’s 3 percent. Less than a month later, Allen was <a href="https://www.masslive.com/politics/2022/02/harvard-professor-danielle-allen-dropping-out-of-democratic-race-for-massachusetts-governor.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">out of the race</a> too. Chang-Díaz hung in there a little longer, but still facing a 33-point deficit in a <a href="https://polsci.umass.edu/sites/default/files/PrimaryToplinesSpring2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June poll</a> from the University of Massachusetts Amherst, she announced on June 23 that she had “no path” to win the primary and was <a href="https://www.bostonherald.com/2022/06/23/sonia-chang-diaz-drops-out-of-race-for-governor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropping out too</a>. Although Chang-Díaz’s name is still appearing on ballots, Healey is now essentially unopposed in Tuesday’s Democratic primary.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And it doesn’t look like she’ll have much trouble in the general election either. <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/governor/2022/massachusetts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Poll after poll</a> has given Healey a commanding lead, most recently <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2022/07/26/metro/suffocating-sense-unease-mass-residents-stressed-by-inflation-supreme-court-decisions-new-poll-finds/?s_campaign=bostonglobe%3Asocialflow%3Atwitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Suffolk University</a> in July (Healey 54 percent, Diehl 23 percent). And according to all three versions of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/massachusetts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight midterm forecast</a>, Healey has a greater than 99 in 100 chance of beating Diehl.<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Sept. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a> That makes Massachusetts the most likely governorship to change parties in the 2022 election — just behind <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/governor/maryland/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Maryland</a>, another blue state where a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2022/07/20/larry-hogan-future-dan-cox/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">moderate Republican governor is retiring</a> and Republicans have nominated a diehard Trump supporter to replace him.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Massachusetts is the likeliest governorship to change parties</h5>
 <p>The 10 likeliest governorships to change parties in the 2022 election, based on the Deluxe version of the FiveThirtyEight forecast as of 5 p.m. Eastern on Sept. 2, 2022</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.ma-gov.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">State</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Incumbent Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Odds of Party Flip</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Massachusetts</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">&gt;99%</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maryland</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>97</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Arizona</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>53</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Kansas</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>45</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nevada</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>37</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Wisconsin</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>34</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Oregon</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>30</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Alaska*</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>19</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Maine</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>17</td>
 </tr><tr><td>New Mexico</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>17</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>*The 19 percent chance that Alaska’s governorship changes parties includes a 10 percent chance that an independent wins and a 9 percent chance that a Democrat wins.</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">It’s true that Massachusetts has elected only one Democratic governor since 1990, and it’s true that Baker is currently one of the <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/07/19/democratic-governors-are-resisting-bidens-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most popular governors in the country</a>. But as partisanship comes to hold <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/all-politics-is-presidential/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">greater and greater sway over gubernatorial elections</a>, Massachusetts may simply be too Democratic (according to FiveThirtyEight partisan lean,<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a> it’s the bluest state in the country) to elect another Republican governor — especially one as Trumpy as Diehl.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Granted, Diehl still has to win his own primary on Tuesday — and some Republicans believe they could still win in November if they nominate self-described “<a href="https://www.wbur.org/news/2022/08/04/mass-governor-chris-doughty-republican" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pragmatic businessman</a>” Chris Doughty. But Doughty’s belief that Trump lost the 2020 election and promise to keep abortion legal in Massachusetts are unlikely to fly in a Republican primary: An <a href="https://assets.nationbuilder.com/fiscalalliancefoundation/pages/72/attachments/original/1661436447/Fiscal_Alliance_August_2022_Primary_Poll_FINAL.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">August poll</a> from Advantage/Fiscal Alliance Foundation gave Diehl a 42-percent-to-27-percent lead. And even if Doughty <em>were</em> to upset Diehl in the primary, <a href="https://www.uml.edu/docs/2022-Mass-Voters-Issues-Topline_tcm18-353564.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls</a> <a href="https://emersonpolling.reportablenews.com/pr/massachusetts-2022-democrats-eye-gubernatorial-pick-up-in-massachusetts-a-g-maura-healey-leads-geoff-diehl-in-general-election" target="_blank" rel="noopener">currently</a> suggest he would do just as poorly as Diehl in the general election. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, Healey is in good shape — not only to flip the Massachusetts governor’s office from red to blue, but also to make history. She would be the <a href="https://www.axios.com/local/boston/2022/06/24/maura-healey-likely-massachusetts-first-female-governor" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first woman elected governor of Massachusetts</a> and the <a href="https://www.outfrontmagazine.com/america-could-have-two-lesbian-governors-come-election-season/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first openly lesbian governor of any state</a>.<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic nominee for governor of Oregon, Tina Kotek, would share this distinction if elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> So no matter what happens in the midterms elsewhere in the country, Massachusetts will give Democrats at least one thing to celebrate.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662462001778459</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Trump’s Presence In The Midterms Is Risky For The GOP</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-trumps-presence-in-the-midterms-is-risky-for-the-gop/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Election Update</category>
			<category>Election Updates</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Trump's Presence In The Midterms Is Risky For The GOP</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/" title="" rel="author">Nate Silver</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 2, 2022, at 8:42 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0826-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0826-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0826-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0826-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/2022-ELECTIONUPDATE-0826-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Upset Democratic special election wins in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/31/democrat-peltola-beats-palin-in-alaska-special-election-upset-00054428" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alaska</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/24/nyregion/pat-ryan-special-election-abortion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York</a> over the past two weeks are the latest sign that the political environment might be unusual for a midterm election. Frankly, the results since the Supreme Court overturned Roe v. Wade have <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looked more like 2018 than 2020</a>, with Democrats competitive even in red-leaning districts. That probably won’t hold. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But even if it’s just a neutral year — as the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generic congressional ballot currently shows</a> — Democrats would probably be pleased. It would likely be enough for them to hold the Senate, and even gain a seat or two. It would even give them a chance in the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Or maybe not. Democrats are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fighting against a <em>lot</em> of midterm election history</a> where the president’s party typically does poorly. They’ve also benefited from a turnout advantage in recent special elections that may not be replicated in November. The FiveThirtyEight forecast does not consider the special election results and hedges based on these historical trends; it’s why it still has Republicans as <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">75 percent favorites to keep the House</a>, although <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats’ chances of retaining the Senate</a> continue to improve and are now 68 percent.<a data-footnote-id="17" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-17" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>17</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, whenever a Democrat gets elected in Alaska — even given the quirks of the instant-runoff process in the state — it’s probably worth asking again if things could go really badly for the GOP.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Last month, I <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-this-be-an-asterisk-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">examined a series of what I called asterisk midterm elections</a>. These were the midterms that were the exceptions to the rule: When the president’s party actually gained seats in the House, or at least fought things to a near-draw while gaining in the Senate. The elections were 1934, 1962, 1998 and 2002, and three of the four involved some type of national emergency (the Great Depression, the Cuban missile crisis and the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks). The 1998 midterm was the exception to this, but it did have a national controversy of its own — a backlash to Republican overreach on the Monica Lewinsky scandal and subsequent impeachment trial. I argued that 2022 has some features in common with these elections, but it had the most in common with 1998 given the partisan overreach that is happening now.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In particular, the involvement of former President Donald Trump makes 2022 different than almost any other midterm.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At this point, we’re used to Trump’s ubiquity in American political life. But this degree of involvement from a former president — or, for that matter, even an ex-presidential <em>candidate</em> — is highly unusual. Take a look, for example, at the <a href="https://trends.google.com/trends/explore?date=2008-01-01%202022-09-01&amp;geo=US&amp;q=%2Fm%2F0cqt90,%2Fm%2F0d06m5,%2Fm%2F02mjmr,%2Fm%2F09b6zr" target="_blank" rel="noopener">amount of Google search traffic for Trump</a> as compared with other former presidents.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2838" height="1454" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-7.53.35-AM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-7.53.35-AM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-7.53.35-AM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-7.53.35-AM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure></div>


<figure><img loading="lazy" width="874" height="1392" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.01.00-AM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.01.00-AM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.01.00-AM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.01.00-AM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">Former Presidents Barack Obama and George W. Bush kept a very low profile after completing their second terms. And the previous losing candidate before Trump, Hillary Clinton, famously <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national/in-the-chappaqua-woods-a-search-for-hillary-clinton/2016/12/17/60daea40-c3c0-11e6-8422-eac61c0ef74d_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">retreated to the woods</a> in Chappaqua, New York, after 2016. Their search traffic quickly dropped to near-zero once their campaigns or presidencies were over, and then stayed there.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump’s search traffic, meanwhile, is much less than during his presidency, but it’s still fairly high. Over the past year, in fact, there’s been <a href="https://trends.google.com/trends/explore?geo=US&amp;q=%2Fm%2F012gx2,%2Fm%2F0cqt90" target="_blank" rel="noopener">about as much search traffic</a> for Trump as for the current president, Joe Biden!</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="2786" height="1458" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.35-AM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.35-AM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.35-AM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.35-AM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><figure><img loading="lazy" width="870" height="1330" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.46-AM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.46-AM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.46-AM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-02-at-8.05.46-AM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">And the amount of news interest in Trump has been increasing recently. Part of that is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-endorsees-have-started-losing-more-but-dont-read-into-that-for-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the string of endorsements</a> he’s made in Republican primaries, but the bigger factor is the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/26/us/politics/trump-documents-search-timeline.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FBI’s seizure of classified documents</a> he had in his possession at his Florida estate, Mar-a-Lago.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">When that seizure occurred, a certain strain of conventional wisdom <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/campaign/3610835-the-mar-a-lago-raid-gave-republicans-an-unexpected-second-wind/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">suggested that this could help Republicans in the midterms</a>, such as by increasing the enthusiasm of GOP voters.<a data-footnote-id="18" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-18" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s also a &lt;a href="https://whyy.org/articles/trump-fbi-mar-a-lago-search-gop-rallies/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;strain of conventional wisdom&lt;/a&gt; that suggests the Mar-a-Lago seizure could help Trump’s nomination chances in 2024. I think that case is overstated, but that’s beyond the scope of our article today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>18</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If that’s true, it’s not showing up in the data. The past four special elections — two in New York, one in Alaska and one in Minnesota — all occurred after the seizure on Aug. 8, and they all showed excellent results for Democrats. And Democrats have <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">actually gained about a point</a> on the generic ballot since then, although it’s a small enough difference that it could be statistical noise.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not exactly some genius insight to suggest that Trump could cause problems for Republicans in the midterms. At the very least, he’s directly put their prospects at risk by <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/its-hard-to-win-a-senate-race-when-youve-never-won-an-election-before/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsing inexperienced candidates</a> like <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/pennsylvania/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mehmet Oz in Pennsylvania</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/senate/arizona/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Blake Masters in Arizona</a>, who are badly underperforming partisan benchmarks in their states.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But it’s also the case that Trump’s continued dominance over the GOP violates a potentially key assumption behind the “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">midterm curse</a>,” which is that a party usually tries to pivot away from its losing candidates.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Sometimes that pivot involves providing voters a menu of new policy options, such as the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/us-policy/2022/01/20/republican-midterm-plan-education-economy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GOP’s “Contract with America” in 1994</a>. Many times it’s a pivot to the center, though it doesn’t need to be; <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2014/02/27/politics/tea-party-greatest-hits" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the tea party movement in 2010 was more conservative</a> in some ways than Bush, but it still offered voters something a little different.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The pivot doesn’t necessarily need to involve a new figurehead for the party, either. It probably helps if you don’t have one, in fact, since then you can frame the election as a referendum on the incumbent party’s performance and <a href="https://themonkeycage.org/2010/06/the_public_is_a_thermostat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">take advantage of thermostatic changes in public opinion</a> rather than as a choice between imperfect alternatives, as presidential elections turn into. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In 2018, for instance, Trump gave Democrats <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2018/10/25/poll-midterm-elections-donald-trump-democrats/1742432002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a lot of ammunition to run on</a>, and they nominated different kinds of candidates in different kinds of districts while preparing for a very large presidential primary field. What you didn’t see, though, was a lot of Clinton, who <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/10/01/politics/clinton-illinois-campaign-event" target="_blank" rel="noopener">didn’t make her first campaign appearance until October</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s play out that counterfactual, though. Imagine that, in 2018, Clinton had been very active on the campaign trail, endorsing candidates that often went against the wishes of the party establishment, repeatedly claiming that the 2016 election had been stolen — and then there had been a FBI seizure of classified secretary of state records in Chappaqua. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Would that have helped Democrats in the midterms? Probably not.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But if anything, Republicans are doubling down on Trump and Trumpism. This week, he <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/trump-demands-redo-2020-election-1234583872/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">demanded a redo of the 2020 election</a>. The leading candidate for the 2024 nomination <em>apart</em> from Trump, Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/08/desantis-trump-fbi-00050462" target="_blank" rel="noopener">defended Trump after the Mar-a-Lago search</a> and has even <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/trump-desantis-rip-off-complaints-1234583383/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">come to mimic</a> some of his mannerisms and manners of speech. Republicans have had <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2022/08/15/has-trump-put-the-republican-party-in-danger-of-repeating-the-2010-senate-race/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">problems with candidate quality</a> in Senate and gubernatorial races before, but this year, inexperienced and/or very right-wing candidates — often ones endorsed by Trump — are the rule and not the exception.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All that said, I still think the Supreme Court’s decision to overturn Roe — and <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/08/10/inflation-rate-drops-in-july-but-cpi-prices-remain-high.html#:~:text=Inflation%20dropped%200.6%25%20from%20its,predicted%20a%20rate%20of%208.7%25." target="_blank" rel="noopener">maybe declining inflation</a> — are the more important factors in Democrats’ recent surge. But Republicans are behaving in atypical ways for an opposition party in the midterms, and they may get an atypically poor outcome as a result.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 13:42:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662124501891474</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What’s Driving Biden’s Approval Rating Up?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-driving-bidens-approval-rating-up/</link>
						<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Monica Potts and Zoha Qamar</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/presidential-approval/" name="">Presidential Approval</a></p>
						
													<h1>What's Driving Biden's Approval Rating Up?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/monica-potts/" title="" rel="author">Monica Potts and Zoha Qamar</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/zoha-qamar/" title="" rel="author">Monica Potts and Zoha Qamar</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 2, 2022, at 6:00 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="0901_POLLA-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0901_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0901_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0901_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0901_POLLA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption><p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DAN DAO / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly polling roundup.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">After hitting a low of 37.5 percent in July, President Biden’s approval rating has ticked up over 5 percentage points in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/?ex_cid=rrpromo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s presidential approval tracker</a>. While he’s still underwater, at 42.7 percent,<a data-footnote-id="19" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-19" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>19</sup></a> it is nonetheless a substantial change. </p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">But will Biden’s upswing continue?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s not a huge mystery why some voters — especially Biden’s own — might be happier with his administration: He’s delivered on quite a few campaign promises recently. After Democratic leaders spent months trying to gain West Virginia Sen. Joe Manchin’s support for broad economic and climate-change legislation, Manchin <a href="https://www.manchin.senate.gov/newsroom/press-releases/manchin-supports-inflation-reduction-act-of-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">finally agreed to a compromise</a> at the end of July, and Biden signed the law, the Inflation Reduction Act, on Aug. 16. Among other things, the law <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/us-policy/2022/08/07/senate-inflation-reduction-act-climate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reduces prescription drug prices for seniors and invests broadly in green energy</a>, including through <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/calculate-bidens-inflation-reduction-act-save/story?id=88458834" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tax credits to consumers</a> who buy environmentally friendly goods like electric vehicles. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The Inflation Reduction Act came after an already busy summer stretch, too. At the end of June, Biden <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/biden-signs-bipartisan-gun-safety-package-law/story?id=85692952" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed a bipartisan gun-safety bill</a>, the first major legislation on the issue <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/understanding-1994-assault-weapons-ban-ended/story?id=65546858" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in about 28 years</a>. Meanwhile, on Aug. 1, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-announces-killing-al-qaeda-leader-kabul-justice/story?id=87768565" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he announced that the U.S. had killed</a> Ayman al-Zawahiri, <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2022/08/01/al-qaeda-leader-ayman-al-zawahiri-killed-drone-strike-afghanistan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">who became the al-Qaeda leader</a> after Osama bin Laden’s death in 2011, in a drone strike. That news struck the opposite tone from the big foreign-policy story last August that arguably started Biden’s downward approval trajectory: the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/07/17/media-bias-role-biden-approval-decline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">messy withdrawal of troops from Afghanistan and the critical news coverage that followed</a>. And on Aug. 10, Biden <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-signs-pact-act-expanding-streamlining-care-veterans/story?id=88192474" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed legislation</a> that makes it easier for veterans exposed to toxic burn pits in Iraq and Afghanistan to receive medical benefits from the Department of Veterans Affairs.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s too recent to be picked up in much polling, but last week Biden also <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2022/08/24/fact-sheet-president-biden-announces-student-loan-relief-for-borrowers-who-need-it-most/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced up to $20,000 of student loan forgiveness</a>, keeping a promise he made on the campaign trail in 2020. So far, a <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3854" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac University poll conducted Aug. 25-29</a> found that Americans approved of the plan, 53 percent to 43 percent. The move was long <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/08/25/student-debt-relief-biden-activists/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a priority of the left wing of Biden’s base</a>. It might also <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-biden-lost-the-support-of-young-americans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">help him with young voters</a> — whom Biden has struggled with lately — as they are more likely to have student loan debt and are worried about their future financial independence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But more than the impact of any one legislative action, it is likely the steady stream of news that has helped Biden the most. The administration is finally <a href="https://apnews.com/article/virus-outbreak-election-2020-ap-top-news-health-care-reform-or-state-wire-2b31c3acef65d01cc90dd7aafe2c5867" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ticking items off a long to-do list</a>, helping to counter the narrative that the White House <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/08/president-joe-biden-running-out-of-time-00044636" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wasn’t getting much done</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, both <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/08/24/biden-approval-rating-on-the-rise/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult</a> and <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/398117/biden-job-rating-rises-highest-year.aspx?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_term=gallupnews&amp;utm_content=1877a63b-65bb-404a-b5d0-a941271cd689&amp;utm_campaign=gallup_news" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup</a> found that Biden’s approval went up not just with Democrats but also with independents. In the Gallup poll, Biden’s approval jumped 9 points with <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/398117/biden-job-rating-rises-highest-year.aspx?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_term=gallupnews&amp;utm_content=1877a63b-65bb-404a-b5d0-a941271cd689&amp;utm_campaign=gallup_news" target="_blank" rel="noopener">independents since July</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is likely because there is more at play than legislative victories. Namely, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory/inflation-eases-consumer-prices-rise-63-july-88890525" target="_blank" rel="noopener">inflation seems to be cooling</a>, which could hint at a more basic reason for <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-biden-cant-win-on-inflation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">why Biden’s disapproval has declined</a>: Gas prices <a href="https://www.eia.gov/petroleum/gasdiesel/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have steadily tumbled</a> since hitting their peak in June. On top of that, the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/08/30/business/economy/jolts-jobs-economy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">job market remains strong</a>. Americans’ worry about the economy <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/398963/economic-confidence-improving-weak.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also seems to be easing some</a>. The Quinnipiac poll found that Americans’ <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3854" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approval of Biden’s handling of the economy</a> had changed the most of any issue surveyed, jumping to 37 percent from 28 percent in July. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s possible, too, that the overall political environment is just better than expected for Democrats. Since the Supreme Court overturned the constitutional right to abortion in June, Democrats <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have outperformed expectations in special elections</a>. They’ve also improved their standing <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the generic ballot</a>, which asks voters which party they’d support in the race for Congress, signaling that 2022 could be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/will-this-be-an-asterisk-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an unusual midterm election</a>. (Historically, the president’s party <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-presidents-party-almost-always-has-a-bad-midterm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">usually struggles in the midterms</a>.) In some ways, then, Biden’s approval rating is a lagging indicator of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/maybe-dobbs-did-change-the-race-well-need-more-time-to-know-for-sure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the change in fortune</a> Democrats were already experiencing.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In the meantime, former President Donald Trump continues to dominate the news after the FBI searched his home in Florida for classified information he kept there in violation of the Presidential Records Act, which requires presidents to turn over any written materials related to their official duties. Information continues to pour out about the <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/doj-responds-trumps-call-special-master-review-materials/story?id=89044148" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sensitive documents found there</a>. It’s unclear how much this episode will help or hurt Trump, but polls do show that most Americans are <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/08/24/biden-approval-rating-on-the-rise/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aware of this news</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/from-mueller-to-mar-a-lago-americans-remain-divided-on-trumps-legal-jeopardy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">think it’s a problem</a>. During his 2020 campaign, Biden promised <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2019/5/20/18631452/joe-biden-2020-presidential-announcement-speech" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a return to normalcy</a> after Trump’s tumultuous tenure, so it’s not unreasonable to think that the news from Mar-a-Lago might remind some voters why they chose Biden in the first place. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But, of course, the midterms are still two months away, and Biden still has <em>two</em> more years in his first term. Given the volatility of the past month in his approval rating, there’s still plenty of time for it to go down once more. Then again, maybe Biden is, at long last, on the rebound.</p>



<h2>Other polling bites</h2>



<ul><li>Republicans are more likely than Democrats to view military and law enforcement organizations favorably — except when it comes to the FBI or Capitol Police. According to an Aug. 20-23 <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/08/26/how-americans-feel-about-law-enforcement-and-milit">poll from The Economist/YouGov</a>, just one-third of Republicans (35 percent) have a very or somewhat favorable perception of the FBI, which is a huge difference from the share who have positive views on the Army (93 percent) or local police forces (87 percent). It also greatly varies from how Democrats view the FBI (72 percent have a favorable opinion). Views toward law enforcement also varied widely by age, with 91 percent of Americans age 65 or older viewing local police favorably versus only 51 percent of those ages 18 to 29.</li><li>It’s not just inflation. Americans are also experiencing “shrinkflation,” the trend in which product quantity decreases despite stagnant or rising prices, especially in grocery stores. <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2022/08/29/consumer-sensitivity-to-shrinkflation/">Morning Consult</a> recently found that about two-thirds of Americans are very (33 percent) or somewhat concerned (32 percent) about the trend, and those who’ve noticed it are pursuing a host of different options. About half of respondents who’ve noticed shrinkflation said they’ve instead purchased a different brand (49 percent), while a similar percentage (48 percent) reported opting for the generic product. Thirty-three percent have also chosen to buy affected items in bulk, rather than in smaller quantities. Meanwhile, 30 percent said shrinkflation has led them to stop purchasing from a particular brand altogether. </li><li>Parents of school-aged children are less likely than other Americans to support COVID-19 restrictions and protocols, per <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/08/30/parents-more-likely-oppose-pandemic-rules-poll">a YouGov survey</a> conducted Aug. 3-5. Asked about a hypothetical future pandemic, 38 percent said they would oppose vaccine requirements, compared with 31 percent of all adults. The survey, however, revealed glaring differences between parents of kids in school based on their 2020 ballot: Sixty-six percent of parents who voted for Biden would favor future vaccine requirements, while only 20 percent of those who voted for Trump agreed.</li><li>An overwhelming share of Americans predominantly pay for items electronically, as opposed to in cash. A July 5-26 <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/397718/americans-using-cash-less-often-foresee-cashless-society.aspx?utm_source=twitter&amp;utm_term=gallupnews&amp;utm_content=b7990fc1-aa25-43ca-ab23-67da5b83a114&amp;utm_campaign=gallup_news">poll from Gallup</a> revealed that almost three-quarters use cash for less than half (13 percent), only a few (49 percent) or none (11 percent) of their purchases, while the other quarter uses cash for half (13 percent), most (8 percent) or all (5 percent) of their purchases. Yet the breakdown is inconsistent across income brackets. A far larger share of those from households annually making less than $40,000 use cash for at least half of their purchases (41 percent), compared with those with household incomes above $100,000 (14 percent). Further, respondents felt a shift in usage from five years ago, when 53 percent said they paid in cash for at least half of their purchases. And with 64 percent of adults saying the U.S. is likely to become a cashless society in their lifetime, that trend seems to fit the bill.</li></ul><h2>Biden approval</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/biden-approval-rating-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="20" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-20" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>20</sup></a> 42.7 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 53.0 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -10.3 percentage points). At this time <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/americans-dont-want-books-banned-but-theyre-divided-over-what-schools-teach/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week</a>, 41.5 percent approved and 53.8 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -12.3 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 39.9 percent and a disapproval rating of 55.8 percent, for a net approval rating of -15.9 points.</p>



<h2>Generic ballot</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-1.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-1.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/generic-ballot-2-1.png?w=1424 2x"></figure><p data-paragraph="main">In our average of polls of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/congress-generic-ballot-polls/" target="_blank">generic congressional ballot</a>,<a data-footnote-id="21" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-21" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 5 p.m. Eastern on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>21</sup></a> Democrats currently lead by 0.9 percentage points (44.6 percent to 43.6 percent). A week ago, Democrats led Republicans by 0.4 points (44.0 percent to 43.6 percent). At this time last month, voters preferred Republicans by 0.3 points (44.4 percent to 44.1 percent).</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662115501807294</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: Why Sarah Palin Lost</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-sarah-palin-lost/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>Ballot Initiatives</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Special Elections</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-why-sarah-palin-lost/">
	<div data-podcast-id="343447" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: Why Sarah Palin Lost">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP5029783479.mp3?updated=1662067684">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS</a>
			</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Democrat and former state Rep. Mary Peltola won Alaska’s special congressional election on Wednesday, defeating Republicans Sarah Palin and Nick Begich III. In this installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast, senior elections analyst Nathaniel Rakich discusses why it is difficult to draw a broader conclusion about the political environment based on the result. Later, senior politics reporter Monica Potts joins to discuss why voters sometimes contradict their partisan beliefs when it comes to voting on ballot measures.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 22:24:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662070501616417</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What Democrats’ Win In Alaska Tells Us About November</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-democrats-win-in-alaska-tells-us-about-november/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Midterms</category>
			<category>2022 Primaries</category>
			<category>Alaska Politics</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header><div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2022-election/" name="">2022 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>What Democrats' Win In Alaska Tells Us About November</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
							
							<p>
								<time>
									Sep. 1, 2022, at 7:31 AM								</time></p>

						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header><figure><span>
									<div>
						<picture><source media="(min-width: 768px)"><source><img alt="U.S House candidate Mary Peltola" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/USA-ELECTION-ALASKA-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/USA-ELECTION-ALASKA-4x3-1.jpg?w=917" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/USA-ELECTION-ALASKA-4x3-1.jpg?w=917 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/USA-ELECTION-ALASKA-4x3-1.jpg?w=1834 2x"></source></source></picture></div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Former state Rep. Mary Peltola has defeated former Gov. Sarah Palin in the special election for Alaska’s vacant U.S. House seat.													<p>REUTERS / Kerry Tasker</p>
											</figcaption></figure></div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">For the second time in as many weeks, Democrats have won a competitive special election. And by the numbers, this win was even more impressive than <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last week’s victory in New York’s 19th District</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Wednesday, the Alaska Division of Elections announced that former state Rep. Mary Peltola had defeated former Gov. Sarah Palin in the special election for the state’s vacant U.S. House seat, becoming the <a href="https://www.adn.com/politics/2022/08/31/democrat-mary-peltola-wins-special-us-house-election-will-be-first-alaska-native-elected-to-congress/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first Alaska Native ever elected to Congress</a> and the first Democrat to win a statewide election since 2008. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Although the actual election took place on Aug. 16, we had to wait until Aug. 31 to learn the results because of Alaska’s new system of ranked choice voting. Instead of picking just one candidate, as voters do in most other states, Alaskans were invited to rank the three candidates on the ballot in the order of their preference. <a href="https://www.elections.alaska.gov/results/22SSPG/RcvDetailedReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">And after all ballots were counted</a>, 40 percent of voters had chosen Peltola as their first choice, 31 percent had chosen Palin and 29 percent had chosen Republican businessman Nick Begich III. Under the rules of ranked choice voting, Begich — as the candidate with the fewest first-choice votes — was then eliminated, and his votes were redistributed to whomever his voters ranked second.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Unsurprisingly, most of Begich’s votes (50 percent) went to his fellow Republican, Palin. But an impressive 29 percent went to Peltola, and 21 percent were “exhausted,” meaning there was no second-choice pick, and the votes were essentially thrown out. That combination was enough for Peltola to win. While Palin gained more votes from the redistribution than Peltola did, Peltola was starting from a higher total, and receiving 29 percent of Begich’s votes was enough to keep her ahead of Palin. In the end, Peltola received 51 percent of the votes counted in the final round, while Palin received 49 percent.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>How a Democrat won the Alaska special election</h5>
 <p>Each candidate’s raw vote total in the first round and final round of the Aug. 16, 2022, Alaska special U.S. House election, and how many votes they gained in between rounds</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.ak-reax.1"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">1st-choice votes</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Votes added in redistribution*</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Final-round votes</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Mary Peltola</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>75,761</td>
 <td>15,445</td>
 <td>91,206</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Sarah Palin</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>58,945</td>
 <td>27,042</td>
 <td>85,987</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nick Begich III</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>53,756</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td>—</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>*11,222 Begich votes were exhausted, meaning no one was ranked second, and 47 were overvotes, meaning multiple people were ranked second.</p>
 <p>Source: Alaska Division of Elections</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Impressively, Peltola managed to prevail despite Alaska being a fairly red state. According to FiveThirtyEight’s partisan lean metric,<a data-footnote-id="22" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-22" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>22</sup></a> Alaska is 15 percentage points redder than the nation as a whole. That means going by the results in the final round, Peltola’s 3-point victory<a data-footnote-id="23" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-23" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peltola’s precise share of the vote was 51.47 percent while Palin’s was 48.53 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>23</sup></a> was an <em>18-point</em> overperformance for Democrats. By contrast, last week, Democrat Pat Ryan won New York’s 19th District, an R+4 seat, by 2 points — just a 6-point overperformance.</p>


<div>
<section><header><h5>Since Dobbs, Democrats have done well in special elections</h5>
 <p>How the final vote-share margins in federal special elections in the 2022 cycle compare with the seats’ FiveThirtyEight partisan leans, as of 11 p.m. on Aug. 31, 2022</p>
 </header><table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.special-elex.9"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" scope="col">Date</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Seat</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Partisan Lean</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Vote Margin</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Margin Swing</th>
 </tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>March 20, 2021</td>
 <td>Louisiana 2nd*</td>
 <td>D+51</td>
 <td>D+66</td>
 <td>D+15</td>
 </tr><tr><td>March 20, 2021</td>
 <td>Louisiana 5th*</td>
 <td>R+31</td>
 <td>R+45</td>
 <td>R+13</td>
 </tr><tr><td>May 1, 2021</td>
 <td>Texas 6th*</td>
 <td>R+11</td>
 <td>R+25</td>
 <td>R+14</td>
 </tr><tr><td>June 1, 2021</td>
 <td>New Mexico 1st</td>
 <td>D+18</td>
 <td>D+25</td>
 <td>D+7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nov. 2, 2021</td>
 <td>Ohio 11th</td>
 <td>D+57</td>
 <td>D+58</td>
 <td>EVEN</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Nov. 2, 2021</td>
 <td>Ohio 15th</td>
 <td>R+19</td>
 <td>R+17</td>
 <td>D+2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Jan. 11, 2022</td>
 <td>Florida 20th</td>
 <td>D+53</td>
 <td>D+60</td>
 <td>D+7</td>
 </tr><tr><td>June 7, 2022</td>
 <td>California 22nd</td>
 <td>R+11</td>
 <td>R+24</td>
 <td>R+14</td>
 </tr><tr><td>June 14, 2022</td>
 <td>Texas 34th*</td>
 <td>D+5</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>R+10</td>
 </tr><tr><td></td>
 <td>Pre-Dobbs average</td>
 <td>D+12</td>
 <td>D+10</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 </tr><tr><td>June 28, 2022</td>
 <td>Nebraska 1st</td>
 <td>R+17</td>
 <td>R+5</td>
 <td>D+12</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Aug. 9, 2022</td>
 <td>Minnesota 1st</td>
 <td>R+15</td>
 <td>R+4</td>
 <td>D+11</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Aug. 16, 2022</td>
 <td>Alaska at-large†</td>
 <td>R+15</td>
 <td>D+3</td>
 <td>D+18</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Aug. 23, 2022</td>
 <td>New York 19th</td>
 <td>R+4</td>
 <td>D+2</td>
 <td>D+6</td>
 </tr><tr><td>Aug. 23, 2022</td>
 <td>New York 23rd</td>
 <td>R+15</td>
 <td>R+7</td>
 <td>D+9</td>
 </tr><tr><td></td>
 <td>Post-Dobbs average</td>
 <td>R+13</td>
 <td>R+2</td>
 <td>D+11</td>
 </tr></tbody></table><footer><p>Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.</p>
 <p>*Top-two primaries: Vote margin is the total vote share of all Democratic candidates combined minus the total vote share of all Republican candidates combined.</p>
 <p>†Ranked choice election: Vote margin is from the final round, after other candidates’ second-place votes had been redistributed.</p>
 <p>Source: State election offices</p>
 </footer></section></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Democrats have clearly overperformed in special elections since the Supreme Court overturned the constitutional right to abortion in Dobbs v. Jackson in June, but the reasons for Peltola’s win may have been more local than national. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Namely, Palin was a very flawed candidate. After her 2008 vice-presidential campaign <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2008/10/06/post-debate-palin-still-seen-as-unqualified-a-bump-for-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">flopped</a>, Palin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/04/us/politics/04palin.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">resigned the governorship</a> (reportedly amid <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/06/us/06palin.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ethics investigations</a>), <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/where-we-live/wp/2016/01/13/a-peek-inside-sarah-palins-arizona-home/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bought a house in Arizona</a> and went on to <a href="https://ew.com/tv/sarah-palin-masked-singer-walking-middle-finger-haters/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">appear on reality TV</a> — giving many Alaskans the sense that she had <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/04/18/1093080089/sarah-palin-is-attempting-a-comeback-in-alaska-but-her-star-has-dimmed-at-home" target="_blank" rel="noopener">abandoned them</a>. According to <a href="https://twitter.com/IvanMoore1/status/1552833494220304384" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a July poll</a> from Alaska Survey Research, 61 percent of Alaska registered voters had a negative opinion of her. It’s hard to win with those kinds of numbers.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It seems likely then, that had a different Republican advanced to the final round, Peltola would have lost. According to that same poll — which <a href="https://twitter.com/IvanMoore1/status/1552833489212346368?s=20&amp;t=Isc_PKtRNZC887AFM4LdQQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost exactly nailed</a> the final margin between Peltola and Palin — Begich would have defeated Peltola <a href="https://twitter.com/IvanMoore1/status/1552833483625545728?s=20&amp;t=Isc_PKtRNZC887AFM4LdQQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">55 percent to 45 percent</a> if he had made it to the final round instead of her. That would still have been bluer than Alaska’s R+15 partisan lean, but it mostly demonstrates how much of Republicans’ underperformance here may have been due to simple candidate quality (or lack thereof).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What’s more, that Republican underperformance disappears if you look not at the results from the final round, but rather at only first-choice votes. Sixty percent of voters selected a Republican (either Palin or Begich) as their preferred candidate, while only 40 percent selected a Democrat (Peltola), perhaps a better gauge of their actual partisan preferences. In fact, by that metric, the Alaska special election was actually an <em>over</em>performance for Republicans. Their 20-point combined margin over Peltola was 5 points better than the state’s R+15 partisan lean.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So it’s not clear what, if any, national lessons we can take away from the Alaska election. But that’s OK — because you should <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-the-special-election-in-georgia-can-and-cant-tell-us-about-the-midterms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">never generalize based on a single special election</a>. They are simply too prone to idiosyncrasies such as, for example, a uniquely flawed candidate. Instead, you have to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/special-elections-so-far-point-to-a-democratic-wave-in-2018/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">average several special elections together</a> before they become <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/some-early-clues-about-how-the-midterms-will-go/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">predictive of the midterms</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And when we do that, it’s clear that, no matter how you count Alaska, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/yes-special-elections-really-are-signaling-a-better-than-expected-midterm-for-democrats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Democrats are punching above their weight</a> in special elections since Dobbs. Other than Alaska, there have been four federal special elections since that <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/supreme-court-overturns-roe-wade-landmark-case-abortion/story?id=85160781" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 24 decision</a>, and Democrats did at least 6 points better than the partisan lean of the districts they ran in each election. If you plug in Alaska’s first-round numbers (the ones that are good for Republicans), the average Democratic overperformance in special elections since Dobbs is 7 points. If you use the final-round numbers (i.e., Peltola’s 3-point defeat of Palin), it’s 11 points.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In other words, while Peltola’s victory is a nice morale boost for Democrats, an extra vote for House Speaker Nancy Pelosi, an important milestone for Alaska Natives and, of course, undoubtedly a thrill for Peltola herself, it’s also kind of beside the point for purposes of predicting the midterms. We already knew that something — probably Dobbs — had <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/generic-ballot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shifted the national environment in Democrats’ favor</a> since midsummer. The Alaska result is, at best, consistent with that and, at worst, doesn’t contradict it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But we also know that things <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-democrats-midterm-chances-dont-hinge-on-bidens-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">typically get worse for the president’s party</a> in the midterm home stretch. There are still more than two months left until Election Day — plenty of time for the political winds to shift once again.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 12:31:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662034501405075</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Explore The Ways Republicans Or Democrats Could Win The Midterms</title>
			<link>https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-flip-senate-house/</link>
						<dc:creator>Ryan Best</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Ryan Best， Jay Boice， Aaron Bycoffe and Nate Silver</dc:creator>
			<category>2022 Election</category>
			<category>2022 Election Forecast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>UPDATED Aug. 31, 2022, at 2:44 PM</p>
<p>Explore The Ways Republicans Or Democrats Could Win The MidtermsPick the winner of each race to see how FiveThirtyEight’s forecast would change.</p>
<p><a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2022-election-forecast/">2022 election forecast</a><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/methodology/how-fivethirtyeights-house-and-senate-models-work/">How our forecast works</a></p>
<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/ryan-best/">Ryan Best</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/jay-boice/">Jay Boice</a>, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/aaron-bycoffe/">Aaron Bycoffe</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nate-silver/">Nate Silver</a></p>
<p>FiveThirtyEight’s Senate and House forecasts are based on myriad factors, with changes in one race often influencing odds in another. To see just how much individual races can change the forecast, first try picking different winners in key Senate races (or feel free to <a tabindex="0">skip ahead to key races in the House</a>!).<a tabindex="0" data-number="1" aria-label="Footnote 1. Select to expand footnote.">1</a> But beware, the choices you make in the Senate affect the House, and vice versa.</p>
<p>iIncumbent candidate Scroll to see more racesDemocrats are <em>slightly favored</em> to win the Senate</p>
<p>Based on FiveThirtyEight’s current forecast</p>
<p>Republicans win33 in 100MAJORITY56REPSEATS5452525456DEMSEATSDemocrats win67 in 100Average: 50.656565454525250505050525254545656REPSEATSDEMSEATSMorelikelyMorelikelyRepublicans are <em>favored</em> to win the House</p>
<p>Based on FiveThirtyEight’s current forecast</p>
<p>Republicans win76 in 100MAJORITY270REPSEATS255240225225240255270DEMSEATSDemocrats win24 in 100Average: 228.7270270255255240240225225225225240240255255270270REPSEATSDEMSEATSMorelikelyMorelikelyWho will control Congress?</p>
<p>Based on FiveThirtyEight’s current forecast</p>
<p><strong>Republicans</strong> win <strong>both</strong> chambers<strong aria-hidden="true">33 in 100</strong><strong>Republicans</strong> win the Senate<br>
<strong>Democrats</strong> win the House<strong aria-hidden="true">&lt;1 in 100</strong><strong>Democrats</strong> win the Senate<br>
<strong>Republicans</strong> win the House<strong aria-hidden="true">43 in 100</strong><strong>Democrats</strong> win <strong>both</strong> chambers<strong aria-hidden="true">23 in 100</strong>Odds displayed in the graphics may not match numeric odds due to rounding.</p>
<p>How this works: We start with the 40,000 simulations that our election forecast runs every time it updates. When you choose the winner of a race, we throw out any simulations where the outcome you picked didn’t happen and recalculate each party’s chances of winning each chamber using just the remaining simulations. If you choose enough unlikely outcomes, we’ll eventually wind up with so few simulations that we can’t produce accurate results. When that happens, we go back to our full set of simulations and run a series of regressions to see how your scenario might look if it turned up more often.</p>
<p>In simplified terms, the regressions start off by looking at the vote share for each candidate in every simulation and seeing how the rest of the map changed in response to big or small wins. Let’s say you picked Democratic Sen. Raphael Warnock to win Georgia. In some of our simulations, Warnock may have won Georgia very narrowly, and in others, he may have lost it very narrowly. But in simulations where he won Georgia by a big margin, Democrats may have also won big in toss-up races and pulled some Democratic-leaning races into their column, while the reverse may be true in simulations where Warnock lost Georgia by a wide margin. We figure out how every other race tended to look in that full range of scenarios, tracking not just whether other Democratic candidates usually won other races but also how much they generally won or lost each one by.</p>
<p>After all of that, we take some representative examples of scenarios that include the picks you made and use what we learned from our regression analysis to adjust all 40,000 simulations, and then recalculate win probabilities for each race and chamber of Congress. Finally, we blend those adjusted simulations with any of the original simulations that still apply and produce a final forecast.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1662030001344217</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
