<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Main stream | FreshRSS</title>
		<link>http://radon</link>
		<description>RSS feed of Main stream | FreshRSS</description>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 08:59:07 +0100</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 07:59:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="http://radon/i/?a=rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>Emergency Podcast: Trump’s Indictment, The Sequel</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/emergency-podcast-trumps-indictment-the-sequel/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<category>Trump indictment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div></div>


<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/emergency-podcast-trumps-indictment-the-sequel/">
	<div data-podcast-id="360601" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Emergency Podcast: Trump's Indictment, The Sequel">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP6651642884.mp3?updated=1686335776">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS </a>
					| <a href="https://music.amazon.com/podcasts/c1a4c9d6-aa5b-4899-b78a-dd62f240ec29/fivethirtyeight-politics">Amazon Music</a>
							| <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/3C0iP88KSoGZk5KNWmuyF1?si=39a47edc33514971">Spotify</a>
					</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Former President Donald Trump was indicted on federal charges on Thursday related to classified documents he took from the White House. In this installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast, the crew discusses the severity and possible political implications of the charges.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:32:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686339001222980</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Other Candidates Are Reacting To Trump’s Federal Indictment</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-indictment-republican-primary-candidates-reaction/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Presidential Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Asa Hutchinson</category>
			<category>Chris Christie</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Mike Pence</category>
			<category>Ron DeSantis</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<category>Tim Scott</category>
			<category>Trump indictment</category>
			<category>Vivek Ramaswamy</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Other Candidates Are Reacting To Trump’s Federal Indictment</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 9, 2023, at 11:56 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Chris Christie Attends Town Hall Event In New Hampshire" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/christie_4x3.jpeg?w=912" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/christie_4x3.jpeg?w=912" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/christie_4x3.jpeg?w=912 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/christie_4x3.jpeg?w=1824 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Former New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie, who announced his 2024 presidential campaign early this week, is one of just two Republican candidates to criticize former President Donald Trump’s behavior that led to his second indictment.													<p>Michael M. Santiago / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Former President Donald Trump <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/live-updates/trump-indictment/?id=99913217" target="_blank" rel="noopener">is reportedly facing multiple felony charges</a> as part of a federal indictment against him surrounding his handling of classified documents. This is only the second time in history a former president has been indicted (the first being <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/trump-1st-current-former-president-indicted-sources/story?id=97860580" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s charges related to allegations of hush money</a> he indirectly paid to Stormy Daniels) and the first time a former president has been federally indicted. This would be remarkable on its own, but Trump is more than just a former president — he is also an active candidate for president. These charges and the case surrounding them will undoubtedly have an impact on the campaign, and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/donald-trump-second-indictment-election-fallout/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it won’t necessarily be bad for Trump</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">An important factor in whether the indictment hurts Trump politically will be how the other candidates react. With the last indictment, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2024-republican-reaction-trump-indictment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s GOP challengers avoided directly criticizing</a> the former president — in fact, they largely defended him, hewing to the general party line that the charges were politically motivated and unjust. This time around, we’re mostly seeing more of the same, but if you squint, you can start to see some cracks in their defenses.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Florida Gov. <a href="https://twitter.com/RonDeSantis/status/1666986884604522499" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ron DeSantis tweeted</a>, “The weaponization of federal law enforcement represents a mortal threat to a free society,” claiming that there has been an “uneven application of the law.” He questioned why the Department of Justice was “so zealous” in its investigations of Trump but not of Hillary Clinton or Hunter Biden before pledging to “bring accountability” to the department if elected. This is obviously hitting many of the same notes that Trump and other Republicans have, with claims of political bias in the DOJ. But notably, it doesn’t really <em>defend</em> Trump either. DeSantis is suggesting the DOJ ought to have been more zealous in investigating Democrats for perceived wrongdoing, but he doesn’t say that it never should have charged Trump at all or that the former president did nothing wrong (which, per his <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/110511303632102309" target="_blank" rel="noopener">posts on Truth Social</a>, is essentially Trump’s position). This is not as forceful as <a href="https://twitter.com/GovRonDeSantis/status/1641575007552778243?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his reaction to Trump’s first indictment</a>, which he called “un-American” and said was the result of a Democratic district attorney “stretching the law” to attack a political opponent. It’s a far cry from a full-throated attack on Trump, but it’s noteworthy to see any movement from DeSantis on this, considering his efforts to align himself with the Trumpist wing of the party. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">South Carolina Sen. Tim Scott took a similar tack, saying <a href="https://twitter.com/votetimscott/status/1666990757901631489" target="_blank" rel="noopener">on Fox News</a> that the charges are an example of “a justice system where the scales are weighted” and pledged on Twitter to “purge all the injustices in our system.” But he too fell short of explicitly defending Trump or wading too deeply into the specifics of the case. So did former South Carolina Gov. Nikki Haley, who said in a campaign statement, “The American people are exhausted by the prosecutorial overreach, double standards, and vendetta politics. It’s time to move beyond the endless drama and distractions.” And, if nothing else, their responses were more measured than businessman Vivek Ramaswamy’s, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/06/08/vivek-ramaswamy-promises-pardon-trump-indictment-00101173" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pledged to pardon Trump</a> if elected.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Other candidates were willing to edge even further away from the party line. Former Vice President Mike Pence, who <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/mike-pence-2024-campaign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">launched his campaign earlier this week</a>, said before the charges were announced that <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/pence-calls-potential-2nd-trump-indictment-extremely-divisive/story?id=99946136" target="_blank" rel="noopener">such an indictment would be “extremely divisive” for the nation</a>. But he added: “No one’s above the law. And if the Department of Justice chooses to move forward with an indictment, I would hope that it would meet the very high threshold for the unprecedented action of a federal indictment against the former president.” Again, this is far from an explicit condemnation of Trump’s actions, but it falls short of completely embracing the idea that the indictment is purely politically motivated and that Trump did nothing wrong. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And this time around, there are candidates in the race who have <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/chris-christie-anti-trump-gop-voice-begins-2024/story?id=99848009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">historically been more comfortable</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/02/asa-hutchinson-presidential-bid-trump-withdraw-00090058" target="_blank" rel="noopener">criticizing the party leader</a>: former New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie and former Arkansas Gov. Asa Hutchinson, both of whom were more accepting of the charges. Before the indictment was announced, Christie <a href="https://twitter.com/firinglineshow/status/1666953387508920320?s=46" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said on PBS</a>, “If [Trump] committed a crime and there is evidence beyond a reasonable doubt to prove that crime, then he must be charged,” and later <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/chris-christie-assesses-trump-potential-second-indictment-self-inflicted-wounds" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told Fox News</a> that Trump’s legal woes are “self-inflicted wounds.” Hutchinson <a href="https://twitter.com/AsaHutchinson/status/1666976882661949440" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released a statement</a> saying, “Donald Trump’s actions—from his willful disregard for the Constitution to his disrespect for the rule of law—should not define our nation or the Republican Party,” and reiterated his call — <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2023/03/11/trump-quit-2024-race-indicted-hutchinson/11452360002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first made in March</a> — for Trump to drop out of the race.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be clear, none of this is a significant departure from the reactions we saw from other GOP contenders the last time Trump was indicted. And the overall response from Republicans, including those running against Trump, has been to support the former president and condemn the indictment rather than his actions. Most of these candidates have a tough needle to thread, wishing to both endear themselves to the party base while also convincing them that Trump is no longer right for the job. And President Biden, for his part, is likely to stay mum on the charges, as he did the last time around. This is particularly crucial for Biden due to the fact that it’s his own Justice Department that indicted Trump, and he <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/06/08/biden-doj-trump-investigation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">emphasized in a press conference yesterday</a> that he has “never once, not one single time, suggested to the Justice Department what they should do or not do relative to bringing a charge or not bringing a charge.” All this means that this indictment <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-indictment-might-be-making-him-more-popular-among-republicans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could result in a bit of a boost for Trump</a>, yet again. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the slight departures from the official party stance, and a cooler response from fellow GOP contenders compared to last time, shows the loyalty may be starting to wane. As Trump faces yet more potential charges in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-know-about-trumps-legal-troubles/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other open investigations</a>, there may come a day when defending the former president becomes more politically risky than calling him out.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 16:56:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686330001150576</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Trump’s First Indictment Didn’t Hurt Him Politically. The Second Could Be Different.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/donald-trump-second-indictment-election-fallout/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<category>Trump indictment</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Trump's First Indictment Didn't Hurt Him Politically. The Second Could Be Different.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a> and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich and Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 9, 2023, at 11:56 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Celebrity Sightings In New York City – May 31, 2023" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/trump_4x3.jpeg?w=912" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/trump_4x3.jpeg?w=912" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/trump_4x3.jpeg?w=912 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/trump_4x3.jpeg?w=1824 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Former President Donald Trump saw his favorability numbers rebound fairly quickly after his first indictment in New York state.													<p>James Devaney / GC Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">For the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-indictment-2024-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">second time in less than three months</a>, former President Donald Trump <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/live-updates/trump-indictment/?id=99913217" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been indicted</a>. This time, it’s a federal probe in connection with his handling of classified documents. (His first indictment was by the Manhattan district attorney’s office on <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/07/nyregion/trump-indictment-bragg-strategy.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">34 counts of falsifying business records</a> with the goal of disrupting the 2016 election.) Trump is scheduled to appear in federal district court in Miami on Tuesday. Sources have told ABC News that Trump will face <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/live-updates/trump-indictment/trump-facing-at-least-7-charges-sources-99951222?id=99913217" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at least seven charges</a>, including corruptly concealing a document or record and conspiracy to obstruct justice.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The legal threat of more criminal charges is obvious — but will they hurt Trump’s chances of winning back the presidency in 2024? The public’s reaction to Trump’s first indictment can give us a clue. First of all, this second indictment is unlikely to significantly dent his popularity among Republicans. After all, Trump’s standing in the GOP primary has only gotten stronger since the New York state indictment came down. On the day before that indictment, Trump led Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis by 19 percentage points in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s national polling average</a> of the primary. Since then, though, his lead has steadily increased — all the way to 33 points on Friday.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1826" height="1080" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-09-at-11.40.45-AM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-09-at-11.40.45-AM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-09-at-11.40.45-AM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-09-at-11.40.45-AM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">(It’s worth noting that some of that may also be due to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/13/us/politics/desantis-trump-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">negative news stories</a> for DeSantis. But according to <a href="https://civiqs.com/results/trump_favorable?annotations=true&amp;uncertainty=true&amp;zoomIn=true&amp;party=Republican" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Civiqs’s tracking polling</a> of how many Republicans view Trump favorably, he had virtually the same favorable and unfavorable ratings on Thursday — 77 percent to 12 percent — as he did right before the New York indictment.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump’s bigger problem is probably with the general electorate. We’ve previously found that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-much-scandals-hurt-candidates-running-for-re-election/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">scandal-plagued incumbents</a> in general elections between 1998 and 2016<a data-footnote-id="1" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-1" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excluding same-party runoffs, like in Louisiana or California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>1</sup></a> performed an average of 9 points worse than they’d otherwise be expected to. Of course, voters are more dug into their partisan camps today than they were in the early 2000s, and Trump was already facing <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trump-recorded-having-extremely-lewd-conversation-about-women-in-2005/2016/10/07/3b9ce776-8cb4-11e6-bf8a-3d26847eeed4_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">plenty of scandals</a> when he won the presidency in 2016. But a <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/20230522_US_WPAi.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">May poll from WPA Intelligence</a> found that an indictment in the classified-documents probe would shave a few points off Trump’s margin in a hypothetical general election against President Biden. WPA Intelligence’s initial query found Biden leading Trump nationally 47 percent to 40 percent. But when asked to suppose that Trump was indicted for mishandling classified documents, allegedly refusing to turn them over and misleading investigators as to their location, respondents said they would support Biden 50 percent to 39 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That said, Trump’s first indictment didn’t seem to permanently damage him politically among the general electorate either. After the New York indictment, the share of Americans with a favorable opinion of him fell from 41 percent on March 29 to 37 percent on April 7, according to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/favorability/donald-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s average</a>. But the share with an unfavorable opinion of him was relatively stable, increasing from 53 percent to 55 percent. And by April 19, both numbers were back to their pre-indictment levels. In other words, it appears that some Trump supporters withheld their support for him for a couple weeks after the indictment, but they didn’t necessarily turn<em> against</em> him either, and they quickly returned to the fold. (This could also have been a product of <a href="https://talkingpointsmemo.com/edblog/why-are-president-trumps-poll-numbers-going-up" target="_blank" rel="noopener">differential nonresponse</a>, the phenomenon where people aren’t as excited about answering polls when things aren’t going well for their preferred party or politician.) This continued a long-standing trend of public opinion on Trump being <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trumps-approval-rating-is-incredibly-steady-is-that-weird-or-the-new-normal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">extremely stable</a>. And there’s also the possibility that the charges won’t be taken as seriously by some voters because they’re being pursued by lawyers within Biden’s administration, a fact that conservative media is already <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/trump-says-federal-indictment-is-election-interference-at-the-highest-level-slams-corrupt-biden-admin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">going out of its way to note</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But polling suggests that the charges in this case could be viewed as more serious than those brought in New York, which relate to a hush-money payment that happened almost seven years ago. According to a <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/649985245/20230530-yahoo-tabs#" target="_blank" rel="noopener">late May poll from YouGov/Yahoo News</a>, Americans said 52 percent to 32 percent that falsifying business records to conceal hush-money payments to a porn star was a serious crime. But they said 63 percent to 20 percent that taking highly classified documents from the White House and obstructing efforts to retrieve them was. That poll question didn’t mention Trump specifically, but a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/r0o0a2nef6/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">different YouGov poll</a>, conducted for The Economist in early June, found that Americans believed 49 percent to 35 percent that Trump should face criminal charges for his handling of classified documents.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And of course, even if the indictment doesn’t hurt Trump politically, that doesn’t mean that an eventual <em>conviction</em> wouldn’t. The YouGov/Yahoo News poll also found that 62 percent of Americans said Trump should not be allowed to serve as president again if he is convicted of a serious crime. That’s the same poll in which 63 percent said taking classified documents was a serious crime. So Trump is not out of the woods; in fact, the biggest test may still be ahead of him.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 16:56:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686330001150575</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The Supreme Court’s New Ruling Could Help Democrats Flip The House In 2024</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/supreme-court-voting-rights-redistricting-implications/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>Alabama</category>
			<category>John Roberts</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<category>Voting Rights</category>
			<category>Voting Rights Act</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/redistricting/" name="">Redistricting</a></p>
						
													<h1>The Supreme Court's New Ruling Could Help Democrats Flip The House In 2024</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 8, 2023, at 3:20 PM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Sen. Rodger Smitherman compares U.S. Representative district maps" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/AP22025127146691-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/AP22025127146691-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/AP22025127146691-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/AP22025127146691-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						After drawing maps during a special session of the state legislature, in which state Sen. Rodger Smitherman compares congressional district maps, Alabama will have to redraw its maps after a Thursday Supreme Court decision.													<p>Mickey Welsh / The Montgomery Advertiser via AP</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The Supreme Court just handed Democrats a massive victory in their quest to retake the House of Representatives in 2024. In a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/roberts-kavanaugh-voting-rights-act-alabama/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">5-4 decision that was as surprising as it was consequential</a>, the high court agreed with a lower court’s ruling that the Voting Rights Act requires Alabama to draw a second predominantly Black congressional district. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Not only does that mean Democrats will very likely gain a seat in Alabama next year, but the decision will probably also <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-a-court-ruling-in-alabama-could-boost-black-political-power-throughout-the-south/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">force other states to redraw their congressional maps</a> as well. And with Democrats needing to flip only five House seats in 2024 to win the majority,<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assuming Democrats win the upcoming special election in Rhode Island’s 1st District, as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>2</sup></a> this decision could be the difference between Republican and Democratic control of the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Currently, <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alabama</a> has six majority-white congressional districts and one majority-Black congressional district. Because white voters in the South are heavily Republican and Black voters are heavily Democratic, in practice this means the state is virtually guaranteed to elect six Republicans and one Democrat.</p>


<div></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/alabama/plaintiffs_plan_a/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as the plaintiffs in this case demonstrated</a>, it’s possible to draw a congressional map of Alabama where Black people are the largest racial group in <em>two</em> districts. In practice, this would mean the state would have two Democratic-leaning districts and five Republican-leaning districts, as in the hypothetical example below.</p>


<div></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Historically, courts have used <a href="https://www.justice.gov/crt/section-2-voting-rights-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Section 2 of the Voting Rights Act</a> — which states that members of racial minorities must have an equal opportunity to elect representatives of their choice — to <a href="http://www.publicmapping.org/what-is-redistricting/redistricting-criteria-the-voting-rights-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">force states to draw districts</a> where nonwhite voters are the dominant voting bloc whenever it is <a href="https://www.justice.gov/crt/case-document/file/1429826/download" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reasonably possible</a>.<a data-footnote-id="3" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-3" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The districts don’t technically have to have a population that is &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; nonwhite — just a large enough population to ensure that their preferred candidate is elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>3</sup></a> In these cases, judges intervene to prevent what’s known as “vote dilution,” where a minority group’s voting power is decreased by packing them all into one district (as happened in Alabama) or spreading them out over several. But even though it was theoretically possible to create a second predominantly Black district, Alabama’s Republican legislature declined to do so when it redrew the state’s congressional map after the 2020 census — so voting-rights activists sued. And rather than reinterpret the Voting Rights Act to weaken those protections and allow Alabama’s map to stand, the Supreme Court upheld them.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This will force Alabama to redraw its congressional map for the 2024 election, and the result will probably look something like the example above, in which Alabama’s 2nd Congressional District goes from having a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-red-or-blue-is-your-state-your-congressional-district/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight partisan lean</a><a data-footnote-id="4" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-4" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Partisan lean is the average margin difference between how a state or district votes and how the country votes overall. This version of partisan lean, meant to be used for congressional and gubernatorial elections, is calculated as 50 percent the state or district’s lean relative to the nation in the most recent presidential election, 25 percent its relative lean in the second-most-recent presidential election and 25 percent a custom state-legislative lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>4</sup></a> of R+34 to having a partisan lean of D+11. That would very likely result in Democrats picking up the seat. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the biggest impact of this decision is the ripple effect it could have in other states. Alabama is not the only state where it is possible to draw an additional minority-opportunity district. For example, a few of the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/louisiana/sb4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">maps proposed</a> during Louisiana’s redistricting process last year included two majority-Black (and thus solidly Democratic) districts and four majority-white (and thus solidly Republican) districts, like this one:</p>


<div></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But the <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/louisiana/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">map that was ultimately enacted</a> had just one majority-Black district versus five majority-white districts:</p>


<div></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Voting-rights advocates sued over that map, and the <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/robinson-v-ardoin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">case is pending</a>. But in light of how the court ruled in Alabama — a very similar case — this case is expected to be resolved in Democrats’ favor too. And there are other racial-gerrymandering lawsuits under consideration in <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/simpson-v-hutchinson/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arkansas</a>, <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/common-cause-florida-v-lee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida</a>, <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/georgia-naacp-v-raffensperger/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Georgia</a>, <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/alexander-v-sc-naacp/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">South Carolina</a> and <a href="https://redistricting.lls.edu/case/lulac-v-abbott/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Texas</a> as well.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Not all of these lawsuits may be successful, and not all of them may result in a guaranteed gain for Democrats. (For example, it’s hard to draw anything more than a slightly Democratic-leaning seat in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/redistricting-2022-maps/arkansas/hb1962/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Arkansas</a>.) And some may not be resolved in time to impact the 2024 elections. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Democrats just banked at least one House pick-up for 2024 in Alabama, with a second very likely to come in Louisiana (although we don’t know when that ruling will come down or be enacted). And it’s very possible that courts will force the creation of new, predominantly nonwhite, Democratic-leaning seats in other states as well. If that happens three more times, that will mean Thursday’s decision alone could be enough to swing the House to Democrats in 2024. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, the 2024 election will hang on many factors other than this. (Chances are that more than five seats will change hands next year, for reasons unrelated to redistricting!) And thanks to a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/28/north-carolina-supreme-court-clears-way-for-partisan-gerrymandering-00094433" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>state</em> court decision</a>, at least one state’s congressional map (North Carolina’s) is expected to be redrawn in a way that could add <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/analysis/house/north-carolina-house/north-carolina-remap-could-cost-democrats-four-seats-2024" target="_blank" rel="noopener">up to four new <em>Republican</em> seats</a>. But now, after Thursday’s ruling, Democrats are newly empowered to fight back against that.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 20:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953866</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Two Supreme Court Conservatives Just Saved The Voting Rights Act</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/roberts-kavanaugh-voting-rights-act-alabama/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>John Roberts</category>
			<category>Redistricting</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<category>The Supreme Court</category>
			<category>Voting Rights</category>
			<category>Voting Rights Act</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/supreme-court/" name="">Supreme Court</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Two Supreme Court Conservatives Just Saved The Voting Rights Act</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 8, 2023, at 2:15 PM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="0320_RobertsSpeech 4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/0320_robertsspeech-4x3.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/0320_robertsspeech-4x3.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/0320_robertsspeech-4x3.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/0320_robertsspeech-4x3.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Chief Justice John Roberts has voted to roll back the Voting Rights Act on multiple occasions  — but on Thursday, he joined the Supreme Court’s liberal justices in upholding a key section.													<p>LARRY DOWNING / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">This term, the most conservative Supreme Court in modern history <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/supreme-court-kill-voting-rights-act/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had the opportunity</a> to gut the last major section of the Voting Rights Act. They didn’t take it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">On Thursday, Chief Justice John Roberts and Justice Brett Kavanaugh <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/22pdf/21-1086_1co6.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">joined the court’s three liberal justices</a>, ruling that Alabama’s congressional map likely violates Section 2 of the Voting Rights Act, which prohibits racially discriminatory voting practices or procedures. Last year, a panel of three federal judges <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/24/us/politics/alabama-congressional-map-redistricting.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">threw out Alabama’s map</a>, which was drawn by the Republican-controlled state legislature in 2021 with only one majority-Black district out of seven, because it was possible to draw a second majority-Black seat in a state with a population that is more than one-quarter Black. Now, Alabama will have to redraw its map to include a second predominantly Black district. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Voting rights advocates were concerned that the Roberts court — which has a track record of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-court-just-made-it-harder-to-fight-voting-restrictions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narrowing the Voting Rights Act</a> in most of the cases where the law has come up — would use the case as an opportunity to gut Section 2. Instead, 10 years after Roberts <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/2012/12-96" target="_blank" rel="noopener">authored an opinion that eviscerated the Voting Rights Act’s other major section</a>, the chief justice wrote that while Section 2 “may impermissibly elevate race in the allocation of political power within the States,” those concerns weren’t present in this case.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So, what happened? Here are two theories for why Roberts and Kavanaugh delivered such a surprise — and what they mean for how we should think about the conservative majority going forward.</p>



<h2><strong>Some conservative justices are worried about going too far</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is the realpolitik view of the Supreme Court’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-supreme-courts-partisan-divide-hasnt-been-this-sharp-in-generations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new center</a>, which includes <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/roberts-is-the-new-swing-justice-that-doesnt-mean-hes-becoming-more-liberal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two extremely conservative justices</a> — Roberts and Kavanaugh — who <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2019/04/07/supreme-court-bromance-john-roberts-brett-kavanaugh-tie-up-court/3342377002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">often vote together</a> and have <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2018/11/brett-kavanaugh-census-ruling-john-roberts-supreme-court.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signaled</a> over the past few years that they care about the court’s <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/us-law-week/kavanaugh-emerges-as-unlikely-liberal-hope-for-court-swing-vote" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ideological reputation</a>. Under this theory, public perceptions of the court matter to at least some of the justices and factor into how quickly they’re willing to reshape the law on controversial issues.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be clear, this is not an understanding of the Supreme Court that any of the justices would endorse. The high court is supposed to operate apart from politics, which means delivering unpopular opinions even in the face of public opposition. But over the years, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/who-can-stop-the-supreme-court/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political science research has indicated</a> that the court does shift with the public mood, and the justices have stepped back from the brink at moments when it seemed like they were about to buck mainstream public opinion in a major way.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And this year, the conservative justices are facing major headwinds. The court has been moving steadily to the right for decades, but <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/msen/scotus-opinion" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a paper published last year</a> by social scientists Stephen Jessee, Neil Malhotra and Maya Sen indicates that it took a sharp conservative turn after the appointment of Justice Amy Coney Barrett in 2020, and Democrats — who usually tend to underestimate the court’s rightward tilt — actually noticed. Then, of course, a five-justice majority overruled Roe v. Wade last summer, a highly unpopular move that <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-rights-are-reshaping-american-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reshaped the contours of the midterm elections</a> and created a historically wide partisan split in perceptions of the court. Last September, a solid majority (58 percent) of Americans disapproved of the court in Gallup’s tracking polling — which is a potentially scary shift for someone like Roberts, given that <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/4732/supreme-court.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">majorities or near-majorities of Americans</a> have approved of the court’s performance for the entirety of his tenure as chief justice.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Roberts <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/07/26/politics/supreme-court-john-roberts-abortion-dobbs/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reportedly lobbied</a> his fellow conservatives to preserve the constitutional right to abortion, and he criticized the decision to chuck it, <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">saying that he would have preferred</a> a “more measured course.” Thursday’s ruling is perhaps an even more dramatic about-face for <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2015/08/john-roberts-voting-rights-act-121222/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a justice who spent the early part of his career</a> trying to weaken the VRA. It’s possible that Republicans’ arguments in the case simply failed to convince even Roberts. But the Dobbs ruling arguably also made it riskier for the conservatives to issue more rulings that narrow or get rid of existing rights: <a href="https://perryundem.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PerryUndem-Guide-to-Impact-of-Dobbs-on-Voters-.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Polling conducted last summer</a> by PerryUndem, a nonpartisan research firm, found that many American voters saw a connection between the overturning of the constitutional right to abortion and their own personal rights and freedoms. </p>



<h2><strong>Republicans are overplaying their hand with the court’s conservative majority</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s also possible that Republicans in this instance simply asked for too much. The Supreme Court’s current majority is historically conservative, but that doesn’t mean the justices are willing to go along with Republicans’ reasoning in every single case. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Yes, the Roberts court has gained a reputation for being highly conservative on voting rights — and that reputation is deserved. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/supreme-court-kill-voting-rights-act/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">As I wrote last fall</a> when this case was being argued, only one of the seven VRA-related cases the court heard in the Roberts era has had a liberal outcome. But as New York University law professor and voting rights expert Richard Pildes told me when I called him for that story, the Republicans who were seeking to preserve Alabama’s map were asking for a radical departure from the way Section 2 has traditionally been interpreted. Up until now, courts have basically concluded that the VRA requires states to prioritize race among other considerations when they draw district lines. In this case, Alabama Republicans were arguing that prioritizing race over other traditional considerations — like avoiding crossing town or county borders — is actually <em>discriminatory</em>. Part of their argument was that as it’s currently enforced, the nation’s seminal law designed to protect and enforce voting rights for racial minorities violates the Constitution’s guarantee of equal protection under the law.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By existing standards, Alabama’s map is a clear Section 2 violation, according to another voting rights expert, University of Southern California law professor Franita Tolson. The lower court judges — including two appeals court judges appointed by former President Donald Trump — certainly thought this was the case. And during the oral argument, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/10/04/high-court-race-neutral-voting-rights-act-00060270" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the conservative justices didn’t seem especially receptive</a> to a “race-neutral” reading of the Voting Rights Act.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So while Republicans have been aggressively pushing the envelope as the court’s balance shifted right, this case may have gone too far. That doesn’t mean the court isn’t conservative — or even that its major decisions aren’t more aligned with the median Republican than the median American, which that recent study indicated — but it is a signal that the court won’t rubber-stamp literally anything Republicans ask for.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The presence of Justice Ketanji Brown Jackson, who was <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/oral_arguments/argument_transcripts/2022/21-1086_f204.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vocally skeptical of the idea</a> that the VRA violates the 14th Amendment during the oral argument, may also have been a factor. There’s some <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/23496550" target="_blank" rel="noopener">limited evidence</a> that greater racial diversity on appeals court panels results in more liberal rulings on issues related to race. The perspective of Jackson, an appointee of President Biden who became the first Black woman to serve on the Supreme Court when she was sworn in last summer, may have helped convince Roberts and Kavanaugh. </p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main">Today’s ruling was surprising, but it underscores something we’ve known for a while: The Supreme Court is historically conservative, but it’s still sometimes unpredictable, and the <em>most</em> conservative voices on the court <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/the-supreme-court-isnt-as-conservative-as-clarence-thomas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t always get their way</a>. Other moves by the court this term have underscored that — for example, the court in April <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/04/21/politics/supreme-court-abortion-pill-mifepristone/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paused a lower-court judge’s ruling</a> that would have taken a commonly used abortion drug off the market while a lawsuit over the legality of the drug’s approval process played out in the courts. Only the court’s two most conservative justices, Samuel Alito and Clarence Thomas, dissented from that order.<br>But the term is far from over. There are many high-profile cases left to be decided, including two cases that could <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/supreme-court-affirmative-action/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">determine the fate of affirmative action in higher education</a>, and it’s always a mistake to draw conclusions about the direction of the court based on one ruling. Today’s ruling shows that the Supreme Court’s conservatives won’t <em>always</em> side with Republicans, even on issues — like voting rights — where they’ve consistently leaned right. An occasional unexpected outcome, however, is not a trend. We’ll need to see how the rest of this term’s cases play out before we can start to say anything definitive about what this ruling means for the trajectory of the court going forward.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 19:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953865</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Beating Biden Isn’t A Priority For Republican Voters In The 2024 Primary (Yet)</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republican-primary-electability/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2020 Democratic Primary</category>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Electability</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Beating Biden Isn't A Priority For Republican Voters In The 2024 Primary (Yet)</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 8, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Former U.S. President Donald Trump looks on during a rally at the Waco Regional Airport on March 25, 2023" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1476355137-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1476355137-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1476355137-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1476355137-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Former President Donald Trump is, according to early surveys of the Republican primary electorate, viewed as the most electable candidate for 2024, which makes it harder to tease out how much Republican voters value electability versus ideological purity.													<p>Brandon Bell / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Four years ago, the Democratic presidential primary was dominated by a concept nobody could clearly define but everyone could tell you was important: “<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/electability/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">electability</a>.” <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/bulletpoint-is-electability-a-self-fulfilling-prophecy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Despite the challenges</a> of measuring <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-improve-the-conversation-about-electability/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this amorphous trait</a>, perceptions about who would have the best chance of winning the general election <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/democrats-think-biden-is-electable-but-hes-not-everyones-first-choice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tended to boost</a> older white male candidates <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-problem-with-electability/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at the expense</a> of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-we-actually-know-about-electability/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">women and people of color</a>. But regardless of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/youll-never-know-which-candidate-is-electable/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whether you could quantify</a> “electability,” Democrats clearly cared a great deal about it: Poll after poll found that more Democrats cared about nominating a candidate who could defeat then-President Donald Trump than one whom they agreed with on most issues.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Today, Republicans find themselves in an analogous position to Democrats’ four years ago: facing an open nomination battle to take on an incumbent president they strongly dislike. But they aren’t necessarily repeating Democrats’ 2020 example. Limited polling suggests that GOP voters may care more about ideological purity than electability when considering the Republican field of presidential contenders. This could be frustrating news for some GOP leaders and donors who want the party to move on from Trump. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Still, the early polling on how much Republicans are prioritizing electability isn’t entirely straightforward, thanks in part to differences in how pollsters word such questions. And even if Republicans do put a greater value on choosing a candidate with whom they agree on most issues rather than one who has a better shot of defeating President Biden, those preferences are not set in stone. The rise and fall of candidates and the twists and turns of the primary season could affect voter priorities. Moreover, although most polls ask voters to choose between two answers, Republicans may believe they can have both ideological purity and electability, since many believe that Trump <em>is</em> the party’s most electable candidate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/23706881/cnn-poll-most-republicans-care-more-about-picking-a-2024-gop-nominee-who-agrees-with-them-on-issues-than-one-who-can-beat-biden.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">March poll from SSRS/CNN</a> provided a strong early signal that Republicans are thinking more about candidates’ views than who is best positioned to defeat Biden. Among Republican registered voters,<a data-footnote-id="5" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-5" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Including independents who leaned toward the GOP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>5</sup></a> 58 percent viewed it as more important for their party to pick a nominee “who shares your positions on major issues” while 42 percent prioritized choosing a nominee “with a strong chance of beating” Biden. SSRS/CNN asked Democratic voters<a data-footnote-id="6" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-6" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Including independents who leaned toward the Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>6</sup></a> the same question nine times during the 2020 election cycle, and in every survey more Democrats prioritized picking a nominee who could defeat Trump than one whom they agreed with on major issues.</p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Republicans seem less worried about ‘electability’ … so far</h2>
 <p>Share of registered voters who said it was more important their party nominated a candidate who was electable versus a candidate who shared the respondent’s policy positions</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.electability.1">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Cycle</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Poll Month</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Electability</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Shared Positions</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Diff.</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>2024</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>March 2023</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">42%</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">58%</td>
 <td>+16</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>March 2020</td>
 <td>65</td>
 <td>29</td>
 <td>+36</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Jan. 2020</td>
 <td>57</td>
 <td>35</td>
 <td>+22</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Dec. 2019</td>
 <td>47</td>
 <td>39</td>
 <td>+8</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Nov. 2019</td>
 <td>56</td>
 <td>39</td>
 <td>+17</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Oct. 2019</td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>39</td>
 <td>+15</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Sept. 2019</td>
 <td>55</td>
 <td>39</td>
 <td>+16</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>Aug. 2019</td>
 <td>54</td>
 <td>39</td>
 <td>+15</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>June 2019</td>
 <td>61</td>
 <td>30</td>
 <td>+31</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>March 2019</td>
 <td>58</td>
 <td>33</td>
 <td>+25</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>Respondents included independents who leaned toward the party in question. Respondents were asked whether it was more important their party nominate a presidential candidate “with a strong chance of beating” the other party’s incumbent president (“electability”) or someone “who shares your positions on major issues” (“shared positions”).</p>
 <p>Source: SSRS/CNN</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">This isn’t the only poll that has shown a Republican preference for ideological purity over electability, either. In a <a href="https://static.foxnews.com/foxnews.com/content/uploads/2023/03/March-24-27-2023_Cross-Tabs_March-29-Release.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">late March poll by Beacon Research/Shaw &amp; Company Research</a> on behalf of Fox News, 72 percent of Republican registered voters said a candidate’s views on the issues were more important than their chances of winning the general election, while just 17 percent said the opposite. Similarly, two surveys by YouGov/The Economist <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/6jir2a8rbh/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in April</a> and <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/1el6dff3an/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">May</a> each found 63 percent of Republican adults prioritized backing a candidate they agreed with on the issues, while fewer than 30 percent prioritized the candidate’s general-election chances.<a data-footnote-id="7" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-7" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all three of these polls, Democrats also said they cared more about a candidate’s position on the issues than electability, although their situation as a party has changed sharply since 2019-20 now that a Democrat is in the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>7</sup></a> And an April poll from the <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/23776922/spia-2024-r-pres-primary-poll-results81-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Georgia’s School of Public and International Affairs</a> found likely GOP primary voters in Georgia felt it was more important to nominate a candidate who shared their views on key issues than choosing one with a strong chance of defeating Biden, 46 percent to 34 percent, although a meaningful chunk (18 percent) volunteered to the pollster that they valued them equally.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, at least one survey has found Republicans cared more about electability than ideological purity. An <a href="https://s.wsj.net/public/resources/documents/WSJ_Poll_April_2023_redacted.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">April poll by Fabrizio, Lee &amp; Associates/Impact Research</a> for The Wall Street Journal found 51 percent of likely GOP primary voters preferred a more electable candidate, while 44 percent preferred someone who shared the voters’ values and views on most issues. This result may not align with other recent survey data because of how the pollsters worded the question, as it included the caveat that the more ideologically aligned candidate “would have a tougher time winning in the general election.” In a way, this wording gave respondents a truer trade-off — issues and values versus electability — compared with the wording used by other pollsters that we’ve looked at. But in this case, slightly more Republicans preferred electability.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There’s no “right” way to ask this sort of question, but how it’s framed can cue voters with information that could encourage them to adopt one position or another. Take Gallup’s polling of Republicans from the 2012 cycle, the last time a Democratic president (Barack Obama) sought reelection. A <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/189035/2016-issues-trump-electability-choosing-nominee.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">December 2011 survey</a> by Gallup/USA Today found 62 percent of Republicans and independents who leaned Republican preferred a candidate who agreed with them on the issues but didn’t have the best chance of winning the general election. However, when <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/149552/perry-looks-better-against-romney-against-obama.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gallup/USA Today asked a form of this question</a> in which the electability option specifically mentioned “beating Obama” at various other times in 2011, the share of Republicans who preferred a candidate with the best chance of winning slightly exceeded the share who valued issue agreement more.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The changing contours of the campaign could also shift voters’ thoughts on electability. We saw it in 2020: While Democrats routinely prioritized electability in SSRS/CNN’s polling, the extent of that preference varied over time. For instance, it’s probably not a coincidence that Democrats’ preference for an electable candidate peaked in a <a href="https://cdn.cnn.com/cnn/2020/images/03/09/rel2a.-.2020.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey taken in March 2020</a>, right after Biden’s victories on Super Tuesday made him the party’s likely nominee. After all, a big part of Biden’s appeal was the notion that he was best positioned to defeat Trump. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Fact is, a candidate’s rise could influence what voters say they want, turning the causation arrow around. Consider a different poll question the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2015/10/02/contrasting-partisan-perspectives-on-campaign-2016/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pew Research Center asked during the 2016 cycle</a>. In March 2015, 57 percent of Republican and Republican-leaning registered voters said they felt it was more important for a candidate to have experience and a proven record than new ideas and a different approach, while 36 percent said the reverse. Six months later, those numbers had more than flipped, to 65 percent preferring new ideas and a different approach versus just 29 percent who wanted experience and a proven record. What happened? Trump — a political outsider if there ever was one — <a href="https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2019/06/14/donald-trump-campaign-announcement-tower-escalator-oral-history-227148/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">came down an escalator</a> that June and surged in GOP primary polls. This time around, perhaps Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis will have a sterling debate performance later this year and rise in the polls, leading GOP voters to start telling pollsters that they prioritize electability — one of DeSantis’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ron-desantis-2024-republican-presidential-announcement/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">selling points as a candidate</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, this brings up another complicating factor in interpreting questions about electability: What if Republicans don’t feel they <em>have</em> to choose? The March SSRS/CNN poll found more than 60 percent of Republicans still thought that Biden didn’t win fairly in 2020. If a majority of the GOP doesn’t believe Trump lost fair and square, does the primary electorate actually view him as “unelectable”? Not to mention, Republican voters ignored <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/02/us/politics/wary-of-donald-trump-gop-leaders-are-caught-in-a-standoff.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">party leaders’ concerns about Trump’s electability in 2016</a> to nominate Trump, and he went on to win the presidency anyway.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In that vein, some recent polling suggests Republicans may view Trump<em>, not DeSantis,</em> as the most electable candidate. <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_053023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monmouth University’s latest poll</a> found that 45 percent of Republican and Republican-leaning voters said Trump was “definitely” the strongest candidate to beat Biden, while another 18 percent said he was “probably” the strongest choice. Only 32 percent thought a different candidate would definitely or probably be the best bet against Biden. The pollster also noted that there’s something of a chicken-and-egg problem regarding electability because its past polling had found that, if voters supported a candidate because of issues or values, they also often thought that candidate was the most electable choice.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">As we get more polling data on this subject, it may become easier to suss out what Republicans think about electability in the 2024 cycle. So far, it appears they may value ideological purity over nominating an electable candidate. Whether that changes could affect a candidate’s chances — but a candidate’s rise or fall could also influence how much voters say they care about electability. Although polls can present these questions as a dichotomous choice, voters don’t necessarily think about electability in such a black-and-white way.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953864</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Chris Christie Should Have Run For President In 2012</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/chris-christie-2024-republican-primary/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Chris Christie</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Marco Rubio</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Chris Christie Should Have Run For President In 2012</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 7, 2023, at 1:32 PM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="2024-TOC-CHRISCHRISTIE-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-CHRISCHRISTIE-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-CHRISCHRISTIE-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-CHRISCHRISTIE-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-CHRISCHRISTIE-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY FIVETHIRTYEIGHT / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">On Tuesday night in New Hampshire, former New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie<a data-footnote-id="8" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-8" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And former contributor to ABC News, FiveThirtyEight’s parent company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>8</sup></a> announced he was running for president. But the announcement came about 12 years too late.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since passing on a presidential campaign in 2012, when he was still a popular first-term governor, Christie has become the poster child for not striking when the political iron is hot. By the time he did run for president, in 2016, his star had fallen — and he arguably starts this campaign in an even worse position. Like in 2016, his biggest impact on the 2024 Republican primary could be in helping to take down a front-runner — but he’s so disliked, even that may be futile.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To be blunt: If Christie wanted to be president, he missed his chance by not running in 2012. “Now is not my time,” <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/post/chris-christie-not-running-for-president-in-2012-source-says/2011/10/04/gIQAGdIvKL_blog.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he said at a press conference</a> announcing his decision on Oct. 4, 2011. Except, in retrospect, it was the best chance he was going to get. In September 2011, he was riding high: A <a href="https://www.nj.com/news/2011/09/gov_chris_christies_approval_i.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fairleigh Dickinson University poll</a> gave him a 54 percent approval rating and only a 36 percent disapproval rating in New Jersey, remarkable numbers for a Republican in a blue state. A <a href="https://big.assets.huffingtonpost.com/20110927econToplines.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">national poll from YouGov/The Economist</a> showed him tied with former Massachusetts Gov. Mitt Romney for first place in the Republican presidential primary. And Republican elites had spent months <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/nyregion/christie-says-no-to-2012-bid-but-gop-keeps-calling.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trying to draft him</a> into a weak GOP field. The national polling leader, Romney, sat at only 22 percent in the <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/2012/president/us/republican_presidential_nomination-1452.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RealClearPolitics average</a> at the time — a level of support that, from 1972 to 2016, has implied only about a 1-in-5 chance of winning the nomination, according to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-analyzed-40-years-of-primary-polls-even-early-on-theyre-fairly-predictive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">an analysis by my colleague Geoffrey Skelley</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But just a few years later, all that Christie curiosity evaporated. After he won reelection in a landslide in 2013, news broke that Christie aides had <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2016/09/19/politics/bridgegate-explained-christie/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">closed traffic lanes on the George Washington Bridge</a> in order to create traffic problems in Fort Lee, New Jersey, to retaliate politically against the city’s mayor, who hadn’t endorsed Christie for reelection. The scandal permanently torpedoed Christie’s approval ratings in New Jersey:</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"> </p><div><iframe title="Christie was a popular governor … until he wasn't" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/vhY5f/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="425" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">And according to Monmouth University polling, his net favorability rating among Republican registered voters nationally fell from +36 points (54 percent favorable to 18 percent unfavorable) in <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_nj_080513/#Question5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">July 2013</a> to -17 points (26 percent to 43 percent) in <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_061515/#Question3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">June 2015</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Christie nevertheless <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/chris-christie-announces-2016-presidential-campaign/story?id=32125633" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jumped into the presidential race</a> at the end of that month. When he did, he ranked only eighth nationally with 4 percent support, according to <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160203020731/https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/election-2016/national-primary-polls/republican/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s polling average</a>. For the rest of the campaign, not a single poll showed him doing better than 6 percent in Iowa or 13 percent in New Hampshire, and he <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/02/10/466207006/chris-christie-drops-out-of-republican-race-for-president" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropped out</a> after finishing sixth in the Granite State. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Today, Christie’s campaign is starting with even less reason for hope. He has not exceeded 3 percent <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in a single poll</a> — national or state — of the full primary field so far this year. He hasn’t been an elected official for more than five years now, so he’s less in the national spotlight: According to Media Cloud, only <a href="https://search.mediacloud.org/search?q=Chris%2520Christie&amp;nq=&amp;start=05-06-2023&amp;end=06-05-2023&amp;p=onlinenews-mediacloud&amp;ss=&amp;cs=34412234%253EUnited%2520States%2520-%2520National&amp;any=any" target="_blank" rel="noopener">676 online articles</a> from national news outlets mentioned him in the past month, <a href="https://search.mediacloud.org/search?q=Chris%2520Christie&amp;nq=&amp;start=05-30-2015&amp;end=06-29-2015&amp;p=onlinenews-mediacloud&amp;ss=&amp;cs=34412234%253EUnited%2520States%2520-%2520National&amp;any=any" target="_blank" rel="noopener">compared with 1,306</a> in the month before his 2016 campaign launch. And after <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/11/15/politics/chris-christie-donald-trump-january-6-cnntv/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">breaking with former President Donald Trump</a> over his false claims that the 2020 election was stolen, Christie is more unpopular than ever among Republican registered voters: His national net favorability rating in the <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_053023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">latest Monmouth poll</a> was -26 points (21 percent to 47 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then again, Christie may know all this. There’s even a <a href="https://twitter.com/SteveKornacki/status/1663913703136194560?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">theory</a> that he’s running for president not to win, but to slay the dragon that is Trump’s front-running campaign — a dragon, it must be noted, that Christie played a key role in enabling as the first governor or senator to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2016-endorsement-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorse Trump’s 2016 campaign</a> (after his own campaign ended, of course). But Christie has spent the last couple of years publicly attacking Trump as a “<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/11/christie-trump-cnn-putin-00096393" target="_blank" rel="noopener">coward</a>” and a “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/03/us/politics/chris-christie-trump-debates.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">child</a>” who “<a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2023/04/21/chris-christie-2024-presidential-election-donald-trump/11704873002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">undermined our democracy</a>.” That’s a level of anti-Trump vitriol that has so far been <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2024-republican-reaction-trump-indictment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">absent from the 2024 primary</a>, despite Trump <a href="https://manhattanda.org/district-attorney-bragg-announces-34-count-felony-indictment-of-former-president-donald-j-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">getting indicted</a> and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-rape-carroll-trial-fe68259a4b98bb3947d42af9ec83d7db" target="_blank" rel="noopener">being found liable for sexual abuse</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Christie could impact the race simply by making the case against Trump; even if he doesn’t personally benefit from it, a slew of aggressive attacks on the front-runner could take the wind out of Trump’s sails and shift support toward, say, Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis. As a template, look no further than what Christie did to Sen. Marco Rubio in 2016. In a debate just days before the New Hampshire primary, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u9OZ8xHTX7c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christie lit into Rubio</a> for his inexperience and canned talking points. After Rubio finished fifth in New Hampshire, a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/02/11/us/politics/marco-rubio.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narrative emerged</a> that Christie had mortally wounded his campaign.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Christie has all but said this is his strategy again in 2024. “You better have somebody on that stage who can do to him what I did to Marco, because that’s the only thing that’s gonna defeat Donald Trump,” <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/3922641-christie-ups-profile-with-acerbic-attacks-on-trump/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he explained</a> in March. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are just a few problems with that. First, Christie’s impact on the 2016 race is probably overstated. Yes, Rubio went from polling at 16 percent in New Hampshire on the day of the debate (according to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/election-2016/primary-forecast/new-hampshire-republican/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s average at the time</a>) to winning just 11 percent in the actual primary. But Trump certainly didn’t owe his win in New Hampshire to Christie: Trump was already the odds-on favorite before the debate. And Rubio actually recovered somewhat to finish second in both South Carolina and Nevada — but at that point, it didn’t really matter, since Trump was well on his way to winning the nomination.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, in order for Christie to be “on that stage” to attack Trump this year, Christie will need to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republican-debate-criteria-2024-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">satisfy the Republican National Committee’s criteria</a> to qualify for the debates: Candidates will need to receive at least 1 percent in three separate polls <em>and</em> have at least 40,000 donors. Given Christie’s moribund support, he may not even meet those standards and make the debates.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Finally, even if Christie gets a platform from which to attack Trump, it may not even make a difference. Remember, almost half of Republicans dislike Christie (and <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_053023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">77 percent</a> think well of Trump), so they probably wouldn’t be too receptive to Christie’s arguments. Christie’s attacks on Trump might not land that much better than attacks on Trump from the <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/403166/americans-trust-media-remains-near-record-low.aspx#:~:text=accurately%20and%20fairly-,Line%20graph.,trust%20in%20the%20mass%20media." target="_blank" rel="noopener">mass media</a> or <a href="https://www.reuters.com/graphics/USA-BIDEN/POLL/nmopagnqapa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">President Biden</a> — two other entities that are unpopular with Republican voters. Sure, Christie might have some credibility that those two don’t because he’s a fellow Republican, but don’t count on that. As Michael Tesler recently wrote for FiveThirtyEight, Republicans’ devotion to Trump is so strong that they <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-polls-very-conservative-voters-2016-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stop considering Republican politicians to be conservative</a> after they start criticizing Trump.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Probably no one will be shocked to learn that Christie has a vanishingly small chance of becoming the Republican nominee for president. Though he once had that potential, his window of opportunity closed long ago. Instead, his best shot at making a difference in this race is as an attack dog. But it’s fair to wonder whether he is now too irrelevant to be effective even at that.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 18:32:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953862</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Mike Pence Is Starting His Presidential Campaign From A Historically Bad Position</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/mike-pence-2024-campaign/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Early Primary Polls</category>
			<category>January 6th</category>
			<category>Mike Pence</category>
			<category>Vice President</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Mike Pence Is Starting His Presidential Campaign From A Historically Bad Position</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 7, 2023, at 1:31 PM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="2024-TOC-MIKEPENCE-4×3" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-MIKEPENCE-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-MIKEPENCE-4x3-1.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-MIKEPENCE-4x3-1.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/2024-TOC-MIKEPENCE-4x3-1.png?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY EMILY SCHERER / GETTY IMAGES</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The American vice presidency, <a href="https://briscoecenter.org/about/news/john-nance-garner-on-the-vice-presidency-in-search-of-the-proverbial-bucket/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to one of its former officeholders</a>, is “not worth a bucket of warm spit.” But for a worthless office, the vice presidency has certainly produced a lot of presidents: Though John Nance Garner, the former VP credited with the colorful aphorism<a data-footnote-id="9" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-9" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Garner may have &lt;a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/being-texan/john-nance-garner/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;actually used the word&lt;/a&gt; “piss” &lt;a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2021/04/walter-mondale-vice-presidency-carter.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;or even&lt;/a&gt; “shit” instead of “spit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>9</sup></a> never reached the White House, a number of his fellow vice presidents have. Overall, the office has proven to be <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/which-offices-are-good-stepping-stones-to-the-presidency/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one of the most common stepping stones</a> to the presidency — or at least to becoming a party’s presidential nominee.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that success rate will face a major test in 2024: Former Vice President Mike Pence has just announced his candidacy for president, entering the race in arguably a weaker position than just about any other modern vice president. This is due in part to the challenges Pence faces, including the unusual prospect of running against the president he served under and his reduced political standing among Republicans since he refused to aid former President Donald Trump’s efforts to overturn the result of the 2020 presidential election.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Pence is the ninth elected vice president since World War II to seek the presidency either as a sitting or former VP.<a data-footnote-id="10" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-10" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This excludes Lyndon Johnson, who became president upon the assassination of John F. Kennedy in 1963, as well as Gerald Ford and Nelson Rockefeller, who were appointed to the vice presidency under the parameters of the 25th Amendment in 1973 and 1974, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>10</sup></a> Of the eight who came before him, six went on to win their party’s presidential nomination at some point. Based on that track record, then, we’d expect Pence to be in a good position to compete for his party’s nomination.</p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Modern vice presidents usually win their party’s nomination</h2>
 <p>Elected vice presidents who ran for president and whether they won their party’s nomination, 1949-present</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.pence-run-05tk.1">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Vice President</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Served as VP</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Year(s) ran</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Won nomination</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Alben W. Barkley</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>1949-1953</td>
 <td>1952</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Richard Nixon</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>1953-1961</td>
 <td>1960, 1968</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Hubert Humphrey</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>1965-1969</td>
 <td>1968, 1972</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Spiro Agnew*</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>1969-1973</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Walter Mondale</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>1977-1981</td>
 <td>1984</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>George H.W. Bush</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>1981-1989</td>
 <td>1988</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Dan Quayle†</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>1989-1993</td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Al Gore</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>1993-2001</td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Dick Cheney</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2001-2009</td>
 <td>—</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Joe Biden</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2009-2017</td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>✓</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Mike Pence</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2017-2021</td>
 <td>2024</td>
 <td></td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>This list does not include elected vice presidents who became president due to the death of the president, such as Lyndon Johnson, or ones appointed to fill the vice presidency under the 25th Amendment, such as Gerald Ford and Nelson Rockefeller. It also does not include runs by sitting or former vice presidents that predate their time as VP.</p>
 <p>*Agnew resigned the vice presidency on Oct. 10, 1973, in the face of a felony charge for tax evasion.</p>
 <p>†Quayle had a short-lived exploratory campaign during the 1996 cycle.</p>
 <p>Sources: CQ Press Guide to U.S. Elections, The American Presidency Project, News Reports</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But to put it bluntly, Pence faces an incredibly steep climb. As of June 5 at 6 p.m., he’s polling at just above 5 percent in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s average</a> of national Republican primary surveys. And limited early polling <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/iowa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in Iowa</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/new-hampshire/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Hampshire</a> has Pence in the low single-digits, too.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1862" height="1076" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">That Pence significantly trails Trump and Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis is clear, but if we consider how Pence’s standing compares to that of past sitting and former vice presidents running for president, the situation looks even more dire. In the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-modern-primary-system-has-shaped-our-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">modern era of presidential primaries</a> — 1972 to present — Pence is polling just about the worst of any vice president at this point in the election cycle. Only Dan Quayle, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/pmextra/sept99/27/quayle092799.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whose campaign for the 2000 GOP nomination never really got going</a> in a cycle that then-Texas Gov. George W. Bush dominated from the start, attracted as little support as Pence. </p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Pence is polling worse than nearly every other modern VP</h2>
 <p>National polling average for sitting or former vice presidents across all presidential primary polls conducted from January through May of the year before the primary, 1972 cycle to present
 <br><br>

 <span></span> Democrat  

 <span></span> Republican </p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="skelley.pence-run-0607.2">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Year</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">President</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Avg.</th>
 <td colspan="1"></td>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>1972</td>
 <td>Hubert Humphrey</td>
 <td data-suffix="%" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">17.3%</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1984</td>
 <td>Walter Mondale</td>
 <td>35.7</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>1988</td>
 <td>George H.W. Bush</td>
 <td>34.6</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>Al Gore</td>
 <td>52.1</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>Dan Quayle</td>
 <td>7.1</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>Joe Biden</td>
 <td>31.1</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>2024</td>
 <td>Mike Pence</td>
 <td>6.8</td>
 <td>
 <div>–</div>
 </td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>This averages all polls in this period that included these vice presidents as a response. Head-to-head polls are excluded. If the same pollster conducted surveys in overlapping periods, the older poll is excluded. If polls included multiple samples, only the most exclusive population of Democratic or Republican respondents is included. If a pollster had more than one question with the same population that asked about different lists of candidates, we averaged the results across all versions.</p>
 <p>Source: POLLS</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">Besides Quayle, most other vice presidents have been more clearly competitive in the polls at this early point, if not clearly ahead. Vice Presidents Walter Mondale, George H.W. Bush, Al Gore and Biden all led their respective primary fields five months into the year before the primary; all would go on to become their party’s nominee.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, it’s still early in the election cycle, but early primary polls have historically been a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-analyzed-40-years-of-primary-polls-even-early-on-theyre-fairly-predictive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">relatively good barometer</a> of a candidate’s chances of winning a presidential nomination. Candidates polling at Pence’s level, especially those who are well-known to voters like he is, have very rarely gone on to enjoy a balloon drop at a party convention. Of course, Pence also faces a challenge none of his modern vice presidential predecessors had to confront: He’s running against the president he served under. At present, Trump is attracting slightly more than half of all support among potential Republican primary voters.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The million-dollar question is, can Pence substantially change his position in the race? One major challenge is that he’s notably less well-liked among Republicans than his main primary opponents. In an average of national polls conducted since May 1, Pence has a favorable rating among Republicans of about 51 percent and an unfavorable rating of about 34 percent, putting his net favorability at +17. By comparison, Trump, DeSantis, former U.N. Ambassador Nikki Haley, South Carolina Sen. Tim Scott and tech entrepreneur Vivek Ramaswamy all polled +20 or better, even though all but Trump and DeSantis are much less well-known to the public than Pence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Pence's favorability lags behind other GOP contenders" aria-label="Scatter Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/nmbW4/10/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="500" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">The reason Pence finds himself more disliked and hovering in the mid-single digits in primary polls is fairly straightforward: Pence’s <a href="https://civiqs.com/results/favorable_mike_pence?uncertainty=true&amp;annotations=true&amp;zoomIn=true&amp;party=Republican" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ratings among Republicans tumbled</a> and have remained relatively low since he refused to assist Trump in subverting the results of the 2020 election. As vice president, Pence presided over the certification of the Electoral College results on Jan. 6, 2021. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/05/us/politics/pence-trump-election.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump tried to pressure Pence</a> to discard electoral votes and overturn now-President Biden’s victory, but Pence <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/11/pence-jan-6-election-certification-script-00016539" target="_blank" rel="noopener">refused to do so</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/05/us/politics/pence-trump-election-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">claiming he had no constitutional right</a> to intercede in the certification process. (Quayle, Pence’s fellow Hoosier, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2021/09/14/new-details-undermine-pences-supposed-hero-turn-jan-6/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reportedly advised an uncertain Pence</a> that the vice president had no authority to avoid certification.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is not to say that all Republican primary voters turned on Pence — he does have a net positive favorability rating — but there’s clear evidence that Jan. 6 damaged Pence’s standing among the party faithful. It hasn’t helped Pence that Trump <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2023/03/14/donald-trump-mike-pence-jan-6-blame/11469303002/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has continued to blame him</a> for his defeat, even as <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/videos/news/nation/2022/02/05/pence-trump-wrong-overturning-election/6671146001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pence has argued</a> that Trump was “wrong” about Pence’s prerogative to help overturn the 2020 result. Unfortunately for him, Pence finds himself in the minority among Republicans when it comes to views about the election’s outcome: In March, 63 percent of Republicans <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/23706881/cnn-poll-most-republicans-care-more-about-picking-a-2024-gop-nominee-who-agrees-with-them-on-issues-than-one-who-can-beat-biden.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told an SSRS/CNN survey</a> that Biden had not won legitimately enough votes to become president, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-republicans-still-wont-accept-that-biden-won/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in line with</a> what most polls have found since the 2020 contest.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Despite his difficulties, Pence may still hope to change some Republican minds. And we do know that it’s not impossible to improve one’s standing: Trump himself <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republicans-dont-like-donald-trump-as-much-as-they-used-to/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quickly went</a> from being rather unpopular among Republicans to somewhat popular early in his 2016 campaign, once the GOP base got to know him more as a candidate and not just as a celebrity. But Pence is running in a GOP that is clearly Trump’s party, whether or not the former president does go on to win the Republican nomination. Not only is Trump polling in the mid-50s in national surveys, but the Trump-like DeSantis is in second with around 20 percent, meaning around 3 in 4 Republicans back a Trumpist vision for the party. Moreover, early data suggests that DeSantis <a href="https://morningconsult.com/2024-gop-primary-election-tracker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has far more second-choice support</a> among Trump backers than Pence.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s impossible to know, but considering his obstacles, Pence may be running not so much to win his party’s nomination but to influence the GOP to move toward a more traditionally conservative path. Political movements often take <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-desantis-2024-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">years to develop and gain traction</a>, so it will be difficult in the near term to gauge just how much impact Pence’s campaign will have on his party’s direction. All in all, Pence’s choice to not interfere in certifying the results of a free and fair election has made it unlikely that he’ll win the 2024 Republican nomination. But at least he can probably sleep at night.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 18:31:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953860</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Doug Burgum Could Surprise In The 2024 Republican Primary</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/doug-burgum-2024-republican-primary/</link>
						<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Nathaniel Rakich</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Campaign Finance</category>
			<category>Doug Burgum</category>
			<category>North Dakota</category>
			<category>Republican Governors</category>
			<category>Republican Primaries</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Doug Burgum Could Surprise In The 2024 Republican Primary</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/nathaniel-rakich/" title="" rel="author">Nathaniel Rakich</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 7, 2023, at 10:39 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="2024-TOC-REP_Doug Burgum_4x3_v02_dnl" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/2024-TOC-REP_Doug-Burgum_4x3_v02_dnl.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/2024-TOC-REP_Doug-Burgum_4x3_v02_dnl.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/2024-TOC-REP_Doug-Burgum_4x3_v02_dnl.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/2024-TOC-REP_Doug-Burgum_4x3_v02_dnl.png?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY DANNY PEREZ / DAN KOECK / REUTERS</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">It’s high season for glossy campaign videos and American flag bunting. In the last 16 hours, three Republicans <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/mike-pence-2024-campaign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have announced</a> they’re <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/chris-christie-2024-republican-primary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">running for president</a> — an unfortunate syzygy for candidates whose meticulously crafted messages are now in danger of getting drowned out. And with his virtually nonexistent national profile, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/north-dakota-to-the-white-house-economy-energy-presidential-announcement-election-2024-candidate-552a70a0?" target="_blank" rel="noopener">North Dakota Gov. Doug Burgum</a> likely has the most to lose from sharing the news cycle with former Vice President Mike Pence and former New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie. On the other hand, he may not care too much: Thanks to <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/now/rich-wealthiest-governors-150108514.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his deep pockets</a> (and the other candidates’ lackluster prospects), Burgum may have the most upside of the three.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">You could be forgiven for never having heard of Burgum before. He’s governor of the nation’s fourth-smallest state by population, and until <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/elections/2023/05/18/burgum-presidential-election-gop-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a couple weeks ago</a>, virtually no one outside of North Dakota was talking about him as a potential future president. (Those reading <a href="https://www.inforum.com/opinion/columns/port-is-north-dakota-gov-doug-burgum-exploring-a-campaign-for-president" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in-state media</a>, though, were hip to it as early as March.) The <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">first polls</a> to include him as an option in the primary were released on May 24 (he received 1 percent in one and 0 percent in the other), and <a href="https://pro.morningconsult.com/trackers/2024-gop-primary-election-tracker" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Morning Consult’s latest poll</a> found that only 23 percent of potential Republican primary voters knew enough about him to form an opinion of him.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/doug-burgum-north-dakota-governor-running-president-fivethirtyeight-99768043</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">So why does Burgum think he has a shot at the White House? Maybe because he’s gone from anonymous dark horse to Republican primary winner once before. In 2016, everyone assumed that then-North Dakota Attorney General Wayne Stenehjem would be the state’s next governor. He led Burgum 59 percent to 10 percent in a <a href="https://www.inforum.com/newsmd/poll-finds-burgum-trailing-stenehjem-by-large-margin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">February poll of the GOP primary</a>, and he <a href="https://www.inforum.com/newsmd/stenehjem-wins-gop-nomination-for-hotly-contested-nd-governors-race-burgum-to-continue-to-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">received the official endorsement</a> of the North Dakota Republican Party at the party convention in April. But in the June primary, Burgum defeated Stenehjem 59 percent to 39 percent.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">How did he pull it off? A big part of it was money. Burgum is a software executive — and a very successful one. He was an <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/richkarlgaard/2017/06/13/americas-best-entrepreneurial-governor/?sh=1c23debb7f21" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early investor in Great Plains Software</a>, which he sold to Microsoft in 2001 for $1.1 billion. With the help of one William Gates of Seattle, Washington, he outraised Stenehjem at least <a href="https://apnews.com/article/2022-midterm-elections-north-dakota-fargo-jack-dalrymple-e2d4ca877aa44f3283d0a64b4652d2af" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$966,000 to $752,000</a> in that 2016 primary. And we say “at least” because that number doesn’t include whatever Burgum self-funded — at the time, North Dakota law didn’t require candidates to disclose contributions they made to their own campaign.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Burgum is reportedly going to use the same playbook in 2024: A source told ABC News that he will self-fund his presidential campaign. Considering that his net worth as of last year was reportedly <a href="https://www.gobankingrates.com/net-worth/politicians/how-rich-are-the-wealthiest-governors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than $1 billion</a>, he could probably pump several million dollars into the race without breaking a sweat. And that would immediately make him one of the primary’s top fundraisers. It was a couple months ago, but as of March 31, only two Republicans had <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/elections/president/2024/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raised more than $12 million</a> or had at least that much money in the bank.<a data-footnote-id="11" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-11" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One name you might not recognize in the table below is Perry Johnson. He’s a businessman running a quixotic presidential campaign who, decent fundraising aside, doesn’t qualify as a major candidate by &lt;a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/heres-how-were-defining-a-major-presidential-candidate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;our definition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>11</sup></a></p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Only a few presidential candidates are flush with cash</h2>
 <p>Fundraising total receipts and cash on hand for Republican presidential candidates as of March 31, 2023</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.doug-burgum.1">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Total Receipts</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Cash on Hand</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Donald Trump</td>
 <td data-prefix="$">$18,272,903</td>
 <td data-prefix="$">$13,931,948</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Vivek Ramaswamy</td>
 <td>11,418,449</td>
 <td>9,367,288</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Nikki Haley</td>
 <td>5,125,431</td>
 <td>4,069,549</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Perry Johnson</td>
 <td>3,763,396</td>
 <td>2,036,476</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Tim Scott</td>
 <td>1,646,202</td>
 <td>21,912,915</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>Asa Hutchinson and Ron DeSantis have not yet reported raising any money to the FEC.</p>
 <p>Source: Federal Election Commission</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">According to political science research, the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/money-and-elections-a-complicated-love-story/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">connection between spending money and winning elections</a> isn’t automatic — just ask former New York City mayor and 2020 presidential candidate Michael Bloomberg. But one of the contexts in which campaign cash <em>can</em> be very helpful is <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2891145" target="_blank" rel="noopener">early on in a primary</a> when the candidate is not very well known. This, of course, is exactly Burgum’s situation. His lack of name recognition is actually an asset when paired with his fat wallet; it will allow him to define himself however he wants for a national audience. As governor, Burgum has been a bit hard to pin down ideologically, and it will be interesting to see how he defines himself once he enters the GOP race. Will we get the wonky, temperate Burgum who <a href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/doug-burgum-is-mulling-a-run-for-president-could-he-be-a-contender-in-a-party-that-loves-trump" target="_blank" rel="noopener">geeks out over energy policy</a> and once called an anti-LGBTQ+ resolution “<a href="https://www.usnews.com/news/politics/articles/2020-07-23/north-dakota-governor-blasts-partys-anti-lgbtq-resolution" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hurtful and divisive</a>”? Or the rock-ribbed conservative Burgum who signed <a href="https://bismarcktribune.com/news/state-and-regional/govt-and-politics/burgum-signs-north-dakota-transgender-sports-bills/article_b353c76a-d8bd-11ed-9146-b72377d48f5e.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">multiple pieces</a> of <a href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/north-dakota-gov-doug-burgum-signs-bill-to-restrict-transgender-k-12-students-pronouns-bathroom-access" target="_blank" rel="noopener">anti-transgender legislation</a> and one of the <a href="https://apnews.com/article/abortion-north-dakota-six-week-ban-2bccde2925d30dd4772aaed84f3c2d98" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strictest abortion bans in the country</a>?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, let’s not get carried away: Burgum is very unlikely to win the actual nomination. (As you may have heard, there’s this guy named Donald Trump who has a dominant lead in both <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">polls</a> and <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2024-election-endorsements/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorsements</a>, both of which <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/we-analyzed-40-years-of-primary-polls-even-early-on-theyre-fairly-predictive/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have historically</a> been <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-2024-endorsements-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pretty predictive</a>.) But Burgum <em>could</em> spend enough to have a meaningful impact on the race. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Let’s say Burgum really commits to the bit and kicks in $50 million of his own money before the end of the year. The list of presidential candidates who have raised the equivalent of $50 million in 2023 dollars by that point in the cycle is full of notable names. If they didn’t win the nomination, most of them were at least an important part of the narrative of the election cycle in which they ran.</p>


<div>
<section>
 <header>
 <h2>Free-spending candidates do well in presidential primaries</h2>
 <p>Democratic and Republican candidates who have raised at least $50 million (in 2023 dollars) in incumbent-less presidential primaries before Jan. 1 of election years since 2000 and where they eventually finished in the primary, based on delegates won</p>
 </header>
 <table data-carpenter-slug="rakich.doug-burgum.2">
 <thead>
 <tr>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Candidate</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Party</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Year</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Total Receipts</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Self-Funded</th>
 <th colspan="1" scope="col">Finish</th>
 </tr>
 </thead>
 <tbody>
 <tr>
 <td>Tom Steyer</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td data-prefix="$" data-suffix="m" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">$244.8m</td>
 <td data-prefix="$" data-suffix="m" data-suffixpadding="1.1em">$240.3m</td>
 <td>T-8th</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Michael Bloomberg</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>237.7</td>
 <td>237.5</td>
 <td>4th</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Hillary Clinton</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>173.1</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>2nd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Barack Obama</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>151.9</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Hillary Clinton</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>147.9</td>
 <td>0.5</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Mitt Romney</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>131.8</td>
 <td>0.1</td>
 <td>3rd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Steve Forbes</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>129.8</td>
 <td>120.3</td>
 <td>4th</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Bernie Sanders</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>129.0</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>2nd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>George W. Bush</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>125.0</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Elizabeth Warren</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>97.3</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>3rd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Bernie Sanders</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>96.0</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>2nd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Rudy Giuliani</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>90.2</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>T-8th</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Mitt Romney</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2012</td>
 <td>77.0</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Joe Biden</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2020</td>
 <td>72.4</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Ben Carson</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>69.2</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>5th</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Howard Dean</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2004</td>
 <td>68.2</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>3rd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>John Edwards</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>64.8</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>3rd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>John McCain</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2008</td>
 <td>61.6</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Ted Cruz</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>60.3</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>2nd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Al Gore</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>52.7</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>1st</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Marco Rubio</td>
 <td><span>R</span></td>
 <td>2016</td>
 <td>50.6</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>3rd</td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
 <td>Bill Bradley</td>
 <td><span>D</span></td>
 <td>2000</td>
 <td>50.6</td>
 <td>0.0</td>
 <td>2nd</td>
 </tr>
 </tbody>
 </table>
 <footer>
 <p>Dollar figures are adjusted for inflation. Steyer and Giuliani tied for 8th place with zero delegates each.</p>
 <p>Sources: Federal Election Commission, Dave Leip’s Atlas of U.S. Presidential Elections</p>
 </footer>
</section>
</div>


<p data-paragraph="main">The 2024 Republican primary already has a clear front-runner in Trump and a clear main alternative in <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/ron-desantis-2024-republican-presidential-announcement/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis</a>. But after that, the field is wide open; according to <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s polling average</a>, the third-place candidate nationally right now is former Vice President Mike Pence with only 5 percent support. Burgum would need his money to give him only about a 5-percentage-point boost to become the main alternative to the main alternative. And given that DeSantis has faced questions about his <a href="https://www.wbur.org/cognoscenti/2023/05/24/desantis-trump-gop-presidential-primary-2024-kaivan-shroff" target="_blank" rel="noopener">awkwardness</a> and <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/news/florida-politics/2023/05/04/desantis-trump-congress-2024-moms-for-liberty-donalds-ziegler/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">political skills</a> — coinciding with his national polling average falling from 30 percent on March 21 to 21 percent today — that could be a valuable place to be. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">That, to be clear, is Burgum’s best-case scenario. He may not spend $50 million — and even if he does, he may not surpass DeSantis, or even Pence. But his first barrage of spending — whether it comes immediately or in several months — will be worth watching closely. In politics, candidates who spend a ton of money <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/sometimes-money-cant-buy-you-votes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eventually encounter diminishing returns</a> — in other words, Burgum’s first $20 million spent will get him further than dollars 100-120 million. Once we see how much he is willing to spend and where he ends up once he has spent the first wave of it, we’ll know a lot more about whether Burgum is a candidate to watch.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 15:39:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953859</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Some Republican Candidates Might Not Make The Debate Stage</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/republican-debate-criteria-2024-primary/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Debates</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Debates</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Republican National Committee</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Some Republican Candidates Might Not Make The Debate Stage</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 6, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Republican presidential candidates before a debate in 2016" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GettyImages-513613220-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GettyImages-513613220-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GettyImages-513613220-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/GettyImages-513613220-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						Former President Donald Trump has so far declined to say whether he would pledge to support the eventual Republican nominee, a key component of the Republican National Committee’s debate qualifications.													<p>Chip Somodevilla / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Whether they’re generating news coverage or raising money (or, in recent years, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2016-election/donald-trump-has-small-hands-marco-rubio-says-n527791" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eyebrows</a>), debates are <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/presidential-primary-debates-can-make-and-break-a-campaign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a critical part</a> of the presidential primary calendar. A great performance can help a lesser-known candidate gain ground in the polls and expand their fundraising reach, while a poor showing can mark the beginning of the end — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/scott-walker-blew-his-last-chance-the-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">or the end, period</a> — for someone’s presidential aspirations. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But before candidates can make or break their campaigns, they need to get on the debate stage. On Friday, the Republican National Committee <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory/republicans-schedule-1st-presidential-debate-aug-23-guarantee-99798499" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released its debate qualification criteria</a> for the party’s first debate on Aug. 23, 2023. The RNC’s guidelines, which establish candidate polling and fundraising thresholds, are pretty similar to Democratic National Committee’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-first-democratic-debate-deadline-is-almost-here-whos-in-and-whos-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">at the start of the 2020 cycle</a>. However, there are a few additional twists and specifications — most notably, the requirement that candidates pledge to support the party’s eventual nominee and the criteria for determining which polls count toward qualification — that could limit the field.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">To make the debate, the RNC will <a href="https://www.gop.com/press-release/rnc-announces-criteria-and-date-for-first-debate-in-milwaukee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">require candidates to meet four separate requirements</a>. First, a contender must be a declared candidate who has filed with the Federal Election Commission.<a data-footnote-id="12" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-12" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A candidate &lt;a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/essay/artII-S1-C5-1/ALDE_00013692/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;must also be eligible to become president&lt;/a&gt; — that is, be a natural-born U.S. citizen, a resident of the country for at least 14 years and age 35 years or older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>12</sup></a> Second, a candidate must have earned 1 percent support in three national polls, or in two national polls and at least one poll of the <a href="https://www.frontloadinghq.com/p/the-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GOP’s first four states</a>, recognized by the RNC and conducted in July and August. Third, a candidate must have at least 40,000 unique contributors to their presidential campaign committee, with at least 200 from 20 states and/or territories. And lastly, a candidate must sign three documents: a pledge to support the GOP’s eventual nominee, a data-sharing agreement with the RNC and a pledge to not participate in any debates not sanctioned by the RNC.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So given these requirements, who would make the stage if the debate were held today? Currently, six candidates are at 1 percent or higher in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/2024/national/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s national polling average</a>: former President Donald Trump, Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, former Vice President Mike Pence (expected to announce his candidacy on June 7), former U.S. Ambassador to the U.N. Nikki Haley, tech entrepreneur Vivek Ramaswamy and South Carolina Sen. Tim Scott. Though the polls taken up until this point won’t count toward debate qualification, these candidates seemingly have good shots at being at 1 percent in July and August surveys. And they can probably attract or already have sufficient donors, as even the lesser-known Ramaswamy <a href="https://americankahani.com/lead-stories/ramaswamy-rising-the-indian-american-candidate-is-likely-to-qualify-for-the-first-republican-primary-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recently announced</a> he had met the donor threshold.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1862" height="1076" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screen-Shot-2023-06-05-at-5.58.33-PM.png?w=1424 2x"></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main">It’s unclear, however, exactly how many polls the RNC will recognize — though it could be a smaller number than those used by the DNC to determine debate qualification in 2019. In its release, the RNC said it would only consider polls conducted by organizations unaffiliated with a candidate or a candidate committee that sampled at least “800 registered likely Republican voters.” This significantly limits the number of polls under consideration, as many primary polls around this time in an election cycle sample registered voters or adults without a likely voter screen, and relatively few have an 800-plus voter sample size. In fact, since Jan. 1, a period of just over 150 days, only <em>seven</em> Republican primary polls in <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-r/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FiveThirtyEight’s database</a> appear to meet those criteria. And because the RNC will only recognize polls conducted from July 1 to just before the debate, pollsters will only have about 50 days to conduct and release qualifying polls. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">By comparison, the DNC in 2019 provided a list of pollsters whose data would count toward qualification and counted any poll publicly released between Jan. 1, 2019, and two weeks before the first debate in June — a period of just over five months. In the end, the DNC <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-first-democratic-debate-deadline-is-almost-here-whos-in-and-whos-out/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had 23 qualifying polls</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Now, pollsters could respond by working to expand their sample size and use a likely voter screen to meet the RNC’s requirement. For instance, an <a href="https://s.wsj.net/public/resources/documents/WSJ_Poll_April_2023_redacted.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">April poll by Fabrizio, Lee &amp; Associates/Impact Research</a> for The Wall Street Journal had a sample of 600 likely Republican primary voters. However, even if that well-known pollster pairing expanded its sample size in future surveys, would they count? Tony Fabrizio <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/06/01/trump-desantis-electability-polling" target="_blank" rel="noopener">currently works with</a> a Trump-aligned super PAC, which may run afoul of the pollster affiliation rule. Republican polling firms that often release national or state-level surveys of likely voters could run into a similar issue, because some of them may be aligned with a candidate’s committee or supportive outside group. Some media-sponsored polls do start polling likely voters in the early summer, but even then they rarely have sample sizes as large as 800.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We reached out to the RNC for comment and clarification about its polling qualification criteria, but as of press time had not heard back.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The stricter guidelines for the polls are not the only place where Republicans have made it harder to qualify for presidential debates, compared to the Democrats’ 2020 requirements. By mandating that candidates reach minimum thresholds for both polling and donors, the RNC has skipped ahead of the DNC’s initial rules in the 2020 cycle. For its first two debates, Democrats allowed candidates <a href="https://democrats.org/news/dnc-announces-details-for-the-first-two-presidential-primary-debates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to qualify via either the polling <em>or</em> donor route</a>, and it wasn’t until <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/it-wont-be-easy-for-many-democrats-to-make-the-september-debate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the third debate</a> that candidates had to meet both a polling and donor threshold to qualify. By necessitating both from the start, Republicans may reduce the number of qualifiers. But if there are too many qualified candidates for one stage, the RNC said it could host a second debate night on Aug. 24, similar to what the Democrats did four years ago. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">However, the RNC <em>is</em> starting out with a lower threshold for unique donors than the DNC did in 2019 — 40,000 versus 65,000 — which may reflect the GOP’s <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/elections-overview/donor-demographics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">comparatively lower amount of small-donor fundraising</a>. Nonetheless, some lesser-known Republican contenders, such as former Arkansas Gov. Asa Hutchinson and radio personality Larry Elder, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/06/02/us/politics/republican-debate-criteria.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expressed frustration</a> with even that comparatively lower figure, viewing it as a serious barrier to their qualification chances.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The final potentially major limitation on the number of candidates are the pledges — particularly the pledge to support the eventual nominee. Trump — who will surely meet the polling and donor requirements — <a href="https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2023/mar/4/trump-wont-commit-republican-national-committees-l/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has not committed to signing it</a>, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/republicans-debate-2024-president-august-6cc406eb00c72835f4f59acb30d71e95" target="_blank" rel="noopener">which much of</a> the <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2024-election/gop-requires-pledge-back-nominee-first-presidential-debate-rcna87498" target="_blank" rel="noopener">coverage of the</a> RNC’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/06/02/republican-national-committee-debate-criteria-00099947" target="_blank" rel="noopener">debate qualification announcement</a> immediately <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-politics/republican-nominees-2024-pledge-debate-trump-desantis-b2350610.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">homed in on</a>. Now, Trump <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2015/09/03/politics/donald-trump-2016-rnc-pledge-meeting/index.html#:~:text=The%20pledge%20continues%3A%20%E2%80%9CI%20further,president%20of%20any%20other%20party.%E2%80%9D" target="_blank" rel="noopener">did sign a similar pledge</a> in September 2015 after <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/donald-trump-taking-pledge-run-party/story?id=32987615" target="_blank" rel="noopener">much back-and-forth with the RNC</a>. But while <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/2016/president/us/2016_republican_presidential_nomination-3823.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">he was ostensibly the GOP’s front-runner</a> back then, Trump is in a much stronger position this time around, polling north of 50 percent and having reshaped the party in his image during his presidency. As such, he may not see much reason to give into the RNC on this debate requirement.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953858</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: The GOP Field Gets Crowded</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-gop-field-gets-crowded/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Debates</category>
			<category>Debt Ceiling</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div></div>


<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-the-gop-field-gets-crowded/">
	<div data-podcast-id="360406" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: The GOP Field Gets Crowded">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP8779640151.mp3?updated=1686005451">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS </a>
					| <a href="https://music.amazon.com/podcasts/c1a4c9d6-aa5b-4899-b78a-dd62f240ec29/fivethirtyeight-politics">Amazon Music</a>
							| <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/3C0iP88KSoGZk5KNWmuyF1?si=39a47edc33514971">Spotify</a>
					</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">By the end of this week, the number of major candidates running for the Republican presidential nomination is expected to grow to nine. Former New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie, former Vice President Mike Pence and North Dakota Gov. Doug Burgum are all expected to jump into the race this week. In this installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast, the crew discusses how these candidates might shape the race.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Also, the Republican National Committee announced the date and criteria for the first primary debate last Friday. The polling criteria are pretty notable, as there may not be that many polls that actually qualify. So is that a good or bad use of polling?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And over the weekend, President Biden signed into law a suspension of the debt ceiling through January 2025 along with some cuts to federal spending.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 23:48:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953857</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Abortion Is Already Tripping Up The 2024 Republican Candidates</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-2024-republican-candidates/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Abortion</category>
			<category>Access To Abortion</category>
			<category>Nebraska</category>
			<category>South Carolina</category>
			<category>State Legislatures</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/abortion/" name="">Abortion</a></p>
						
													<h1>Abortion Is Already Tripping Up The 2024 Republican Candidates</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 5, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt='A pro-life demonstrator holds a sign with a photo of Donald Trump that reads "Most Pro-Life President Ever."' src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1195734670-1024.jpg?w=1024" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1195734670-1024.jpg?w=1024" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1195734670-1024.jpg?w=1024 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/GettyImages-1195734670-1024.jpg?w=2048 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						A pro-life demonstrator holds a sign with a photo of Donald Trump that reads “Most Pro-Life President Ever.”													<p>NICHOLAS KAMM / AFP via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Ask six Republican candidates for president whether they think there should be a national ban on abortion, and you’ll get at least seven different answers. In just the past two months, current and prospective candidates have committed at various points to <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Health/wireStory/haley-commits-federal-abortion-ban-republicans-congress-99572325" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the general idea</a> of a federal bans on abortion (<a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/tim-scott-supports-national-20-week-abortion-ban-would-consider-15-week-limit" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>maybe </em>15 weeks of pregnancy</a>), said <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-abortion-2024-president-81373a7c8523db24f928d713ff90aa31" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it’s a states’ rights issue</a> but they’re <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/05/16/ron-desantis-to-fight-donald-trump-on-abortion.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">looking at “alternatives,”</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/16/desantis-trump-florida-six-week-abortion-ban-00097154" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expressed support for six-week bans at the state level</a> while declining to say whether they think a national version would be appropriate, and said they support efforts to <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/mike-pence-abortion-pill-supreme-court-mifepristone-off-the-market/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">get a widely used abortion drug “off the market.”</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">All of this waffling might suggest that the Republican Party is struggling to find a path forward on abortion after last year’s midterm elections, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/abortion-rights-are-reshaping-american-politics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">where abortion rights was a drag</a> on GOP candidates in swing states. But something more complicated is happening. Republicans passed a significant number of first-trimester restrictions at the state level this spring, ranging from full bans to bans on abortion after 12 weeks of pregnancy, none of which are popular with most Americans. And many of the GOP candidates <em>are</em> coalescing around some form of national ban, even if they aren’t on the same page about the specifics. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So the GOP isn’t backing down on its efforts to restrict abortion, even in the face of fairly broad public opposition. The dispute now — in state legislatures and among the presidential candidates — is more about how far to go and how quickly. Presidential candidates are in a tough spot — caught between state legislatures, courts intervening in unexpected ways and unambiguously negative polling numbers on abortion restrictions. That’s particularly true for higher-polling candidates like former President Donald Trump and Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, who need to weigh how a gung-ho attitude about abortion restrictions — while probably helpful during the primary — would play in a general election. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Since the beginning of the year, seven states have passed new restrictions on abortion early in pregnancy, including three near-total bans (<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/utah-governor-signs-legislation-banning-clinics-providing-abortions-rcna75206" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Utah</a>, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/04/25/1171816825/north-dakota-abortion-law" target="_blank" rel="noopener">North Dakota</a> and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/abortion-pills-now-banned-wyoming-after-governor-signs/story?id=97961145" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wyoming</a>),<a data-footnote-id="13" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-13" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These were essentially clean-up efforts, as &lt;a href="https://www.ksl.com/article/50495823/utah-supreme-court-allows-halt-on-abortion-trigger-law-to-remain-in-place" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/08/25/politics/abortion-north-dakota/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/judge-temporarily-blocks-wyoming-abortion-ban" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;states&lt;/a&gt; had trigger bans in place when Roe was overturned, but courts blocked them from going into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>13</sup></a> two bans on abortion after about six weeks of pregnancy (<a href="https://apnews.com/article/florida-abortion-ban-approved-c9c53311a0b2426adc4b8d0b463edad1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Florida</a> and <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/south-carolina-6-week-abortion-ban-heads-governors/story?id=99565825" target="_blank" rel="noopener">South Carolina</a>), and two bans on abortion after 12 weeks of pregnancy (<a href="https://apnews.com/article/transgender-health-care-abortion-ban-nebraska-1a88067bf403559116df7c09e004e472" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nebraska</a> and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/abortion-veto-override-north-carolina-4282913637b499490494dd3e3cce3478" target="_blank" rel="noopener">North Carolina</a>). Not all of those bans are currently in effect — some, like Wyoming’s full ban and South Carolina’s six-week ban, were <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/05/26/politics/south-carolina-abortion-law/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">temporarily blocked</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/03/22/health/wyoming-abortion-ban.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by the courts</a>, and others won’t become law until <a href="https://www.sltrib.com/news/politics/2023/02/14/breaking-utah-abortion-clinics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a later date</a> — but they showed that GOP lawmakers are serious about continuing to restrict abortion access, even in purplish states like North Carolina and Florida. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The bans in Nebraska and South Carolina followed <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-republicans-keep-failing-to-pass-abortion-bans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">high-profile failures to pass new abortion restrictions last summer</a>, indicating that in some places, there might actually be more anti-abortion momentum now than there was immediately after Dobbs. The only (<em>very</em> mild) concessions to public opinion were in <a href="https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/politics/2023/03/20/tennessee-house-passes-narrow-exceptions-to-states-total-abortion-ban/70029056007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tennessee</a>, <a href="https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/idaho-s-amended-abortion-laws-summary-3223468/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Idaho</a> and <a href="https://www.wvlegislature.gov/Bill_Status/bills_history.cfm?INPUT=3199&amp;year=2023&amp;sessiontype=RS" target="_blank" rel="noopener">West Virginia</a>, where lawmakers added language to the existing near-total bans either clarifying that ectopic pregnancies were not included, or not subject to reporting requirements.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/05/04/north-carolina-abortion-ban/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">12-week bans</a> were <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/19/us/abortion-transgender-bill-nebraska.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">explicitly presented as compromises</a> — a way to outlaw second-trimester abortion without alienating the handful of moderate Republicans who thought a six-week ban went too far. And in South Carolina, the six-week ban that ultimately passed was <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/may/23/south-carolina-abortion-ban-six-weeks" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also an unhappy middle ground</a> for conservative Republicans — who wanted a full ban — and moderate Republicans, who wanted a 12-week ban. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But all of the first-trimester restrictions that passed this year have political risks. Full bans are overwhelmingly unpopular with Americans overall, which is likely why they only passed in highly conservative states. But a FiveThirtyEight analysis of polls conducted between September 2021 and May 2023 found that Americans are ambivalent about 15-week bans and unambiguously oppose six-week bans. According to our analysis, an average of 44 percent of Americans overall were in favor of a 15-week ban during this period, while the same share were opposed. Meanwhile, only 34 percent of Americans supported a six-week ban, and a majority (54 percent) were opposed. There are fewer polls on 12-week bans, but <a href="https://carolinaforward.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Carolina-Forward-May-2023-Poll-Report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a survey of North Carolina likely voters</a> conducted by Change Research for the left-leaning group Carolina Forward in early May found that less than half of respondents wanted abortion to be illegal at 12 weeks or earlier, while 59 percent wanted to either keep North Carolina’s current restriction on abortion after 20 weeks, or get rid of restrictions on access altogether. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So any early restriction is going to be controversial — and the GOP’s push to tighten abortion laws is generally at odds with public sentiment overall. <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2023/04/26/nearly-a-year-after-roes-demise-americans-views-of-abortion-access-increasingly-vary-by-where-they-live/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A recent poll</a> by the Pew Research Center found that in areas where abortion was prohibited in the aftermath of the Dobbs decision, the share of people who think it should be easier to get an abortion rose from 31 percent in 2019 to 43 percent in 2023. There was a similar uptick in states where abortion was restricted or the law was being disputed in the courts. The poll also found that a majority of Americans (62 percent) think that states are making it too hard to get an abortion, including a substantial minority (39 percent) of Republicans. A majority (53 percent) of Republicans also think it should either be easier (20 percent) or about as difficult as it is now (33 percent) to get an abortion in their area, while less than half (44 percent) think it should be harder. And <a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/poll-finding/kff-tracking-poll-may-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent Kaiser Family Foundation poll</a> found that Americans overall are much more likely to say that the Democratic Party represents their view on abortion (42 percent) compared to the Republican Party (26 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">None of this polling points to much of an appetite for more abortion restrictions, even among a solid chunk of Republicans. And it’s especially difficult for presidential candidates to find a position that both pleases anti-abortion advocates <em>and</em> isn’t broadly unpopular. <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2023-04/Reuters%20Medication%20Abortion%20Survey%20Topline%20FINAL%204.13.23_0.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A Reuters/Ipsos poll conducted in April</a> found that only 21 percent of Americans support a national ban on abortion without exceptions, and just over one-third (35 percent) are in favor of a national ban at six weeks’ gestation. The idea of banning abortion nationally — even at a later point in pregnancy, like 15 weeks — seems to be fairly politically toxic: <a href="https://today.yougov.com/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/09/21/most-americans-support-national-right-abortion" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A YouGov/Economist poll conducted last fall</a> found that there was more support for establishing a national right to abortion (51 percent) than banning abortion at 15 weeks, while allowing states to enact stricter laws on their own (39 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">GOP candidates, however, aren’t running in a general election yet. They’re facing demands from anti-abortion groups to commit to some kind of federal ban — one prominent group <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/20/us/politics/trump-abortion-susan-b-anthony.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">threatened to campaign against</a> any candidate who refuses to support a 15-week national ban — and from a significant (and vocal) chunk of their own electorate who also want more restrictions. This is likely one reason why candidates like former South Carolina Gov. Nikki Haley <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/14/us/politics/nikki-haley-republicans-federal-abortion-ban.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are floundering for answers</a>, and willing — like <a href="https://apnews.com/article/florida-abortion-ban-approved-c9c53311a0b2426adc4b8d0b463edad1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DeSantis</a> and South Carolina Sen. Tim Scott — to <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/05/31/tim-scott-2024-abortion-axios-event" target="_blank" rel="noopener">endorse specific state laws</a> while refusing to say (or simply not addressing) whether they’d sign a similar measure at the national level. Imposing abortion restrictions on the entire country is an especially unpopular move at a moment when many Americans don’t think lawmakers should be doing <em>anything</em> to make it harder to get an abortion.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So as the primary continues, Republican candidates may be forced to endorse stances that they agree with in principle but could hurt them later. And so far, none of the candidates seem to have much of a strategy for convincing Americans that enacting more restrictions on abortion is the right approach.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953856</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Who Gave Up More In The Debt Ceiling Negotiations: Biden Or Republicans?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/who-gave-up-more-in-the-debt-ceiling-negotiations-biden-or-republicans/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Debt Ceiling</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Kevin McCarthy</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/debt-ceiling/" name="">Debt Ceiling</a></p>
						
													<h1>Who Gave Up More In The Debt Ceiling Negotiations: Biden Or Republicans?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p><span>A FiveThirtyEight Chat</span></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 2, 2023, at 8:45 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="SlackChat_060123_v01_DG" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/SlackChat_060123_v01_DG.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/SlackChat_060123_v01_DG.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/SlackChat_060123_v01_DG.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/SlackChat_060123_v01_DG.png?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
						
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/slack-chat/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">politics chat</a>. The transcript below has been lightly edited.</p>



<div><hr><span></span></div>




<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a>, senior reporter): On Wednesday night, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/05/31/politics/house-vote-debt-limit-bill/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the House voted</a> to approve a debt ceiling deal, pulling the country back from a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-default-consequences/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">catastrophic potential default</a>. And on Thursday night, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/06/01/politics/senate-vote-debt-limit-latest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Senate passed the bill too</a>. The deal will <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/29/business/debt-ceiling-agreement.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">suspend the debt limit</a> until the first quarter of 2025, with some cuts to government spending and new work requirements for some recipients of government benefits. There were some dramatic moments — including a <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/05/30/1178878967/mccarthy-house-conservatives-debt-ceiling-deal-vote" target="_blank" rel="noopener">last-minute rebellion</a> from far-right Republicans — but ultimately <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/interactive/2023/house-vote-debt-ceiling-deal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the 314-117 vote in favor of the bill</a> was decisive and bipartisan.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Of course, both houses of Congress had to agree on the deal. But the Republican-controlled House was always going to be the bigger hurdle for both President Biden and Republican House Speaker Kevin McCarthy, who had <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/23/us/politics/mccarthy-democrats-republicans-debt-limit-deal.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a very slim majority</a> to work with. So let’s talk about the political ramifications of the deal-making process and the vote in the House. How did the vote break down among Democrats and Republicans, and were you surprised by anything that happened over the course of the day on Wednesday?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kaleigh Rogers</a>, technology and politics reporter):<strong> </strong>Well, as expected, the outer fringes of both parties were not super stoked about this compromise, since it didn’t fully meet either side’s ideal. That meant it was up to members in the center to get it over the finish line, which they did without too much drama.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Geoffrey Skelley</a>, senior elections analyst): No doubt about that, Kaleigh. If we look at a breakdown <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/Votes/2023243" target="_blank" rel="noopener">of the vote</a>, it turns out that Republicans with more conservative voting records — and from redder districts — were somewhat more likely to vote against the bill than other Republicans. The same was true (although to a lesser extent) for more liberal Democrats from bluer seats, compared with other Democrats.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts </strong>(<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/monica-potts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monica Potts</a>, senior politics reporter):<strong> </strong>I was a bit surprised to see how much of the support for the deal <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/31/us/politics/debt-ceiling-house-vote.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">came from Democrats</a>: 165 Democrats voted for it, while only 149 Republicans did, and 71 Republicans opposed it (compared to 46 Democrats). It’s hard to see how it would have passed without Democratic support, and Kevin McCarthy’s leadership was already shaky. I wonder what this will mean within McCarthy’s own caucus, that he couldn’t get enough support from his own party to pass it without Democratic help. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley</strong>:<strong> </strong>The spin from all directions was interesting yesterday. You had <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/06/01/mccarthy-debt-ceiling-victory-negotiations" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a fair amount</a> of <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/house/4029398-house-debt-ceiling-passage-takeaways/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">press coverage</a> — and many Republicans — casting the vote as proof that McCarthy can successfully lead a narrow House majority <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/20-house-republicans-oppose-mccarthy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after he struggled</a> to become speaker back in January. But then you <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/house-gop-hardliners-trash-debt-limit-bill-party-leaders-try-shore-vot-rcna86687" target="_blank" rel="noopener">had other right-wing voices</a> suggesting the vote was proof <a href="https://twitter.com/russvought/status/1664086804000043009?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that McCarthy is weak</a> because the legislation passed with even more Democratic votes. I suspect it is too early to know for sure! A final judgment on this episode may rest on whether the party’s right flank attempts to force McCarthy out via <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/far-right-members-unhappy-debt-deal-float-threatening-mccarthys-speake-rcna86797" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a motion to vacate the chair</a>, and if such an action receives significant support among the broader GOP caucus.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But at the end of the day, McCarthy did get roughly two-thirds of his caucus to back a debt ceiling hike, which is an accomplishment <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/05/30/1178773376/the-debt-ceiling-compromise-isnt-sitting-well-with-some-conservative-republicans" target="_blank" rel="noopener">given the rhetoric</a> from some in the party who opposed the agreement. (Although that kind of talk is sometimes bluster.) Really, though, McCarthy was always going to need some Democratic votes to get this over the line. That’s frustrating to members on the far right, but an actual bipartisan deal was never going to get their unabashed approval. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>So is this a win for McCarthy? Or not?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>Based on what I laid out above, I guess my early view is that it’s a win for McCarthy. But the size of the win is yet to be determined.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>It’s a modest win for McCarthy. A modest but perhaps slightly larger win for Biden.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts: </strong>The deal is pretty far from the <a href="https://waysandmeans.house.gov/house-republicans-pass-limit-save-grow-act-to-rein-in-wasteful-spending-and-grow-the-economy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Republican version</a> the House passed in April. I would say it’s a bigger win for Biden than for Republicans, but it was sort of a forced crisis in that raising the debt ceiling is just about paying for things already approved by Congress. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>And Biden said he wouldn’t negotiate at all! There are definitely some concessions in the deal to Republicans. Let’s talk a bit about what each side gave up. What made this deal a compromise, and who gave the most?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>That’s the thing, right? Biden was able to get this deal together without conceding a ton to the GOP. But <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/04/20/1170976929/jeff-zients-biden-debt-limit-spending-cuts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">his original position</a> was that this shouldn’t even be a discussion. He started by saying that raising the debt ceiling should be entirely divorced from spending talks, and obviously that didn’t happen. There could be some strategy there — stake out an extreme position so that any minor concession feels like a compromise — but it also sets a precedent for debt ceiling talks down the line as an opportunity for Republicans to squeeze spending cuts out of Democrats in order to do what ought to be a pretty standard bureaucratic function.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts: </strong>On some of the things the sides had to give up: <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/the-gop-wants-to-implement-medicaid-work-requirements-heres-what-that-means" target="_blank" rel="noopener">House Republicans really wanted</a> to add work requirements to Medicaid for <a href="https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/tough-tradeoffs-under-republican-work-requirement-plan-some-people-lose-medicaid-or-states-could-pay-to-maintain-coverage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">some adults</a>, and they had to drop that demand, although they did get an expansion to work requirements in the food stamp program. This has been a Republican goal for a while: Arkansas tried a work-requirement program for Medicaid in 2018 before it was halted by the courts, arguing that the requirements would help <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/debt-ceiling-biden-mccarthy-meeting-white-house/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">people find work</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/03/29/707930567/arkansas-gov-asa-hutchinson-on-medicaid-work-requirement" target="_blank" rel="noopener">move off coverage</a>. That program — and work requirements in general — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/30/progressives-food-aid-requirements-debt-deal-00099290" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are opposed by progressives</a>. It’s worth saying that most studies show that work requirements <a href="https://www.cepr.net/report/the-dismal-economics-of-snaps-work-hours-test-and-time-limit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t increase work participation</a>; instead they actually <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w28877" target="_blank" rel="noopener">decrease participation in safety net programs</a>. A Kaiser Health study of the Arkansas program found that 18,000 people <a href="https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/disability-and-technical-issues-were-key-barriers-to-meeting-arkansas-medicaid-work-and-reporting-requirements-in-2018/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">were kicked off Medicaid in Arkansas</a> while it lasted, many of whom were either not required to work or were already working but had problems meeting the reporting requirements. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>Eh, it probably was untenable for Biden to not give up something without making this more of a crisis. If he had been more strident — or if McCarthy gave less ground — there’d have been a higher chance of the country ending up in default, rather than getting a hard-fought negotiation that, while going down to the last minute, wasn’t necessarily a hair’s breadth from failing. Moreover, McCarthy would have had a very difficult time selling a clean debt ceiling hike to most of his membership, which was necessary for the legislation to reach the floor barring a miracle discharge petition — and it was in Biden’s interest to avoid a calamity just as much as it was for McCarthy. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So yeah, the strategy seems to be: Stake out an early position of “we’re not negotiating,” but in reality negotiate.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts: </strong>I agree with Kaleigh and Geoffrey that in some ways the negotiation itself is a win for Republicans. The idea that the debt ceiling is a tool for negotiating spending cuts has become more normal.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>So … is it fair to say the real winner here was bipartisanship? (I didn’t think bipartisanship was allowed to win anymore!)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>Call me Pollyanna but, honestly, yes. And it’s not a bad look for Biden, who has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/biden-new-year-pitch-bipartisanship-fa34cf2386e48332d1e76cf7a170a1bb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long made his ability to reach across the aisle</a> and find compromise key to his brand.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>There’s not a <a href="https://www.ipr.northwestern.edu/news/2021/the-state-of-bipartisanship.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ton of bipartisanship available</a> these days, but this is a pretty good example of getting a bipartisan result! Despite the closely-divided House, more than two-thirds of each party backed the agreement!</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts: </strong>Maybe I am cynical but I am seeing everyone as a bit of a loser. Plenty of economists have called for an end to the debt ceiling in general: It doesn’t govern future spending, and the U.S. is obligated to meet its financial obligations. Not reaching a deal <a href="https://www.moodysanalytics.com/-/media/article/2023/debt-limit-scenario-update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could have caused a disaster</a>, and I’m not sure anyone got enough of what they wanted to make that flirtation with disaster worth it.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>Yes, in the long run, the debt ceiling — a thing <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/05/24/the-us-isnt-the-only-country-with-a-debt-ceiling-heres-how-denmark-avoids-the-drama.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most other developed countries do not have</a> — should probably go the way of the dodo so we stop doing this every one or two years.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>What’s it going to take for that to happen, though? The danger of default is such an effective bargaining chip.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>It’ll take some sort of one-party action when that party has complete control of the government. But I think the biggest hang-up is the perceived risk of voting for getting rid of the debt ceiling or raising it so high as to be irrelevant.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>It’s a bit like the filibuster in that way. Everyone likes it when they get to wield it, and hates it when it’s wielded against them.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>But are everyday Americans really going to care if the debt ceiling goes bye-bye? As you wrote earlier this week, Kaleigh, <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-spending-cuts-confusing-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">their views on it are pretty muddled</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>I think members in competitive seats, or deep-red seats, are afraid of the ads that would ensue during the next election season. Imagine: “[insert representative] voted to run up debt in this country” with some small type at the bottom of the screen noting the vote. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>It’s definitely a subject <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-spending-cuts-confusing-polls/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the average American says they</a> don’t understand well or follow closely. If Congress were to eliminate the debt ceiling, there would of course be ways to spin it during campaign season to point out how members voted, as you note, Geoffrey, but that’s also true of this vote on the deal.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>ameliatd: </strong>Now we’re talking about our bread and butter: elections. <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/biden-reelection-2024-chances/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biden has just launched his reelection campaign</a>. What — if anything — does the deal mean for his chances in 2024?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>geoffrey.skelley: </strong>Biden <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/28/biden-bipartisan-debt-ceiling-agreement-00099133" target="_blank" rel="noopener">can sell this deal</a> as proof of his bipartisan bona fides and commitment to responsible government vs. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/10/chaos-trump-white-house/616616/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the chaos associated with Trump</a>. So in that way, it may well be useful for his overall profile with <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voters who helped elect him in 2020</a> but aren’t solidly in the Democrats’ camp.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">At the same time, we’re so far from the true 2024 general election campaign that it may not matter a great deal. Avoiding a debt default crisis almost certainly won’t matter as much as an actual crisis would have.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Monica Potts: </strong>I agree with Geoffrey that Biden can sell this as an example of bipartisanship. I don’t know if voters will remember this particular fight, but I think a lot will depend on the overall economy and how people are feeling about their financial situation when they vote. Americans care about how they’re doing financially, so that will matter more than this deal I think.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>kaleigh: </strong>I’d agree with Geoffrey’s last point. This is almost a non-contributing factor to 2024, whereas defaulting on the debt would have been a huge blow to Biden’s campaign. But default would have been a crisis for everybody who is currently in office, so the only way through this was always going to be a compromise.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 13:45:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953855</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Trump Is Polling Much Better Among Very Conservative Primary Voters Than In 2016</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-polls-very-conservative-voters-2016-2024/</link>
						<dc:creator>Michael Tesler</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Michael Tesler</dc:creator>
			<category>2016 Election</category>
			<category>2016 Presidential Election</category>
			<category>2016 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>2024 Presidential Election</category>
			<category>2024 Republican Primary</category>
			<category>Conservatives</category>
			<category>DW-Nominate</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Trump Is Polling Much Better Among Very Conservative Primary Voters Than In 2016</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/michael-tesler/" title="" rel="author">Michael Tesler</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Jun. 1, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="TrumpPollingNumbers4x3_v01_DG" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/TrumpPollingNumbers4x3_v01_DG.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/TrumpPollingNumbers4x3_v01_DG.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/TrumpPollingNumbers4x3_v01_DG.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/TrumpPollingNumbers4x3_v01_DG.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>AP Photo/Alex Brandon</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Shortly before the 2016 presidential primaries began, the influential conservative outlet the National Review devoted an entire edition of its biweekly magazine to making the ideological case “<a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/rnc-strips-national-review-debate-hosting-gig-cover/story?id=36438101" target="_blank" rel="noopener">against Trump</a>.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The issue featured essays from over 20 prominent conservatives explaining why Donald Trump’s campaign was “<a href="https://www.cnn.com/videos/politics/2016/01/22/national-review-magazine-opposes-donald-trump-sot-nr.cnn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a menace to conservatism</a>.” It also included a <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/2016/01/donald-trump-conservative-movement-menace/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">scathing editorial</a> from the National Review’s editors, which disparaged the Republican Party’s then-presidential frontrunner as “a philosophically unmoored political opportunist who would trash the broad conservative ideological consensus within the GOP in favor of a free-floating populism with strong-man overtones.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">With Trump’s campaign rhetoric rejecting the party’s “broad conservative ideological consensus” in favor of heterodox positions on issues from <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/05/11/us/politics/where-trump-breaks-with-the-republican-party.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">government spending</a> to <a href="https://www.cato.org/blog/once-upon-time-all-conservatives-believed-free-market" target="_blank" rel="noopener">restricting free markets</a> to <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/trumps-foreign-policy-views-a-sharp-departure-from-gop-orthodoxy/2016/03/21/6ef0d9f6-efa3-11e5-89c3-a647fcce95e0_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">isolationist foreign policies</a>, it’s not surprising that he <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/03/02/how-political-science-helps-explain-the-rise-of-trump-most-voters-arent-ideologues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">performed relatively poorly</a> with <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/paperback/9780691196435/identity-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“very conservative” voters</a> in the 2016 Republican primaries. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But that prior pattern has now completely reversed itself in early polling on the 2024 Republican primaries. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="'Very conservative' Republicans have warmed to Trump" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/POUyS/6/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="500" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">In a <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/Poll-Release-Legacy?releaseid=2323" target="_blank" rel="noopener">February 2016 poll</a> from Quinnipiac University, Trump received only 27 percent support among Republican and Republican-leaning registered voters who described themselves as “very conservative” — 18 percentage points worse than he did with “somewhat conservative” GOP primary voters. <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3870" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quinnipiac’s March 2023 poll</a>, however, suggests that Trump now has the support of 61 percent of “very conservative” Republican primary voters — 18 points <em>higher</em> than his support among the “somewhat conservatives.”<a data-footnote-id="14" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-14" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2016 survey offered respondents a list of six candidates, and the 2023 survey listed 15 options. Both surveys included some version of “don’t know” and “wouldn’t vote.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>14</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Trump’s strong showing among the most conservative voters shows up in other early polling on the 2024 primaries as well. A late <a href="https://www.surveyusa.com/client/PollReport.aspx?g=1886a8ba-63cb-43c2-a591-ae8e7c391515" target="_blank" rel="noopener">April SurveyUSA Poll</a> of likely primary voters in North Carolina had him winning 72 percent of “very conservative” Republicans, compared with less than half of other Republican voters. Likewise, another <a href="https://www.patrickruffini.com/p/the-six-republican-parties" target="_blank" rel="noopener">late April survey from Echelon Insights</a> showed Trump polling 27 percentage points better among “very conservative” Republicans in head-to-head nationwide primary matchups against Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis than he did with “somewhat conservative” Republicans (77 percent to 50 percent).</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These results raise the question of <em>why</em> the ideology of Trump’s base has changed so dramatically from 2016 to 2023.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are undoubtedly multiple factors at play here, but perhaps the biggest are the profound ways in which <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/trump-and-the-shifting-meaning-of-conservative-using-activists-pairwise-comparisons-to-measure-politicians-perceived-ideologies/EC8511D8EB16CD947D9B5DC8201F0515" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trump’s presidency shifted the meaning of conservatism in U.S. politics</a>. As political scientists Dan Hopkins and Hans Noel documented in a <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-trump-has-redefined-conservatism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previous piece for FiveThirtyEight</a>, Trump has come to define who and what Republican Party activists — that is, people who volunteer for political campaigns, donate money, work for politicians, etc. — think of as conservative. Their research, for instance, found that GOP activists viewed Trump critics like former Sens. Ben Sasse and Patrick Toomey as much less conservative than their voting records in Congress indicated. Meanwhile, GOP activists viewed Trump boosters as the most reliably conservative politicians. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But Trump has also powerfully redefined what constitutes conservatism for rank-and-file Republican voters, according to my analyses of data from <a href="https://cces.gov.harvard.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Cooperative Election Survey</a> — a massive academic survey administered by YouGov that asks over 50,000 respondents every two years to, among other things, rate politicians’ ideologies on a seven-point scale from “very liberal” to “very conservative.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">According to CES data, Republicans nationwide now view Trump as more conservative than they did immediately before the 2016 general election. On the other hand, Utah Republicans perceived Sen. Mitt Romney as a lot less conservative <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/invoking-faith-emotional-mitt-romney-announces-hell-vote/story?id=68779768" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after his February 2020 vote</a> to convict Trump during his first impeachment trial. But that decline pales in comparison to the utter evaporation of former Rep. Liz Cheney’s conservative credentials. Wyoming Republicans repeatedly rated Cheney as a solid conservative in 2016, 2018 and 2020. Yet her reputation as a stalwart conservative vanished entirely after she voted to impeach Trump in January 2021 and subsequently became one of the former president’s most vocal critics in Congress as vice chair of the House committee investigating the Jan. 6 insurrection — so much so, that Wyoming Republicans placed her all the way on the liberal side of the ideological spectrum in the 2022 CES.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Republicans now define 'conservative' as pro-Trump" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/am0ET/6/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="550" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Romney and Cheney are not the only politicians whose conservative bona fides have been questioned after criticizing Trump. The seven Republican senators who voted to convict the former president during his second impeachment trial were all rated as much less conservative than we would otherwise expect from their Senate voting records, as measured by the first dimension of <a href="https://voteview.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DW-NOMINATE</a> — a political science metric that scores congressional voting records from -1 (most liberal) to 1 (most conservative). Even after we control for those voting records, Republican CES respondents, on average, rated the GOP senators who convicted Trump a full category (i.e., “middle of the road” instead of “somewhat conservative” or “conservative” instead of “very conservative”) more liberal than the senators who acquitted him on the CES’s seven-point ideological scale.<a data-footnote-id="15" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-15" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using DW-NOMINATE scores and Republican senator ideology scores from 2022. We looked only at the 50 Republican members of the Senate at the time of Trump’s second impeachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>15</sup></a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Pro-impeachment senators are perceived as more liberal" aria-label="Scatter Plot" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/UQY7x/7/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="650" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">It certainly seems from these results, then, that Trump has not only reshaped the Republican Party in his own image; he has also redefined what it means to be a conservative. So, while an awful lot can change over the course of the primary campaign, it appears that Trump will garner disproportionate support from self-described “very conservative” Republicans in the 2024 primaries. Conservatism, after all, is becoming increasingly synonymous with Trumpism in the minds of GOP voters.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953854</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Are Black And Hispanic Americans Abandoning Biden?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/biden-approval-black-hispanic-voters/</link>
						<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</dc:creator>
			<category>2024 Election</category>
			<category>Black Voters</category>
			<category>Hispanic Voters</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Presidential Approval</category>
			<category>U.S. Economy</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/2024-election/" name="">2024 Election</a></p>
						
													<h1>Are Black And Hispanic Americans Abandoning Biden?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/amelia-thomson-deveaux/" title="" rel="author">Amelia Thomson-DeVeaux</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									May 31, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Union Workers Hold Caravan Rally To Support Joe Biden" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1280955329.jpg?w=968" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1280955329.jpg?w=968" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1280955329.jpg?w=968 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1280955329.jpg?w=1936 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						President Joe Biden’s 2020 campaign was criticized for insufficient outreach to Hispanic voters, as some have drifted toward the GOP in the most recent two elections, and his approval rating among this group appears to have taken further hits since the midterms.													<p>Joe Raedle / Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">President Biden has an enthusiasm problem — <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/so-about-that-supposed-lack-of-enthusiasm-for-biden/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">again</a>. Since he kicked off his reelection bid in late April, asking Americans for another four years to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ChjibtX0UzU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“finish this job,”</a> there’s been plenty of attention to his <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/29/us/politics/black-voters-biden-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">potential</a> <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/04/27/politics/democrats-biden-black-voters-midterms/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">weaknesses</a> among key voting blocs, particularly Black voters. <a href="https://catalist.us/whathappened2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New data</a> from the 2022 midterm elections also reinforces earlier election analysis suggesting that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/30/upshot/midterms-election-black-turnout.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">turnout was down</a> among Black and Hispanic Americans compared to the 2018 midterms, underscoring concerns that support for Biden could be slipping among voters of color.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We took a look at the numbers and found that yes, Biden’s approval has dropped dramatically among Black Americans since he took office in January 2021. But the biggest decline wasn’t among Black Americans: It was among Hispanic Americans. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="Biden has lost ground with Black and Hispanic Americans" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/oiUNX/4/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="600" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">These approval trends, and other recent polls, suggest that while Biden does have reasons to be concerned about tepid interest among Black voters, his problems aren’t confined to this group. During the 2020 election, the Biden campaign was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/latino-groups-warn-that-bidens-sluggish-outreach-could-have-devastating-results/2020/09/13/82dab318-f44b-11ea-bc45-e5d48ab44b9f_story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">criticized for its flawed outreach</a> to Hispanic voters, and key segments of this group, including Hispanic voters living in Miami and the Rio Grande Valley, went on to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/02/us/politics/trump-latino-voters-2020.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">support former President Donald Trump</a> in surprisingly high numbers. Hispanic Americans now may be even less supportive of Biden than Black Americans, exposing another vulnerability for the president as he heads into his reelection campaign. Biden’s approval <em>has</em> recently recovered slightly among Black Americans, though, rising from an average of about 60 percent approval in July 2022 to an average of around 70 percent in April 2023. That improvement coincided with growing optimism among Black Americans about the state of the economy, suggesting that Biden may be able to repair some damage among this key group — particularly if views on the economy continue to improve.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Biden’s overall approval rating <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been underwater</a> since the summer of 2021, falling during the botched withdrawal of troops from Afghanistan and remaining low as inflation surged. Voters of color, in particular, seem disappointed with Biden’s performance, with favorability ratings falling more than 13 percentage points among Black and Hispanic Americans between the spring of 2021 and the spring of 2023.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Apart from the sour economy, voters of color have plenty of reasons to be frustrated with Biden’s first term. He came into office with a string of lofty promises — comprehensive federal <a href="https://www.rev.com/blog/transcripts/joe-biden-racial-equity-plan-speech-transcript-july-28" target="_blank" rel="noopener">voting rights legislation</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/02/08/us/politics/biden-police-state-of-the-union.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">police reform</a>, clear <a href="https://www.rev.com/blog/transcripts/joe-biden-speech-transcript-august-6-national-association-of-latino-elected-officials-conference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pathways to citizenship for immigrants</a> — none of which were enacted during his first two years in office, when Democrats controlled Congress. Now, with Republicans in charge of the House of Representatives, there’s little chance that these policies will pass, leaving Biden with broken promises to answer for. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/05/25/george-floyd-death-anniversary-biden-race-agenda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A recent Ipsos/Washington Post poll found</a> that only 34 percent of Black Americans say that Biden’s policies have helped Black people, while 14 percent say they’ve hurt Black people and nearly half (49 percent) say they haven’t made a difference.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And there’s evidence from recent polls that some voters of color are less likely than Democrats overall to want Biden to run for reelection. For example, <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/qsy7ekuxik/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a YouGov/Economist poll</a> conducted April 29 to May 2 found that less than half (46 percent) of Black respondents and only 37 percent of Hispanic respondents want Biden to run for a second term, compared to 54 percent of Democrats overall. Add that to the fact that Black turnout does seem to have fallen overall in the 2022 midterms, while Republicans maintained their 2020 levels of support among Latinos — plus a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/29/us/politics/black-voters-biden-2024.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent slew</a> of anecdotal reporting about Black voters’ frustration with Biden — and it looks like a fairly bleak picture for the president. After all, Black voters were key to Biden’s primary victory back in 2020, and Trump’s inroads among Hispanic voters <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narrowed Democrats’ margins</a> during the general election, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/27/us/politics/latino-voters-biden-democrats.html?auth=login-email&amp;login=email" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prompting anxiety on the left</a> about the future of the party’s diverse coalition if the trend continues. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">There are two separate worries here. One is that if voters of color are uninspired by Biden, they simply won’t turn out to vote. Democratic activists have long complained that mainstream candidates like Biden <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-catch-22-facing-black-voters-at-the-ballot-box/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">take voters of color for granted</a>, assuming they will continue to vote for Democrats because the Republican Party ignores them at best and is openly hostile to them at worst. But of course, that’s not a fair assumption: People always have the option to simply not vote. And then there’s the possibility that some voters of color could actually flip to Republicans. That’s particularly true of Latinos, a complex constituency with plenty of reasons to consider Republican candidates.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But the situation isn’t as dreary for Biden as it appears — at least, when it comes to Black voters. For one thing, even if Black voters aren’t especially enthusiastic about the idea of a second Biden term, they haven’t soured on him personally. <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/1bt14vgnnc/cbsnews_20230425_1%20%281%29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A YouGov/CBS News poll</a> conducted from April 21-24 found that Black respondents are much likelier (at 76 percent) than Hispanic (55 percent) or white (42 percent) respondents to say they like how Biden handles himself personally. The same poll found that Black respondents (73 percent) are much likelier than white (52 percent) or Hispanic (48 percent) respondents to say they would feel “accepting” about Biden running for reelection, and less likely (13 percent) than white (22 percent) or Hispanic (23 percent) respondents to say they would be “disappointed.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Meanwhile, that YouGov/Economist poll suggests that Black voters continue to see Biden as the Democrats’ strongest candidate: The poll found that 50 percent of Black Americans believe that Biden is the strongest candidate Democrats could nominate for president in 2024, compared to 32 percent of Hispanic respondents and 22 percent of white respondents. And the bottom line from 2022 might not be as bad for Democrats as it seems, at least among Black voters — <a href="https://catalist.us/whathappened2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a recent analysis from the Democratic-leaning firm Catalist</a> found that while Black turnout did fall, levels of Black support for Democrats increased in highly contested races in the South, where Black candidates were running for major offices and Democratic campaigns and organizations focused a significant amount of resources on getting out the vote. (On the other hand, a lack of investment among Black voters in other places may have hurt Democrats in at least one state — in the Wisconsin U.S. Senate election, only 84 percent of Black voters went for the Democrat, down from 90 percent in 2020.)</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Part of Biden’s challenge is that perceptions of the success of his presidency <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/whats-driving-bidens-approval-rating-up/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">are closely tied</a> to how the economy is doing, which is something that’s very hard for the president to control directly. There are some signs that Black and Hispanic Americans’ outlook on the economy is improving — although it’s still far from rosy. <a href="https://civiqs.com/results/economy_us_now?uncertainty=true&amp;annotations=true&amp;zoomIn=true&amp;race=Black%20or%20African-American" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A recent tracking poll from Civiqs</a> shows that less than half (44 percent) of Black Americans say the current condition of the national economy is fairly bad or worse, down from around 57 percent in late June 2022. Hispanic Americans’ view of the economy is more negative, but it’s also improved since last summer.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">So a lot could depend on what happens to the economy over the next year — especially <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/05/10/inflation-slowed-in-april-what-to-expect-for-the-rest-of-2023.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">whether inflation continues to slow</a>, whether the country is able to avoid a recession caused by the federal government’s attempts to curb inflation and whether a debt ceiling deal goes through. If the economy improves, Biden will be in a stronger position overall, and voters of color may be less skeptical about whether he deserves a second term. But whatever happens, it’s clear that the Biden campaign will need to actively engage with Black and Hispanic voters if the president wants to maintain the Democratic Party’s diverse coalition in 2024.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>Additional contributions from Ryan Best, Cooper Burton and Holly Fuong.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953853</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Politics Podcast: There’s A Debt Ceiling Agreement … For Now</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-theres-a-debt-ceiling-agreement-for-now/</link>
						<dc:creator>Galen Druke</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>FiveThirtyEight</dc:creator>
			<category>Debt</category>
			<category>Debt Ceiling</category>
			<category>Deficit Reduction</category>
			<category>FiveThirtyEight Podcasts</category>
			<category>LGBTQ</category>
			<category>Politics Podcast</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div></div>


<div data-href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/politics-podcast-theres-a-debt-ceiling-agreement-for-now/">
	<div data-podcast-id="360298" data-podcast-duration="0" data-podcast-title="Politics Podcast: There's A Debt Ceiling Agreement ... For Now">

					<span><span>FiveThirtyEight</span></span>
			
		
		<button aria-label="Play"></button>

					<div>
		
		
							<div>
					<div>
						<div></div>
					</div>

					<div> </div>

					<audio preload="none" controls="controls">
						<source src="https://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/traffic.megaphone.fm/ESP1634575944.mp3?updated=1685483052">
					</source></audio>
				</div>
			
					</div>
		
	</div>
</div>
<aside>
	<div>
		More: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457">Apple Podcasts</a> |
		<span><a data-android-url="" href="http://m.espn.com/general/cast?id=14554755">ESPN App</a> |</span>
		<a href="https://www.espn.com/espnradio/feeds/rss/podcast.xml?id=14554755">RSS </a>
					| <a href="https://music.amazon.com/podcasts/c1a4c9d6-aa5b-4899-b78a-dd62f240ec29/fivethirtyeight-politics">Amazon Music</a>
							| <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/3C0iP88KSoGZk5KNWmuyF1?si=39a47edc33514971">Spotify</a>
					</div>
	</aside>




<p data-paragraph="main">Over the weekend, the White House and House Speaker Kevin McCarthy announced an agreement to suspend the debt ceiling and make cuts to discretionary spending. According to the Treasury Department, the U.S. will run out of cash to pay its bills on June 5, meaning the clock is ticking for the bill to pass the House, Senate and be signed by President Biden. The bill is expected to be taken up in the House on Wednesday.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In this installment of the FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast, the crew talks about what’s in the agreement, why polls on the debt ceiling have been straight-up contradictory and what could happen if the legislation isn’t passed by next Monday. They also discuss the significant increase in laws involving sexuality and gender in Republican-led states and what Americans think about them. And Galen speaks with senior writer Monica Potts about her new book, “The Forgotten Girls.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>You can listen to the episode by clicking the “play” button in the audio player above or by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>downloading it in iTunes</em></a><em>, the </em><a href="http://www.espn.com/espn/mobile/products/products/_/id/6857590" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>ESPN App</em></a><em> or your favorite podcast platform. If you are new to podcasts, </em><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/how-to-listen-to-fivethirtyeight-podcasts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>learn how to listen</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><em>The FiveThirtyEight Politics podcast is recorded Mondays and Thursdays. Help new listeners discover the show by </em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/fivethirtyeight-elections/id1077418457?mt=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>leaving us a rating and review on iTunes</em></a><em>. Have a comment, question or suggestion for “good polling vs. bad polling”? Get in touch by email, </em><a href="https://twitter.com/FiveThirtyEight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>on Twitter</em></a><em> or in the comments.</em></p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 22:42:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953851</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why Debt Ceiling Polls Keep Giving Us Conflicting Results</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-spending-cuts-confusing-polls/</link>
						<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Kaleigh Rogers</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Debt Ceiling</category>
			<category>Donald Trump</category>
			<category>Drugs</category>
			<category>Economy</category>
			<category>Government Spending</category>
			<category>Inflation</category>
			<category>Pollapalooza</category>
			<category>Polls</category>
			<category>Supreme Court</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" name="">Pollapalooza</a></p>
						
													<h1>Why Debt Ceiling Polls Keep Giving Us Conflicting Results</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/kaleigh-rogers/" title="" rel="author">Kaleigh Rogers</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									May 30, 2023, at 10:21 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="Pola_DebtCeiling_4x3_v04_ag" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Pola_DebtCeiling_4x3_v04_ag.png?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Pola_DebtCeiling_4x3_v04_ag.png?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Pola_DebtCeiling_4x3_v04_ag.png?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Pola_DebtCeiling_4x3_v04_ag.png?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>ABC News photo illustration</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">Welcome to <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/pollapalooza/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pollapalooza</a>, our weekly-ish polling roundup.</p>


<div><hr><span></span></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">The White House and Speaker of the House <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/29/business/debt-ceiling-agreement.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have come to a tentative</a> — though as yet <a href="https://www.msnbc.com/rachel-maddow-show/maddowblog/striking-debt-ceiling-deal-one-thing-passing-another-rcna86762" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unpassed</a> — agreement for raising the debt ceiling. But does this agreement match what Americans have been hoping for in this crisis? Yes, it does. Also, no, it does not. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">If you think <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-chat-political-consequences/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congress and the White House have been divided</a> on how to resolve the <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/videos/whats-the-deal-with-the-fight-over-the-debt-ceiling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">debt ceiling crisis</a>, wait until you see what the American people think about it. Over the past few weeks, pollsters have attempted to capture where Americans stand on this contentious economic battle, and the results are as clear as mud. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This was illustrated quite dramatically last Tuesday, when two polls on the debt ceiling were released with wildly different results. In one, from <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2023/05/23/politics/cnn-poll-debt-ceiling-increase-spending-cuts/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SSRS/CNN</a>, 60 percent of Americans said Congress shouldn’t raise the debt ceiling unless it cuts spending at the same time. In the other, from <a href="https://maristpoll.marist.edu/polls/raising-the-u-s-debt-ceiling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marist/NPR/PBS NewsHour</a>, 52 percent of Americans said Congress should raise the debt ceiling first and worry about spending cuts separately. The headline takeaways were in direct opposition: A majority of Americans say the debt ceiling should be raised with spending cuts … and also a majority of Americans say the debt ceiling should be raised without spending cuts. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">These two polls are just the tip of the iceberg. For every recent poll finding on Americans’ views of the debt ceiling debate, there seemed to be a poll showing just the opposite. In a <a href="https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2023/5/5/voters-want-congress-to-act-quickly-on-the-debt-limit-and-believe-we-should-raise-taxes-on-the-wealthy-rather-than-sacrifice-essential-government-programs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Data For Progress poll</a> from May 3-4, a majority of likely voters (58 percent) said Congress should act as soon as possible to raise the debt ceiling and not “waste time” negotiating on spending. But in a <a href="https://tippinsights.com/voters-even-dems-want-budget-cuts-not-tax-hikes-i-i-tipp-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TIPP/Issues &amp; Insights poll</a> from May 3-5, a plurality of Americans (46 percent) said Congress should raise the debt ceiling in exchange for spending cuts. Meanwhile, 58 percent of U.S. adults said debt payments and federal spending should be handled as separate issues, according to an <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/05/05/debt-ceiling-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ABC News/Washington Post poll</a> conducted April 28-May 3. But then, 60 percent of registered voters said Congress should only raise the debt ceiling with spending restraints, according to a May 17-18 <a href="https://harvardharrispoll.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/HHP_May2023_KeyResults.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">poll from Harris/Harvard CAPS.</a></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">OK, so Americans’ views on whether raising the debt ceiling should be tied to spending caps vary a lot by poll. But the one thing they can all agree on is that, one way or the other, the debt ceiling needs to be raised, right? Er … about that … </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In a <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/ved8z2hzyt/20230508_yahoo_tabs.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouGov/Yahoo News survey</a> from early May, 40 percent of Americans said they were in favor of raising the debt limit, while 35 percent were opposed and 25 percent were unsure. An <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2023-05/2023%20Reuters%20Ipsos%20Tracking%20-%20Core%20Political%20Presidential%20Approval%20Tracker%20May%202023.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ipsos/Reuters poll conducted May 5-7</a> Uno-reverso’d those results — 43 percent of Americans supported raising the ceiling, while 54 percent opposed it. And when YouGov, in early May, tried <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/riblsd67kk/crosstabs_Debt%20Ceiling.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presenting respondents with a more detailed explanation</a> of what raising the debt ceiling entails before asking them if they supported or opposed it, Americans were evenly divided: 39 percent for raising the debt ceiling, 40 percent against it. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Whew! OK, so — what the heck is going on?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">First of all, this isn’t anything new: Congress has had debt limit fights in the past, and <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/what-americans-think-about-the-fight-over-the-debt-ceiling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public opinion polling was just as conflicted then</a> as it is now. Second, many of the discrepancies can be explained by simple differences in question wording. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The wording of questions on the debt ceiling, even when ostensibly measuring the same sentiments, varied widely from poll to poll. In the ABC News/Washington Post poll, for example, the question about whether to raise the debt ceiling with or without spending cuts <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/tablet/2023/05/05/april-28-may-3-2023-washington-post-abc-news-poll/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">opened with a brief synopsis of the situation</a>: “Congress typically passes legislation on a regular basis to allow the government to pay its debts. Without this step, the government could default on its debts.” That might have primed most respondents to say that the issues of debt payment and federal spending should be handled separately. Meanwhile, in the Harris/Harvard CAPS poll, the question led with, “The current size of the national debt is $31 trillion.” That might have steered respondents toward saying that Congress should raise the debt ceiling only with restraints on future spending.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The polls’ different samples may also have contributed to the different results. Some populations may be more engaged on the topic than others. For example, likely voters (like the ones queried by Data for Progress) might be likelier than all adults (like the ones queried by TIPP) to be aware of the consequences of a default. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">But perhaps the biggest factor is how complex of an issue the debt limit fight is — and how poorly many Americans understand it. Let’s go back to that YouGov poll from early May. The pollster quizzed respondents on the correct definition of the debt ceiling: Is it a limit on government spending or a limit on the government’s borrowing to finance spending that already has been approved? While about half of Americans (52 percent) correctly chose the latter definition, a quarter chose the incorrect one, and another 18 percent said they weren’t sure. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Furthermore, in a <a href="https://www.monmouth.edu/polling-institute/reports/monmouthpoll_us_052423/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monmouth University poll</a> conducted May 18-23 — just last week! — fewer than half of Americans (45 percent) said they had heard “a lot” about the debt ceiling debate, while 40 percent had heard “a little” and 15 percent had heard “nothing at all.” And in an <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/few-are-following-the-debate-closely-but-most-want-congress-to-increase-the-debt-limit-with-deficit-reduction-conditions/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=few-are-following-the-debate-closely-but-most-want-congress-to-increase-the-debt-limit-with-deficit-reduction-conditions" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Associated Press/NORC Center for Public Affairs Research poll</a> conducted May 11-15, just 21 percent of U.S. adults said they were following the negotiations over the debt ceiling “extremely closely” or “very closely,” and 20 percent said they understood the situation “extremely well” or “very well.” </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Instead, partisan breakdowns of the polling results show many Americans’ views line up with their party’s perspective. Given how volatile the results are, and the fact that few Americans say they are following the topic closely or understand it well, this suggests Americans <a href="https://twitter.com/aedwardslevy/status/1661122764214771715" target="_blank" rel="noopener">don’t have strong, fixed opinions on this issue</a>, making them even more susceptible to partisan messaging. </p>



<h2><strong>Other polling bites</strong></h2>



<ul>
<li>Amid <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/clarence-thomas-harlan-crow-real-estate-scotus">recent reporting that has raised questions</a> (and prompted <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/23/us/politics/harlan-crow-clarence-thomas-judiciary-committee.html">a Senate inquiry</a>) about ethical standards on the Supreme Court, just-released polling results from last year show public confidence in the high court reached an all-time low in 2022. Just 18 percent of U.S. adults said they had a “great deal” of confidence in the Supreme Court, while 46 percent said they had “some” and 36 percent said “hardly any,” according to the <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/public-confidence-in-the-u-s-supreme-court-is-at-its-lowest-since-1973/">General Social Survey by the Associated Press/NORC</a>. This is the lowest confidence level since the GSS began tracking confidence in the court in 1973. Justice Clarence Thomas (who is at the center of the ethics scandals), in particular, is unpopular. A recent <a href="https://law.marquette.edu/poll/category/poll-release/">Marquette Law School poll</a> found Thomas had a net favorability of -11 percentage points, making him the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/05/24/clarence-thomas-unfavorable-ratings/">least popular justice on the court</a>.</li>



<li>Despite inflation <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2023/05/10/business/cpi-inflation-fed">slowing for the 10th month in a row</a> in April, more Americans say they’re feeling the pinch of rising prices. Sixty-one percent of Americans said recent price increases have caused a financial hardship for their household, according to a <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/505928/say-inflation-causing-financial-hardship.aspx">Gallup poll conducted April 3-17</a>. This is up 6 points since the last time Gallup surveyed on this question in November 2022 and is the highest since the pollster started asking in November 2021. Lower-income Americans were more likely than middle- and upper-income Americans to report that price increases have caused a hardship, and they were also more likely to report that the hardship is severe enough to affect their ability to maintain their standard of living. </li>



<li>Former President Donald Trump’s supporters have an image problem, according to a <a href="https://tippinsights.com/can-trump-escape-the-maga-extremist-label-i-i-tipp-poll/">TIPP/Issues &amp; Insights poll from May 3-5</a>. When asked whether they “agree or disagree with describing Trump supporters as MAGA extremists,” 50 percent of U.S. adults agreed, including 24 percent of Republicans. </li>



<li>The majority of Americans say they’ve never taken any psychedelics … but those who have tried magic mushrooms say they had a pretty good time. A <a href="https://docs.cdn.yougov.com/w0tzky5izb/crosstabs_Psychedelics.pdf">YouGov survey conducted May 16-19</a> asked U.S. adults if they had ever tried LSD (acid), psilocybin (magic mushrooms), MDMA, DMT, mescaline (peyote), Ketamine, or Salvia. Sixty-eight percent said they hadn’t tried any of the psychedelics, while 12 percent had tried acid, 12 percent had tried ’shrooms and 10 percent had taken MDMA. But among those who had tried psilocybin, 83 percent said they had a somewhat or very positive experience. As more states <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/us-states-considering-legalization-psychedelic-mushrooms-therapeutic-use">consider legalizing or decriminalizing</a> certain psychedelics such as psilocybin, perhaps these numbers will shift. (Or if you’re currently on a psychedelic, they might be shifting all over the room right now.) </li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Biden approval</strong></h2>



<figure><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1150" height="920" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/biden-approval-rating-2.png" alt="" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/biden-approval-rating-2.png" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=712 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/biden-approval-rating-2.png?w=1424 2x"></figure>



<p data-paragraph="main"><br>According to FiveThirtyEight’s <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/biden-approval-rating/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">presidential approval tracker</a>,<a data-footnote-id="16" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-16" data-footnote-content="&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 9 a.m. Eastern on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;"><sup>16</sup></a> 41.5 percent of Americans approve of the job Biden is doing as president, while 54.8 percent disapprove (a net approval rating of -13.3 points). At this time last week, 42.1 percent approved and 53.5 percent disapproved (a net approval rating of -11.3 points). One month ago, Biden had an approval rating of 43.0 percent and a disapproval rating of 52.5 percent, for a net approval rating of -9.5 points.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 15:21:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953850</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How Bad Could A Government Default Get?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/debt-ceiling-default-consequences/</link>
						<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Monica Potts</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Debt Ceiling</category>
			<category>Democrats</category>
			<category>Economy</category>
			<category>Joe Biden</category>
			<category>Republicans</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/debt-ceiling/" name="">Debt Ceiling</a></p>
						
													<h1>How Bad Could A Government Default Get?</h1>
																			<h2>Hint: Ordinary Americans will be hurt almost immediately.</h2>
											</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/monica-potts/" title="" rel="author">Monica Potts</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									May 26, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img decoding="async" alt="DebtCeiling_4x3_Horiz_v08_ag" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/DebtCeiling_4x3_Horiz_v08_ag.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/DebtCeiling_4x3_Horiz_v08_ag.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/DebtCeiling_4x3_Horiz_v08_ag.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/DebtCeiling_4x3_Horiz_v08_ag.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>ABC News photo illustration</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">With less than a week until the U.S. runs out of cash, economists and policymakers are using words like “<a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/world/heres-what-would-happen-to-the-global-economy-if-the-u-s-defaults-on-its-debt#:~:text=A%20default%20could%20shatter%20the,and%20ignite%20an%20international%20crisis." target="_blank" rel="noopener">cataclysmic event</a>” and “<a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/yellen-warns-of-economic-calamity-if-congress-doesnt-raise-debt-limit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">calamity</a>” to describe what will happen if Congress doesn’t raise the debt limit. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">It seems bad. <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/world/heres-what-would-happen-to-the-global-economy-if-the-u-s-defaults-on-its-debt#:~:text=A%20default%20could%20shatter%20the,and%20ignite%20an%20international%20crisis." target="_blank" rel="noopener">Economists are predicting</a> that if the government is unable to pay its bills, it could bring much of the global financial system to a halt. But everyday people will be affected too. So who would a failure to raise the debt limit hurt first — and who would be hurt the most?</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">You can think of the impact of the default as a sinkhole, pulling down the people closest to the epicenter first but spreading out to more and more people until (depending on how long it lasts) it finally engulfs the U.S. economy. The first people who are likely to be affected are those who get money directly from the government, including government employees and recipients of government direct payments, like retirees, veterans and disabled Americans who rely on social security income. Soon, though, the government’s inability to pay its bills might hit health care providers who are reimbursed through Medicare and Medicaid. Homebuyers, too, could get hit by higher interest rates, making it even more difficult for them to purchase houses in an already-competitive market. All of this adds up to a potential economic slowdown that could cause a severe recession if the crisis drags on.</p>



<h2><strong>People and organizations who get paid by the government</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">The looming crisis is simple: If the Treasury were to hit the debt limit, it would no longer be able to borrow money — even to make good on debts <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/2023/04/24/how-worried-should-we-be-if-the-debt-ceiling-isnt-lifted/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Congress has already incurred</a>. That means it wouldn’t bring in enough money to meet all of its obligations, forcing the government to make decisions about where available cash should go. If a default happens, the government is likely to prioritize monthly Treasury interest payments that preserve its ability to borrow in the future and minimize chaos in the financial markets, according to <a href="https://www.moodysanalytics.com/-/media/article/2023/debt-limit-scenario-update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a Moody’s Analytics report</a> published earlier this month. When making tradeoffs about which of its financial obligations to fulfill, direct payments to people and institutions who rely on government money could be affected. (An additional complication is that <a href="https://bipartisanpolicy.org/blog/life-after-debt-limit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prioritizing some payments</a> over others <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/lawsuit-yellen-should-ignore-unconstitutional-debt-limit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">may not be legal</a>, so the government could face a raft of lawsuits.) </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">A lot of people rely on the government to pay its bills on time. There are <a href="https://www.fedscope.opm.gov/ibmcognos/bi/v1/disp?b_action=powerPlayService&amp;m_encoding=UTF-8&amp;BZ=1AAABlt0x0I142n1OwW6CQBT8mX3YHmrePmSLBw7L7hJJKljh3lBcrSmwBrn49w1wsO3BmbxkMm8mGa~Il0WZ702qo_vgepvqJyA6cyWFetVKGIpXGIhYCCniQIR_yKUJEYievbFr5F5tdrLcREBJ7brBdgNQcnTNwfYQxLDCrmot_Hqxq_rv6mSvH6a9NO7W2m5YQKCBksv8_Ru~p4DwBQi3VV9~ASEh0Vj0dKGWKs8yo8o0zzK5NdHDkhe~R0dExhGRc2SMIQuQEbKRjMmT7eobEAIdgFA2DeD6zdXVcHbdP5sBhUA_AlkO9Am0ng1_N9gEIH_M~wKfOKl5zHTzhBk~yS1m1w%3D%3D" target="_blank" rel="noopener">almost 2 million</a> federal government employees whose direct income could be affected. That doesn’t include the roughly 1.3 million active-duty military personnel, <a href="https://demographics.militaryonesource.mil/chapter-1-total-military-force" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as of last count</a>, and an additional <a href="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/press-releases/2021/veterans-report.html#:~:text=Nearly%203.9%20million%20veterans%20(19.5,600%2C000%20veterans%20received%20pension%20payments" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3.9 million veterans who receive</a> disability support. The <a href="https://www.govexec.com/management/2021/10/what-debt-default-would-mean-federal-agencies-and-their-employees/185866/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">government could furlough or lay off workers</a> in an effort to save money during a debt-ceiling crisis, leaving many of these people without an income. These tradeoffs could start to happen immediately, since one of the first bills that’s coming due is $12 billion in promised veterans’ benefits on June 1, and an additional $5 billion in federal salaries and insurance is scheduled to be paid out on June 9, <a href="https://bipartisanpolicy.org/download/?file=/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Debt-Limit-Analysis-May-2023.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to an analysis</a> by the Bipartisan Policy Center.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Additionally, just about <a href="https://www.ssa.gov/OACT/FACTS/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">66 million Americans</a> received some form of social security benefit, like retirement or disability income, as of the end of 2022. That number <a href="https://www.cbpp.org/research/social-security/social-security-disability-insurance" target="_blank" rel="noopener">included 7.6 million</a> disabled workers who receive Social Security Disability Insurance. Federal policy already limits the ability of recipients to save, because of asset limits, and the amount of additional income allowed, so going without any one check could pose a severe hardship, said Kimberly Knackstedt, director of the Disability Economic Justice Team at the left-leaning The Century Foundation. “That sort of insecurity of, ‘Is this check that’s already not enough to get housing and food going to come this month, or is it not,’ is causing serious concern for us and for people around the country,” Knackstedt said.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Almost <a href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/pdf/empsit.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">6 million people are receiving unemployment</a> payments, too. While unemployment insurance is administered by the states, it relies on federal money that could also be disrupted, according to Bernard Yaros, an economist at Moody’s Analytics who focuses on federal fiscal policy. The government has multiple Social Security payments set throughout the month of June, according to the BPC analysis, which could be delayed.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">And it’s not just individuals who rely on government payments. Industries that contract with the federal government, like the aerospace industry and defense contractors, are vulnerable, <a href="https://www.moodysanalytics.com/-/media/article/2023/debt-limit-scenario-update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to Moody’s</a>. Health care institutions <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2023/05/22/what-a-debt-ceiling-breach-could-mean-for-health-care-00098077" target="_blank" rel="noopener">could also suffer</a>, especially small and rural hospitals, because they rely on Medicaid and Medicare payments for much of their revenue. States heavily reliant on these industries, like Virginia, could see hits to their local economy that might be bigger than the impact on the country as a whole. </p>



<h2><strong>Homebuyers</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Homebuyers would also be hard hit. The housing market, <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/econres/notes/feds-notes/house-price-growth-and-inflation-during-covid-19-20221117.html#:~:text=House%20prices%20have%20risen%20rapidly,highest%20level%20in%20many%20decades." target="_blank" rel="noopener">walloped by dramatic ups and downs during the COVID-19 pandemic</a>, is just reaching a tenuous stability. Mortgage interest rates <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/MORTGAGE30US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remain high</a>, which has kept some buyers out of the market, but there are just enough buyers and sellers to see some activity. <a href="https://www.zillow.com/research/debt-ceiling-32626/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">That could all change with a crash</a>, which is what might happen if large numbers of people are suddenly pushed out of the market by higher rates. Jeff Tucker, a senior economist at the real-estate marketplace Zillow, estimated that rates could go up by an additional 2 percentage points. If that happened, he said, “the housing market would get pushed down further 23 percent from … the pace we were expecting for this summer.”</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moreover, homebuying <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/research/rethinking-homeownership-incentives-to-improve-household-financial-security-and-shrink-the-racial-wealth-gap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remains an important wealth-building tool</a>, and it’s already been a market where <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/03/realestate/housing-market-buyer-wealth-race.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">those looking for affordable options have struggled to gain a foothold</a>. A longer default could mean that rates remain high for a while, making it even more difficult for non-wealthy people to buy. “I think the longer term impact there will be to widen inequality from a wealth-building perspective,” Tucker said. White adults are already much more likely to be able to afford a home, and the median age of first-time homebuyers is rising. A debt default crisis would make that problem worse just as a diverse generation of millennials enters prime home-buying years, he said.</p>



<h2><strong>The entire economy</strong></h2>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then there’s the threat to the broader economy, which isn’t as direct, but is still very serious. Think about it this way: In addition to the tumult that’s likely to ensue in the financial markets, if all of the people who rely on the government for payments are suddenly struggling, then those effects will ripple out to the economy, because they and the other recipients of government payments won’t be buying goods and services to the same degree. That’s part of the reason economists warn that a debt default could create a recession, even if the crisis is short. A prolonged crisis could have severe consequences, especially because the economy is already fragile. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Moody’s calculated the result of a short debt-ceiling breach as a 0.7 percent decline in real GDP, 1.5 million jobs lost and an unemployment rate that nears 5 percent. But a debt-ceiling breach that lasts through July would cause “economic carnage.” The Moody’s report forecasts real GDP would fall by 4.6 percent in the second half of this year, and an unemployment rate that rises to 8 percent. The downturn could have lasting effects in the form of higher interest rates and reduced growth throughout the next decade.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">In all, though, the financial credibility of the American government itself could be seriously harmed — which could have long-term economic impacts on ordinary people too. In 2011, a similar debt-ceiling fight led <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/sandp-considering-first-downgrade-of-us-credit-rating/2011/08/05/gIQAqKeIxI_story.html?itid=lk_inline_manual_17" target="_blank" rel="noopener">S&amp;P to downgrade the U.S.’s credit rating</a>, and something like that could happen again, costing taxpayers money. (Indeed, Fitch, a major credit-rating agency, <a href="https://www.fitchratings.com/research/sovereigns/fitch-places-united-states-aaa-on-rating-watch-negative-24-05-2023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has already issued a warning</a>.) Once it defaults on its debts, even for a short while, a message about the faith the world can have in the U.S.’s political and financial systems will already have been sent. “You would be forgiven if you looked at all the data right now and said, ‘Oh, the consumer is resilient. The economy is resilient. We can, it can withstand this brinksmanship,’” Yaros said. But inflation is still high, and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2023/04/27/recession-gdp-slow-economy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">risk of a recession is just under the surface</a>, which means the economy could already be headed toward a downturn in the year to come. “The debt limit would just accelerate that, or it would just pour kerosene on,” he said. </p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1686271500953849</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The House Is About To Have 435 Members. That’s Pretty Rare.</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/house-435-members-pretty-rare/</link>
						<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Geoffrey Skelley</dc:creator>
			<category>Congress</category>
			<category>Full Count</category>
			<category>House of Representatives</category>
			<category>Resignation</category>
			<category>Retirements</category>
			<category>Scandals</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/house-of-representatives/" name="">House of Representatives</a></p>
						
													<h1>The House Is About To Have 435 Members. That's Pretty Rare.</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/geoffrey-skelley/" title="" rel="author">Geoffrey Skelley</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Mar. 7, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img alt="Virginia State Sen. Jennifer McClellan" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/GettyImages-1245793439-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/GettyImages-1245793439-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/GettyImages-1245793439-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/GettyImages-1245793439-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
						When she’s sworn in as the new representative for Virginia’s 4th Congressional District, state Sen. Jennifer McClellan will be the 435th seated member of the House.													<p>Ryan M. Kelly for The Washington Post via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">When Virginia state Sen. Jennifer McClellan is sworn into the House of Representatives <a href="https://uploads.disquscdn.com/images/a878c18b95cb7701f2773f193c296a4a19fd2f5784a9bc34e0ce61a9d17b9d8c.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this evening</a>, Congress’s lower chamber will be something it hasn’t been in a long time: full.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">The last time the U.S. had a full House — with all 435 of its voting representatives seated — was nearly three and a half years ago. And even then, it wasn’t full for long. When Wisconsin Rep. Sean Duffy <a href="https://bioguide.congress.gov/search/bio/D000614" target="_blank" rel="noopener">resigned on</a> Sept. 23, 2019, <a href="https://www.jsonline.com/story/news/politics/2019/08/26/sean-duffy-says-hes-leaving-congress-september/2120442001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to care for his newborn baby</a> with a heart defect, he left a House that had had 435 members for all of six days. In the 1,261 days since, there’s been at least one empty seat in the House.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"></p><div><iframe title="The House will be full for the first time since 2019" aria-label="Interactive line chart" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/D2Pff/7/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" height="538" data-external="1" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin"></iframe></div>



<p data-paragraph="main">Though this has been an unusually long run in modern times, the timing and number of vacancies generally come down to chance. Members <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/more-people-are-resigning-from-congress-than-at-any-time-in-recent-history/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sometimes resign and leave office</a> before their terms expire, whether for another work opportunity (inside government or outside) or because of a scandal. Less predictable circumstances, like a member’s health problems or even death, also affect whether the House is at capacity. The current Congress (the 118th) began with one seat empty because Virginia Rep. Donald McEachin won reelection in November 2022 but died <a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-and-regional/govt-and-politics/tonight-he-lost-that-battle-congressman-donald-mceachin-dies-at-61/article_a43716c5-1c6b-53db-a601-17fb27c6f8fc.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">later that month</a>; McClellan was elected on Feb. 21 to fill his old seat. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/biden-vulnerable-primary-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-97670358</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">And when vacancies happen to overlap, it can produce periods like the current run of musical chairs. Duffy’s resignation came less than a week after the House got back to full strength for the first time since January 2017 (about two and a half years). Wisconsin’s governor scheduled a special election for May 2020 to fill Duffy’s seat, but <a href="https://www.wpr.org/tiffany-wins-northwoods-special-election-congress" target="_blank" rel="noopener">by the time of that contest</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/30/nyregion/rep-chris-collins-ny-insider-trading.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">five other</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2019/10/27/rep-katie-hill-to-resign-amid-allegations-of-inappropriate-relationships-with-staffers-000301" target="_blank" rel="noopener">seats had</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/01/07/rep-duncan-hunter-resigns-from-congress-095725" target="_blank" rel="noopener">become vacant</a> <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/rep-mark-meadows-resigns-congress-take-chief-staff-role-n1172621" target="_blank" rel="noopener">due to resignations</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2019/10/17/elijah-cummings-dies-baltimore/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">or deaths</a>.<a data-footnote-id="2" href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-json/wp/v2/espn_verticals/398#fn-2" data-footnote-content='&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four of those five vacancies didn’t have special elections before the Wisconsin one. But in Maryland’s 7th District, Rep. Elijah Cummings died on Oct. 17, 2019, and Rep. Kweisi Mfume won a April 28, 2020, &lt;a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/politics/elections/bs-md-pol-7th-congressional-district-election-20200428-bo7fnkygqbhwtnbiqgz52xmu2e-story.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;special election to succeed&lt;/a&gt; Cummings — two weeks before the special election for Duffy’s old seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;'><sup>2</sup></a> And while the 2020 general election held elections for 435 seats, two were left vacant at the start of the 117th Congress due to <a href="https://www.wbrz.com/news/congressman-luke-letlow-moved-to-icu-for-covid-19-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the death of</a> Louisiana Rep.-elect Luke Letlow in December 2020 and an extremely close election in New York’s 22nd District <a href="https://www.syracuse.com/politics/2021/02/rep-claudia-tenney-sworn-into-office-to-represent-ny-22-in-congress.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">that delayed the seating</a> of Rep. Claudia Tenney. In the spring of 2021, appointments to President Biden’s administration opened up seats in <a href="https://www.thenewsstar.com/story/news/2021/01/20/louisiana-political-heavyweights-seek-replace-congressman-cedric-richmond-march-20-election/4221132001/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Louisiana</a>, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2021/03/15/977558590/deb-haaland-confirmed-as-first-native-american-interior-secretary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New Mexico</a> and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/10/politics/marcia-fudge-confirmed-hud-secretary/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ohio</a>, and a host of other resignations and deaths occurred — <a href="https://www.wral.com/butterfield-leaving-congress-a-few-days-early-for-dc-law-firm/20649319/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">even in the</a> last few <a href="https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-168/issue-204/house-section/article/H10549-6?q=%7B%22search%22%3A%5B%22resignation+AND+%5C%22mike+doyle%5C%22%22%5D%7D&amp;s=2&amp;r=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">days of the</a> outgoing Congress in December 2022.</p>


<div></div>


<p data-paragraph="main">But one trend that isn’t necessarily down to chance may also be contributing to lengthier vacancies, which reduces the likelihood of having all 435 seats filled. States <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-some-house-districts-wont-have-a-representative-for-almost-a-year/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">have been taking longer</a> to hold special elections for vacancies than in the past — both because elections now need more lead time because of laws regarding overseas balloting and expanded mail voting, but also because of governors’ political maneuvering to delay filling a seat likely to go to the opposition party.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Before we get too comfortable, however, this full House is going to turn into a weaker poker hand pretty soon. That’s because Rep. David Cicilline of Rhode Island <a href="https://www.providencejournal.com/story/news/politics/2023/02/21/rep-david-cicilline-resigning-house-seat-congress-will-lead-rhode-island-foundation/69926910007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announced on Feb. 21</a> that he would resign effective June 1 to become CEO of the Rhode Island Foundation. It’s unclear when Rhode Island <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/meetthepressblog/r-special-election-date-will-wait-cicilline-vacates-seat-rcna71611" target="_blank" rel="noopener">will hold a special election for Cicilline’s seat</a>, but it might not be until later this year. If that’s the case, that would leave plenty of time for <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorkers-arent-the-only-ones-who-really-dislike-george-santos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">other members to resign</a> — or for something unexpected to occur. One way or the other, though, it seems like our full House won’t last very long.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/poll-ended-dilbert-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-97670065</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1678243500842456</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Does It Matter Where COVID-19 Came From?</title>
			<link>https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/covid-lab-leak/</link>
						<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<dc:creator>Maggie Koerth</dc:creator>
			<category>China</category>
			<category>Coronavirus</category>
			<category>COVID-19</category>
			<description><![CDATA[<div>

			<div>

				<header>
					<div>
													<p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/covid-19/" name="">COVID-19</a></p>
						
													<h1>Does It Matter Where COVID-19 Came From?</h1>
																	</div>

										<div>
						<div>
															<p>By <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/contributors/maggie-koerth/" title="" rel="author">Maggie Koerth</a></p>
																					<p>
								<time>
									Mar. 7, 2023, at 6:00 AM								</time>
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
													</div> 
					</div>
					
				</header>

				
		<figure>
			<span>
									<div>
						<picture>
															<source media="(min-width: 768px)">
							
															<source>
								<img alt="A staff works in the pop-up Huoyan Laboratory specialized in the nucleic acid test on 2019-nCoV in Wuhan" src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1199139684-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1080px) 66vw, 684px" data-src="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1199139684-4x3-1.jpg?w=916" data-srcset="https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1199139684-4x3-1.jpg?w=916 1x, https://fivethirtyeight.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/GettyImages-1199139684-4x3-1.jpg?w=1832 2x">
													</source></source></picture>
					</div>

				
			</span>

			
								<figcaption>
																			<p>Feature China / Future Publishing via Getty Images</p>
											</figcaption>
							
		</figure>

		
			</div>

			
		</div>





<p data-paragraph="main">The Department of Energy says COVID-19 was caused by a lab leak. But that doesn’t mean COVID-19 was definitely caused by a lab leak. In fact, the agency’s report, which made headlines last week, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/02/28/1160157977/u-s-dept-of-energy-says-with-low-confidence-that-covid-may-have-leaked-from-a-la" target="_blank" rel="noopener">states it has “low confidence” in its own conclusion</a>. Scientific evidence, on the other hand, has <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abp8715" target="_blank" rel="noopener">overwhelmingly pointed</a> toward <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2023/02/28/1160162845/what-does-the-science-say-about-the-origin-of-the-sars-cov-2-pandemic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a natural spillover from animals to humans</a> — the same origin of <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2014/04/how-dangerous-viruses-could-escape-from-laboratories.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nearly every other outbreak</a> in history and <a href="https://news.un.org/en/story/2022/07/1122522" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a growing threat</a>. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">What this DOE report <em>does</em> prove is that COVID-19’s origins have become extremely politicized. With congressional hearings, a federal advisory board and government reports pitting the conclusions of the U.S. intelligence community against the conclusions of scientists, it raises the question – if a lab leak were the true origin of COVID-19, would it change how we prepare for pandemics? Clearly, a sizable portion of the American political system is engaged with the idea that proving COVID-19 began with a lab leak matters. But <em>why</em> does it matter? Is it motivated by the political goal of assigning blame or the public health goal of planning for the future? </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">This is not, after all, the first time scientists have thought about lab safety. Or the first time anyone has talked about, or implemented, biosecurity regulations. We spoke to Angela Rasmussen, a virologist and one of the scientists investigating COVID-19’s origins, to understand how scientists were thinking about lab safety before the pandemic politicized it — and what needs to happen to protect the world from pandemics, wherever they might come from. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>Maggie Koerth: Whether COVID-19 came from a lab leak or if it was a zoonotic spillover, does that change what we have to do to prepare for or mitigate the risk of future pandemics?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Angela Rasmussen:<strong> </strong>Yes, it matters. But also, no, it doesn’t. So we already know that lab accidents are potentially dangerous. We also already know that they’ve happened before. But as far as I know, there’s been <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4542197/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one lab-associated pandemic</a>, and that was a flu pandemic in 1977, that started … likely as a result of a vaccine trial. Lab-acquired infections are a known risk. We also know how to mitigate that risk pretty well. That doesn’t mean we eliminate the risk. But it does mean we can mitigate it significantly, and of course we should. No matter what, we’re not going to be like, “Oh, it was zoonotic. So let’s not worry about biosafety biosecurity anymore.” Nobody at all is ever going to say that because we were already worried about biosafety and biosecurity. </p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/biden-vulnerable-primary-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-97670358</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">But I do think that the reason why it matters where the pandemic came from is that if people are saying that it’s a lab leak, one of the consequences of this is that people are going to say, “It was that person’s fault, get them out of here, hold them accountable, whatever. And maybe shut down a lab. But don’t worry about zoonosis.” When in reality, we should not neglect lab safety. And we should certainly hold people accountable. But we also shouldn’t be taking resources away from the <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanmic/article/PIIS2666-5247(21)00187-7/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noopener">threat of zoonosis</a> because it’s <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/spillover-diseases-are-emerging-faster-than-ever-beforethanks-to-humans" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a much, much bigger threat</a>.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: Biosafety and biosecurity, and regulation around those things, aren’t new ideas. What was the discussion around lab safety like in the years leading up to COVID, before it was politicized?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR<strong>: </strong>If you really want to go all the way back to the beginning, that was in response partly to the anthrax attacks after 9/11. I think that was a wake-up call to the government that people could conduct bioterrorism with few resources. What came out of that was the Select Agents and Toxins Act, which basically made it a federal crime to mishandle a list of pathogens that are considered to be exceptionally dangerous or candidates for development into bio weapons. This differs from country to country.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Then in 2010, <a href="https://academic.oup.com/jid/article/213/9/1364/2459266" target="_blank" rel="noopener">two experiments were done</a>; one by Yoshihiro Kawaoka and one by Ron Fouchier. They basically selected variants of H5N1 [influenza virus] that were transmissible amongst ferrets by the airborne route. And that got a lot of people’s attention because H5N1 doesn’t transmit very efficiently between people by the airborne route. It really doesn’t transmit efficiently between people at all. The fear of so-called gain of function experiments began with those data, and there was a whole big discussion about, you know, should they publish their findings? Should they publish their methods? They did end up publishing both. But then there was a moratorium that was imposed on all research on influenza and coronaviruses that would potentially be considered gain of function. [That led to] the Pandemic Potential Pathogen Care and Oversight Framework, and that is how, currently, the [National Institutes of Health] or the Department of Health and Human Services regulates [biosafety].</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: You’re talking here about two different things that both sort of get lumped together under the word “biosafety”: Regulation of lab security and practice and regulation of types of experiments that could be dangerous. Should we be talking about those separately? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: Boy, on this topic I’m seeing everything getting mixed up. I think some of it reflects the fact that some people, because of the lab leak theory, which can be a very compelling story, have just decided, “This seems like a pretty dangerous thing. I guess I better jump into this field now.” And I think there’s a lot of people who are essentially newcomers to it, who don’t necessarily have a lot of technical knowledge. So I do think that these efforts are being sort of wrongly conflated. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: What are your thoughts on the recommendations made by the National Science Advisory Board for Biosecurity, which earlier this year </strong><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/27/science/biosecurity-virus-pathogens-covid-lab-leak.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>issued a report</strong></a><strong> that was particularly centered on new proposed regulations for gain of function research?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: They basically said that now we need to start regulating everything that deals with a pathogen. Their new recommendations were maddening because they were both so vague, but also so potentially broad in scope, that it could mean essentially a stoppage of any research that involves a virus, even if it’s a virus that doesn’t make anything or anybody sick.</p>


<p>Watch: https://abcnews.go.com/fivethirtyeight/video/poll-ended-dilbert-fivethirtyeight-politics-podcast-97670065</p>


<p data-paragraph="main">It has kind of turned into this creep, where a lot of people who don’t actually do any of this work and don’t have a very good technical understanding of it can come in and say, “Oh, look at this, this experiment could cause a zombie apocalypse, or this could cause the extinction of the human race with transmissible bird flu.” And none of these things are really very accurate or likely. But a lot of that sort of fear-based messaging is, I think, really motivating. It really is a big problem. And many of my colleagues and I have been talking about this. If we can’t do a lot of the work that we do, [the result is] no more vaccines, no more antiviral therapies, no more understanding zoonotic pathogens that are going to emerge.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: I think it’s easy to see this, though, as an industry — in this case, virology — pushing back against regulation, just because that’s what industries do. Are there regulations you would support? Things you’d like to see changed? </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: I do think that making the [Pandemic Potential Pathogen Care and Oversight Framework] more broadly applicable to multiple agencies across the U.S. government, and making it smarter [would be good]. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">We already have a lot of regulation. And we’re happy to comply with more, if that makes sense. But right now, I haven’t seen any proposals that actually make sense or that would meaningfully address actual threats that we do work with. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: If there were a lab leak situation that led to a pandemic, what kinds of changes would you expect to see? What would you like to see people who believe COVID-19 was a lab leak pushing for?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: The one thing that we should all be pushing for, and one thing that has kind of gotten lost in this conversation, is that every country regulates biosafety differently and biosecurity differently. Even between Canada and the U.S., for example, things are regulated differently. And this is kind of a big problem when it comes to responding to “lab leaks” or trying to think about this as an international effort. There is no sort of treaty mechanism that would allow an organization like [the World Health Organization] to put together a multinational working group that would have any enforcement power. There is discussion about a pandemic treaty at the World Health Assembly. So I think that really a lot of the focus should go toward that, because that’s going to address international collaborative efforts to get to the bottom of any sort of new emerging pathogen, whether it’s from a lab or whether it’s from nature. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: I’m curious if there’s anything valuable that COVID-19 and the arguments over where it came from have taught you about those cultural differences within science, and how science is done in different parts of the world. </strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: Yeah, it has been really instructive. I know people who are scientists, either from China or in China. What I’ve learned about the situation in China is that there are very, very different political pressures that scientists are working under. I’m familiar with the U.S. and the Canadian system. There’s always some politics involved. [But] there’s a whole different set of considerations that I think scientists in China have to deal with. There’s also a whole different reward system. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">One of the arguments that, to me, is crazy is [that] the Wuhan Institute of Virology developed the secret reverse genetics clone of the SARS2 precursor and didn’t publish it, because [virologist] <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/02/09/1044985/shi-zhengli-covid-lab-leak-wuhan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shi Zhengli</a> was afraid that she’d get blamed for starting the pandemic that hadn’t started yet. That makes zero sense to me because I found that in many Chinese institutions, people get significant cash bonuses when they write a Nature, Science or Cell paper. If you’re the senior author of these high profile papers, you get compensated for it quite a lot, actually thousands of dollars.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main">I’ve also noticed that a lot of times when people are talking about especially safety practices, there’s an assumption that things are inferior in China. That’s not the case at all. These so-called safety problems that were occurring at the Wuhan Institute of Virology, BSL-4 lab, were actually not safety problems. They were, to me, indicative of a biosafety maximum containment lab, where they were doing what they normally do for containment lab, which is constantly reevaluating how you might be able to do things better and installing multiple redundant systems so that you don’t have the containment breach.</p>



<p data-paragraph="main"><strong>MK: So you’re actually coming away from this a little bit more confident in international standards?</strong></p>



<p data-paragraph="main">AR: I wouldn’t say I’m more confident in international standards because there aren’t any. I’m more confident, though, that in some ways, while China is different, and there’s clearly different pressures that scientists in China have to work under, it’s kind of like the institutions in any other country I’ve worked in. I’ve never seen anything that indicates to me that there’s a culture of lax regulation of high containment labs. </p>



<p data-paragraph="main">Add to that, individual labs will have individual challenges. The U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Disease has had these terrible plumbing problems where their containment labs are getting flooded. There’s all these problems. So it’s not like just China that would have potential safety issues, or literally physical problems, engineering failures with their containment labs. That can happen anywhere. I think the difference is how proactive your institution is about trying to prevent those from happening in the first place. But it looks to me like WIV is constantly working to improve its biosafety and biocontainment practices.</p>]]></description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1678243500842455</guid>
		</item>

	</channel>
</rss>
